1 Esdras

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9

The First Book of Esdras

1

1 And Josias held the [a]feast of the passover in Jerusalem unto his Lord, and offered the passover the fourteenth day of the first month;

2 Having set the priests according to their [b]daily courses, being arrayed in long garments, in the temple of the Lord.

3 And he spake unto the Levites, the holy ministers of Israel, that they should hallow themselves unto the Lord, to set the holy ark of the Lord in the house that king Solomon the son of David had built:

4 [c]And said, Ye shall no more bear the ark upon your shoulders: now therefore serve the Lord your God, and minister unto his people Israel, and prepare you after your families and [d]kindreds,

5 According as David the king of Israel prescribed, and according to [e]the magnificence of Solomon his son: and standing in the temple according to [d]the several dignity of the families of you the Levites, who minister in the presence of your brethren the children of Israel,

6 Offer the passover in order, and make ready the sacrifices for your brethren, and keep the passover according to the commandment of the Lord, which was given unto Moses.

7 And unto the people [f]that was found there Josias gave thirty thousand lambs and kids, and three thousand calves: these things were given of the king’s allowance, according as he promised, to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites.

8 And Helkias, Zacharias, and [*]Syelus, the governors of the temple, gave to the priests for the passover two thousand and six hundred sheep, and three hundred calves.

9 And Jeconias, and Samaias, and Nathanael his brother, and Assabias, and Ochiel, and Joram, captains over thousands, gave to the Levites for the passover five thousand sheep, and [*]seven hundred calves.

10 And when these things were done, the priests and Levites, having the unleavened bread, stood in very comely order according to the [d]kindreds,

11 And according to [d]the several dignities of the fathers, before the people, to offer to the Lord, as it is written in the book of Moses: [*]and thus did they in the morning.

12 And they roasted the passover with fire, [g]as appertaineth: as for the sacrifices, they sod them in brass pots and pans [*]with a good savour,

13 And set them before all the people: and afterward they prepared for themselves, and for the priests their brethren, the sons of Aaron.

14 For the priests offered the fat until night: and the Levites prepared for themselves, and the priests their brethren, the sons of Aaron.

15 The holy singers also, the sons of Asaph, were in their order, according to the appointment [*]of David, to wit, [h]Asaph, Zacharias, and Jeduthun, who was [*]of the king’s retinue.

16 Moreover the porters were at every gate; it was not lawful for any to go from his [b]ordinary service: for their brethren the Levites prepared for them.

17 Thus were the things that belonged to the sacrifices of the Lord accomplished in that day, that they might hold the passover,

18 And offer sacrifices upon the altar of the Lord, according to the commandment of king Josias.

19 So the children of Israel [f]which were present held the passover at that time, and [i]the feast of sweet bread seven days.

20 And [k]such a passover was not kept in Israel since the time of the prophet Samuel.

21 Yea, all the kings of Israel held not such a passover as Josias, and the priests, and the Levites, and the Jews, held with all Israel that were found dwelling at Jerusalem.

22 In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josias was this passover kept.

23 [l]And the works or Josias were upright before his Lord with an heart full of godliness.

24 [l]As for the things that came to pass in his time, they were written in former times, concerning those that sinned, and [*]did wickedly against the Lord above all people and kingdoms, and how they grieved him [*]exceedingly, so that the words of the Lord rose up against Israel.

25 [m]Now after all these acts of Josias it came to pass, that Pharaoh the king of Egypt came to raise war at Carchamis upon Euphrates: and Josias went out against him.

26 [*]But the king of Egypt sent to him, saying, What have I to do with thee, O king of Judea?

27 I am not sent out from the Lord God against thee; for my war is upon Euphrates: and now the Lord is with me, yea, the Lord is with me hasting me forward: depart from me, and [n]be not against the Lord.

28 Howbeit Josias did not turn back his chariot from him, but undertook to fight with him, not regarding the words of the prophet Jeremy spoken by the mouth of the Lord:

29 But joined battle with him in the plain of Magiddo, and the princes came against king Josias.

30 Then said the king unto his servants, Carry me away out of the battle; for I am very weak. And immediately his servants took him away out of the battle.

31 Then gat he up upon his second chariot; and being brought back to Jerusalem died, and was buried in his father’s sepulchre.

32 And in all Jewry they mourned for Josias, yea, Jeremy the prophet lamented for Josias, and the chief men with the women made lamentation for him unto this day: and this was given out [o]for an ordinance to be done continually in all the nation of Israel.

33 These things are written in the book of the stories of the kings of Judah, and every one of the acts that Josias did, and his glory, and his understanding in the law of the Lord, and the things that he had done before, and the things now recited, are reported in the book of the kings of Israel and Judea.

34 [p]And the people took Joachaz the son of Josias, and [q]made him king instead of Josias his father, when he was twenty and three years old.

35 And he reigned in Judea and in Jerusalem three months: and then the king of Egypt deposed him from reigning in Jerusalem.

36 And he set a tax upon the land of an hundred talents of silver and one talent of gold.

37 The king of Egypt also [q]made king Joacim his brother king of Judea and Jerusalem.

38 And he bound Joacim and the nobles: but Zaraces his brother he apprehended, and brought him out of Egypt.

39 [r]Five and twenty years old was [*]Joacim when he was made king in the land of Judea and Jerusalem; and he did evil before the Lord.

40 [*]Wherefore against him Nabuchodonosor the king of Babylon came up, and bound him with a chain of brass, and carried him into Babylon.

41 Nabuchodonosor also took of the holy vessels of the Lord, and carried them away, and set them in his own temple at Babylon.

42 But those things that are recorded of him, and of his uncleaness and impiety, are written in the chronicles of the kings.

43 [*]And Joacim his son reigned in his stead: he [q]was made king being [s]eighteen years old;

44 [t]And reigned but three months and ten days in Jerusalem; and did evil before the Lord.

45 So after a year Nabuchodonosor sent and caused him to be brought into Babylon with [u]the holy vessels of the Lord;

46 And [q]made Zedechias king of Judea and Jerusalem, when he was one and twenty years old; and he reigned eleven years:

47 And he did evil also in the sight of the Lord, and cared not for the words that were spoken unto him by the prophet Jeremy from the mouth of the Lord.

48 [*]And after that king Nabuchodonosor had made him to swear by the name of the Lord, he forswore himself, and rebelled; and hardening his neck, his heart, he transgressed the laws of the Lord God of Israel.

49 The governors also of the people and of the priests [x]did many things against the laws, and passed all the pollutions of all nations, and defiled the temple of the Lord, which was sanctified in Jerusalem.

50 Nevertheless the God of their fathers sent by his messenger to call them back, because he spared them and his tabernacle also.

51 But they [y]had his messengers in derision; and, look, when the Lord spake unto them, they made a sport of his prophets:

52 So far forth, that he, being wroth with his people for their great ungodliness, commanded the kings of the Chaldees to come up against them;

53 Who slew their young men with the sword, yea, even within the compass of their holy temple, and spared neither young man nor maid, old man nor child, among them; for he delivered all into their hands.

54 And they took all [u]the holy vessels of the Lord, both great and small, with the vessels of the ark of God, and the king’s treasures, and carried them away into Babylon.

55 [*]As for the house of the Lord, they burnt it, and brake down the walls of Jerusalem, and set fire upon her towers:

56 And as for her glorious things, they never ceased till they had consumed and brought them all to nought: and the people that were not slain with the sword he carried unto Babylon:

57 Who became servants to him and his children, till the Persians reigned, to fulfil the word of the Lord [z]spoken by the mouth of Jeremy:

58 Until the land had enjoyed her sabbaths, the whole time of her desolation shall she [*]rest, until the full term of seventy years.

2

1 [*][a]In the first year of Cyrus king of the Persians, that the word of the Lord might be accomplished, that he had promised by the mouth of Jeremy;

2 The Lord [c]raised up the spirit of Cyrus the king of the Persians, and he made proclamation through all his kingdom, and also by writing,

3 Saying, Thus saith Cyrus king of the Persians; The Lord of Israel, the most high Lord, hath [b]made me king of the whole world,

4 And commanded me to build him an house at Jerusalem in Jewry.

5 If therefore there be any of you that are of his people, let the Lord, even his Lord, be with him, and let him go up to Jerusalem that is in Judea, and build the house of the Lord of Israel: for [*]he is the Lord that dwelleth in Jerusalem.

6 Whosoever then dwell in the places about, let them help him, those, I say, that are his neighbours, with gold, and with silver,

7 With gifts, with horses, and with cattle, and other things, which have been set forth by vow, for the temple of the Lord at Jerusalem.

8 Then the chief of the families of Judea and of the tribe of Benjamin stood up; the priests also, and the Levites, and all they whose [c]mind the Lord had moved to go up, and to build an house for the Lord at Jerusalem,

9 And they that dwelt round about them, and helped them in all things with silver and gold, with [*]horses and cattle, and with very many free gifts of a great number whose minds were stirred up thereto.

10 King Cyrus also brought forth the holy vessels, [d]which Nabuchodonosor had carried away from Jerusalem, [d]and had set up in his [e]temple of idols.

11 Now when Cyrus king of the Persians had brought them forth, he delivered them to Mithridates his treasurer:

12 And by him they were delivered to [*]Sanabassar the governor of Judea.

13 And this was the number of them; A thousand golden cups, and a thousand of silver, [*]censers of silver twenty nine, vials of gold thirty, and of silver [*]two thousand four hundred and ten, and a thousand other vessels.

14 So all the vessels of gold and of silver, which were carried away, were [*]five thousand four hundred threescore and nine.

15 These were brought back by Sanabassar, together with them of the captivity, from Babylon to Jerusalem.

16 [*][f]But in the time of Artexerxes king of the Persians Belemus, and Mithridates, and Tabellius, and [*]Rathumus, and Beeltethmus, and [*]Semellius the [g]secretary, with others that were in commission with them, dwelling in Samaria and other places, wrote unto him against them that dwelt in Judea and Jerusalem these letters following;

17 To king Artexerxes our lord, Thy servants, Rathumus the [h]storywriter, and Semellius the [g]scribe, and the rest of their council, and the judges that are in [i]Celosyria and [i][k]Phenice.

18 Be it now known to the lord king, that the Jews that are up from you to us, being come into Jerusalem, that rebellious and wicked city, do build the marketplaces, and repair the walls of it and do lay the foundation of the temple.

19 Now if this city and the walls thereof be made up again, they will not only refuse to give tribute, but also rebel against kings.

20 And forasmuch as the things pertaining to the temple are now in hand, we think it meet not to neglect such a matter,

21 But to speak unto our lord the king, to the intent that, if it be thy pleasure it may be sought out in the books of thy fathers:

22 And thou shalt find in the chronicles what is written concerning these things, and shalt understand that that city was rebellious, troubling both kings and cities:

23 And that the Jews were rebellious, and raised always wars therein; for the which cause even this city was made desolate.

24 Wherefore now we do declare unto thee, O lord the king, that if this city be built again, and the walls thereof set up anew, thou shalt from henceforth have no passage into [i]Celosyria and Phenice.

25 Then the king wrote back again to Rathumus the [h]storywriter, [l]to Beeltethmus, [l]to Semellius the [g]scribe, and to the rest that were in commission, and dwellers in Samaria and Syria and Phenice, after this manner;

26 I have read the epistle which ye have sent unto me: therefore I commanded to make diligent search, and it hath been found that that city was from the beginning practising against kings;

27 And the men therein were given to rebellion and war: and that mighty kings and fierce were in Jerusalem, who reigned and exacted tributes in [i]Celosyria and Phenice.

28 Now therefore I have commanded to hinder those men from building the city, and heed to be taken that there be no more done in it;

29 And that those wicked workers proceed no further to the annoyance of kings,

30 Then king Artexerxes his letters being read, Rathumus, and Semellius the [g]scribe, and the rest that were in commission with them, removing in haste toward Jerusalem with a troop of horsemen and [*]a multitude of people in battle array, began to hinder the builders; [*]and the building of the temple in Jerusalem ceased until the second year of the reign of Darius king of the Persians.

3

1 Now when Darius reigned, he [a]made a great feast unto all his subjects, and unto all his household, and unto all the [b]princes of [c]Media and Persia,

2 And to all the [k]governors and captains and lieutenants that were under him, [d]from India unto Ethiopia, of an hundred twenty and seven provinces.

3 And when they had eaten and drunken, and being satisfied [e]were gone home, then Darius the king [e]went into his bedchamber, and slept, and soon after [f]awaked.

4 Then three young men, that were of the guard that kept the king’s body, spake one to another;

5 Let every one of us speak a sentence: he that shall overcome, and whose sentence shall seem wiser than the others, unto him shall the king Darius give great gifts, and great things in token of victory:

6 As, [g]to be clothed in purple, to drink in gold, and to sleep upon gold, and [h]a chariot with bridles of gold, and an headtire of [h]fine linen, and [g][h]a chain about his neck:

7 And he shall sit next to Darius because of his wisdom, and shall be called Darius his cousin.

8 And then every one wrote his sentence, sealed it, and laid it under king Darius his pillow;

9 And said that, when the king is risen, [i]some will give him the writings; and of whose side the king and [j]the three [b]princes of Persia shall judge that his sentence is the wisest, to him shall the victory be given, as was appointed.

10 The first wrote, Wine is the strongest.

11 The second wrote, The king is strongest.

12 The third wrote, Women are strongest: but above all things Truth beareth away the victory.

13 Now when the king was risen up, they took their writings, and delivered them unto him, and so he read them:

14 And sending forth he called all the [b]princes of Persia and Media, and the [k]governors, and the captains, and the lieutenants, and the chief officers;

15 And sat him down in the [*]royal seat of judgment; and the writings were read before them.

16 And he said, Call the young men, and they shall declare their own sentences. So they were called, and came in.

17 And he said unto them, Declare unto us your mind concerning the writings. Then began the first, who had spoken of the strength of wine;

18 And he said thus, O ye men, how exceeding strong is wine! it causeth all men to err that drink it:

19 It maketh the mind of the king and of the fatherless child to be all one; of the bondman and of the freeman, of the poor man and of the rich:

20 [l]It turneth also every thought into [m]jollity and mirth, so that a man remembereth neither sorrow nor debt:

21 And it maketh every heart rich, so that a man remembereth neither king nor governor; and it maketh to speak all things by talents:

22 And when they are in their cups, they forget their love both to friends and brethren, and a little after draw out swords:

23 But when they are from the wine, they remember not what they have done.

24 O ye men, is not wine the strongest, that enforceth to do thus? And when he had so spoken, he held his peace.

4

1 Then the second, that had spoken of the strength of the king, began to say,

2 O ye men, do not men excel in strength that [*]bear rule over sea and land and all things in them?

3 But yet the king is more mighty: for he is lord of all these things, and hath dominion over them; and whatsoever he commandeth them they do.

4 If he bid them make war the one against the other, they do it: if he send them out against the enemies, they go, and break down mountains walls and towers.

5 They slay and are slain, and transgress not the king’s commandment: if they get the victory, they bring all to the king, as well the spoil, as all things else.

6 Likewise for those that are no soldiers, and have not to do with wars, but use husbundry, when they have reaped again that which they had sown, they bring it to the king, and compel one another to pay tribute unto the king.

7 And yet he is but one man: if he command to kill, they kill; if he command to spare, they spare;

8 If he command to smite, they smite; if he command to make desolate, they make desolate; if he command to build, they build;

9 If he command [a]to cut down, they cut down; if he command to plant, they plant.

10 So all his people and his armies obey him: [b]furthermore he lieth down, he eateth and drinketh, and taketh his rest:

11 And [c]these keep watch round about him, neither [*]may any one depart, and do his own business, neither disobey they him in any thing.

12 O ye men, how should not the king be mightiest, when in such sort he is obeyed? And he held his tongue.

13 Then the third, who had spoken of women, and of the truth, (this was [d]Zorobabel) began to speak.

14 O ye men, it is not the great king, nor the multitude of men, neither is it wine, that [*]excelleth; who is it then that ruleth them, or hath the lordship over them? are they not women?

15 Women have borne the king and all the people that bear rule by sea and land.

16 Even of them came they: and they nourished them up that planted the vineyards, from whence the wine cometh.

17 [e]These also make garments for men; these bring glory unto men; and without women cannot men be.

18 Yea, and if men have gathered together gold and silver, or any other goodly thing, do they not love a woman which is comely in favour and beauty?

19 And letting all those things go, do they not gape, and even [f]with open mouth fix their eyes fast on her; and have not all men more desire unto her than unto silver or gold, or any goodly thing whatsoever?

20 [g]A man leaveth his own father that brought him up, and his own country, and cleaveth unto his wife.

21 He sticketh not to spend his life with his wife. and remembereth neither father, nor mother, nor country.

22 By this also ye must know that women have dominion over you: do ye not labour and toil, and give and bring all to the woman?

23 Yea, a man taketh his sword, and goeth his way to rob and to steal, to sail upon the sea and upon rivers;

24 And looketh upon a lion, and goeth in the darkness; and when he hath stolen, spoiled, and robbed, he bringeth it to his love.

25 Wherefore a man loveth his wife better than father or mother.

26 Yea, many there be that have [*]run out of their wits for women, and [h]become servants for their sakes.

27 Many also have perished, have erred, and sinned, for women.

28 And now do ye not believe me? is not the king great in his power? do not all regions fear to touch him?

29 Yet did I see him and Apame the king’s concubine, the daughter of the admirable [*]Bartacus, sitting [i]at the right hand of the king,

30 And taking the crown from the king’s head, and setting it upon her own head; she also [k]struck the king with her left hand.

31 And yet [*]for all this the king [f]gaped and gazed upon her with open mouth: if she laughed upon him, he laughed also: but if she took any displeasure at him, the king was fain to flatter, that she might [*]be reconciled to him again.

32 O ye men, how can it be but women should be strong, seeing they do thus?

33 Then the king and the [l]princes looked one upon another: so he began to speak of the truth.

34 O ye men, are not women strong? great is the earth, high is the heaven, swift is the sun in his course, for he compasseth the heavens round about, and fetcheth his course again to his own place in one day.

35 Is he not great that maketh these things? therefore great is the truth, and stronger than all things.

36 All the earth [*]crieth upon the truth, and the heaven blesseth it: all works shake and tremble at it, and with it is no unrighteous thing.

37 Wine is wicked, the king is wicked, women are wicked, all the children of men are wicked, and such are all their wicked works; and [m]there is no truth in them; in their unrighteousness also they shall perish.

38 As for the truth, it endureth, and is always strong; it liveth and conquereth for evermore.

39 With her there is no [n]accepting of persons or rewards; but she doeth the things that are just, and refraineth from all unjust and wicked things; and all men [o]do well like of her works.

40 Neither in her judgment is any unrighteousness; and she is the strength, [p]kingdom, power, and majesty, of all ages. Blessed be [q]the God of truth.

41 And with that he held his peace. And all the people then shouted, and said, Great is Truth, and mighty above all things.

42 Then said the king unto him, Ask what thou wilt more [r]than is appointed in the writing, and we will give it thee, because thou art found wisest; and [s]thou shalt sit next me, and [s]shalt be called my cousin.

43 Then said he unto the king, Remember thy vow, which thou hast vowed to build Jerusalem, in the day when thou camest to thy kingdom,

44 And to send away all the vessels that were taken away out of Jerusalem, [t]which Cyrus set apart, when he vowed to destroy Babylon, and to send them again thither.

45 Thou also hast vowed to build up the temple, which [u]the Edomites burned when Judea was made desolate by the Chaldees.

46 And now, O lord the king, this is that which I require, and which I desire of thee, and this is the princely liberality [x]proceeding from thyself: I desire therefore that thou make good the vow, the performance whereof with thine own mouth thou hast vowed to [y]the King of heaven.

47 Then Darius the king stood up, and kissed him, and wrote letters for him unto all the [z]treasurers and [z]lieutenants and captains and governors, that they should safely convey on their way both him, and all those that go up with him to build Jerusalem.

48 He wrote letters also unto the [z]lieutenants that were in [a]Celosyria and Phenice, and unto them in Libanus, that they should bring [b]cedar wood from Libanus unto Jerusalem, and that they should build the city with him.

49 Moreover he wrote for all the Jews that went out of his realm up into Jewry, concerning their freedom, that no officer, no [z]ruler, no lieutenant, nor [*]treasurer, should forcibly enter into their doors;

50 And that all the country which they hold should be free without tribute; and that [u]the Edomites should give over the villages of the Jews which then they held:

51 Yea, that there should be yearly given twenty talents to the building of the temple, until the time that it were built;

52 And other ten talents yearly, to maintain the burnt offerings upon the altar every day, as they had a commandment to offer seventeen:

53 And that all they that went from Babylon to build the city should have free liberty, as well they as their posterity, and all the priests that went away.

54 He wrote also concerning. the charges, and the priests’ vestments wherein they minister;

55 And likewise for the charges of the Levites, to be given them until the day that the house were finished, and Jerusalem builded up.

56 And he commanded to give to all that kept the city [*]pensions and [c]wages.

57 He sent away also all the vessels from Babylon, [t]that Cyrus had set apart; and all that Cyrus had given in commandment, the same charged he also to be done, and sent unto Jerusalem.

58 Now when this young man was gone forth, [d]he lifted up his face to heaven [e]toward Jerusalem, and praised [y]the King of heaven,

59 And said, From thee cometh victory, from thee cometh wisdom, and [f]thine is the glory, and I am thy servant.

60 Blessed art thou, [g]who hast given me wisdom: for to thee I give thanks, O Lord of our fathers.

61 And so he took the letters, and went out, and came unto Babylon, and told it all his brethren.

62 And they praised the God of their fathers, because he had given them freedom and liberty

63 To go up, and to build Jerusalem, and [h]the temple which is called by his name: and they feasted [i]with instruments of musick and gladness seven days.

5

1 After this were the principal men of the families chosen according to their tribes, to go up with their wives and sons and daughters, with their menservants and maidservants, and their cattle.

2 And Darius sent with them [a]a thousand horsemen, till they had brought them back to Jerusalem safely, and [b]with musical instruments [c][d]tabrets and [d]flutes.

3 And all their brethren played, and he made them go up together with them.

4 And these are the names of the men which went up, according to their families among their tribes, after [e]their several heads.

5 [f]The priests, [g]the sons of Phinees the son of Aaron: [h]Jesus [g]the son of Josedec, the son of Saraias, and [*]Joacim the son of [i]Zorobabel, the son of [i]Salathiel, of the house of David, [k]out of the kindred of Phares, of the tribe of Judah;

6 [*]Who spake wise sentences before Darius the king of Persia [l]in the second year of his reign, in the month [m]Nisan, which is the first month.

7 [n]And these are they of Jewry that came up from the captivity, where they dwelt as strangers, whom Nabuchodonosor the king of Babylon had carried away unto Babylon.

8 [*]And they returned unto Jerusalem, and to the other parts of Jewry, every man to his own city, who came with Zorobabel, with Jesus, Nehemias, and [o]Zacharias, and Reesaias, Enenius, Mardocheus. Beelsarus, [p]Aspharasus, [q]Reelius, Roimus, and Baana, their [r]guides.

9 The number of them of the nation, and their [r]governors, sons of [s]Phoros, two thousand an hundred seventy and two; the sons of [t]Saphat, [u]four hundred seventy and two:

10 The sons of Ares, seven hundred fifty and six:

11 The sons of Phaath Moab, two thousand eight hundred and twelve:

12 The sons of Elam, a thousand two hundred fifty and four: the sons of [x]Zathul, nine hundred forty and five: the sons of [y]Corbe, seven hundred and five: the sons of Bani, six hundred forty and eight:

13 The sons of Bebai, six hundred twenty and three: the sons of [z]Sadas, three thousand two hundred twenty and two:

14 The sons of Adonikam, six hundred sixty and seven: the sons of [a]Bagoi, two thousand sixty and six: the sons of Adin, four hundred fifty and four:

15 The sons of [b]Aterezias, ninety and two: the sons of Ceilan and Azetas threescore and seven: the sons of Azuran, four hundred thirty and two:

16 The sons of Ananias, an hundred and one: the sons of Arom, thirty two: and the sons of [c]Bassa, three hundred twenty and three: the sons of Azephurith, an hundred and two:

17 The sons of Meterus, three thousand and five: the sons of [d]Bethlomon, an hundred twenty and three:

18 They of Netophah, fifty and five: they of Anathoth, an hundred fifty and eight: they of [e]Bethsamos, forty and two:

19 They of [f]Kiriathiarius, twenty and five: they of Caphira and Beroth, seven hundred forty and three: they of Pira, seven hundred:

20 They of Chadias and Ammidoi, four hundred twenty and two: they of [g]Cirama and [h]Gabdes, six hundred twenty and one:

21 They of [i]Macalon, an hundred twenty and two: they of [k]Betolius, fifty and two: the sons of [l]Nephis, an hundred fifty and six:

22 The sons of [m]Calamolalus and Onus, seven hundred twenty and five: the sons of Jerechus, two hundred forty and five:

23 The sons of [n]Annas, three thousand three hundred and thirty.

24 The priests: the sons of [o]Jeddu, the son of Jesus among the sons of Sanasib, nine hundred seventy and two: the sons of [p]Meruth, a thousand fifty and two:

25 The sons of [q]Phassaron, a thousand forty and seven: the sons of [r]Carme, [s]a thousand and seventeen.

26 The Levites: [t]the sons of Jessue, and Cadmiel, and Banuas, and Sudias, seventy and four.

27 The holy singers: the sons of Asaph, an hundred twenty and eight.

28 The porters: the sons of [u]Salum, the sons of [x]Jatal, the sons of Talmon, the sons of [y]Dacobi, the sons of [z]Teta, the sons of [a]Sami, in all an hundred thirty and nine.

29 The servants of the temple: the sons of [b]Esau, the sons of [c]Asipha, the sons of Tabaoth, the sons of [d]Ceras, the sons of [e]Sud, the sons of [f]Phaleas, the sons of Labana, the sons of [g]Graba,

30 The sons of [h]Acua, the sons of Uta, the sons of [i]Cetab, the sons of Agaba, the sons of [k]Subai, the sons of Anan, the sons of [l]Cathua, the sons of [m]Geddur,

31 The sons of [n]Airus, the sons of [o]Daisan, the sons of [p]Noeba, the sons of Chaseba, the sons of [q]Gazera, the sons of [r]Azia, the sons of [s]Phinees, the sons of Azare, the sons of [t]Bastai, the sons of [u]Asana, the sons of [x]Meani, the sons of [y]Naphisi, the sons of [z]Acub, the sons of [a]Acipha, the sons of [b]Assur, the sons of Pharacim, the sons of [c]Basaloth,

32 The sons of [d]Meeda, the sons of Coutha, the sons of [e]Charea, the sons of [f]Charcus, the sons of [g]Aserer, the sons of [h]Thomoi, the sons of [i]Nasith, the sons of Atipha.

33 The sons of the servants of Solomon: the sons of [k]Azaphion, the sons of [l]Pharira, the sons of [m]Jeeli, the sons of [n]Lozon, the sons of [o]Israel, the sons of [p]Sapheth,

34 The sons of [q]Hagia, the sons of [r]Pharacareth, the sons of Sabi, the sons of Sarothie, the sons of Masias, the sons of Gar, the sons of Addus, the sons of Suba, the sons of Apherra, the sons of Barodis, the sons of Sabat, the sons of Allom.

35 All the ministers of the temple, and the sons of the servants of Solomon, were three hundred seventy and two.

36 These came up from Thermeleth and Thelersas, Charaathalar leading them, and Aalar;

37 Neither could they shew their families, nor their stock, how they were of Israel: the sons of [s]Ladan, the son of [t]Ban, the sons of [u]Necodan, six hundred fifty and two.

38 And of the priests that usurped the office of the priesthood, and were not found: the sons of [x]Obdia, the sons of [y]Accoz, the sons of Addus, who married Augia one of the daughters of [z]Barzelus, and was named after his name.

39 And when the description of the kindred of these men was sought in the register, and was not found, they were removed from executing the office of the priesthood:

40 For unto them said [*]Nehemias and Atharias, that they should not be partakers of the holy things, till there arose up an high priest clothed with [*]doctrine and truth.

41 So of Israel, from them of twelve years old and upward, they were all in number forty thousand, beside [a]menservants and womenservants two thousand three hundred and sixty.

42 Their [a]menservants and handmaids were seven thousand three hundred [b]forty and seven: the singing men and singing women, two hundred forty and five:

43 Four hundred thirty and five camels, [c]seven thousand thirty and six horses, two hundred forty and five mules, [c]five thousand five hundred twenty and five [*]beasts used to the yoke.

44 And certain of the chief of their families, when they came to the temple of God that is in Jerusalem, vowed to set up the house again [h]in his own place according to their ability,

45 And to give into the holy treasury of the works a thousand [d]pounds of gold, five thousand of silver, and an hundred priestly vestments.

46 And so dwelt the priests and the Levites and the people in Jerusalem, and in the country, the singers also and the porters; and all Israel in their villages.

47 [e]But when the seventh month was at hand, [*]and when the children of Israel were every man in [f]his own place, they came all together with one consent into the open place [*]of the first gate which is toward the east.

48 Then stood up [g]Jesus the son of Josedec, and his brethren the priests and [g]Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, and his brethren, and made ready the altar of the God of Israel,

49 To offer burnt sacrifices upon it, according as it is expressly commanded in the book of Moses the man of God.

50 And there were gathered unto them out of the other nations of the land, and they erected the altar [h]upon his own place, because all the nations of the land were at enmity with them, and oppressed them; and they offered sacrifices according to the time, and burnt offerings to the Lord both morning and evening.

51 Also they held the feast of tabernacles, as it is commanded in the law, and offered sacrifices daily, as was meet:

52 And after that, the [*]continual oblations, and the sacrifice of the sabbaths, and of the new moons, and of all holy feasts.

53 And all they that had [*]made any vow to God began to offer sacrifices to God from [i]the first day of the seventh month, although the temple of the Lord was not yet built.

54 And they gave unto the masons and carpenters money, meat, and drink, with cheerfulness.

55 Unto them of Zidon also and Tyre they gave carrs, that they should bring [k]cedar trees from Libanus, [l]which should be brought by floats to the haven of [m]Joppa, according as it was commanded them by Cyrus king of the Persians.

56 [n]And in the second year and second month after his coming to the temple of God at Jerusalem began Zorobabel the son of Salathiel, and Jesus the son of Josedec, and their brethren, and the priests, and the Levites, and all they that were come unto Jerusalem out of the captivity:

57 And they laid the foundation of the house of God in the first day of the second month, in the second year after they were come to Jewry and Jerusalem.

58 And they appointed the Levites from twenty years old over the works of the Lord. Then stood up Jesus, and his sons and brethren, and Cadmiel his brother, and the sons of Madiabun, with the sons of Joda the son of Eliadun, with their sons and brethren, all Levites, with one accord [*]setters forward of the business, labouring to advance the works in the house of God. So the workmen built the temple of the Lord.

59 And the priests stood arrayed in their vestments with musical instruments and trumpets; and the Levites the sons of Asaph had cymbals,

60 Singing songs of thanksgiving, and praising the Lord, [*]according as David the king of Israel had ordained.

61 And they sung with loud voices songs to the praise of the Lord, because his mercy and glory is for ever in all Israel.

62 And all the people sounded trumpets, and shouted with a loud voice, singing songs of thanksgiving unto the Lord for the rearing up of the house of the Lord.

63 Also of the priests and Levites, and of the chief of their families, the ancients who had seen the former house came to the building of this with weeping and great crying.

64 But many with trumpets and joy shouted with loud voice,

65 Insomuch that the trumpets might not be [*]heard for the weeping of the people: yet the multitude sounded marvellously, so that it was heard afar off.

66 [o]Wherefore when the enemies of the tribe of Judah and Benjamin heard it, they came to know what that noise of trumpets should mean.

67 And they perceived that they that were of the captivity did build the temple unto the Lord God of Israel.

68 So they went to Zorobabel and Jesus, and to the chief of the families, and said unto them, We will build together with you.

69 For we likewise, as ye, do obey your Lord, and do sacrifice unto him from the days of [*]Azbazareth the king of the Assyrians, who brought us hither.

70 [*]Then Zorobabel and Jesus and the chief of the families of Israel said unto them, It is not for us and you to build together an house unto the Lord our God.

71 We ourselves alone will build unto the Lord of Israel, according as Cyrus the king of the Persians hath commanded us.

72 But the heathen of the land lying heavy upon the inhabitants of Judea, and holding them strait, hindered their building;

73 And by their secret plots, and popular persuasions and commotions, they hindered the finishing of the building all the time that king Cyrus lived: so they were hindered from building for the space of two years, [*]until the reign of Darius.

6

1 [*]Now [a]in the second year of the reign of Darius [b]Aggeus and Zacharias the son of [*]Addo, the prophets, prophesied unto the Jews in Jewry and Jerusalem in the name of the Lord God of Israel, [*][c]which was upon them.

2 Then stood up Zorobabel the son of Salatiel, and Jesus the son of Josedec, and began to build the house of the Lord at Jerusalem, the prophets of the Lord being with them, and helping them.

3 At the same time came unto them [*]Sisinnes the governor of Syria and Phenice, with [*]Sathrabuzanes and his companions, and said unto them,

4 By whose appointment do ye build this house and this roof, and perform all the other things? and who are the workmen that perform these things?

5 Nevertheless the [e]elders of the Jews obtained favour, because [d]the Lord had visited the captivity;

6 [*]And they were not hindered from building, until such time as signification was given unto Darius concerning them, and an answer received.

7 The copy of the letters which Sisinnes, governor of Syria and Phenice, and Sathrabuzanes, with their companions, rulers in Syria and Phenice, wrote and sent unto Darius; To king Darius, greeting:

8 Let all things be known unto our lord the king, that being come into the country of Judea, and entered into the city of Jerusalem we found in the city of Jerusalem the [e]ancients of the Jews that were of the captivity

9 Building an house unto the Lord, great and new, of hewn and costly stones, and the timber already laid upon the walls.

10 And those works are done with great speed, and the work goeth on prosperously in their hands, and with all glory and diligence is it made.

11 Then asked we these [e]elders, saying, By whose commandment build ye this house, and lay the foundations of these works?

12 Therefore to the intent that we might give knowledge unto thee by writing, we demanded of them who were the chief doers, and we required of them the names in writing of their principal men.

13 So they gave us this answer, We are the servants of the Lord which made heaven and earth.

14 And as for this house, it was builded many years ago by a king of Israel great and strong, and was finished.

15 But when our fathers [f]provoked God unto wrath, and sinned against the Lord of Israel which is in heaven, he gave them over into the power of Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon, of the Chaldees;

16 Who pulled down the house, and burned it, and carried away the people captives unto Babylon.

17 But in the first year that king Cyrus reigned over the country of Babylon Cyrus the king wrote to build up this house.

18 And the holy vessels of gold and of silver, that Nabuchodonosor had carried away out of the house at Jerusalem, and had [g]set them in his own temple [h]those Cyrus the king brought forth again out of the temple at Babylon, and they were delivered to [*]Zorobabel and to Sanabassarus the ruler,

19 With commandment that he should carry away the same vessels, and put them in the temple at Jerusalem; and that the temple of the Lord should be built in his place.

20 Then the same Sanabassarus, being come hither, laid the foundations of the house of the Lord at Jerusalem; and from that time to this being still a building, it is not yet fully ended.

21 Now therefore, if it seem good unto the king, let search be made among the [*]records of king Cyrus:

22 And if it be found that the building of the house of the Lord at Jerusalem hath been done with the consent of king Cyrus, and if our lord the king be so minded, let him signify unto us thereof.

23 [i]Then commanded king Darius to seek among the [k]records at Babylon: and so at Ecbatane the palace, which is in the country of Media, there was found a [*]roll wherein these things were recorded.

24 In the first year of the reign of Cyrus king Cyrus commanded that the house of the Lord at Jerusalem should be built again, where they do sacrifice [l]with continual fire:

25 Whose height shall be sixty cubits and the breadth sixty cubits, with three rows of hewn stones, and one row of new wood of that country; and the expences thereof to be given out of the house of king Cyrus:

26 And that the holy vessels of the house of the Lord, both of gold and silver, that Nabuchodonosor took out of the house at Jerusalem, and brought to Babylon, should be restored to the house at Jerusalem, and be set in the place where they were before.

27 And also he commanded that Sisinnes the governor of Syria and Phenice, and Sathrabuzanes, and their companions, and those which were appointed rulers in Syria and Phenice, should be careful not to meddle with the place, but suffer Zorobabel, the servant of the Lord, and governor of Judea, and the [e]elders of the Jews, to build the house of the Lord in that place.

28 I have commanded also to have it built up whole again; and that they look diligently to help those that be of the captivity of the Jews, till the house of the Lord be finished:

29 And out of the tribute of [m]Celosyria and Phenice a portion carefully to be given these men for the sacrifices of the Lord, that is, to Zorobabel the governor, for bullocks, and rams, and lambs;

30 And also corn, salt, wine, and oil, and that continually every year without further question, according as the priests that be in Jerusalem shall signify to be daily spent:

31 That [*]offerings may be made to [n]the most high God for the king and for his children, and that they may pray for their lives.

32 And he commanded that whosoever should transgress, yea, or make light of any thing afore spoken or written, out of [o]his own house should a tree be taken, and he thereon be hanged, and all his goods seized for the king.

33 The Lord therefore, whose name is there called upon, utterly destroy every king and nation, that stretcheth out his hand to hinder or endamage that house of the Lord in Jerusalem.

34 I Darius the king have ordained that according unto these things it be done with diligence.

7

1 [a]Then Sisinnes the governor of [b]Celosyria and Phenice, and Sathrabuzanes, with their companions following the commandments of king Darius,

2 Did very carefully oversee the holy works, assisting the [c]ancients of the Jews and governors of the temple.

3 And so the holy works prospered, when Aggeus and Zacharias the prophets prophesied.

4 And they finished these things by the commandment of the Lord God of Israel, and with [*]the [d]consent of Cyrus, Darius, and Artexerxes, kings of Persia.

5 [*]And thus was the holy house finished in [*]the three and twentieth day of the month Adar, in the sixth year of Darius king of the Persians

6 And the children of Israel, the priests, and the Levites, and others that were of the captivity, that were added unto them, did according to the things written in the book of Moses.

7 And to the dedication of the temple of the Lord they offered an hundred bullocks two hundred rams, four hundred lambs;

8 And twelve goats for the sin of all Israel, according to the number of the [*]chief of the tribes of Israel.

9 The priests also and the Levites stood arrayed in their vestments, according to their [*]kindreds, in the service of [e]the Lord God of Israel, according to the book of Moses: and the porters at every gate.

10 And the children of Israel [*]that were of the captivity held the passover the fourteenth day of the first month, after that the priests and the Levites were sanctified.

11 They that were of the captivity were not all sanctified together: but the Levites were all sanctified together.

12 And so they offered the passover for all them of the captivity, and for their brethren the priests, and for themselves.

13 And the children of Israel that came out of the captivity did eat, even all they that had separated themselves from the abominations of the people of the land, and sought the Lord.

14 And they kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days, making merry before the Lord,

15 For that he had turned the [*]counsel of the king of Assyria toward them, to strengthen their hands in the works of [e]the Lord God of Israel.

8

1 [*][a]And after these things, when Artexerxes the king of the Persians reigned came Esdras the son of Saraias, the son of [*]Ezerias, the son of Helchiah, the son of Salum,

2 The son of Sadduc, the son of Achitob, the son of Amarias, the son of [*]Ezias, the son of [*][b][*]Meremoth, the son of [*]Zaraias, the son of [*][*]Savias, the son of Boccas, the son of Abisum, the son of Phinees, the son of Eleazar, the son of Aaron [*]the chief priest.

3 This Esdras went up from Babylon, as a scribe, being very ready in the law of Moses, that was given by the God of Israel.

4 And the king did him honour: for he found grace in his sight in all his requests.

5 There went up with him also certain of the children of Israel, of the priest of the Levites, of the holy singers, porters, and [*]ministers of the temple, unto Jerusalem,

6 In the seventh year of the reign of Artexerxes, in the fifth month, this was the king’s seventh year; for they went from Babylon in the first day of the first month, and came to Jerusalem, according to the [*][d]prosperous journey which the Lord gave them.

7 For Esdras had very great skill, so that he omitted nothing of the law and commandments of the Lord, but taught all Israel the ordinances and judgments.

8 Now the copy of the [*]commission, which was written from Artexerxes the king, and came to Esdras the priest and [e]reader of the law of the Lord, is this that followeth;

9 King Artexerxes unto Esdras the priest and [e]reader of the law of the Lord sendeth greeting:

10 Having determined to deal graciously, I have given order, that such of the nation of the Jews, and of the priests and Levites being within our realm, as are willing and desirous should go with thee unto Jerusalem.

11 As many therefore as have a mind thereunto, let them depart with thee, as it hath seemed good both to me and my seven friends the counsellors;

12 That they may look unto the affairs of Judea and Jerusalem, agreeably to that which is in the law of the Lord;

13 And carry the gifts unto the Lord of Israel to Jerusalem, which I and my friends have vowed, and all the gold and silver that in the country of Babylon can be [*]found, to the Lord in Jerusalem,

14 With that also which is given of the people for the temple of the Lord their God at Jerusalem: and that silver and gold may be collected for bullocks, rams, and lambs, and things thereunto appertaining;

15 To the end that they may offer sacrifices unto the Lord upon the altar of the Lord their God, which is in Jerusalem.

16 And whatsoever thou and thy brethren will do [*]with the silver and gold, that do, according to the will of thy God.

17 And the holy vessels of the Lord, which are given thee for the use of the temple of thy God, which is in Jerusalem, thou shalt set before thy God in Jerusalem.

18 And whatsoever thing else thou shalt remember for the use of the temple of thy God, thou shalt give it out of the king’s treasury.

19 And I king Artexerxes have also commanded the keepers of the treasures in Syria and Phenice, that whatsoever Esdras the priest and the reader of the law of [f]the most high God shall send for, they should give it him with speed,

20 To the sum of an hundred talents of silver, likewise also of wheat even to an hundred [*]cors, and an hundred [g]pieces of wine, and [*]other things in abundance.

21 Let all things be performed after the law of God diligently unto [f]the most high God, that wrath come not upon the kingdom of the king and his sons.

22 I command you also, that ye require no tax, nor any other imposition, of any of the priests, or Levites, or holy singers, or porters, or ministers of the temple, or of any that have doings in this temple, and that no man have authority to impose any thing upon them.

23 And thou, Esdras, according to the wisdom of God ordain judges and justices, that they may judge in all Syria and Phenice [*]all those that know the law of thy God; and those that know it not thou shalt teach.

24 And whosoever shall transgress the law of thy God, and of the king, shall be punished diligently, whether it be by death, or other punishment, by penalty of money, or by imprisonment.

25 Then said Esdras the scribe, Blessed be the only Lord God of my fathers, who hath put these things into the heart of the king, to glorify his house that is in Jerusalem:

26 And hath honoured me in the sight of the king, and his counsellors, and all his friends and nobles.

27 Therefore was I encouraged by the help of the Lord my God, and gathered together men of Israel to go up with me.

28 [g]And these are the chief according to their families and [h]several dignities, that went up with me from Babylon in the reign of king Artexerxes:

29 Of the sons of Phinees, Gerson: of the sons of Ithamar, [i]Gamael: of the sons of David, [j]Lettus [k]the son of Sechenias:

30 [k]Of the sons of Pharez, Zacharias; and with him were counted an hundred and fifty men:

31 Of the sons of Pahath Moab, Eliaonias, the son of [l]Zaraias, and with him two hundred men:

32 [m]Of the sons of Zathoe, Sechenias the son of Jezelus, and with him three hundred men: of the sons of Adin, Obeth the son of Jonathan, and with him [*]two hundred and fifty men:

33 Of the sons of Elam, Josias son of [n]Gotholias, and with him seventy men:

34 Of the sons of Saphatias, [o]Zaraias son of Michael, and with him [p]threescore and ten men:

35 Of the sons of Joab, [q]Abadias son of [r]Jezelus, and with him two hundred and [s]twelve men:

36 [t]Of the sons of Banid, Assalimoth son of Josaphias, and with him an hundred and threescore men:

37 Of the sons of Babi, Zacharias son of Bebai, and with him twenty and eight men:

38 Of the sons of [u]Astath, Johannes son of [x]Acatan, and with him an hundred and ten men:

39 Of the sons of Adonikam the last, and these are the names of them, Eliphalet, Jewel, and [y]Samaias, and with them [z]seventy men:

40 Of the sons of [*]Bago, Uthi the son of Istalcurus, and with him seventy men.

41 And these I gathered together [*]to the river called Theras, where we pitched our tents three days: and then [*]I surveyed them.

42 [*]But when I had found there none of the priests and Levites,

43 Then sent I unto Eleazar, and [a]Iduel, and [b]Masman,

44 And Alnathan, and Mamaias, and [c]Joribas, and Nathan, Eunatan, Zacharias, and Mosollamon, principal men and learned.

45 And I bade them that they should go unto [d]Saddeus the captain, [e]who was in the place of [f]the treasury:

46 And commanded them that they should speak unto [d]Daddeus, and to [g]his brethren, and to the treasurers in that place, to send us such men as might execute the priests’ office in the house of the Lord.

47 And by the mighty hand of our Lord they brought unto us skilful men of the sons of [h]Moli the son of Levi, the son of Israel, [i]Asebebia, and his sons, and his brethren, who were eighteen.

48 [j]And Asebia, and Annus, and Osaias his brother, of the sons of Channuneus, and their sons, were twenty men.

49 And [l]of the servants of the temple whom David had ordained, and the principal men for the service of the Levites to wit, [k]the servants of the temple two hundred and twenty, the catalogue of whose names were shewed.

50 And there I [*]vowed a fast unto the young men before our Lord, to desire of him [l]a prosperous journey both for us and them that were with us, for our children, and for the [*]cattle:

51 For [m]I was ashamed to ask the king footmen, and horsemen, and conduct for safeguard against our adversaries.

52 For we had said unto the king, that the power of the Lord our God should be with them that seek him, to support them in all ways.

53 And again we besought our Lord as touching these things, and found him favourable unto us.

54 Then I separated twelve of the chief of the priests, [mm]Esebrias, and Assanias, and ten men of their brethren with them:

55 And I [n]weighed them the gold, and the silver, and the holy vessels of the house of our Lord, which the king, and his council, and the princes, and all Israel, had given.

56 And when I had [n]weighed it, I delivered unto them six hundred and fifty talents of silver, and silver vessels of an hundred talents, and an hundred talents of gold,

57 And twenty golden vessels, and [*]twelve vessels of brass, even of fine brass, glittering like gold.

58 And I said unto them, Both ye are holy unto the Lord, and the vessels are holy, and the gold and the silver is a vow unto the Lord, the Lord of our fathers.

59 Watch ye, and keep them till ye deliver them to the chief of the priests and Levites, and to the principal men of the families of Israel, in Jerusalem, into the chambers of the house of our God.

60 So the priests and the Levites, who had received the silver and the gold and the vessels, brought them unto Jerusalem, into the temple of the Lord.

61 And [o]from the river Theras we departed the twelfth day of the first month, and came to Jerusalem by the mighty hand of our Lord, which was with us: and from the [*][p]beginning of our journey the Lord delivered us from every enemy, and so we came to Jerusalem.

62 And when we had been there three days, the gold and silver that was [n]weighed was delivered in the house of our Lord on the fourth day [*]unto Marmoth the priest the son of Iri.

63 And with him was Eleazar the son of Phinees, and with them were Josabad the son of Jesu and [*]Moeth the son of Sabban, Levites: all was delivered them by number and weight.

64 And all the weight of them was written up the same hour.

65 Moreover they that were come out of the captivity offered sacrifice unto [q]the Lord God of Israel, even twelve bullocks for all Israel, fourscore and sixteen rams,

66 [*]Threescore and twelve lambs, goats for [r]a peace offering, twelve; all of them a sacrifice to the Lord.

67 And they delivered the king’s [s]commandments unto the king’s [t]stewards’ and to the governors of [u]Celosyria and Phenice; and they honoured the people and the temple of God.

68 [x]Now when these things were done, the rulers came unto me, and said,

69 The nation of Israel, the princes, the priests and Levites, have not put away from them the strange people of the land, nor the pollutions of the Gentiles to wit, of the Canaanites, Hittites, Pheresites, Jebusites, and the Moabites, Egyptians, and [y]Edomites.

70 For both they and their sons have married with their daughters, and the holy seed is mixed with the strange people of the land; and from the beginning of this matter the rulers and the great men have been partakers of this iniquity.

71 And as soon as I had heard these things, I rent my clothes, and the holy garment, and pulled off the hair from off my head and beard, and sat me down sad and [z]very heavy.

72 So all they that were then moved at the word of [q]the Lord God of Israel assembled unto me, whilst I mourned for the iniquity: but I sat still [z]full of heaviness until the evening sacrifice.

73 Then rising up from [a]the fast with my clothes and the holy garment rent, and bowing my knees, and stretching forth my hands unto the Lord,

74 I said, O Lord, I am confounded and [b]ashamed before thy face;

75 For our sins [*]are multiplied above our heads, and our ignorances have reached up unto heaven.

76 For ever since the time of our fathers we have been and are in great sin, even unto this day.

77 And for our sins and our fathers’ we with our brethren and our kings and our priests were given up unto the kings of the earth, to the sword, and to captivity, and [c]for a prey with shame, unto this day.

78 And now in some measure hath mercy been shewed unto us from thee, O Lord, that there should be left us a root and a name in the place of thy sanctuary;

79 And to discover unto us a light in the house of the Lord our God, and [d]to give us [*]food in the time of our servitude.

80 Yea, when we were in bondage, we were not forsaken of our Lord; but he made us gracious before the kings of Persia, [d]so that they gave us food;

81 Yea, and honoured the temple of our Lord, and raised up the desolate Sion, that they have given us a sure abiding in Jewry and Jerusalem.

82 And now, O Lord, what shall we say, having these things? for we have transgressed thy [e]commandments, which thou gavest by the hand of thy servants the prophets, saying,

83 That the land, which ye enter into to possess as an heritage, is a land polluted with the pollutions of the strangers of the land, and they have filled it with their uncleanness.

84 Therefore now shall ye not join your daughters unto their sons, neither shall ye take their daughters unto your sons.

85 Moreover ye shall never seek to have peace with them, that ye may be strong, and eat the good things of the land, and that ye may leave the inheritance of the land unto your children for evermore.

86 And all that is befallen is done unto us for our wicked works and great sins; for thou, O Lord, didst make our sins light,

87 And didst give unto us such [f]a root: but we have turned back again to transgress thy law, and to mingle ourselves with the uncleanness of the nations of the land.

88 [*]Mightest not thou be angry with us to destroy us, till thou hadst [g]left us neither [f]root, seed, nor name?

89 O Lord of Israel, thou art true: for we are left [f]a root this day.

90 Behold, now are we before thee in our iniquities, for we cannot stand any longer by reason of these things before thee.

91 [h]And as Esdras in his prayer made his confession, weeping, and lying flat upon the ground before the temple, there gathered unto him from Jerusalem a very great multitude of men and women and children: for there was great weeping among the multitude.

92 Then Jechonias the son of Jeelus, one of the sons of Israel, called out, and said, O Esdras, we have sinned against the Lord God, we have married strange women of the nations of the land, and now is all Israel [*]aloft.

93 Let us make an oath to the Lord, that we will put away all our wives, which we have taken of the heathen, with their children,

94 Like as thou hast decreed, and as many as do obey the law of the Lord.

95 Arise and put in execution: for to thee doth this matter appertain, and we will be with thee: do valiantly.

96 So Esdras arose, and took an oath of the chief of the priests and Levites [*]of all Israel to do after these things; and so they sware.

9

1 Then Esdras rising from the court of the temple went to the chamber of Joanan the son of Eliasib,

2 And remained there, and did eat no meat nor drink water, mourning for the great iniquities of the multitude.

3 And there was a proclamation in all Jewry and Jerusalem to all them that were of the captivity, that they should be gathered together at Jerusalem:

4 And that whosoever met not there within two or three days according as the elders that bare rule appointed, their cattle should be seized to the use of the temple, and himself [*]cast out from them that were of the captivity.

5 [a]And in three days were all they of the tribe of Judah and Benjamin gathered together at Jerusalem the twentieth day of the ninth month.

6 And all the multitude sat trembling in the broad court of the temple because of the present foul weather.

7 So Esdras arose up, and said unto them, Ye have transgressed the law in marrying strange wives, thereby to increase the sins of Israel.

8 And now [b]by confessing give glory unto the Lord God of our fathers,

9 And do his will, and separate yourselves from the heathen of the land, and from the strange women.

10 Then cried the whole multitude, and said with a loud voice, Like as thou hast spoken, so will we do.

11 But forasmuch as the people are many, and it is foul weather, so that we cannot stand without, and this is not a work of a day or two, seeing our sin in these things is spread far:

12 Therefore let the rulers of the multitude [*]stay, and let all them of our habitations that have strange wives come at the time appointed,

13 And with them the [c]rulers and judges of every place, till we turn away the wrath of the Lord from us for this matter.

14 Then Jonathan the son of Azael and Ezechias the son of Theocanus accordingly took this matter upon them: and Mosollam and Levis and Sabbatheus helped them.

15 And they that were of the captivity did according to all these things.

16 And Esdras the priest chose unto him the principal men of their families, all by name: and in the first day of the tenth month they sat together to examine the matter.

17 [*]So their cause that held strange wives was brought to an end [d]in the first day of the first month.

18 And of the priests that were come together, and had strange wives, there were found:

19 Of the sons of Jesus the son of Josedec, and his brethren; [e]Matthelas and Eleazar, and [f]Joribus and [g]Joadanus.

20 And they gave their hands to put away their wives and to offer [*]rams to make reconcilement for their [*][gg]errors.

21 And of the sons of Emmer; Ananias, and Zabdeus, and [h]Eanes, and [i]Sameius, and [j]Hiereel, and [k]Azarias.

22 And of the sons of [l]Phaisur; Elionas, Massias Israel, and Nathanael, and [m]Ocidelus and [n]Talsas.

23 And of the Levites; Jozabad, and Semis, and [o]Colius, who was called [p]Calitas, and [q]Patheus, and Judas, and Jonas.

24 Of the holy singers; [r]Eleazurus, Bacchurus.

25 Of the porters; Sallumus, and [s]Tolbanes.

26 Of them of Israel, of the sons of [t]Phoros; [u]Hiermas, and [w]Eddias, and Melchias, and [x]Maelus, and Eleazar, and [y]Asibias, and Baanias.

27 Of the sons of Ela; Matthanias, Zacharias, and [z]Hierielus, and Hieremoth, and [a]Aedias.

28 And of the sons of [b]Zamoth; [c]Eliadas, [d]Elisimus, [e]Othonias, Jarimoth, and [f]Sabatus, and [g]Sardeus.

29 Of the sons of Babai; Johannes, and Ananias and [h]Josabad, and [i]Amatheis.

30 Of the sons of [k]Mani; [l]Olamus, [m]Mamuchus, [n]Jedeus, Jasubus, [o]Jasael, and Hieremoth.

31 [*]And of the sons of Addi; Naathus, and Moosias, Lacunus, and Naidus, and Mathanias, and Sesthel, Balnuus, and Manasseas.

32 And of the sons of Annas; Elionas and Aseas, and Melchias, and Sabbeus, and Simon Chosameus.

33 And of the sons of Asom; [p]Altaneus, and [q]Matthias, and [r]Baanaia, Eliphalet, and Manasses, and Semei.

34 And of the sons of Maani; Jeremias, Momdis, Omaerus, Juel, Mabdai, and Pelias, and Anos, Carabasion, and Enasibus, and Mamnitanaimus, Eliasis, Bannus, Eliali, Samis, Selemias, Nathanias: and [s]of the sons of Ozora; Sesis, Esril, Azaelus, Samatus, Zambis, Josephus.

35 And of the sons of Ethma; Mazitias, Zabadaias, Edes, Juel, Banaias.

36 All these had taken strange wives, and they put them away with their children.

37 [t]And the priests and Levites, and they that were of Israel, dwelt in Jerusalem, and in the country, [u]in the first day of the seventh month: so the children of Israel were in their [*][w]habitations.

38 [x]And the whole multitude came together with one accord into [y]the broad place of the holy porch [z]toward the east:

39 [*]And they spake unto Esdras the priest and [a]reader, that he would bring the law of Moses, that was given of [b]the Lord God of Israel.

40 So Esdras the chief priest brought the law unto the whole multitude from man to woman, and to all the priests, to hear law [c]in the first day of the seventh month.

41 And he read in [d]the broad court before the holy porch from morning unto midday, before both men and women; and the multitude gave heed unto the law.

42 And Esdras the priest and [a]reader of the law stood up upon a pulpit of wood, which was made for that purpose.

43 And there stood up by him Mattathias, Sammus, Ananias, Azarias, Urias, [e]Ezecias, [f]Balasamus, upon the right hand:

44 And upon his left hand stood [g]Phaldaius, Misael, Melchias, [h]Lothasubus, and [i]Nabarias.

45 Then took Esdras the book of the law before the multitude: for he sat [*]honourably in the first place in the sight of them all.

46 And when he opened the law, they stood all straight up. So Esdras blessed the Lord God most High, the God of hosts, [k]Almighty.

47 And all the people answered, Amen; and lifting up their hands they fell to the ground, and worshipped the Lord.

48 Also Jesus, Anus, Sarabias, Adinus, Jacubus, Sabateas, [l]Auteas, Maianeas, and Calitas, Asrias, and Joazabdus, and Ananias, Biatas, the Levites, taught the law of the Lord, making them withal to [m]understand it.

49 [*]Then spake [n]Attharates unto Esdras the [o]chief priest, and [a]reader, and to the Levites that taught the multitude, even to all, saying,

50 This day is holy unto the Lord; (for they all wept when they heard the law:)

51 Go then, and eat the fat, and drink the sweet, and send part to [*]them that have nothing;

52 For this day is holy unto the Lord: and be not sorrowful; for the Lord will bring you to honour.

53 So the Levites published all things to the people, saying, This day is holy to the Lord; be not sorrowful.

54 Then went they their way, every one to eat and drink, and make merry, and to give [p]part to them that had nothing, and to make great cheer;

55 Because they [m]understood the words wherein they were instructed, and for the which they had been assembled.

a 1.1 2 Kin. 23. 21. To ver. 22, 2 Chr. 35. 1–19.

b 1.2 2 Chr. 31. 2. Neh. 13. 30. ver. 16. Luke 1. 5, 8 in the Gk.

c 1.4 2 Chr. 35. 3. Comp. Ex. 18. 4.

d 1.4 ver. 10, 11. ch. 5. 4 (Gk.). & 8. 28.

e 1.5 Comp. 2 Chr. 35. 4.

d 1.5 ver. 10, 11. ch. 5. 4 (Gk.). & 8. 28.

f 1.7 Gk. as ver. 19. See Judg. 20. 48 marg.

* 1.8 Or, Jehiel. 2 Chr. 35. 8.

* 1.9 [Or,] five hundred calves. 2 Chr. 35. 9.

d 1.10 ver. 10, 11. ch. 5. 4 (Gk.). & 8. 28.

d 1.11 ver. 10, 11. ch. 5. 4 (Gk.). & 8. 28.

* 1.11 2 Chr. 35. 12, and so of the bullocks.

g 1.12 Comp. 2 Chr. 35. 13.

* 1.12 [Or,] with good speed, or, willingly. 2 Chr. 35. 13.

* 1.15 2 Chr. 35. 15, of David and Asaph.

h 1.15 See 1 Chr. 6. 39.

* 1.15 2 Chr. 35. 15, the king’s seer.

b 1.16 2 Chr. 31. 2. Neh. 13. 30. ver. 16. Luke 1. 5, 8 in the Gk.

f 1.19 Gk. as ver. 19. See Judg. 20. 48 marg.

i 1.19 Gk. as in Luke 22. 1.

k 1.20 2 Kin. 23. 22, 23.

l 1.23 2 Kin. 23. 24–28.

l 1.24 2 Kin. 23. 24–28.

* 1.24 Or, were ungodly. ver. 49. 2 Pet. 2. 6. Jude 15 in the Gk.

* 1.24 Or, sensibly.

m 1.25 2 Kin. 23. 29, 30. To ver. 33, 2 Chr. 35. 20–27.

* 1.26 About B.C. 610.

n 1.27 So 2 Chr. 13. 12. Acts 5. 39.

o 1.32 From 2 Chr. 35. 25?

p 1.34 To ver. 38, 2 Kin. 23. 30–35. 2 Chr. 36. 1–4.

q 1.34 See 2 Macc. 9. 23.

q 1.37 See 2 Macc. 9. 23.

r 1.39 To ver. 43, 2 Kin. 23. 36–24. 6. 2 Chr. 36. 5–8.

* 1.39 2 Chr. 36. 4, 5. Jehoiakim, or, Eliakim.

* 1.40 About B.C. 606.

* 1.43 About B.C. 599.

q 1.43 See 2 Macc. 9. 23.

s 1.43 2 Kin. 24. 8. Comp. 2 Chr. 36. 9.

t 1.44 To ver. 58, 2 Chr. 36. 9–21. Comp. 2 Kin. 24. 8–25. 21.

u 1.45 Comp. ver. 41, 54.

q 1.46 See 2 Macc. 9. 23.

* 1.48 B.C. 593.

x 1.49 ver. 24 (Gk.).

y 1.51 Gal. 6. 7 (Gk.).

u 1.54 Comp. ver. 41, 54.

* 1.55 About B.C. 588.

z 1.57 Jer. 25. 11. & 29. 10.

* 1.58 Or, keep sabbath. 2 Chr. 36. 21 (Heb. and Gk.).

* 2.1 About B.C. 536.

a 2.1 2 Chr. 36. 22, 23. To ver. 15, Ezra 1. 1–11.

c 2.2 Gk. as ver. 2, not as ver. 9.

b 2.3 See 2 Macc. 9. 23.

* 2.5 Or, this.

c 2.8 Gk. as ver. 2, not as ver. 9.

* 2.9 Heb. substance, Ezra 1. 6.

d 2.10 ch. 1. 41. Comp. ch. 4. 44.

d 2.10 ch. 1. 41. Comp. ch. 4. 44.

e 2.10 1 Macc. 1. 47 (Gk.). 1 Cor. 8. 10.

* 2.12 Shashbazzar, Ezra 1. 8. Greek, the first part of the word is corruptly joined to the word going before. [Comp. ch. 6. 18].

* 2.13 Heb. knives, Ezra 1. 9.

* 2.13 Ezra 1. 10, but four hundred and ten.

* 2.14 Ezra 1. 11, but five thousand four hundred.

* 2.16 About B.C. 522.

f 2.16 To ver. 30, Ezra 4. 7–24.

* 2.16 Bahumus, and the name which followeth is but an epithet to the former, Ezra 4. [8], 9. [So ver. 25].

* 2.16 Shimsai, Ezra 4. 8, 9.

g 2.16 ver. 17, 25, 30. Acts 19. 35 in the Gk.

h 2.17 Gk. more full in ver. 25.

g 2.17 ver. 17, 25, 30. Acts 19. 35 in the Gk.

i 2.17 ver. 24, 27. ch. 4. 48. & 6. 29. & 7. 1. & 8. 67. 2 Macc. 3. 5, 8. & 4. 4. & 8. 8. & 10. 11. So 1 Macc. 10. 69.

i 2.17 ver. 24, 27. ch. 4. 48. & 6. 29. & 7. 1. & 8. 67. 2 Macc. 3. 5, 8. & 4. 4. & 8. 8. & 10. 11. So 1 Macc. 10. 69.

k 2.17 See Acts 11. 19.

i 2.24 ver. 24, 27. ch. 4. 48. & 6. 29. & 7. 1. & 8. 67. 2 Macc. 3. 5, 8. & 4. 4. & 8. 8. & 10. 11. So 1 Macc. 10. 69.

h 2.25 Gk. more full in ver. 25.

l 2.25 ver. 16 marg.

l 2.25 ver. 16 marg.

g 2.25 ver. 17, 25, 30. Acts 19. 35 in the Gk.

i 2.27 ver. 24, 27. ch. 4. 48. & 6. 29. & 7. 1. & 8. 67. 2 Macc. 3. 5, 8. & 4. 4. & 8. 8. & 10. 11. So 1 Macc. 10. 69.

g 2.30 ver. 17, 25, 30. Acts 19. 35 in the Gk.

* 2.30 Or, a great number of soldiers.

* 2.30 About B.C. 520.

a 3.1 Luke 5. 29.

b 3.1 See Rev. 6. 15.

c 3.1 See Acts 2. 9.

k 3.2 ver. 2. So ch. 4. 47, 48, 49.

d 3.2 See Esther 1. 1.

e 3.3 Judith 13. 1. Luke 12. 36 in the Gk. See Wisd. 2. 1.

e 3.3 Judith 13. 1. Luke 12. 36 in the Gk. See Wisd. 2. 1.

f 3.3 Acts 16. 27 (Gk.).

g 3.6 See Dan. 5. 29.

h 3.6 So Gen. 41. 42, 43.

h 3.6 So Gen. 41. 42, 43.

g 3.6 See Dan. 5. 29.

h 3.6 So Gen. 41. 42, 43.

i 3.9 See Luke 12. 20 marg.

j 3.9 Dan. 6. 2.

b 3.9 See Rev. 6. 15.

b 3.14 See Rev. 6. 15.

k 3.14 ver. 2. So ch. 4. 47, 48, 49.

* 3.15 Or, council.

l 3.20 So Eccles. 10. 19. See Ps. 104. 15.

m 3.20 Wisd. 2. 9 marg. Ecclus. 13. 8 (Engl.).

* 4.2 Or, have the command.

a 4.9 Comp. Deut. 20. 19, 20.

b 4.10 Gk. as ver. 31.

c 4.11 ch. 3. 4.

* 4.11 Or, can.

d 4.13 See Ezra 3. 2 marg.

* 4.14 Gk. is of force.

e 4.17 Prov. 31. 13, 19.

f 4.19 ver. 31 (Gk.).

g 4.20 Gen. 2. 24.

* 4.26 Or, grown desperate.

h 4.26 Gen. 29. 20.

* 4.29 Joseph. Antiq. lib. 11. cap. 3. Rabsaces Themasius.

i 4.29 See Ps. 45. 9.

k 4.30 See Matt. 26. 67 text.

* 4.31 Or, hereat. Gk. as ver. 10.

f 4.31 ver. 31 (Gk.).

* 4.31 Or, be friends with him. Gk. as Matt. 5. 24.

l 4.33 See Rev. 6. 15.

* 4.36 Or, praiseth the truth, Athanasius.

m 4.37 So John 8. 44. 1 John 2. 4.

n 4.39 Wisd. 6. 7. Ecclus. 35. 12–16. See Deut. 10. 17.

o 4.39 See Rom. 1. 32.

p 4.40 Comp. 1 Chr. 29. 11.

q 4.40 See Deut. 32. 4.

r 4.42 ch. 3. 5, 6.

s 4.42 ch. 3. 7. Comp. Gen. 41. 39, 40.

s 4.42 ch. 3. 7. Comp. Gen. 41. 39, 40.

t 4.44 Comp. ch. 1. 41. & 2. 10. & 6. 18, 19 with ver. 57.

u 4.45 See Ps. 137. 7. Comp. ver. 50.

x 4.46 ver. 42.

y 4.46 Dan. 4. 37. ver. 58. Tobit 13. 7, 11.

z 4.47 ver. 49 (Gk.). So ch. 3. 2, 14.

z 4.47 ver. 49 (Gk.). So ch. 3. 2, 14.

z 4.48 ver. 49 (Gk.). So ch. 3. 2, 14.

a 4.48 See ch. 2. 17.

b 4.48 ch. 5. 55. See Judg. 9. 15.

z 4.49 ver. 49 (Gk.). So ch. 3. 2, 14.

* 4.49 Or, steward. ver. 47. ch. 8. 67. Rom. 16. 23 (Gk.).

u 4.50 See Ps. 137. 7. Comp. ver. 50.

* 4.56 Or, portions of land. Deut. 10. 9 (Gk.).

c 4.56 See 1 Macc. 3. 28.

t 4.57 Comp. ch. 1. 41. & 2. 10. & 6. 18, 19 with ver. 57.

d 4.58 See Luke 6. 20.

e 4.58 See Dan. 6. 10.

y 4.58 Dan. 4. 37. ver. 58. Tobit 13. 7, 11.

f 4.59 Matt. 6. 13.

g 4.60 Comp. 1 Kin. 3. 12.

h 4.63 1 Kin. 8. 43. See 1 Kin. 8. 29.

i 4.63 ch. 5. 2.

a 5.2 Comp. Neh. 2. 9.

b 5.2 ch. 4. 63.

c 5.2 Gk. as Gen. 31. 27. 1 Sam. 18. 6, &c.

d 5.2 Isai. 5. 12 (Gk.). So Ezek. 28. 13.

d 5.2 Isai. 5. 12 (Gk.). So Ezek. 28. 13.

e 5.4 ch. 1. 5, 11 (Gk.).

f 5.5 Neh. 12. 1.

g 5.5 1 Chr. 6. 4, 14, 15.

h 5.5 ver. 48. Ezra 3. 2 marg. See Neh. 12. 7.

g 5.5 1 Chr. 6. 4, 14, 15.

* 5.5 [Or,] Joacim and Zorobabel. This place is corrupt: for Joacim was the son of Jeshua, Neh. 12. 10, and not Zorobabel, who was of the tribe of Judah. Comp. Judith 4. 6.

i 5.5 ver. 48. See 1 Chr. 3. 17, 19.

i 5.5 ver. 48. See 1 Chr. 3. 17, 19.

k 5.5 1 Chr. 2. 5, 9, &c.

* 5.6 Zorobabel.

l 5.6 ch. 2. 30.

m 5.6 See Neh. 2. 1.

n 5.7 To ver. 46, Ezra 2. 1–70. Neh. 7. 6–73.

* 5.8 About B.C. 536.

o 5.8 Saraiah.

p 5.8 Or, Mispar.

q 5.8 Or, Reelaiah.

r 5.8 Gk. as ver. 9.

r 5.9 Gk. as ver. 9.

s 5.9 Parosh, Ezra 2. 3. Neh. 7. 8, where for brevity look for the true numbers of the particulars following : for here they vary much, and the names much more.

t 5.9 Shephatia[h].

u 5.9 Or, three hundred seventy-two.

x 5.12 Zattu.

y 5.12 Zacchai.

z 5.13 Azgad.

a 5.14 Bigui.

b 5.15 Ater-hezekiah.

c 5.16 Bezai.

d 5.17 Bethlehem.

e 5.18 Azmaveth.

f 5.19 Kirjathjarim.

g 5.20 Rama[h].

h 5.20 Gaba.

i 5.21 Michmas.

k 5.21 Bethel.

l 5.21 Magbish.

m 5.22 Lodhadid.

n 5.23 Senaah.

o 5.24 Jedaiah. See Ezra 2. 36.

p 5.24 Immer.

q 5.25 Pashur.

r 5.25 Harim.

s 5.25 Or, two hundred and seventeen, according to some copies.

t 5.26 Thus it is read, Ezra 2. 40, the sons of Jeshua, and Kadmiel, of the sons of Hodaviah.

u 5.28 Shallum.

x 5.28 Ater.

y 5.28 Akkub.

z 5.28 Hatita.

a 5.28 Shobai.

b 5.29 Ziha.

c 5.29 Hasupha.

d 5.29 Keros.

e 5.29 Siaha.

f 5.29 Padon.

g 5.29 Agabah.

h 5.30 Akkub.

i 5.30 Hagab.

k 5.30 Shamlai.

l 5.30 Giddel.

m 5.30 Gahar.

n 5.31 Reaiah.

o 5.31 Rezin.

p 5.31 Nekoda.

q 5.31 Gazzam.

r 5.31 Huzza.

s 5.31 Paseah.

t 5.31 Besai.

u 5.31 Asnah.

x 5.31 Mehunim.

y 5.31 Nephusim.

z 5.31 Bakbuk.

a 5.31 Hakupha.

b 5.31 Harhur.

c 5.31 Bazluth.

d 5.32 Mehida.

e 5.32 Harsha.

f 5.32 Barkos.

g 5.32 Sisera.

h 5.32 Thamah.

i 5.32 Neziah.

k 5.33 Sophereth.

l 5.33 Peruda.

m 5.33 Jaalah.

n 5.33 Darkon.

o 5.33 Giddel.

p 5.33 Shephatiah.

q 5.34 Hattil.

r 5.34 Pochereth Hazzebaim, Ezra 2. 57 (Heb.).

s 5.37 Delaiah.

t 5.37 Tobiah.

u 5.37 Nekoda.

x 5.38 Habaiah.

y 5.38 Koz.

z 5.38 Barzillai.

* 5.40 Nehemias, who also is Atharias: two of one: Ezra 2. 63. See Neh. 8. 9. Comp. ch. 9. 49.

* 5.40 Heb. Urim and Thummim. See Ex. 28. 30.

a 5.41 ver. 1, 42 (Gk.).

a 5.42 ver. 1, 42 (Gk.).

b 5.42 Comp. Ezra 2. 65. Neh. 7. 67.

c 5.43 Comp. Ezra 2. 66, 67. Neh. 7. 68, 69.

c 5.43 Comp. Ezra 2. 66, 67. Neh. 7. 68, 69.

* 5.43 asses. Ezra 2. 67. Neh. 7. 69.

h 5.44 Thamah.

d 5.45 Luke 19. 13 marg.,

e 5.47 To ver. 55, Ezra 3. 1–7. So Neh. 7. 73. ch. 9. 37.

* 5.47 B.C 535.

f 5.47 ch. 6. 32. See John 16. 32 marg.

* 5.47 Or, before the east gate.

g 5.48 See ver. 5.

g 5.48 See ver. 5.

h 5.50 Gk. as ver. 44.

* 5.52 Or, daily sacrifice. ver. 50? Ex. 29. 38?

* 5.53 Gr. hallowed.

i 5.53 ver. 47.

k 5.55 ch. 4. 48. See Judg. 9. 15.

l 5.55 So 2 Chr. 2. 16.

m 5.55 See Josh. 19. 46.

n 5.56 To ver. 65, Ezra 3. 8–13.

* 5.58 Or, overseers, or, encouragers of them that wrought in the house of the Lord.

* 5.60 Or, after the manner of David king of Israel.

* 5.65 Or, discerned. See John 8. 43.

o 5.66 To ver. 73, Ezra 4. 1–5.

* 5.69 Or, Esarhaddon, Ezra 4. 2.

* 5.70 About B.C. 534.

* 5.73 [Or,] until the second year of Darius, Ezra 4. 5, 6, 7, 24.

* 6.1 About B.C. 520.

a 6.1 Comp. ch. 5. 73. Ezra 4. 24.

b 6.1 To ver. 22, Ezra 5. 1–17.

* 6.1 Or, Iddo. Ezra 5. 1.

* 6.1 Or, which was called on them.

c 6.1 Rather as Ezra 5. 1.

* 6.3 Or, Tatnai. Ezra 5. 3.

* 6.3 Or, Shetharboznai. Ezra 5. 3.

e 6.5 ch. 7. 2. Gk. as ver. 5, 11, 27. ch. 9. 12. See Judith 6. 16.

d 6.5 See Luke 1. 68.

* 6.6 About B.C. 519.

e 6.8 ch. 7. 2. Gk. as ver. 5, 11, 27. ch. 9. 12. See Judith 6. 16.

e 6.11 ch. 7. 2. Gk. as ver. 5, 11, 27. ch. 9. 12. See Judith 6. 16.

f 6.15 Heb. 3. 16.

g 6.18 See ch. 4. 44.

h 6.18 Comp. ch. 4. 44.

* 6.18 Or, Zorobabel, which is also Sanabassar the ruler, so as Zorobabel seemeth to be added to the text, Ezra 1. 8. Comp. ch. 2. 12. ver. 20.

* 6.21 Or, rolls. ver. 23.

i 6.23 To ver. 34, Ezra 6. 1–12.

k 6.23 Gk. as ver. 21.

* 6.23 Or, place.

l 6.24 Comp. Num. 16. 46.

e 6.27 ch. 7. 2. Gk. as ver. 5, 11, 27. ch. 9. 12. See Judith 6. 16.

m 6.29 See ch. 2. 17.

* 6.31 [Or,] drink-offerings.

n 6.31 ch. 8. 19, 21. Judith 13. 18. Esther 16. 16. See Mark 5. 7.

o 6.32 See ch. 5. 47.

a 7.1 To ver. 15, Ezra 6. 13–22.

b 7.1 See ch. 2. 17.

c 7.2 See ch. 6. 8.

* 7.4 Or, the decree.

d 7.4 ch. 6. 22. 2 Macc. 4. 39.

* 7.5 B.C. 515.

* 7.5 Heb. the third day, Ezra 6. 15.

* 7.8 Or, tribes.

* 7.9 Chald. divisions, Ezra 6. 18.

e 7.9 ver. 15. Luke 1. 68.

* 7.10 Or, with those that, &c.

* 7.15 Or, mind.

e 7.15 ver. 15. Luke 1. 68.

* 8.1 About B.C. 457.

a 8.1 To ver. 27, Ezra 7. 1–28.

* 8.1 Azarias.

* 8.2 Ezias.

* 8.2 Meraioth.

b 8.2 Ezra 7. 3.

* 8.2 Some copies want these three names.

* 8.2 Some copies want these three names.

* 8.2 c Uzzi.

* 8.2 Some copies want these three names.

* 8.2 Heb. was first, Ezra 7. 5.

* 8.5 Or, Nethinims. Ezra 7. 7. So ver. 22, 49 (Gk.).

* 8.6 Or, success. Ecclus. 10. 5.

d 8.6 ver. 50.

* 8.8 Or, decree. ver. 67, 82. 2 Macc. 7. 30 in the Gk.

e 8.8 ch. 9. 39, 42, 49.

e 8.9 ch. 9. 39, 42, 49.

* 8.13 Or, got.

* 8.16 [Or,] with the rest of, Ezra 7. 18.

f 8.19 ch. 6. 31. See Mark 5. 7.

* 8.20 Or, measures.

g 8.20 See John 2. 6.

* 8.20 Or, salt, Ezra 7. 22.

f 8.21 ch. 6. 31. See Mark 5. 7.

* 8.23 Chald. of [all] those that know, Ezra 7. 25.

g 8.28 To ver. 67, Ezra 8. 1–36.

h 8.28 See ch. 1. 4.

i 8.29 Or, Daniel.

j 8.29 Or, Chattus.

k 8.29 Ezra 8. 3, of the sons of Shechaniah, of the sons of Pharosh.

k 8.30 Ezra 8. 3, of the sons of Shechaniah, of the sons of Pharosh.

l 8.31 Zerachaiah. [Ezra 8. 4 (Heb.)].

m 8.32 Or, of the sons of Shechaniah the son of Jahaziel.

* 8.32 Heb. fifty men. [Ezra 8. 6].

n 8.33 Or, Athaliah.

o 8.34 Or, Zebadiah.

p 8.34 Or, four-score men.

q 8.35 Or, Obadiah.

r 8.35 Or, Jehiel.

s 8.35 Or, eighteen men.

t 8.36 Or, of the sons of Shelomith, the son of Josiphiah.

u 8.38 Or, Azgad.

x 8.38 Or, Catan. [Comp. Ezra 8. 12].

y 8.39 Or, Shemaia[h].

z 8.39 Or, sixty men.

* 8.40 [Heb. Bigvai].

* 8.41 Or, to the river called Ahava, Ezra 8. 15.

* 8.41 Or, he numbered the people and the priests : but found none of the sons of Levi. [Comp. Ezra 8. 15].

* 8.42 Or, he numbered the people and the priests : but found none of the sons of Levi. [Comp. Ezra 8. 15].

a 8.43 Or, Ariel.

b 8.43 Or, Shemaiah.

c 8.44 Or, Jarib. These men’s names with their generations are rightly distinguished, Ezra 8. 16.

d 8.45 Or, Iddo.

e 8.45 Or, of.

f 8.45 Or, Casiphia.

d 8.46 Or, Iddo.

g 8.46 Or, the Nethinims at the place of Casiphia.

h 8.47 Or, Machli. [Ezra 8. 18 (Heb.)].

i 8.47 Or, Sherebia[h]. Ezra 8. 18.

j 8.48 Or, Also Hashabia[h], and with him Jeshaiah of the sons of Merari with his brethren, Ezra 8. 19.

l 8.49 Zerachaiah. [Ezra 8. 4 (Heb.)].

k 8.49 See ver. 5.

* 8.50 [Or,] proclaimed. [Ezra 8. 21].

l 8.50 ver. 6.

* 8.50 Heb. substance. [Ezra 8. 21].

m 8.51 ver. 74.

mm 8.54 Or, Sherebiah and Hashabiah. Ezra 8. 24.

n 8.55 ver. 56, 62. See Matt. 26. 15 (Gk.).

n 8.56 ver. 56, 62. See Matt. 26. 15 (Gk.).

* 8.57 Heb. two vessels, Ezra 8. 27.

o 8.61 ver. 41.

* 8.61 [Or,] dangers in the way.

p 8.61 1 Macc. 5. 46 (Gk.).

n 8.62 ver. 56, 62. See Matt. 26. 15 (Gk.).

* 8.62 Or, unto Meremoth the son of Uriah the priest. [Ezra 8. 33].

* 8.63 [Or,] Noadiah the son of Binnui. [Ezra 8. 33].

q 8.65 So ver. 72. ch. 9. 39. Luke 1. 68.

* 8.66 Heb. Seventy-seven lambs, twelve hegoats for a sin offering, Ezra 8. 35.

r 8.66 Gk. as Gk. of Ex. 20. 24. & 24. 5, &c.

s 8.67 See ver. 8.

t 8.67 ch. 4. 49 marg.

u 8.67 See ch. 2. 17.

x 8.68 To ver. 90, Ezra 9. 1–15.

y 8.69 Comp. Ezra 9. 1.

z 8.71 ver. 72. Matt. 26. 38. Mark 6. 26. & 14. 34. Luke 18. 23, 24 in the Gk.

q 8.72 So ver. 72. ch. 9. 39. Luke 1. 68.

z 8.72 ver. 72. Matt. 26. 38. Mark 6. 26. & 14. 34. Luke 18. 23, 24 in the Gk.

a 8.73 Comp. Ezra 9. 5.

b 8.74 ver. 51.

* 8.75 Gk. have abounded. Rom. 5. 20.

c 8.77 2 Esdr. 2. 6. Judith 4. 12 (Gk.). & 7. 26 (Gk.). & 9. 4. & 16. 5.

d 8.79 ver. 80.

* 8.79 Heb. life. Ezra 9. 8, [9].

d 8.80 ver. 80.

e 8.82 See ver 8.

f 8.87 ver. 78, 88, 89. See Isai. 27. 6.

* 8.88 Or, Be not angry, &c.

g 8.88 Mal. 4. 1.

f 8.88 ver. 78, 88, 89. See Isai. 27. 6.

f 8.89 ver. 78, 88, 89. See Isai. 27. 6.

h 8.91 To ch. 10. 4, Ezra 10. 1–8.

* 8.92 Or, exalted. Deut. 28. 13 (Heb. & Gk.). Baruch 2. 5. Comp. Ezra 10. 2.

* 8.96 Heb. and of all Israel, Ezra 10. 5.

* 9.4 [Or,]utterly destroyed. But comp. Ezra 10. 8 (Heb.).

a 9.5 To ver. 36, Ezra 10. 9–44.

b 9.8 See Josh. 7. 19.

* 9.12 Or, stand. Gk. as ver. 11.

c 9.13 Gk. as ch. 6. 8, not as ver. 12.

* 9.17 About B.C. 456.

d 9.17 Rather as Ezra 10. 17 (Heb. & Gk.).

e 9.19 Maaseiah.

f 9.19 Jarib.

g 9.19 Gedaliah.

* 9.20 Heb. a ram. [Ezra 10. 19].

* 9.20 Or, purification.

gg 9.20 [Comp. Gk. with Lev. 4. 22, 23 (Heb.)].

h 9.21 Harim.

i 9.21 Maaseiah.

j 9.21 Jehiel.

k 9.21 Uzziah.

l 9.22 Pashur.

m 9.22 Jozabad.

n 9.22 Elasah.

o 9.23 Kelaiah.

p 9.23 Kelita.

q 9.23 Pethahiah.

r 9.24 Eliashib.

s 9.25 Telem.

t 9.26 Parosh.

u 9.26 Ramiah.

w 9.26 Jeziah.

x 9.26 Miamin.

y 9.26 Malchiah.

z 9.27 Jehiel.

a 9.27 Abdi.

b 9.28 Zattu.

c 9.28 Elioenai.

d 9.28 Eliashib.

e 9.28 Mattaniah.

f 9.28 Zabad.

g 9.28 Aziza.

h 9.29 Zabbai.

i 9.29 Athlai.

k 9.30 Bani.

l 9.30 Meshullam.

m 9.30 Malluch.

n 9.30 Adaiah.

o 9.30 Sheal.

* 9.31 Of the names in ver. 31, 32, 34, 35, see Ezra 10. 30, 31, 34–43.

p 9.33 Mattenai. [Ezra 10. 33].

q 9.33 Mattathah.

r 9.33 Zabad.

s 9.34 Ezra 10. 40 marg.

t 9.37 Neh. 7. 73. So ch. 5. 46, 47.

u 9.37 ver. 40.

* 9.37 Or, villages. Gk. not as ch. 5. 46.

w 9.37 ver. 12.

x 9.38 To ver. 55, Neh. 8. 1–12.

y 9.38 ver. 6, 41 (Gk.).

z 9.38 Comp. Neh. 3. 26 with Neh. 8. 1.

* 9.39 About B.C. 445.

a 9.39 ch. 8. 8.

b 9.39 See ch. 8. 65.

c 9.40 ver. 37.

d 9.41 ver. 38 (Gk.).

a 9.42 ch. 8. 8.

e 9.43 Or, Hilkiah.

f 9.43 Or, Maaseiah.

g 9.44 Or, Pedaiah.

h 9.44 Or, Hashum.

i 9.44 Comp. Neh. 8. 4.

* 9.45 Heb. above them all. [Neh. 8. 5].

k 9.46 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

l 9.48 Or, Hodijah.

m 9.48 ver. 55.

* 9.49 Then Nehemiah, and Ezra the priest the scribe, and the Levites that instructed the people, said unto all the people, Neh. 8. 9.

n 9.49 See ch. 5. 40 marg.

o 9.49 ver. 40.

a 9.49 ch. 8. 8.

* 9.51 Or, the poor. So ver. 54. Comp. Neh. 8. 10.

p 9.54 ver. 51.

m 9.55 ver. 55.

1 John

1
2
3
4
5

THE FIRST EPISTLE GENERAL OF JOHN

1

1  That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled, of the Word of life; 2 (For the life was manifested, and we have seen it, and bear witness, and shew unto you that eternal life, which was with the Father, and was manifested unto us;) 3  That which we have seen and heard declare we unto you, that ye also may have fellowship with us: and truly our fellowship is with the Father, and with his Son Jesus Christ. 4  And these things write we unto you, that your joy may be full.

5  This then is the message which we have heard of him, and declare unto you, that God is light, and in him is no darkness at all. 6  If we say that we have fellowship with him, and walk in darkness, we lie, and do not the truth: 7  But if we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the blood of Jesus Christ his Son cleanseth us from all sin. 8  If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us. 9  If we confess our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness. 10  If we say that we have not sinned, we make him a liar, and his word is not in us.

2

1  My little children, these things write I unto you, that ye sin not. And if any man sin, we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous: 2  And he is the propitiation for our sins: and not for ours only, but also for the sins of the whole world. 3  And hereby we do know that we know him, if we keep his commandments. 4  He that saith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in him. 5  But whoso keepeth his word, in him verily is the love of God perfected: hereby know we that we are in him. 6  He that saith he abideth in him ought himself also so to walk, even as he walked.

7  Brethren, I write no new commandment unto you, but an old commandment which ye had from the beginning. The old commandment is the word which ye have heard from the beginning. 8  Again, a new commandment I write unto you, which thing is true in him and in you: because the darkness is past, and the true light now shineth. 9  He that saith he is in the light, and hateth his brother, is in darkness even until now. 10  He that loveth his brother abideth in the light, and there is none [†]occasion of stumbling in him. 11  But he that hateth his brother is in darkness, and walketh in darkness, and knoweth not whither he goeth, because that darkness hath blinded his eyes. 12  I write unto you, little children, because your sins are forgiven you for his name’s sake. 13  I write unto you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the wicked one. I write unto you, little children, because ye have known the Father. 14  I have written unto you, fathers, because ye have known him that is from the beginning. I have written unto you, young men, because ye are strong, and the word of God abideth in you, and ye have overcome the wicked one. 15  Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world. If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him. 16  For all that is in the world, the lust of the flesh, [‡]and the lust of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world. 17  And the world passeth away, and the lust thereof: but he that doeth the will of God abideth for ever.

18  Little children, it is the last time: and as ye have heard that antichrist shall come, even now are there many antichrists; whereby we know that it is the last time. 19  They went out from us, but they were not of us; for if they had been of us, they would no doubt have continued with us: but they went out, that they might be made manifest that they were not all of us. 20  But ye have an unction from the Holy One, and ye know all things. 21  I have not written unto you because ye know not the truth, but because ye know it, and that no lie is of the truth. 22  Who is a liar but he that denieth that Jesus is the Christ? He is antichrist, that denieth the Father and the Son. 23  Whosoever denieth the Son, the same hath not the Father: (but) he that acknowledgeth the Son hath the Father also. 24 Let that therefore abide in you, which ye have heard from the beginning. If that which ye have heard from the beginning shall remain in you, ye also shall continue in the Son, and in the Father. 25  And this is the promise that he hath promised us, even eternal life. 26  These things have I written unto you concerning them that seduce you. 27  But the anointing which ye have received of him abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you: but as the same anointing teacheth you of all things, and is truth, and is no lie, and even as it hath taught you, ye shall abide in [∥]him. 28  And now, little children, abide in him; that, when he shall appear, we may have confidence, and not be ashamed before him at his coming. 29  If ye know that he is righteous, [∥]ye know that every one [‡]that doeth righteousness is born of him.

3

1  Behold, what manner of love the Father hath bestowed upon us, that we should be called the sons of God: therefore the world knoweth us not, because it knew him not. 2  Beloved, now are we the sons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we shall be: but we know that, when he shall appear, we shall be like him; for we shall see him as he is. 3  And every man that hath this hope in him purifieth himself, even as he is pure. 4  Whosoever committeth sin transgresseth also the law: for sin is the transgression of the law. 5  And ye know that he was manifested to take away our sins; and in him is no sin. 6  Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not: whosoever sinneth hath not seen him, neither known him. 7  Little children, let no man deceive you: he that doeth righteousness is righteous, even as he is righteous. 8  He that committeth sin is of the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. For this purpose the Son of God was manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil. 9  Whosoever is born of God doth not commit sin; for his seed remaineth in him: and he cannot sin, because he is born of God. 10  In this the children of God are manifest, and the children of the devil: whosoever doeth not righteousness is not of God, neither he that loveth not his brother. 11  For this is the [∥]message that ye heard from the beginning, that we should love one another. 12  Not as Cain, who was of that wicked one, and slew his brother. And wherefore slew he him? Because his own works were evil, and his brother’s righteous.

13  Marvel not, my brethren, if the world hate you. 14  We know that we have passed from death unto life, because we love the brethren. He that loveth not his brother abideth in death. 15  Whosoever hateth his brother is a murderer: and ye know that no murderer hath eternal life abiding in him. 16  Hereby perceive we the love of God, because he laid down his life for us: and we ought to lay down our lives for the brethren. 17  But whoso hath this world’s good, and seeth his brother [‡]have need, and shutteth up his bowels of compassion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him? 18  My little children, let us not love in word, neither in tongue; but in deed and in truth. 19  And hereby we know that we are of the truth, and shall [†]assure our hearts before him. 20  For if our heart condemn us, God is greater than our heart, and knoweth all things. 21  Beloved, if our heart condemn us not, then have we confidence toward God. 22  And whatsoever we ask, we receive of him, because we keep his [‡]commandments, and do those things that are pleasing in his sight. 23  And this is his commandment, That we should believe on the name of his Son Jesus Christ, and love one another, as he gave us commandment. 24  And he that keepeth his commandments dwelleth in him, and he in him. And hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the Spirit which he hath given us.

4

1  Beloved, believe not every spirit, but try the spirits whether they are of God: because many false prophets are gone out into the world. 2  Hereby know ye the Spirit of God: Every spirit that confesseth that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is of God: 3  And every spirit that confesseth not that Jesus Christ is come in the flesh is not of God: and this is that spirit of antichrist, whereof ye have heard that it should come; and even now already is it in the world. 4  Ye are of God, little children, and have overcome them: because greater is he that is in you, than he that is in the world. 5  They are of the world: therefore speak they of the world, and the world heareth them. 6  We are of God: he that knoweth God heareth us; he that is not of God heareth not us. Hereby know we the spirit of truth, and the spirit of error.

7  Beloved, let us love one another: for love is of God; and every one that loveth is born of God, and knoweth God. 8  He that loveth not knoweth not God; for God is love. 9  In this was manifested the love of God toward us, because that God sent his only begotten Son into the world, that we might live through him. 10  Herein is love, not that we loved God, but that he loved us, and sent his Son to be the propitiation for our sins. 11  Beloved, if God so loved us, we ought also to love one another. 12  No man hath seen God at any time. If we love one another, God dwelleth in us, and his love is perfected in us. 13  Hereby know we that we dwell in him, and he in us, because he hath given us of his Spirit. 14  And we have seen and do testify that the Father sent the Son to be the Saviour of the world. 15  Whosoever shall confess that Jesus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God. 16  And we have known and believed the love that God hath to us. God is love; and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him. 17  Herein is [†]our love made perfect, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment: because as he is, so are we in this world. 18  There is no fear in love; but perfect love casteth out fear: because fear hath torment. He that feareth is not made perfect in love. 19  We love him, because he first loved us. 20  If a man say, I love God, and hateth his brother, he is a liar: for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath seen, how can he love God whom he hath not seen? 21  And this commandment have we from him, That he who loveth God love his brother also.

5

1  Whosoever believeth that Jesus is the Christ is born of God: and every one that loveth him that begat loveth him also that is begotten of him. 2  By this we know that we love the children of God, when we love God, and keep his commandments. 3  For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments: and his commandments are not grievous. 4  For whatsoever is born of God overcometh the world: and this is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith. 5  Who is he that overcometh the world, but he that believeth that Jesus is the Son of God? 6  This is he that came by water and blood, even Jesus Christ; not by water only, but by water and blood. And it is the Spirit that beareth witness, because the Spirit is truth. 7  For there are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost: and these three are one. 8  And there are three that bear witness in earth, the Spirit, and the water, and the blood: and these three agree in one. 9  If we receive the witness of men, the witness of God is greater: for this is the witness of God which he hath testified of his Son. 10  He that believeth on the Son of God hath the witness in himself: he that believeth not God hath made him a liar; because he believeth not the record that God gave of his Son. 11  And this is the record, that God hath given to us eternal life, and this life is in his Son. 12  He that hath the Son hath life; and he that hath not the Son [‡]of God hath not life. 13  These things have I written unto you that believe on the name of the Son of God; that ye may know that ye have eternal life, and that ye may believe on the name of the Son of God. 14  And this is the confidence that we have [∥]in him, that, if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us: 15  And if we know that he hear us, whatsoever we ask, we know that we have the petitions that we desired of him. 16  If any man see his brother sin a sin which is not unto death, he shall ask, and he shall give him life for them that sin not unto death. There is a sin unto death: I do not say that he shall pray for it. 17  All unrighteousness is sin: and there is a sin not unto death. 18  We know that whosoever is born of God sinneth not; but he that is begotten of God keepeth himself, and that wicked one toucheth him not. 19  And we know that we are of God, and the whole world lieth in wickedness. 20  And we know that the Son of God is come, and hath given us an understanding, that we may know him that is true, and we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and eternal life. 21  Little children, keep yourselves from idols. Amen.

† 2.10 Gr scandal.

‡ 2.16 [1611 omits and]

∥ 2.27 Or, it.

∥ 2.29 Or, know ye.

‡ 2.29 [1611 which]

∥ 3.11 Or, commandment.

‡ 3.17 [1611 hath]

† 3.19 Gr. persuade.

‡ 3.22 [1611 commandment]

† 4.17 Gr. love with us.

‡ 5.12 [1611 omits of God]

∥ 5.14 Or, concerning him.

1 Kings

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22

The First Book of the Kings

Commonly Called the Third Book of the Kings

1

1  Now king David was old and [†]stricken in years; and they covered him with clothes, but he gat no heat. 2  Wherefore his servants said unto him, [†]Let there be sought for my lord the king [†]a young virgin: and let her stand before the king, and let her [†]cherish him, and let her lie in thy bosom, that my lord the king may get heat. 3  So they sought for a fair damsel throughout all the coasts of Israel, and found Abishag a Shunammite, and brought her to the king. 4  And the damsel was very fair, and cherished the king, and ministered to him: but the king knew her not.

5 ¶ Then Adonijah the son of Haggith exalted himself, saying, I will [†]be king: and he prepared him chariots and horsemen, and fifty men to run before him. 6  And his father had not displeased him [†]at any time in saying, Why hast thou done so? and he also was a very goodly man; and his mother bare him after Absalom. 7  And [†]he conferred with Joab the son of Zeruiah, and with Abiathar the priest: and they [†]following Adonijah helped him. 8  But Zadok the priest, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and Nathan the prophet, and Shimei, and Rei, and the mighty men which belonged to David, were not with Adonijah. 9  And Adonijah slew sheep and oxen and fat cattle by the stone of Zoheleth, which is by [∥]En-rogel, and called all his brethren the king’s sons, and all the men of Judah the king’s servants: 10  But Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah, and the mighty men, and Solomon his brother, he called not.

11 ¶ Wherefore Nathan spake unto Bath-sheba the mother of Solomon, saying, Hast thou not heard that Adonijah the son of [*]Haggith doth reign, and David our lord knoweth it not? 12  Now therefore come, let me, I pray thee, give thee counsel, that thou mayest save thine own life, and the life of thy son Solomon. 13  Go and get thee in unto king David, and say unto him, Didst not thou, my lord, O king, swear unto thine handmaid, saying, Assuredly Solomon thy son shall reign after me, and he shall sit upon my throne? why then doth Adonijah reign? 14  Behold, while thou yet talkest there with the king, I also will come in after thee, and [†]confirm thy words.

15 ¶ And Bath-sheba went in unto the king into the chamber: and the king was very old; and Abishag the Shunammite ministered unto the king. 16  And Bath-sheba bowed, and did obeisance unto the king. And the king said, [†]What wouldest thou? 17  And she said unto him, My lord, thou swarest by the LORD thy God unto thine handmaid, saying, Assuredly Solomon thy son shall reign after me, and he shall sit upon my throne. 18  And now, behold, Adonijah reigneth; and now, my lord the king, thou knowest it not: 19  And he hath slain oxen and fat cattle and sheep in abundance, and hath called all the sons of the king, and Abiathar the priest, and Joab the captain of the host: but Solomon thy servant hath he not called. 20  And thou, my lord, O king, the eyes of all Israel are upon thee, that thou shouldest tell them who shall sit on the throne of my lord the king after him. 21  Otherwise it shall come to pass, when my lord the king shall sleep with his fathers, that I and my son Solomon shall be counted [†]offenders.

22 ¶ And, lo, while she yet talked with the king, Nathan the prophet also came in. 23  And they told the king, saying, Behold Nathan the prophet. And when he was come in before the king, he bowed himself before the king with his face to the ground. 24  And Nathan said, My lord, O king, hast thou said, Adonijah shall reign after me, and he shall sit upon my throne? 25  For he is gone down this day, and hath slain oxen and fat cattle and sheep in abundance, and hath called all the king’s sons, and the captains of the host, and Abiathar the priest; and, behold, they eat and drink before him, and say, [†]God save king Adonijah. 26 But me, even me thy servant, and Zadok the priest, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and thy servant Solomon, hath he not called. 27  Is this thing done by my lord the king, and thou hast not shewed it unto thy servant, who should sit on the throne of my lord the king after him?

28 ¶ Then king David answered and said, Call me Bath-sheba. And she came [†]into the king’s presence, and stood before the king. 29  And the king sware, and said, As the LORD liveth, that hath redeemed my soul out of all distress, 30  Even as I sware unto thee by the LORD God of Israel, saying, Assuredly Solomon thy son shall reign after me, and he shall sit upon my throne in my stead; even so will I certainly do this day. 31  Then Bath-sheba bowed with her face to the earth, and did reverence to the king, and said, Let my lord king David live for ever.

32 ¶ And king David said, Call me Zadok the priest, and Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada. And they came before the king. 33  The king also said unto them, Take with you the servants of your lord, and cause Solomon my son to ride upon [†]mine own mule, and bring him down to Gihon: 34  And let Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet anoint him there king over Israel: and blow ye with the trumpet, and say, God save king Solomon. 35  Then ye shall come up after him, that he may come and sit upon my throne; for he shall be king in my stead: and I have appointed him to be ruler over Israel and over Judah. 36  And Benaiah the son of Jehoiada answered the king, and said, Amen: the LORD God of my lord the king say so too. 37  As the LORD hath been with my lord the king, even so be he with Solomon, and make his throne greater than the throne of my lord king David. 38  So Zadok the priest, and Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the Cherethites, and the Pelethites, went down, and caused Solomon to ride upon king David’s mule, and brought him to Gihon. 39  And Zadok the priest took an horn of oil out of the tabernacle, and anointed Solomon. And they blew the trumpet; and all the people said, God save king Solomon. 40  And all the people came up after him, and the people piped with [∥]pipes, and rejoiced with great joy, so that the earth rent with the sound of them.

41 ¶ And Adonijah and all the guests that were with him heard it as they had made an end of eating. And when Joab heard the sound of the trumpet, he said, Wherefore is this noise of the city being in an uproar? 42  And while he yet spake, behold, Jonathan the son of Abiathar the priest came: and Adonijah said unto him, Come in; for thou art a valiant man, and bringest good tidings. 43  And Jonathan answered and said to Adonijah, Verily our lord king David hath made Solomon king. 44  And the king hath sent with him Zadok the priest, and Nathan the prophet, and Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, and the Cherethites, and the Pelethites, and they have caused him to ride upon the king’s mule: 45  And Zadok the priest and Nathan the prophet have anointed him king in Gihon: and they are come up from thence rejoicing, so that the city rang again. This is the noise that ye have heard. 46  And also Solomon sitteth on the throne of the kingdom. 47  And moreover the king’s servants came to bless our lord king David, saying, God make the name of Solomon better than thy name, and make his throne greater than thy throne. And the king bowed himself upon the bed. 48  And also thus said the king, Blessed be the LORD God of Israel, which hath given one to sit on my throne this day, mine eyes even seeing it. 49  And all the guests that were with Adonijah were afraid, and rose up, and went every man his way.

50 ¶ And Adonijah feared because of Solomon, and arose, and went, and caught hold on the horns of the altar. 51  And it was told Solomon, saying, Behold, Adonijah feareth king Solomon: for, lo, he hath caught hold on the horns of the altar, saying, Let king Solomon swear unto me to day that he will not slay his servant with the sword. 52  And Solomon said, If he will shew himself a worthy man, there shall not an hair of him fall to the earth: but if wickedness shall be found in him, he shall die. 53  So king Solomon sent, and they brought him down from the altar. And he came and bowed himself to king Solomon: and Solomon said unto him, Go to thine house.

2

1  Now the days of David drew nigh that he should die; and he charged Solomon his son, saying, 2  I go the way of all the earth: be thou strong therefore, and shew thyself a man; 3  And keep the charge of the LORD thy God, to walk in his ways, to keep his statutes, and his commandments, and his judgments, and his testimonies, as it is written in the law of Moses, that thou mayest [*][∥]prosper in all that thou doest, and whithersoever thou turnest thyself: 4  That the LORD may continue his word which he spake concerning me, saying, If thy children take heed to their way, to walk before me in truth with all their heart and with all their soul, [*]there shall not [†]fail thee (said he) a man on the throne of Israel. 5  Moreover thou knowest also what Joab the son of Zeruiah did to me, and what he did to the two captains of the hosts of Israel, unto [*]Abner the son of Ner, and unto [*]Amasa the son of Jether, whom he slew, and [†]shed the blood of war in peace, and put the blood of war upon his girdle that was about his loins, and in his shoes that were on his feet. 6  Do therefore according to thy wisdom, and let not his hoar head go down to the grave in peace. 7  But shew kindness unto the sons of [*]Barzillai the Gileadite, and let them be of those that eat at thy table: for so they came to me when I fled because of Absalom thy brother. 8 And, behold, thou hast with thee [*]Shimei the son of Gera, a Benjamite of Bahurim, which cursed me with a [†]grievous curse in the day when I went to Mahanaim: but he came down to meet me at Jordan, and I sware to him by the LORD, saying, [*]I will not put thee to death with the sword. 9  Now therefore hold him not guiltless: for thou art a wise man, and knowest what thou oughtest to do unto him; but his hoar head bring thou down to the grave with blood. 10  So [*]David slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David. 11  And the days that David [*]reigned over Israel were forty years: seven years reigned he in Hebron, and thirty and three years reigned he in Jerusalem.

12 ¶ [*]Then sat Solomon upon the throne of David his father; and his kingdom was established greatly.

13 ¶ And Adonijah the son of Haggith came to Bath-sheba the mother of Solomon. And she said, Comest thou peaceably? And he said, Peaceably. 14  He said moreover, I have somewhat to say unto thee. And she said, Say on. 15  And he said, Thou knowest that the kingdom was mine, and that all Israel set their faces on me, that I should reign: howbeit the kingdom is turned about, and is become my brother’s: for it was his from the LORD. 16  And now I ask one petition of thee, [†]deny me not. And she said unto him, Say on. 17  And he said, Speak, I pray thee, unto Solomon the king, (for he will not say thee nay,) that he give me Abishag the Shunammite to wife. 18  And Bath-sheba said, Well; I will speak for thee unto the king.

19 ¶ Bath-sheba therefore went unto king Solomon, to speak unto him for Adonijah. And the king rose up to meet her, and bowed himself unto her, and sat down on his throne, and caused a seat to be set for the king’s mother; and she sat on his right hand. 20  Then she said, I desire one small petition of thee; I pray thee, say me not nay. And the king said unto her, Ask on, my mother: for I will not say thee nay. 21  And she said, Let Abishag the Shunammite be given to Adonijah thy brother to wife. 22  And king Solomon answered and said unto his mother, And why dost thou ask Abishag the Shunammite for Adonijah? ask for him the kingdom also; for he is mine elder brother; even for him, and for Abiathar the priest, and for Joab the son of Zeruiah. 23  Then king Solomon sware by the LORD, saying, God do so to me, and more also, if Adonijah have not spoken this word against his own life. 24 Now therefore, as the LORD liveth, which hath established me, and set me on the throne of David my father, and who hath made me an house, as he [*]promised, Adonijah shall be put to death this day. 25  And king Solomon sent by the hand of Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; and he fell upon him that he died.

26 ¶ And unto Abiathar the priest said the king, Get thee to Anathoth, unto thine own fields; for thou art [†]worthy of death: but I will not at this time put thee to death, because thou barest the ark of the Lord GOD before David my father, and because thou hast been afflicted in all wherein my father was afflicted. 27  So Solomon thrust out Abiathar from being priest unto the LORD; that he might [*]fulfil the word of the LORD, which he spake concerning the house of Eli in Shiloh.

28 ¶ Then tidings came to Joab: for Joab had turned after Adonijah, though he turned not after Absalom. And Joab fled unto the tabernacle of the LORD, and caught hold on the horns of the altar. 29  And it was told king Solomon that Joab was fled unto the tabernacle of the LORD; and, behold, he is by the altar. Then Solomon sent Benaiah the son of Jehoiada, saying, Go, fall upon him. 30  And Benaiah came to the tabernacle of the LORD, and said unto him, Thus saith the king, Come forth. And he said, Nay; but I will die here. And Benaiah brought the king word again, saying, Thus said Joab, and thus he answered me. 31  And the king said unto him, Do as he hath said, and fall upon him, and bury him; that thou mayest take away the innocent blood, which Joab shed, from me, and from the house of my father. 32  And the LORD shall return his blood upon his own head, who fell upon two men more righteous and better than he, and slew them with the sword, my father David not knowing thereof, to wit, [*]Abner the son of Ner, captain of the host of Israel, and [*]Amasa the son of Jether, captain of the host of Judah. 33  Their blood shall therefore return upon the head of Joab, and upon the head of his seed for ever: but upon David, and upon his seed, and upon his house, and upon his throne, shall there be peace for ever from the LORD. 34  So Benaiah the son of Jehoiada went up, and fell upon him, and slew him: and he was buried in his own house in the wilderness.

35 ¶ And the king put Benaiah the son of Jehoiada in his room over the host: and Zadok the priest did the king put in the room of Abiathar.

36 ¶ And the king sent and called for Shimei, and said unto him, Build thee an house in Jerusalem, and dwell there, and go not forth thence any whither. 37 For it shall be, that on the day thou goest out, and passest over the brook Kidron, thou shalt know for certain that thou shalt surely die: thy blood shall be upon thine own head. 38  And Shimei said unto the king, The saying is good: as my lord the king hath said, so will thy servant do. And Shimei dwelt in Jerusalem many days. 39  And it came to pass at the end of three years, that two of the servants of Shimei ran away unto Achish son of Maachah king of Gath. And they told Shimei, saying, Behold, thy servants be in Gath. 40  And Shimei arose, and saddled his ass, and went to Gath to Achish to seek his servants: and Shimei went, and brought his servants from Gath. 41  And it was told Solomon that Shimei had gone from Jerusalem to Gath, and was come again. 42  And the king sent and called for Shimei, and said unto him, Did I not make thee to swear by the LORD, and protested unto thee, saying, Know for a certain, on the day thou goest out, and walkest abroad any whither, that thou shalt surely die? and thou saidst unto me, The word that I have heard is good. 43  Why then hast thou not kept the oath of the LORD, and the commandment that I have charged thee with? 44  The king said moreover to Shimei, Thou knowest all the wickedness which thine heart is privy to, that thou didst to David my father: therefore the LORD shall return thy wickedness upon thine own head; 45  And king Solomon shall be blessed, and the throne of David shall be established before the LORD for ever. 46  So the king commanded Benaiah the son of Jehoiada; which went out, and fell upon him, that he died. And the [*]kingdom was established in the hand of Solomon.

3

1  And [*]Solomon made affinity with Pharaoh king of Egypt, and took Pharaoh’s daughter, and brought her into the city of David, until he had made an end of building his own house, and the house of the LORD, and the wall of Jerusalem round about. 2  Only the people sacrificed in high places, because there was no house built unto the name of the LORD, until those days. 3  And Solomon loved the LORD, walking in the statutes of David his father: only he sacrificed and burnt incense in high places. 4  And the king went to Gibeon to sacrifice there; for that was the great high place: a thousand burnt offerings did Solomon offer [‡]upon that altar.

5 ¶ In Gibeon the LORD appeared to Solomon in a dream by night: and God said, Ask what I shall give thee. 6  And Solomon said, Thou hast shewed unto thy servant David my father great [∥]mercy, according as he walked before thee in truth, and in righteousness, and in uprightness of heart with thee; and thou hast kept for him this great kindness, that thou hast given him a son to sit on his throne, as it is this day. 7  And now, O LORD my God, thou hast made thy servant king instead of David my father: and I am but a little child: I know not how to go out or come in. 8  And thy servant is in the midst of thy people which thou hast chosen, a great people, that cannot be numbered nor counted for multitude. 9 [*] Give therefore thy servant an [†]understanding heart to judge thy people, that I may discern between good and bad: for who is able to judge this thy so great a people? 10  And the speech pleased the Lord, that Solomon had asked this thing. 11  And God said unto him, Because thou hast asked this thing, and hast not asked for thyself [†]long life; neither hast asked riches for thyself, nor hast asked the life of thine enemies; but hast asked for thyself understanding [†]to discern judgment; 12  Behold, I have done according to thy [‡]words: lo, I have given thee a wise and an understanding heart; so that there was none like thee before thee, neither after thee shall any arise like unto thee. 13  And I have also [*]given thee that which thou hast not asked, both riches, and honour: so that there [∥]shall not be any among the kings like unto thee all thy days. 14  And if thou wilt walk in my ways, to keep my statutes and my commandments, as [*]thy father David did walk, then I will lengthen thy days. 15  And Solomon awoke; and, behold, it was a dream. And he came to Jerusalem, and stood before the ark of the covenant of the LORD, and offered up burnt offerings, and offered peace offerings, and made a feast to all his servants.

16 ¶ Then came there two women, that were harlots, unto the king, and stood before him. 17  And the one woman said, O my lord, I and this woman dwell in one house; and I was delivered of a child with her in the house. 18  And it came to pass the third day after that I was delivered, that this woman was delivered also: and we were together; there was no stranger with us in the house, save we two in the house. 19  And this woman’s child died in the night; because she overlaid it. 20  And she arose at midnight, and took my son from beside me, while thine handmaid slept, and laid it in her bosom, and laid her dead child in my bosom. 21  And when I rose in the morning to give my child suck, behold, it was dead: but when I had considered it in the morning, behold, it was not my son, which I did bear. 22  And the other woman said, Nay; but the living is my son, and the dead is thy son. And this said, No; but the dead is thy son, and the living is my son. Thus they spake before the king. 23  Then said the king, The one saith, This is my son that liveth, and thy son is the dead: and the other saith, Nay; but thy son is the dead, and my son is the living. 24  And the king said, Bring me a sword. And they brought a sword before the king. 25  And the king said, Divide the living child in two, and give half to the one, and half to the other. 26  Then spake the woman whose the living child was unto the king, for her bowels [†]yearned upon her son, and she said, O my lord, give her the living child, and in no wise slay it. But the other said, Let it be neither mine nor thine, but divide it. 27  Then the king answered and said, Give her the living child, and in no wise slay it: she is the mother thereof. 28  And all Israel heard of the judgment which the king had judged; and they feared the king: for they saw that the wisdom of God was [†]in him, to do judgment.

4

1  So king Solomon was king over all Israel. 2 And these were the princes which he had; Azariah the son of Zadok [∥]the priest, 3  Elihoreph and Ahiah, the sons of Shisha, [∥]scribes; Jehoshaphat the son of Ahilud, the [∥]recorder. 4  And Benaiah the son of Jehoiada was over the host: and Zadok and Abiathar were the priests: 5  And Azariah the son of Nathan was over the officers: and Zabud the son of Nathan was principal officer, and the king’s friend: 6  And Ahishar was over the household: and [*]Adoniram the son of Abda was over the [∥]tribute.

7 ¶ And Solomon had twelve officers over all Israel, which provided victuals for the king and his household: each man his month in a year made provision. 8 And these are their names: [∥]The son of Hur, in mount Ephraim: 9 [∥] The son of Dekar, in Makaz, and in Shaalbim, and Beth-shemesh, and Elon-beth-hanan: 10 [∥] The son of Hesed, in Aruboth; to him pertained Sochoh, and all the land of Hepher: 11 [∥] The son of Abinadab, in all the region of Dor; which had Taphath the daughter of Solomon to wife: 12  Baana the son of Ahilud; to him pertained Taanach and Megiddo, and all Beth-shean, which is by Zartanah beneath Jezreel, from Beth-shean to Abel-meholah, even unto the place that is beyond Jokneam: 13 [∥] The son of Geber, in Ramoth-gilead; to him pertained the towns of Jair the son of Manasseh, which are in Gilead; to him also pertained the region of Argob, which is in Bashan, threescore great cities with walls and brasen bars: 14  Ahinadab the son of Iddo had [∥]Mahanaim: 15  Ahimaaz was in Naphtali; he also took Basmath the daughter of Solomon to wife: 16  Baanah the son of Hushai was in Asher and in Aloth: 17  Jehoshaphat the son of Paruah, in Issachar: 18  Shimei the son of Elah, in Benjamin: 19  Geber the son of Uri was in the country of Gilead, in the country of Sihon king of the Amorites, and of Og king of Bashan; and he was the only officer which was in the land.

20 ¶ Judah and Israel were many, as the sand which is by the sea in multitude, eating and drinking, and making merry. 21  And [*]Solomon reigned over all kingdoms from the river unto the land of the Philistines, and unto the border of Egypt: they brought presents, and served Solomon all the days of his life.

22 ¶ And Solomon’s [†]provision for one day was thirty [†]measures of fine flour, and threescore measures of meal, 23  Ten fat oxen, and twenty oxen out of the pastures, and an hundred sheep, beside harts, and roebucks, and fallowdeer, and fatted fowl. 24  For he had dominion over all the region on this side the river, from Tiphsah even to Azzah, over all the kings on this side the river: and he had peace on all sides round about him. 25  And Judah and Israel dwelt [†]safely, every man under his vine and under his fig tree, from Dan even to Beer-sheba, all the days of Solomon.

26 ¶ And [*]Solomon had forty thousand stalls of horses for his chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen. 27  And those officers provided victual for king Solomon, and for all that came unto king Solomon’s table, every man in his month: they lacked nothing. 28  Barley also and straw for the horses and [∥]dromedaries brought they unto the place where the officers were, every man according to his charge.

29 ¶ And [*]God gave Solomon wisdom and understanding exceeding much, and largeness of heart, even as the sand that is on the sea shore. 30  And Solomon’s wisdom excelled the wisdom of all the children of the east country, and all the wisdom of Egypt. 31  For he was wiser than all men; than Ethan the Ezrahite, and Heman, and Chalcol, and Darda, the sons of Mahol: and his fame was in all nations round about. 32  And he spake three thousand proverbs: and his songs were a thousand and five. 33  And he spake of trees, from the cedar tree that is in Lebanon even unto the hyssop that springeth out of the wall: he spake also of beasts, and of fowl, and of creeping things, and of fishes. 34  And there came of all people to hear the wisdom of Solomon, from all kings of the earth, which had heard of his wisdom.

5

1  And Hiram king of Tyre sent his servants unto Solomon; for he had heard that they had anointed him king in the room of his father: for Hiram was ever a lover of David. 2  And [*]Solomon sent to Hiram, saying, 3  Thou knowest how that David my father could not build an house unto the name of the LORD his God for the wars which were about him on every side, until the LORD put them under the soles of his feet. 4  But now the LORD my God hath given me rest on every side, so that there is neither adversary nor evil occurrent. 5  And, behold, I [†]purpose to build an house unto the name of the LORD my God, [*]as the LORD spake unto David my father, saying, Thy son, whom I will set upon thy throne in thy room, he shall build an house unto my name. 6  Now therefore command thou that they hew me cedar trees out of Lebanon; and my servants shall be with thy servants: and unto thee will I give hire for thy servants according to all that thou shalt [†]appoint: for thou knowest that there is not among us any that can skill to hew timber like unto the Sidonians.

7 ¶ And it came to pass, when Hiram heard the words of Solomon, that he rejoiced greatly, and said, Blessed be the LORD this day, which hath given unto David a wise son over this great people. 8  And Hiram sent to Solomon, saying, I have [†]considered the things which thou sentest to me for: and I will do all thy desire concerning timber of cedar, and concerning timber of fir. 9  My servants shall bring them down from Lebanon unto the sea: and I will convey them by sea in floats unto the place that thou shalt [†]appoint me, and will cause them to be discharged there, and thou shalt receive them: and thou shalt accomplish my desire, in giving food for my household.

10  So Hiram gave Solomon cedar trees and fir trees according to all his desire. 11  And Solomon gave Hiram twenty thousand [†]measures of wheat for food to his household, and twenty measures of pure oil: thus gave Solomon to Hiram year by year. 12  And the LORD gave Solomon wisdom, [*]as he promised him: and there was peace between Hiram and Solomon; and they two made a league together.

13 ¶ And king Solomon raised a [†]levy out of all Israel; and the levy was thirty thousand men. 14  And he sent them to Lebanon, ten thousand a month by courses: a month they were in Lebanon, and two months at home: and [*]Adoniram was over the levy. 15  And Solomon had threescore and ten thousand that bare burdens, and fourscore thousand hewers in the mountains; 16  Beside the chief of Solomon’s officers which were over the work, three thousand and three hundred, which ruled over the people that wrought in the work. 17  And the king commanded, and they brought great stones, costly stones, and hewed stones, to lay the foundation of the house. 18  And Solomon’s builders and Hiram’s builders did hew them, and the [∥]stonesquarers: so they prepared timber and stones to build the house.

6

1  And [*]it came to pass in the four hundred and [‡]eightieth year after the children of Israel were come out of the land of Egypt, in the fourth year of Solomon’s reign over Israel, in the month Zif, which is the second month, that he [†]began to build the house of the LORD. 2  And the house which king Solomon built for the LORD, the length thereof was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof twenty cubits, and the height thereof thirty cubits. 3  And the porch before the temple of the house, twenty cubits was the length thereof, according to the breadth of the house; and ten cubits was the breadth thereof before the house. 4  And for the house he made [∥]windows of narrow lights.

5 ¶ And [∥]against the wall of the house he built [†]chambers round about, against the walls of the house round about, both of the temple and of the oracle: and he made [†]chambers round about: 6  The nethermost chamber was five cubits broad, and the middle was six cubits broad, and the third was seven cubits broad: for without in the wall of the house he made [†]narrowed rests round about, that the beams should not be fastened in the walls of the house. 7  And the house, when it was in building, was built of stone made ready before it was brought thither: so that there was neither hammer nor axe nor any tool of iron heard in the house, while it was in building. 8  The door for the middle chamber was in the right [†]side of the house: and they went up with winding stairs into the middle chamber, and out of the middle into the third. 9  So he built the house, and finished it; and covered the house [∥]with beams and boards of cedar. 10 And then he built chambers against all the house, five cubits high: and they rested on the house with timber of cedar.

11 ¶ And the word of the LORD came to Solomon, saying, 12  Concerning this house which thou art in building, if thou wilt walk in my statutes, and execute my judgments, and keep all my commandments to walk in them; then will I perform my word with thee, [*]which I spake unto David thy father: 13  And I will dwell among the children of Israel, and will not forsake my people Israel. 14  So Solomon built the house, and finished it.

15  And he built the walls of the house within with boards of cedar, [∥]both the floor of the house, and the walls of the cieling: and he covered them on the inside with wood, and covered the floor of the house with planks of fir. 16  And he built twenty cubits on the sides of the house, both the floor and the walls with boards of cedar: he even built them for it within, even for the oracle, even for the most holy place. 17  And the house, that is, the temple before it, was forty cubits long. 18  And the cedar of the house within was carved with [∥]knops and [†]open flowers: all was cedar; there was no stone seen. 19  And the oracle he prepared in the house within, to set there the ark of the covenant of the LORD. 20  And the oracle in the forepart was twenty cubits in length, and twenty cubits in breadth, and twenty cubits in the height thereof: and he overlaid it with [†]pure gold; and so covered the altar which was of cedar. 21  So Solomon overlaid the house within with pure gold: and he made a partition by the chains of gold before the oracle; and he overlaid it with gold. 22  And the whole house he overlaid with gold, until he had finished all the house: also the whole altar that was by the oracle he overlaid with gold.

23 ¶ And within the oracle he made two cherubims of [∥][†]olive tree, each ten cubits high. 24  And five cubits was the one wing of the cherub, and five cubits the other wing of the cherub: from the uttermost part of the one wing unto the uttermost part of the other were ten cubits. 25  And the other cherub was ten cubits: both the cherubims were of one measure and one size. 26  The height of the one cherub was ten cubits, and so was it of the other cherub. 27  And he set the cherubims within the inner house: and [*][∥]they stretched forth the wings of the cherubims, so that the wing of the one touched the one wall, and the wing of the other cherub touched the other wall; and their wings touched one another in the midst of the house. 28  And he overlaid the cherubims with gold. 29  And he carved all the walls of the house round about with carved figures of cherubims and palm trees and [†]open flowers, within and without. 30  And the floor of the house he overlaid with gold, within and without.

31 ¶ And for the entering of the oracle he made doors of olive tree: the lintel and side posts were [∥]a fifth part of the wall. 32  The [∥]two doors also were of olive tree; and he carved upon them carvings of cherubims and palm trees and [†]open flowers, and overlaid them with gold, and spread gold upon the cherubims, and upon the palm trees. 33  So also made he for the door of the temple posts of olive tree, [∥]a fourth part of the wall. 34  And the two doors were of fir tree: the two leaves of the one door were folding, and the two leaves of the other door were folding. 35  And he carved thereon cherubims and palm trees and open flowers: and covered them with gold fitted upon the carved work.

36 ¶ And he built the inner court with three rows of hewed stone, and a row of cedar beams.

37 ¶ In the fourth year was the foundation of the house of the LORD laid, in the month Zif: 38  And in the eleventh year, in the month Bul, which is the eighth month, was the house finished [∥]throughout all the parts thereof, and according to all the fashion of it. So was he seven years in building it.

7

1  But Solomon was building his own house [*]thirteen years, and he finished all his house.

2 ¶ He built also the house of the forest of Lebanon; the length thereof was an hundred cubits, and the breadth thereof fifty cubits, and the height thereof thirty cubits, upon four rows of cedar pillars, with cedar beams upon the pillars. 3 And it was covered with cedar above upon the [†]beams, that lay on forty five pillars, fifteen in a row. 4 And there were windows in three rows, and [†]light was against light in three ranks. 5  And all the [∥]doors and posts were square, with the windows: and light was against light in three ranks.

6 ¶ And he made a porch of pillars; the length thereof was fifty cubits, and the breadth thereof thirty cubits: and the porch was [∥]before them: and the other pillars and the thick beam were [∥]before them.

7 ¶ Then he made a porch for the throne where he might judge, even the porch of judgment: and it was covered with cedar [†]from one side of the floor to the other.

8 ¶ And his house where he dwelt had another court within the porch, which was of the like work. Solomon made also an house for Pharaoh’s daughter, [*]whom he had taken to wife, like unto this porch. 9 All these were of costly stones, according to the measures of hewed stones, sawed with saws, within and without, even from the foundation unto the coping, and so on the outside toward the great court. 10  And the foundation was of costly stones, even great stones, stones of ten cubits, and stones of eight cubits. 11  And above were costly stones, after the measures of hewed stones, and cedars. 12  And the great court round about was with three rows of hewed stones, and a row of cedar beams, both for the inner court of the house of the LORD, and for the porch of the house.

13 ¶ And king Solomon sent and fetched Hiram out of Tyre. 14 He was [†]a widow’s son of the tribe of Naphtali, and his father was a man of Tyre, a worker in brass: and he was filled with wisdom, and understanding, and cunning to work all works in brass. And he came to king Solomon, and wrought all his work. 15  For he [†]cast two pillars of brass, of eighteen cubits high apiece: and a line of twelve cubits did compass either of them about. 16  And he made two chapiters of molten brass, to set upon the tops of the pillars: the height of the one chapiter was five cubits, and the height of the other chapiter was five cubits: 17  And nets of checker work, and wreaths of chain work, for the chapiters which were upon the top of the pillars; seven for the one chapiter, and seven for the other chapiter. 18  And he made the pillars, and two rows round about upon the one network, to cover the chapiters that were upon the top, with pomegranates: and so did he for the other chapiter. 19  And the chapiters that were upon the top of the pillars were of lily work in the porch, four cubits. 20  And the chapiters upon the two pillars had pomegranates also above, over against the belly which was by the network: and the pomegranates were two hundred in rows round about upon the other chapiter. 21 [*] And he set up the pillars in the porch of the temple: and he set up the right pillar, and called the name thereof [∥]Jachin: and he set up the left pillar, and called the name thereof [∥]Boaz. 22  And upon the top of the pillars was lily work: so was the work of the pillars finished.

23 ¶ And he made a molten sea, ten cubits [†]from the one brim to the other: it was round all about, and his height was five cubits: and a line of thirty cubits did compass it round about. 24  And under the brim of it round about there were knops compassing it, ten in a cubit, [*]compassing the sea round about: the knops were cast in two rows, when it was cast. 25  It stood upon twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east: and the sea was set above upon them, and all their hinder parts were inward. 26 And it was an hand breadth thick, and the brim thereof was wrought like the brim of a cup, with flowers of lilies: it contained two thousand baths.

27 ¶ And he made ten bases of brass; four cubits was the length of one base, and four cubits the breadth thereof, and three cubits the height of it. 28  And the work of the bases was on this manner: they had borders, and the borders were between the ledges: 29  And on the borders that were between the ledges were lions, oxen, and cherubims: and upon the ledges there was a base above: and beneath the lions and oxen were certain additions made of thin work. 30  And every base had four brasen wheels, and plates of brass: and the four corners thereof had undersetters: under the laver were undersetters molten, at the side of every addition. 31  And the mouth of it within the chapiter and above was a cubit: but the mouth thereof was round after the work of the base, a cubit and an half: and also upon the mouth of it were gravings with their borders, foursquare, not round. 32  And under the borders were four wheels; and the axletrees of the wheels were [†]joined to the base: and the height of a wheel was a cubit and half a cubit. 33  And the work of the wheels was like the work of a chariot wheel: their axletrees, and their naves, and their felloes, and their spokes, were all molten. 34 And there were four undersetters to the four corners of one base: and the undersetters were of the very base itself. 35  And in the top of the base was there a round compass of half a cubit high: and on the top of the base the ledges thereof and the borders thereof were of the same. 36  For on the plates of the ledges thereof, and on the borders thereof, he graved cherubims, lions, and palm trees, according to the [†]proportion of every one, and additions round about. 37 After this manner he made the ten bases: all of them had one casting, one measure, and one size.

38 ¶ Then made he ten lavers of brass: one laver contained forty baths: and every laver was four cubits: and upon every one of the ten bases one laver. 39  And he put five bases on the right [†]side of the house, and five on the left side of the house: and he set the sea on the right side of the house eastward over against the south.

40 ¶ And Hiram made the lavers, and the shovels, and the basons. So Hiram made an end of doing all the work that he made king Solomon for the house of the LORD: 41  The two pillars, and the two bowls of the chapiters that were on the top of the two pillars; and the two networks, to cover the two bowls of the chapiters which were upon the top of the pillars; 42  And four hundred pomegranates for the two networks, even two rows of pomegranates for one network, to cover the two bowls of the chapiters that were [†]upon the pillars; 43  And the ten bases, and ten lavers on the bases; 44  And one sea, and twelve oxen under the sea; 45  And the pots, and the shovels, and the basons: and all these vessels, which Hiram made to king Solomon for the house of the LORD, were of [†]bright brass. 46  In the plain of Jordan did the king cast them, [†]in the clay ground between Succoth and Zarthan. 47  And Solomon left all the vessels unweighed, [†]because they were exceeding many: neither was the weight of the brass [†]found out.

48  And Solomon made all the vessels that pertained unto the house of the LORD: the altar of gold, and the table of gold, whereupon the shewbread was, 49  And the candlesticks of pure gold, five on the right side, and five on the left, before the oracle, with the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs of gold, 50  And the bowls, and the snuffers, and the basons, and the spoons, and the [†]censers of pure gold; and the hinges of gold, both for the doors of the inner house, the most holy place, and for the doors of the house, to wit, of the temple. 51  So was ended all the work that king Solomon made for the house of the LORD. And Solomon brought in the [†]things [*]which David his father had dedicated; even the silver, and the gold, and the vessels, did he put among the treasures of the house of the LORD.

8

1  Then [*]Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the [†]chief of the fathers of the children of Israel, unto king Solomon in Jerusalem, that they might bring up the ark of the covenant of the LORD out of the city of David, which is Zion. 2  And all the men of Israel assembled themselves unto king Solomon at the feast in the month Ethanim, which is the seventh month. 3  And all the elders of Israel came, and the priests took up the ark. 4  And they brought up the ark of the LORD, and the tabernacle of the congregation, and all the holy vessels that were in the tabernacle, even those did the priests and the Levites bring up. 5  And king Solomon, and all the congregation of Israel, that were assembled unto him, were with him before the ark, sacrificing sheep and oxen, that could not be told nor numbered for multitude. 6  And the priests brought in the ark of the covenant of the LORD unto his place, into the oracle of the house, to the most holy place, even under the wings of the cherubims. 7  For the cherubims spread forth their two wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubims covered the ark and the staves thereof above. 8  And they drew out the staves, that the [†]ends of the staves were seen out in the [∥]holy place before the oracle, and they were not seen without: and there they are unto this day. 9  There was nothing in the ark [*]save the two tables of stone, which Moses put there at Horeb, [∥]when the LORD made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of the land of Egypt. 10  And it came to pass, when the priests were come out of the holy place, that the cloud [*]filled the house of the LORD, 11  So that the priests could not stand to minister because of the cloud: for the glory of the LORD had filled the house of the LORD.

12 ¶ Then spake Solomon, The LORD [*]said that he would dwell in the thick darkness. 13  I have surely built thee an house to dwell in, a settled place for thee to abide in for ever. 14  And the king turned his face about, and blessed all the congregation of Israel: (and all the congregation of Israel stood;) 15  And he said, Blessed be the LORD God of Israel, which spake with his mouth unto David my father, and hath with his hand fulfilled it, saying, 16  Since the day that I brought forth my people Israel out of Egypt, I chose no city out of all the tribes of Israel to build an house, that my name might be therein; but I chose [*]David to be over my people Israel. 17  And it was in the heart of David my father to build an house for the name of the LORD God of Israel. 18  And the LORD said unto David my father, Whereas it was in thine heart to build an house unto my name, thou didst well that it was in thine heart. 19  Nevertheless thou shalt not build the house; but thy son that shall come forth out of thy loins, he shall build the house unto my name. 20  And the LORD hath performed his word that he spake, and I am risen up in the room of David my father, and sit on the throne of Israel, as the LORD promised, and have built an house for the name of the LORD God of Israel. 21  And I have set there a place for the ark, wherein is the covenant of the LORD, which he made with our fathers, when he brought them out of the land of Egypt.

22 ¶ And Solomon stood before [*]the altar of the LORD in the presence of all the congregation of Israel, and spread forth his hands toward heaven: 23  And he said, [*]LORD God of Israel, there is no God like thee, in heaven above, or on earth beneath, who keepest covenant and mercy with thy servants that walk before thee with all their heart: 24  Who hast kept with thy servant David my father that thou promisedst him: thou spakest also with thy mouth, and hast fulfilled it with thine hand, as it is this day. 25  Therefore now, LORD God of Israel, keep with thy servant David my father that thou promisedst him, saying, [*][†]There shall not fail thee a man in my sight to sit on the throne of Israel; [†]so that thy children take heed to their way, that they walk before me as thou hast walked before me. 26  And now, O God of Israel, let thy word, I pray thee, be verified, which thou spakest unto thy servant David my father. 27  But will God indeed dwell on the earth? behold, the heaven and heaven of heavens cannot contain thee; how much less this house that I have builded? 28  Yet have thou respect unto the prayer of thy servant, and to his supplication, O LORD my God, to hearken unto the cry and to the prayer, which thy servant prayeth before thee to day: 29  That thine eyes may be open toward this house night and day, even toward the place of which thou hast said, [*]My name shall be there: that thou mayest hearken unto the prayer which thy servant shall make [∥]toward this place. 30  And hearken thou to the supplication of thy servant, and of thy people Israel, when they shall pray [∥]toward this place: and hear thou in heaven thy dwelling place: and when thou hearest, forgive.

31 ¶ If any man trespass against his neighbour, [†]and an oath be laid upon him to cause him to swear, and the oath come before thine altar in this house: 32  Then hear thou in heaven, and do, and judge thy servants, condemning the wicked, to bring his way upon his head; and justifying the righteous, to give him according to his righteousness.

33 ¶ When thy people Israel be smitten down before the enemy, because they have sinned against thee, and shall turn again to thee, and confess thy name, and pray, and make supplication unto thee [∥]in this house: 34  Then hear thou in heaven, and forgive the sin of thy people Israel, and bring them again unto the land which thou gavest unto their fathers.

35 ¶ When heaven is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against thee; if they pray toward this place, and confess thy name, and turn from their sin, when thou afflictest them: 36  Then hear thou in heaven, and forgive the sin of thy servants, and of thy people Israel, that thou teach them the good way wherein they should walk, and give rain upon thy land, which thou hast given to thy people for an inheritance.

37 ¶ If there be in the land famine, if there be pestilence, blasting, mildew, locust, or if there be caterpiller; if their enemy besiege them in the land of their [∥]cities; whatsoever plague, whatsoever sickness there be; 38  What prayer and supplication soever be made by any man, or by all thy people Israel, which shall know every man the plague of his own heart, and spread forth his hands toward this house: 39  Then hear thou in heaven thy dwelling place, and forgive, and do, and give to every man according to his ways, whose heart thou knowest; (for thou, even thou only, knowest the hearts of all the children of men;) 40  That they may fear thee all the days that they live in the land which thou gavest unto our fathers. 41  Moreover concerning a stranger, that is not of thy people Israel, but cometh out of a far country for thy name’s sake; 42 (For they shall hear of thy great name, and of thy strong hand, and of thy stretched out arm;) when he shall come and pray toward this house; 43  Hear thou in heaven thy dwelling place, and do according to all that the stranger calleth to thee for: that all people of the earth may know thy name, to fear thee, as do thy people Israel; and that they may know that [†]this house, which I have builded, is called by thy name.

44 ¶ If thy people go out to battle against their enemy, whithersoever thou shalt send them, and shall pray unto the LORD [†]toward the city which thou hast chosen, and toward the house that I have built for thy name: 45  Then hear thou in heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their [∥]cause. 46  If they sin against thee, ([*]for there is no man that sinneth not,) and thou be angry with them, and deliver them to the enemy, so that they carry them away captives unto the land of the enemy, far or near; 47  Yet if they shall [†]bethink themselves in the land whither they were carried captives, and repent, and make supplication unto thee in the land of them that carried them captives, saying, We have sinned, and have done perversely, we have committed wickedness; 48 And so return unto thee with all their heart, and with all their soul, in the land of their enemies, which led them away captive, and pray unto thee toward their land, which thou gavest unto their fathers, the city which thou hast chosen, and the house which I have built for thy name: 49  Then hear thou their prayer and their supplication in heaven thy dwelling place, and maintain their [∥]cause, 50  And forgive thy people that have sinned against thee, and all their transgressions wherein they have transgressed against thee, and give them compassion before them who carried them captive, that they may have compassion on them: 51 For they be thy people, and thine inheritance, which thou broughtest forth out of Egypt, from the midst of the furnace of iron: 52  That thine eyes may be open unto the supplication of thy servant, and unto the supplication of thy people Israel, to hearken unto them in all that they call for unto thee. 53  For thou didst separate them from among all the people of the earth, to be thine inheritance, [*]as thou spakest by the hand of Moses thy servant, when thou broughtest our fathers out of Egypt, O Lord GOD.

54 And it was so, that when Solomon had made an end of praying all this prayer and supplication unto the LORD, he arose from before the altar of the LORD, from kneeling on his knees with his hands spread up to heaven. 55  And he stood, and blessed all the congregation of Israel with a loud voice, saying, 56  Blessed be the LORD, that hath given rest unto his people Israel, according to all that he promised: there hath not [†]failed one word of all his good promise, which he promised by the hand of Moses his servant. 57  The LORD our God be with us, as he was with our fathers: let him not leave us, nor forsake us: 58  That he may incline our hearts unto him, to walk in all his ways, and to keep his commandments, and his statutes, and his judgments, which he commanded our fathers. 59  And let these my words, wherewith I have made supplication before the LORD, be nigh unto the LORD our God day and night, that he maintain the cause of his servant, and the cause of his people Israel [†]at all times, as the matter shall require: 60  That all the people of the earth may know that the LORD is God, and that there is none else. 61  Let your heart therefore be perfect with the LORD [‡]our God, to walk in his statutes, and to keep his commandments, as at this day.

62 ¶ And [*]the king, and all Israel with him, offered sacrifice before the LORD. 63  And Solomon offered a sacrifice of peace offerings, which he offered unto the LORD, two and twenty thousand oxen, and an hundred and twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the children of Israel dedicated the house of the LORD. 64 [*] The same day did the king hallow the middle of the court that was before the house of the LORD: for there he offered burnt offerings, and meat offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings: because the brasen altar that was before the LORD was too little to receive the burnt offerings, and meat offerings, and the fat of the peace offerings. 65  And at that time Solomon held a feast, and all Israel with him, a great congregation, from the entering in of Hamath unto the river of Egypt, before the LORD our God, seven days and seven days, even fourteen days. 66  On the eighth day he sent the people away: and they [∥]blessed the king, and went unto their tents joyful and glad of heart for all the goodness that the LORD had done for David his servant, and for Israel his people.

9

1  And [*]it came to pass, when Solomon had finished the building of the house of the LORD, and the king’s house, and all Solomon’s desire which he was pleased to do, 2  That the LORD appeared to Solomon the second time, [*]as he had appeared unto him at Gibeon. 3  And the LORD said unto him, I have heard thy prayer and thy supplication, that thou hast made before me: I have hallowed this house, which thou hast built, [*]to put my name there for ever; and mine eyes and mine heart shall be there perpetually. 4  And if thou wilt walk before me, as David thy father walked, in integrity of heart, and in uprightness, to do according to all that I have commanded thee, and wilt keep my statutes and my judgments: 5  Then I will establish the throne of thy kingdom upon Israel for ever, [*]as I promised to David thy father, saying, There shall not fail thee a man upon the throne of Israel. 6  But if ye shall at all turn from following me, ye or your children, and will not keep my commandments and my statutes which I have set before you, but go and serve other gods, and worship them: 7  Then will I cut off Israel out of the land which I have given them; and this house, which I have hallowed [*]for my name, will I cast out of my sight; and Israel shall be a proverb and a byword among all people: 8  And at this house, which is high, every one that passeth by it shall be astonished, and shall hiss; and they shall say, [*]Why hath the LORD done thus unto this land, and to this house? 9  And they shall answer, Because they forsook the LORD their God, who brought forth their fathers out of the land of Egypt, and have taken hold upon other gods, and have worshipped them, and served them: therefore hath the LORD brought upon them all this evil.

10 ¶ And [*]it came to pass at the end of twenty years, when Solomon had built the two houses, the house of the LORD, and the king’s house, 11 (Now Hiram the king of Tyre had furnished Solomon with cedar trees and fir trees, and with gold, according to all his desire,) that then [‡]king Solomon gave Hiram twenty cities in the land of Galilee. 12  And Hiram came out from Tyre to see the cities which Solomon had given him; and they [†]pleased him not. 13  And he said, What cities are these which thou hast given me, my brother? And he called them the land of [∥]Cabul unto this day. 14  And Hiram sent to the king sixscore talents of gold.

15 ¶ And this is the reason of the levy which king Solomon raised; for to build the house of the LORD, and his own house, and Millo, and the wall of Jerusalem, and Hazor, and Megiddo, and Gezer. 16  For Pharaoh king of Egypt had gone up, and taken Gezer, and burnt it with fire, and slain the Canaanites that dwelt in the city, and given it for a present unto his daughter, Solomon’s wife. 17  And Solomon built Gezer, and Beth-horon the nether, 18  And Baalath, and Tadmor in the wilderness, in the land, 19  And all the cities of store that Solomon had, and cities for his chariots, and cities for his horsemen, and [†]that which Solomon desired to build in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion. 20  And all the people that were left of the Amorites, Hittites, Perizzites, Hivites, and Jebusites, which were not of the children of Israel, 21  Their children that were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel also were not able utterly to destroy, upon those did Solomon levy a tribute of bondservice unto this day. 22  But of the children of Israel did Solomon [*]make no bondmen: but they were men of war, and his servants, and his princes, and his captains, and rulers of his chariots, and his horsemen. 23 These were the chief of the officers that were over Solomon’s work, five hundred and fifty, which bare rule over the people that wrought in the work.

24 ¶ But [*]Pharaoh’s daughter came up out of the city of David unto her house which Solomon had built for her: then did he build Millo.

25 ¶ And three times in a year did Solomon offer burnt offerings and peace offerings upon the altar which he built unto the LORD, and he burnt incense [†]upon the altar that was before the LORD. So he finished the house.

26 ¶ And king Solomon made a navy of ships in Ezion-geber, which is beside Eloth, on the [†]shore of the Red sea, in the land of Edom. 27  And Hiram sent in the navy his servants, shipmen that had knowledge of the sea, with the servants of Solomon. 28  And they came to Ophir, and fetched from thence gold, four hundred and twenty talents, and brought it to king Solomon.

10

1  And when the [*]queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon concerning the name of the LORD, she came to prove him with hard questions. 2  And she came to Jerusalem with a very great train, with camels that bare spices, and very much gold, and precious stones: and when she was come to Solomon, she communed with him of all that was in her heart. 3  And Solomon told her all her [†]questions: there was not any thing hid from the king, which he told her not. 4  And when the queen of Sheba had seen all Solomon’s wisdom, and the house that he had built, 5  And the meat of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the [†]attendance of his ministers, and their apparel, and his [∥]cupbearers, and his ascent by which he went up unto the house of the LORD; there was no more spirit in her. 6  And she said to the king, It was a true [†]report that I heard in mine own land of thy [∥]acts and of thy wisdom. 7  Howbeit I believed not the words, until I came, and mine eyes had seen it: and, behold, the half was not told me: [†]thy wisdom and prosperity exceedeth the fame which I heard. 8  Happy are thy men, happy are these thy servants, which stand continually before thee, and that hear thy wisdom. 9  Blessed be the LORD thy God, which delighted in thee, to set thee on the throne of Israel: because the LORD loved Israel for ever, therefore made he thee king, to do judgment and justice. 10  And she gave the king an hundred and twenty talents of gold, and of spices very great store, and precious stones: there came no more such abundance of spices as these which the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon. 11  And the navy also of Hiram, that brought gold from Ophir, brought in from Ophir great plenty of almug trees, and precious stones. 12  And the king made of the almug trees [∥][†]pillars for the house of the LORD, and for the king’s house, harps also and psalteries for singers: there came no such [*]almug trees, nor were seen unto this day. 13  And king Solomon gave unto the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatsoever she asked, beside that which Solomon gave her [†]of his royal bounty. So she turned and went to her own country, she and her servants.

14 ¶ Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred threescore and six talents of gold, 15 Beside that he had of the merchantmen, and of the traffick of the spice merchants, and of all the kings of Arabia, and of the [∥]governors of the country.

16 ¶ And king Solomon made two hundred targets of beaten gold: six hundred shekels of gold went to one target. 17 And he made three hundred shields of beaten gold; three pound of gold went to one shield: and the king put them in the [*]house of the forest of Lebanon.

18 ¶ Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with the best gold. 19  The throne had six steps, and the top of the throne was round [†]behind: and there were [†]stays on either side on the place of the seat, and two lions stood beside the stays. 20  And twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other upon the six steps: there was not [†]the like made in any kingdom.

21 ¶ And all king Solomon’s drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon were of pure gold; [∥]none were of silver: it was nothing accounted of in the days of Solomon. 22  For the king had at sea a navy of Tharshish with the navy of Hiram: once in three years came the navy of Tharshish, bringing gold, and silver, [∥]ivory, and apes, and peacocks. 23  So king Solomon exceeded all the kings of the earth for riches and for wisdom.

24 ¶ And all the earth [†]sought to Solomon, to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. 25  And they brought every man his present, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and garments, and armour, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year.

26 ¶ [*]And Solomon gathered together chariots and horsemen: and he had a thousand and four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, whom he bestowed in the cities for chariots, and with the king at Jerusalem. 27  And the king [†]made silver to be in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars made he to be as the sycomore trees that are in the vale, for abundance.

28 ¶ [*][†]And Solomon had horses brought out of Egypt, and linen yarn: the king’s merchants received the linen yarn at a price. 29  And a chariot came up and went out of Egypt for six hundred shekels of silver, and an horse for an hundred and fifty: and so for all the kings of the Hittites, and for the kings of Syria, did they bring them out [†]by their means.

11

1  But king Solomon loved [*]many strange women, [∥]together with the daughter of Pharaoh, women of the Moabites, Ammonites, Edomites, Zidonians, and Hittites; 2  Of the nations concerning which the LORD said unto the children of Israel, [*]Ye shall not go in to them, neither shall they come in unto you: for surely they will turn away your heart after their gods: Solomon clave unto these in love. 3  And he had seven hundred wives, princesses, and three hundred concubines: and his wives turned away his heart. 4  For it came to pass, when Solomon was old, that his wives turned away his heart after other gods: and his heart was not perfect with the LORD his God, as was the heart of David his father. 5  For Solomon went after [*]Ashtoreth the goddess of the Zidonians, and after Milcom the abomination of the Ammonites. 6  And Solomon did evil in the sight of the LORD, and [†]went not fully after the LORD, as did David his father. 7  Then did Solomon build an high place for Chemosh, the abomination of Moab, in the hill that is before Jerusalem, and for Molech, the abomination of the children of Ammon. 8  And likewise did he for all his strange wives, which burnt incense and sacrificed unto their gods.

9 ¶ And the LORD was angry with Solomon, because his heart was turned from the LORD God of Israel, [*]which had appeared unto him twice, 10  And [*]had commanded him concerning this thing, that he should not go after other gods: but he kept not that which the LORD commanded. 11  Wherefore the LORD said unto Solomon, Forasmuch as this [†]is done of thee, and thou hast not kept my covenant and my statutes, which I have commanded thee, [*]I will surely rend the kingdom from thee, and will give it to thy servant. 12  Notwithstanding in thy days I will not do it for David thy father’s sake: but I will rend it out of the hand of thy son. 13  Howbeit I will not rend away all the kingdom; but will give one tribe to thy son for David my servant’s sake, and for Jerusalem’s sake which I have chosen.

14 ¶ And the LORD stirred up an adversary unto Solomon, Hadad the Edomite: he was of the king’s seed in Edom. 15 [*] For it came to pass, when David was in Edom, and Joab the captain of the host was gone up to bury the slain, after he had smitten every male in Edom; 16 (For six months did Joab remain there with all Israel, until he had cut off every male in Edom:) 17  That Hadad fled, he and certain Edomites of his father’s servants with him, to go into Egypt; Hadad being yet a little child. 18  And they arose out of Midian, and came to Paran: and they took men with them out of Paran, and they came to Egypt, unto Pharaoh king of Egypt; which gave him an house, and appointed him victuals, and gave him land. 19  And Hadad found great favour in the sight of Pharaoh, so that he gave him to wife the sister of his own wife, the sister of Tahpenes the queen. 20  And the sister of Tahpenes bare him Genubath his son, whom Tahpenes weaned in Pharaoh’s house: and Genubath was in Pharaoh’s household among the sons of Pharaoh. 21  And when Hadad heard in Egypt that David slept with his fathers, and that Joab the captain of the host was dead, Hadad said to Pharaoh, [†]Let me depart, that I may go to mine own country. 22  Then Pharaoh said unto him, But what hast thou lacked with me, that, behold, thou seekest to go to thine own country? And he answered, [†]Nothing: howbeit let me go in any wise.

23 ¶ And God stirred him up another adversary, Rezon the son of Eliadah, which fled from his lord Hadadezer king of Zobah: 24  And he gathered men unto him, and became captain over a band, [*]when David slew them of Zobah: and they went to Damascus, and dwelt therein, and reigned in Damascus. 25  And he was an adversary to Israel all the days of Solomon, beside the mischief that Hadad did: and he abhorred Israel, and reigned over Syria.

26 ¶ And [*]Jeroboam the son of Nebat, an Ephrathite of Zereda, Solomon’s servant, whose mother’s name was Zeruah, a widow woman, even he lifted up his hand against the king. 27 And this was the cause that he lifted up his hand against the king: Solomon built Millo, and [†]repaired the breaches of the city of David his father. 28  And the man Jeroboam was a mighty man of valour: and Solomon seeing the young man that he [†]was industrious, he made him ruler over all the [†]charge of the house of Joseph. 29  And it came to pass at that time when Jeroboam went out of Jerusalem, that the prophet Ahijah the Shilonite found him in the way; and he had clad himself with a new garment; and they two were alone in the field: 30  And Ahijah caught the new garment that was on him, and rent it in twelve pieces: 31  And he said to Jeroboam, Take thee ten pieces: for thus saith the LORD, the God of Israel, Behold, I will rend the kingdom out of the hand of Solomon, and will give ten tribes to thee: 32 (But he shall have one tribe for my servant David’s sake, and for Jerusalem’s sake, the city which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel:) 33  Because that they have forsaken me, and have worshipped Ashtoreth the goddess of the Zidonians, Chemosh the god of the Moabites, and Milcom the god of the children of Ammon, and have not walked in my ways, to do that which is right in mine eyes, and to keep my statutes and my judgments, as did David his father. 34  Howbeit I will not take the whole kingdom out of his hand: but I will make him prince all the days of his life for David my servant’s sake, whom I chose, because he kept my commandments and my statutes: 35  But [*]I will take the kingdom out of his son’s hand, and will give it unto thee, even ten tribes. 36  And unto his son will I give one tribe, that David my servant may have a [†]light alway before me in Jerusalem, the city which I have chosen me to put my name there. 37  And I will take thee, and thou shalt reign according to all that thy soul desireth, and shalt be king over Israel. 38  And it shall be, if thou wilt hearken unto all that I command thee, and wilt walk in my ways, and do that is right in my sight, to keep my statutes and my commandments, as David my servant did; that I will be with thee, and build thee a sure house, as I built for David, and will give Israel unto thee. 39  And I will for this afflict the seed of David, but not for ever. 40  Solomon sought therefore to kill Jeroboam. And Jeroboam arose, and fled into Egypt, unto Shishak king of Egypt, and was in Egypt until the death of Solomon.

41 ¶ And the rest of the [∥]acts of Solomon, and all that he did, and his wisdom, are they not written in the book of the acts of Solomon? 42  And the [†]time that Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel was [*]forty years. 43  And Solomon slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David his father: and [*]Rehoboam his son reigned in his stead.

12

1  And [*]Rehoboam went to Shechem: for all Israel were come to Shechem to make him king. 2  And it came to pass, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who was yet in [*]Egypt, heard of it, (for he was fled from the presence of king Solomon, and Jeroboam dwelt in Egypt;) 3  That they sent and called him. And Jeroboam and all the congregation of Israel came, and spake unto Rehoboam, saying, 4  Thy father made our [*]yoke grievous: now therefore make thou the grievous service of thy father, and his heavy yoke which he put upon us, lighter, and we will serve thee. 5  And he said unto them, Depart yet for three days, then come again to me. And the people departed.

6 ¶ And king Rehoboam consulted with the old men, that stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, and said, How do ye advise that I may answer this people? 7  And they spake unto him, saying, If thou wilt be a servant unto this people this day, and wilt serve them, and answer them, and speak good words to them, then they will be thy servants for ever. 8  But he forsook the counsel of the old men, which they had given him, and consulted with the young men that were grown up with him, and which stood before him: 9  And he said unto them, What counsel give ye that we may answer this people, who have spoken to me, saying, Make the yoke which thy father did put upon us lighter? 10  And the young men that were grown up with him spake unto him, saying, Thus shalt thou speak unto this people that spake unto thee, saying, Thy father made our yoke heavy, but make thou it lighter unto us; thus shalt thou say unto them, My little finger shall be thicker than my father’s loins. 11  And now whereas my father did lade you with a heavy yoke, I will add to your yoke: my father hath chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions.

12 ¶ So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king had appointed, saying, Come to me again the third day. 13  And the king answered the people [†]roughly, and forsook the old men’s counsel that they gave him; 14  And spake to them after the counsel of the young men, saying, My father made your yoke heavy, and I will add to your yoke: my father also chastised you with whips, but I will chastise you with scorpions. 15  Wherefore the king hearkened not unto the people; for the cause was from the LORD, that he might perform his saying, which the LORD [*]spake by Ahijah the Shilonite unto Jeroboam the son of Nebat.

16 ¶ So when all Israel saw that the king hearkened not unto them, the people answered the king, saying, What portion have we in David? neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse: to your tents, O Israel: now see to thine own house, David. So Israel departed unto their tents. 17 But as for the children of Israel which dwelt in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. 18  Then king Rehoboam sent Adoram, who was over the tribute; and all Israel stoned him with stones, that he died. Therefore king Rehoboam [†]made speed to get him up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem. 19  So Israel [∥]rebelled against the house of David unto this day. 20  And it came to pass, when all Israel heard that Jeroboam was come again, that they sent and called him unto the congregation, and made him king over all Israel: there was none that followed the house of David, but the tribe of Judah [*]only.

21 ¶ And when Rehoboam was come to Jerusalem, he assembled all the house of Judah, with the tribe of Benjamin, an hundred and fourscore thousand chosen men, which were warriors, to fight against the house of Israel, to bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam the son of Solomon. 22  But [*]the word of God came unto Shemaiah the man of God, saying, 23  Speak unto Rehoboam, the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and unto all the house of Judah and Benjamin, and to the remnant of the people, saying, 24  Thus saith the LORD, Ye shall not go up, nor fight against your brethren the children of Israel: return every man to his house; for this thing is from me. They hearkened therefore to the word of the LORD, and returned to depart, according to the word of the LORD.

25 ¶ Then Jeroboam built Shechem in mount Ephraim, and dwelt therein; and went out from thence, and built Penuel. 26  And Jeroboam said in his heart, Now shall the kingdom return to the house of David: 27  If this people go up to do sacrifice in the house of the LORD at Jerusalem, then shall the heart of this people turn again unto their lord, even unto Rehoboam king of Judah, and they shall kill me, and go again to Rehoboam king of Judah. 28  Whereupon the king took counsel, and made two calves of gold, and said unto them, It is too much for you to go up to Jerusalem: [*]behold thy gods, O Israel, which brought thee up out of the land of Egypt. 29  And he set the one in Beth-el, and the other put he in Dan. 30  And this thing became a sin: for the people went to worship before the one, even unto Dan. 31  And he made an house of high places, and made priests of the lowest of the people, which were not of the sons of Levi. 32  And Jeroboam ordained a feast in the eighth month, on the fifteenth day of the month, like unto the feast that is in Judah, and he [∥]offered upon the altar. So did he in Beth-el, [∥]sacrificing unto the calves that he had made: and he placed in Beth-el the priests of the high places which he had made. 33  So he [∥]offered upon the altar which he had made in Beth-el the fifteenth day of the eighth month, even in the month which he had devised of his own heart; and ordained a feast unto the children of Israel: and he offered upon the altar, [†]and burnt incense.

13

1  And, behold, there came a man of God out of Judah by the word of the LORD unto Beth-el: and Jeroboam stood by the altar [∥]to burn incense. 2  And he cried against the altar in the word of the LORD, and said, O altar, altar, thus saith the LORD; Behold, a child shall be born unto the house of David, [*]Josiah by name; and upon thee shall he offer the priests of the high places that burn incense upon thee, and men’s bones shall be burnt upon thee. 3  And he gave a sign the same day, saying, This is the sign which the LORD hath spoken; Behold, the altar shall be rent, and the ashes that are upon it shall be poured out. 4  And it came to pass, when king Jeroboam heard the saying of the man of God, which had cried against the altar in Beth-el, that he put forth his hand from the altar, saying, Lay hold on him. And his hand, which he put forth against him, dried up, so that he could not pull it in again to him. 5  The altar also was rent, and the ashes poured out from the altar, according to the sign which the man of God had given by the word of the LORD. 6  And the king answered and said unto the man of God, Intreat now the face of the LORD thy God, and pray for me, that my hand may be restored me again. And the man of God besought [†]the LORD, and the king’s hand was restored [‡]him again, and became as it was before. 7  And the king said unto the man of God, Come home with me, and refresh thyself, and I will give thee a reward. 8  And the man of God said unto the king, If thou wilt give me half thine house, I will not go in with thee, neither will I eat bread nor drink water in this place: 9  For so was it charged me by the word of the LORD, saying, Eat no bread, nor drink water, nor turn again by the same way that thou camest. 10  So he went another way, and returned not by the way that he came to Beth-el.

11 ¶ Now there dwelt an old prophet in Beth-el; and his [‡]sons came and told him all the works that the man of God had done that day in Beth-el: the words which he had spoken unto the king, them they told also to their father. 12  And their father said unto them, What way went he? For his sons had seen what way the man of God went, which came from Judah. 13  And he said unto his sons, Saddle me the ass. So they saddled him the ass: and he rode thereon, 14  And went after the man of God, and found him sitting under an oak: and he said unto him, Art thou the man of God that camest from Judah? And he said, I am. 15  Then he said unto him, Come home with me, and eat bread. 16  And he said, I may not return with thee, nor go in with thee: neither will I eat bread nor drink water with thee in this place: 17  For [†]it was said to me by the word of the LORD, Thou shalt eat no bread nor drink water there, nor turn again to go by the way that thou camest. 18  He said unto him, I am a prophet also as thou art; and an angel spake unto me by the word of the LORD, saying, Bring him back with thee into thine house, that he may eat bread and drink water. But he lied unto him. 19  So he went back with him, and did eat bread in his house, and drank water.

20 ¶ And it came to pass, as they sat at the table, that the word of the LORD came unto the prophet that brought him back: 21  And he cried unto the man of God that came from Judah, saying, Thus saith the LORD, Forasmuch as thou hast disobeyed the mouth of the LORD, and hast not kept the commandment which the LORD thy God commanded thee, 22  But camest back, and hast eaten bread and drunk water in the place, of the which the Lord did say to thee, Eat no bread, and drink no water; thy carcase shall not come unto the sepulchre of thy fathers.

23 ¶ And it came to pass, after he had eaten bread, and after he had drunk, that he saddled for him the ass, to wit, for the prophet whom he had brought back. 24  And when he was gone, a lion met him by the way, and slew him: and his carcase was cast in the way, and the ass stood by it, the lion also stood by the carcase. 25  And, behold, men passed by, and saw the carcase cast in the way, and the lion standing by the carcase: and they came and told it in the city where the old prophet dwelt. 26  And when the prophet that brought him back from the way heard thereof, he said, It is the man of God, who was disobedient unto the word of the LORD: therefore the LORD hath delivered him unto the lion, which hath [†]torn him, and slain him, according to the word of the LORD, which he spake unto him. 27  And he spake to his sons, saying, Saddle me the ass. And they saddled him. 28  And he went and found his carcase cast in the way, and the ass and the lion standing by the carcase: the lion had not eaten the carcase, nor [†]torn the ass. 29  And the prophet took up the carcase of the man of God, and laid it upon the ass, and brought it back: and the old prophet came to the city, to mourn and to bury him. 30  And he laid his carcase in his own grave; and they mourned over him, saying, Alas, my brother! 31  And it came to pass, after he had buried him, that he spake to his sons, saying, When I am dead, then bury me in the sepulchre wherein the man of God is buried; lay my bones beside his bones: 32  For the saying which he cried by the word of the LORD against the altar in Beth-el, and against all the houses of the high places which are in the cities of Samaria, shall surely come to pass.

33 ¶ After this thing Jeroboam returned not from his evil way, but [†]made again of the lowest of the people priests of the high places: whosoever would, he [†]consecrated him, and he became one of the priests of the high places. 34  And this thing became sin unto the house of Jeroboam, even to cut it off, and to destroy it from off the face of the earth.

14

1  At that time Abijah the son of Jeroboam fell sick. 2  And Jeroboam said to his wife, Arise, I pray thee, and disguise thyself, that thou be not known to be the wife of Jeroboam; and get thee to Shiloh: behold, there is Ahijah the prophet, which told me that [*]I should be king over this people. 3  And take [†]with thee ten loaves, and [∥]cracknels, and a [∥]cruse of honey, and go to him: he shall tell thee what shall become of the child. 4  And Jeroboam’s wife did so, and arose, and went to Shiloh, and came to the house of Ahijah. But Ahijah could not see; for his eyes [†]were set by reason of his age.

5 ¶ And the LORD said unto Ahijah, Behold, the wife of Jeroboam cometh to ask a thing of thee for her son; for he is sick: thus and thus shalt thou say unto her: for it shall be, when she cometh in, that she shall feign herself to be another woman. 6 And it was so, when Ahijah heard the sound of her feet, as she came in at the door, that he said, Come in, thou wife of Jeroboam; why feignest thou thyself to be another? for I am sent to thee with [†]heavy tidings.

7  Go, tell Jeroboam, Thus saith the LORD God of Israel, Forasmuch as I exalted thee from among the people, and made thee prince over my people Israel, 8  And rent the kingdom away from the house of David, and gave it thee: and yet thou hast not been as my servant David, who kept my commandments, and who followed me with all his heart, to do that only which was right in mine eyes; 9  But hast done evil above all that were before thee: for thou hast gone and made thee other gods, and molten images, to provoke me to anger, and hast cast me behind thy back: 10  Therefore, behold, [*]I will bring evil upon the house of Jeroboam, and will cut off from Jeroboam [*]him that pisseth against the wall, and him that is shut up and left in Israel, and will take away the remnant of the house of Jeroboam, as a man taketh away dung, till it be all gone. 11  Him that dieth of Jeroboam in the city shall the dogs eat; and him that dieth in the field shall the fowls of the air eat: for the LORD hath spoken it. 12  Arise thou therefore, get thee to thine own house: and when thy feet enter into the city, the child shall die. 13  And all Israel shall mourn for him, and bury him: for he only of Jeroboam shall come to the grave, because in him there is found some good thing toward the LORD God of Israel in the house of Jeroboam. 14  Moreover the LORD shall raise him up a king over Israel, who shall cut off the house of Jeroboam that day: but what? even now. 15  For the LORD shall smite Israel, as a reed is shaken in the water, and he shall root up Israel out of this good land, which he gave to their fathers, and shall scatter them beyond the river, because they have made their groves, provoking the LORD to anger. 16  And he shall give Israel up because of the sins of Jeroboam, who did sin, and who made Israel to sin.

17 ¶ And Jeroboam’s wife arose, and departed, and came to Tirzah: and when she came to the threshold of the door, the child died; 18  And they buried him; and all Israel mourned for him, according to the word of the LORD, which he spake by the hand of his servant Ahijah the prophet. 19  And the rest of the acts of Jeroboam, how he warred, and how he reigned, behold, they are written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel. 20  And the days which Jeroboam reigned were two and twenty years: and he [†]slept with his fathers, and Nadab his son reigned in his stead.

21 ¶ And Rehoboam the son of Solomon reigned in Judah. [*]Rehoboam was forty and one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which the LORD did choose out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there. And his mother’s name was Naamah an Ammonitess. 22  And Judah did evil in the sight of the LORD, and they provoked him to jealousy with their sins which they had committed, above all that their fathers had done. 23  For they also built them high places, and [∥]images, and groves, on every high hill, and under every green tree. 24  And there were also sodomites in the land: and they did according to all the abominations of the nations which the LORD cast out before the children of Israel.

25 ¶ And it came to pass in the fifth year of king Rehoboam, that Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem: 26  And he took away the treasures of the house of the LORD, and the treasures of the king’s house; he even took away all: and he took away all the shields of gold [*]which Solomon had made. 27  And king Rehoboam made in their stead brasen shields, and committed them unto the hands of the chief of the [†]guard, which kept the door of the king’s house. 28 And it was so, when the king went into the house of the LORD, that the guard bare them, and brought them back into the guard chamber.

29 ¶ Now the rest of the acts of Rehoboam, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 30  And there was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all their days. 31  And Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David. And his mother’s name was Naamah an Ammonitess. And Abijam his son reigned in his stead.

15

1  Now in the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam the son of Nebat reigned Abijam over Judah. 2  Three years reigned he in Jerusalem. [*]And his mother’s name was Maachah, the daughter of Abishalom. 3  And he walked in all the sins of his father, which he had done before him: and his heart was not perfect with the LORD his God, as the heart of David his father. 4  Nevertheless for David’s sake did the LORD his God give him a [∥]lamp in Jerusalem, to set up his son after him, and to establish Jerusalem: 5  Because David did that which was right in the eyes of the LORD, and turned not aside from any thing that he commanded him all the days of his life, [*]save only in the matter of Uriah the Hittite. 6  And there was war between Rehoboam and Jeroboam all the days of his life. 7  Now the rest of the acts of Abijam, and all that he did, are they not written in the [*]book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? And there was war between Abijam and Jeroboam. 8  And Abijam slept with his fathers; and they buried him in the city of David: and [*]Asa his son reigned in his stead.

9 ¶ And in the twentieth year of Jeroboam king of Israel reigned Asa over Judah. 10  And forty and one years reigned he in Jerusalem. And his [∥]mother’s name was Maachah, the daughter of Abishalom. 11  And Asa did that which was right in the eyes of the LORD, as did David his father. 12  And he took away the sodomites out of the land, and removed all the idols that his fathers had made. 13  And also [*]Maachah his mother, even her he removed from being queen, because she had made an idol in a grove; and Asa [†]destroyed her idol, and burnt it by the brook Kidron. 14  But the high places were not removed: nevertheless Asa’s heart was perfect with the LORD all his days. 15  And he brought in the [†]things which his father had dedicated, and the things which himself had dedicated, into the house of the LORD, silver, and gold, and vessels.

16 ¶ And there was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days. 17  And Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah, and built Ramah, that he might not suffer any to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. 18  Then Asa took all the silver and the gold that were left in the treasures of the house of the LORD, and the treasures of the king’s house, and delivered them into the hand of his servants: and king Asa sent them to [*]Ben-hadad, the son of Tabrimon, the son of Hezion, king of Syria, that dwelt at Damascus, saying, 19  There is a league between me and thee, and between my father and thy father: behold, I have sent unto thee a present of silver and gold; come and break [‡]thy league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may [†]depart from me. 20  So Ben-hadad hearkened unto king Asa, and sent the captains of the hosts which he had against the cities of Israel, and smote Ijon, and Dan, and Abel-beth-maachah, and all Cinneroth, with all the land of Naphtali. 21  And it came to pass, when Baasha heard thereof, that he left off building of Ramah, and dwelt in Tirzah. 22  Then king Asa made a proclamation throughout all Judah; none was [†]exempted: and they took away the stones of Ramah, and the timber thereof, wherewith Baasha had builded; and king Asa built with them Geba of Benjamin, and Mizpah. 23  The rest of all the acts of Asa, and all his might, and all that he did, and the cities which he built, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? Nevertheless in the time of his old age he was diseased in his feet. 24  And Asa slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David his father: and [*]Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his stead.

25 ¶ And Nadab the son of Jeroboam [†]began to reign over Israel in the second year of Asa king of Judah, and reigned over Israel two years. 26  And he did evil in the sight of the LORD, and walked in the way of his father, and in his sin wherewith he made Israel to sin.

27 ¶ And Baasha the son of Ahijah, of the house of Issachar, conspired against him; and Baasha smote him at Gibbethon, which [‡]belonged to the Philistines; for Nadab and all Israel laid siege to Gibbethon. 28  Even in the third year of Asa king of Judah did Baasha slay him, and reigned in his stead. 29  And it came to pass, when he reigned, that he smote all the house of Jeroboam; he left not to Jeroboam any that breathed, until he had destroyed him, according unto [*]the saying of the LORD, which he spake by his servant Ahijah the Shilonite: 30  Because of the sins of Jeroboam which he sinned, and which he made Israel sin, by his provocation wherewith he provoked the LORD God of Israel to anger.

31 ¶ Now the rest of the acts of Nadab, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 32  And there was war between Asa and Baasha king of Israel all their days. 33  In the third year of Asa king of Judah began Baasha the son of Ahijah to reign over all Israel in Tirzah, twenty and four years. 34  And he did evil in the sight of the LORD, and walked in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin wherewith he made Israel to sin.

16

1  Then the word of the LORD came to Jehu the son of Hanani against Baasha, saying, 2  Forasmuch as I exalted thee out of the dust, and made thee prince over my people Israel; and thou hast walked in the way of Jeroboam, and hast made my people Israel to sin, to provoke me to anger with their sins; 3  Behold, I will take away the posterity of Baasha, and the posterity of his house; and will make thy house like [*]the house of Jeroboam the son of Nebat. 4 [*] Him that dieth of Baasha in the city shall the dogs eat; and him that dieth of his in the fields shall the fowls of the air eat. 5  Now the rest of the acts of Baasha, and what he did, and his might, are they not written in the [*]book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 6  So Baasha slept with his fathers, and was buried in Tirzah: and Elah his son reigned in his stead. 7  And also by the hand of the prophet Jehu the son of Hanani came the word of the LORD against Baasha, and against his house, even for all the evil that he did in the sight of the LORD, in provoking him to anger with the work of his hands, in being like the house of Jeroboam; and because he killed him.

8 ¶ In the [‡]twenty and sixth year of Asa king of Judah began Elah the son of Baasha to reign over Israel in Tirzah, two years. 9  And his servant Zimri, captain of half his chariots, conspired against him, as he was in Tirzah, drinking himself drunk in the house of Arza [†]steward of his house in Tirzah. 10  And Zimri went in and smote him, and killed him, in the twenty and seventh year of Asa king of Judah, and reigned in his stead.

11 ¶ And it came to pass, when he began to reign, as soon as he sat on his throne, that he slew all the house of Baasha: he left him not one that pisseth against a wall, [∥]neither of his kinsfolks, nor of his friends. 12  Thus did Zimri destroy all the house of Baasha, according to the word of the LORD, which he spake against Baasha [†]by Jehu the prophet, 13  For all the sins of Baasha, and the sins of Elah his son, by which they sinned, and by which they made Israel to sin, in provoking the LORD God of Israel to anger with their vanities. 14  Now the rest of the acts of Elah, and all that he did, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?

15 ¶ In the twenty and seventh year of Asa king of Judah did Zimri reign seven days in Tirzah. And the people were encamped against Gibbethon, which belonged to the Philistines. 16  And the people that were encamped heard say, Zimri hath conspired, and hath also slain the king: wherefore all Israel made Omri, the captain of the host, king over Israel that day in the camp. 17  And Omri went up from Gibbethon, and all Israel with him, and they besieged Tirzah. 18  And it came to pass, when Zimri saw that the city was taken, that he went into the palace of the king’s house, and burnt the king’s house over him with fire, and died, 19  For his sins which he sinned in doing evil in the sight of the LORD, in walking in the way of Jeroboam, and in his sin which he did, to make Israel [‡]to sin. 20  Now the rest of the acts of Zimri, and his treason that he wrought, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel?

21 ¶ Then were the people of Israel divided into two parts: half of the people followed Tibni the son of Ginath, to make him king; and half followed Omri. 22  But the people that followed Omri prevailed against the people that followed Tibni the son of Ginath: so Tibni died, and Omri reigned.

23 ¶ In the thirty and [‡]first year of Asa king of Judah began Omri to reign over Israel, twelve years: six years reigned he in Tirzah. 24  And he bought the hill Samaria of Shemer for two talents of silver, and built on the hill, and called the name of the city which he built, after the name of Shemer, owner of the hill, [†]Samaria.

25 ¶ But Omri wrought evil in the eyes of the LORD, and did worse than all that were before him. 26  For he walked in all the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and in his sin wherewith he made Israel to sin, to provoke the LORD God of Israel to anger with their vanities. 27  Now the rest of the acts of Omri which he did, and his might that he shewed, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 28  So Omri slept with his fathers, and was buried in Samaria: and Ahab his son reigned in his stead.

29 ¶ And in the thirty and eighth year of Asa king of Judah began Ahab the son of Omri to reign over Israel: and Ahab the son of Omri reigned over Israel in Samaria twenty and two years. 30  And Ahab the son of Omri did evil in the sight of the LORD above all that were before him. 31  And it came to pass, [†]as if it had been a light thing for him to walk in the sins of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, that he took to wife Jezebel the daughter of Ethbaal king of the Zidonians, and went and served Baal, and worshipped him. 32  And he reared up an altar for Baal in the house of Baal, which he had built in Samaria. 33  And Ahab made a grove; and Ahab did more to provoke the LORD God of Israel to anger than all the kings of Israel that were before him.

34 ¶ In his days did Hiel the Beth-elite build Jericho: he laid the foundation thereof in Abiram his firstborn, and set up the gates thereof in his youngest son Segub, [*]according to the word of the LORD, which he spake by Joshua the son of Nun.

17

1  And [†]Elijah the Tishbite, who was of the inhabitants of Gilead, said unto Ahab, [*]As the LORD God of Israel liveth, before whom I stand, there shall not be dew nor rain these years, but according to my word. 2  And the word of the LORD came unto him, saying, 3  Get thee hence, and turn thee eastward, and hide thyself by the brook Cherith, that is before Jordan. 4 And it shall be, that thou shalt drink of the brook; and I have commanded the ravens to feed thee there. 5  So he went and did according unto the word of the LORD: for he went and dwelt by the brook Cherith, that is before Jordan. 6  And the ravens brought him bread and flesh in the morning, and bread and flesh in the evening; and he drank of the brook. 7  And it came to pass [†]after a while, that the brook dried up, because there had been no rain in the land.

8 ¶ And the word of the LORD came unto him, saying, 9  Arise, get thee to [*]Zarephath, which belongeth to Zidon, and dwell there: behold, I have commanded a widow woman there to sustain thee. 10  So he arose and went to Zarephath. And when he came to the gate of the city, behold, the widow woman was there gathering of sticks: and he called to her, and said, Fetch me, I pray thee, a little water in a vessel, that I may drink. 11  And as she was going to fetch it, he called to her, and said, Bring me, I pray thee, a morsel of bread in thine hand. 12  And she said, As the LORD thy God liveth, I have not a cake, but an handful of meal in a barrel, and a little oil in a cruse: and, behold, I am gathering two sticks, that I may go in and dress it for me and my son, that we may eat it, and die. 13  And Elijah said unto her, Fear not; go and do as thou hast said: but make me thereof a little cake first, and bring it unto me, and after make for thee and for thy son. 14  For thus saith the LORD God of Israel, The barrel of meal shall not waste, neither shall the cruse of oil fail, until the day that the LORD [†]sendeth rain upon the earth. 15  And she went and did according to the saying of Elijah: and she, and he, and her house, did eat [∥]many days. 16  And the barrel of meal wasted not, neither did the cruse of oil fail, according to the word of the LORD, which he spake [†]by Elijah.

17 ¶ And it came to pass after these things, that the son of the woman, the mistress of the house, fell sick; and his sickness was so sore, that there was no breath left in him. 18  And she said unto Elijah, What have I to do with thee, O thou man of God? art thou come unto me to call my sin to remembrance, and to slay my son? 19  And he said unto her, Give me thy son. And he took him out of her bosom, and carried him up into a loft, where he abode, and laid him upon his own bed. 20  And he cried unto the LORD, and said, O LORD my God, hast thou also brought evil upon the widow with whom I sojourn, by slaying her son? 21  And he [†]stretched himself upon the child three times, and cried unto the LORD, and said, O LORD my God, I pray thee, let this child’s soul come [†]into him again. 22  And the LORD heard the voice of Elijah; and the soul of the child came into him again, and he revived. 23  And Elijah took the child, and brought him down out of the chamber into the house, and delivered him unto his mother: and Elijah said, See, thy son liveth.

24 ¶ And the woman said to Elijah, Now by this I know that thou art a man of God, and that the word of the LORD in thy mouth is truth.

18

1 And it came to pass after many days, that the word of the LORD came to Elijah in the third year, saying, Go, shew thyself unto Ahab; and I will send rain upon the earth. 2  And Elijah went to shew himself unto Ahab. And there was a sore famine in Samaria. 3  And Ahab called [†]Obadiah, which was [†]the governor of his house. (Now Obadiah feared the LORD greatly: 4 For it was so, when [†]Jezebel cut off the prophets of the LORD, that Obadiah took an hundred prophets, and hid them by fifty in a cave, and fed them with bread and water.) 5  And Ahab said unto Obadiah, Go into the land, unto all fountains of water, and unto all brooks: peradventure we may find grass to save the horses and mules alive, [†]that we lose not all the beasts. 6  So they divided the land between them to pass throughout it: Ahab went one way by himself, and Obadiah went another way by himself.

7 ¶ And as Obadiah was in the way, behold, Elijah met him: and he knew him, and fell on his face, and said, Art thou that my lord Elijah? 8  And he answered him, I am: go, tell thy lord, Behold, Elijah is here. 9  And he said, What have I sinned, that thou wouldest deliver thy servant into the hand of Ahab, to slay me? 10  As the LORD thy God liveth, there is no nation or kingdom, whither my lord hath not sent to seek thee: and when they said, He is not there; he took an oath of the kingdom and nation, that they found thee not. 11  And now thou sayest, Go, tell thy lord, Behold, Elijah is here. 12 And it shall come to pass, as soon as I am gone from thee, that the Spirit of the LORD shall carry thee whither I know not; and so when I come and tell Ahab, and he cannot find thee, he shall slay me: but I thy servant fear the LORD from my youth. 13  Was it not told my lord what I did when Jezebel slew the prophets of the LORD, how I hid an hundred men of the LORD’s prophets by fifty in a cave, and fed them with bread and water? 14  And now thou sayest, Go, tell thy lord, Behold, Elijah is here: and he shall slay me. 15  And Elijah said, As the LORD of hosts liveth, before whom I stand, I will surely shew myself unto him to day. 16  So Obadiah went to meet Ahab, and told him: and Ahab went to meet Elijah.

17 ¶ And it came to pass, when Ahab saw Elijah, that Ahab said unto him, Art thou he that troubleth Israel? 18  And he answered, I have not troubled Israel; but thou, and thy father’s house, in that ye have forsaken the commandments of the LORD, and thou hast followed Baalim. 19  Now therefore send, and gather to me all Israel unto mount Carmel, and the prophets of Baal four hundred and fifty, and the prophets of the groves four hundred, which eat at Jezebel’s table. 20  So Ahab sent unto all the children of Israel, and gathered the prophets together unto mount Carmel.

21  And Elijah came unto all the people, and said, How long halt ye between two [∥]opinions? if the LORD be God, follow him: but if Baal, then follow him. And the people answered him not a word. 22  Then said Elijah unto the people, I, even I only, remain a prophet of the LORD; but Baal’s prophets are four hundred and fifty men. 23  Let them therefore give us two bullocks; and let them choose one bullock for themselves, and cut it in pieces, and lay it on wood, and put no fire under: and I will dress the other bullock, and lay it on wood, and put no fire under: 24  And call ye on the name of your gods, and I will call on the name of the LORD: and the God that answereth by fire, let him be God. And all the people answered and said, [†]It is well spoken. 25  And Elijah said unto the prophets of Baal, Choose you one bullock for yourselves, and dress it first; for ye are many; and call on the name of your gods, but put no fire under. 26  And they took the bullock which was given them, and they dressed it, and called on the name of Baal from morning even until noon, saying, O Baal, [∥]hear us. But there was no voice, nor any that [∥]answered. And they [∥]leaped upon the altar which was made. 27  And it came to pass at noon, that Elijah mocked them, and said, Cry [†]aloud: for he is a god; either [∥]he is talking, or he [†]is pursuing, or he is in a journey, or peradventure he sleepeth, and must be awaked. 28  And they cried [‡]aloud, and cut themselves after their manner with knives and lancets, till [†]the blood gushed out upon them. 29  And it came to pass, when midday was past, and they prophesied until the time of the [†]offering of the evening sacrifice, that there was neither voice, nor any to answer, nor any [†]that regarded. 30  And Elijah said unto all the people, Come near unto me. And all the people came near unto him. And he repaired the altar of the LORD that was broken down. 31  And Elijah took twelve stones, according to the number of the tribes of the sons of Jacob, unto whom the word of the LORD came, saying, [*]Israel shall be thy name: 32  And with the stones he built an altar in the name of the LORD: and he made a trench about the altar, as great as would contain two measures of seed. 33  And he put the wood in order, and cut the bullock in pieces, and laid him on the wood, and said, Fill four barrels with water, and pour it on the burnt sacrifice, and on the wood. 34  And he said, Do it the second time. And they did it the second time. And he said, Do it the third time. And they did it the third time. 35  And the water [†]ran round about the altar; and he filled the trench also with water. 36 And it came to pass at the time of the offering of the evening sacrifice, that Elijah the prophet came near, and said, LORD God of Abraham, Isaac, and of Israel, let it be known this day that thou art God in Israel, and that I am thy servant, and that I have done all these things at thy word. 37  Hear me, O LORD, hear me, that this people may know that thou art the LORD God, and that thou hast turned their heart back again. 38  Then the fire of the LORD fell, and consumed the burnt sacrifice, and the wood, and the stones, and the dust, and licked up the water that was in the trench. 39  And when all the people saw it, they fell on their faces: and they said, The LORD, he is the God; the LORD, he is the God. 40  And Elijah said unto them, [∥]Take the prophets of Baal; let not one of them escape. And they took them: and Elijah brought them down to the brook Kishon, and slew them there.

41 ¶ And Elijah said unto Ahab, Get thee up, eat and drink; for there is [∥]a sound of abundance of rain. 42  So Ahab went up to eat and to drink. And Elijah went up to the top of Carmel; and he cast himself down upon the earth, and put his face between his knees, 43  And said to his servant, Go up now, look toward the sea. And he went up, and looked, and said, There is nothing. And he said, Go again seven times. 44  And it came to pass at the seventh time, that he said, Behold, there ariseth a little cloud out of the sea, like a man’s hand. And he said, Go up, say unto Ahab, [†]Prepare thy chariot, and get thee down, that the rain stop thee not. 45  And it came to pass in the mean while, that the heaven was black with clouds and wind, and there was a great rain. And Ahab rode, and went to Jezreel. 46  And the hand of the LORD was on Elijah; and he girded up his loins, and ran before Ahab [†]to the entrance of Jezreel.

19

1  And Ahab told Jezebel all that Elijah had done, and withal how he had slain all the prophets with the sword. 2  Then Jezebel sent a messenger unto Elijah, saying, So let the gods do to me, and more also, if I make not thy life as the life of one of them by to morrow about this time. 3  And when he saw that, he arose, and went for his life, and came to Beer-sheba, which belongeth to Judah, and left his servant there.

4 ¶ But he himself went a day’s journey into the wilderness, and came and sat down under a juniper tree: and he requested [†]for himself that he might die; and said, It is enough; now, O LORD, take away my life; for I am not better than my fathers. 5  And as he lay and slept under a juniper tree, behold, then an angel touched him, and said unto him, Arise and eat. 6  And he looked, and, behold, there was a cake baken on the coals, and a cruse of water at his [†]head. And he did eat and drink, and laid him down again. 7  And the angel of the LORD came again the second time, and touched him, and said, Arise and eat; because the journey is too great for thee. 8  And he arose, and did eat and drink, and went in the strength of that meat forty days and forty nights unto Horeb the mount of God.

9 ¶ And he came thither unto a cave, and lodged there; and, behold, the word of the LORD came to him, and he said unto him, What doest thou here, Elijah? 10  And he said, I have been very jealous for the LORD God of hosts: for the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, thrown down thine altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword; and [*]I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away. 11  And he said, Go forth, and stand upon the mount before the LORD. And, behold, the LORD passed by, and a great and strong wind rent the mountains, and brake in pieces the rocks before the LORD; but the LORD was not in the wind: and after the wind an earthquake; but the LORD was not in the earthquake: 12  And after the earthquake a fire; but the LORD was not in the fire: and after the fire a still small voice. 13 And it was so, when Elijah heard it, that he wrapped his face in his mantle, and went out, and stood in the entering in of the cave. And, behold, there came a voice unto him, and said, What doest thou here, Elijah? 14  And he said, I have been very jealous for the LORD God of hosts: because the children of Israel have forsaken thy covenant, thrown down thine altars, and slain thy prophets with the sword; and I, even I only, am left; and they seek my life, to take it away. 15  And the LORD said unto him, Go, return on thy way to the wilderness of Damascus: and when thou comest, anoint Hazael to be king over Syria: 16  And Jehu the son of Nimshi shalt thou anoint to be king over Israel: and [*]Elisha the son of Shaphat of Abel-meholah shalt thou anoint to be prophet in thy room. 17 And [*]it shall come to pass, that him that escapeth the sword of Hazael shall Jehu slay: and him that escapeth from the sword of Jehu shall Elisha slay. 18 [*] Yet [∥]I have left me seven thousand in Israel, all the knees which have not bowed unto Baal, and every mouth which hath not kissed him.

19 ¶ So he departed thence, and found Elisha the son of Shaphat, who was plowing with twelve yoke of oxen before him, and he with the twelfth: and Elijah passed by him, and cast his mantle upon him. 20  And he left the oxen, and ran after Elijah, and said, Let me, I pray thee, kiss my father and my mother, and then I will follow thee. And he said unto him, [†]Go back again: for what have I done to thee? 21  And he returned back from him, and took a yoke of oxen, and slew them, and boiled their flesh with the instruments of the oxen, and gave unto the people, and they did eat. Then he arose, and went after Elijah, and ministered unto him.

20

1  And Ben-hadad the king of Syria gathered all his host together: and there were thirty and two kings with him, and horses, and chariots: and he went up and besieged Samaria, and warred against it. 2  And he sent messengers to Ahab king of Israel into the city, and said unto him, Thus saith Ben-hadad, 3  Thy silver and thy gold is mine; thy wives also and thy children, even the goodliest, are mine. 4  And the king of Israel answered and said, My lord, O king, according to thy saying, I am thine, and all that I have. 5  And the messengers came again, and said, Thus speaketh Ben-hadad, saying, Although I have sent unto thee, saying, Thou shalt deliver me thy silver, and thy gold, and thy wives, and thy children; 6  Yet I will send my servants unto thee to morrow about this time, and they shall search thine house, and the houses of thy servants; and it shall be, that whatsoever is [†]pleasant in thine eyes, they shall put it in their hand, and take it away. 7  Then the king of Israel called all the elders of the land, and said, Mark, I pray you, and see how this man seeketh mischief: for he sent unto me for my wives, and for my children, and for my silver, and for my gold; and [†]I denied him not. 8  And all the elders and all the people said unto him, Hearken not unto him, nor consent. 9  Wherefore he said unto the messengers of Ben-hadad, Tell my lord the king, All that thou didst send for to thy servant at the first I will do: but this thing I may not do. And the messengers departed, and brought him word again. 10  And Ben-hadad sent unto him, and said, The gods do so unto me, and more also, if the dust of Samaria shall suffice for handfuls for all the people that [†]follow me. 11  And the king of Israel answered and said, Tell him, Let not him that girdeth on his harness boast himself as he that putteth it off.

12 And it came to pass, when Ben-hadad heard this [†]message, as he was drinking, he and the kings in the [∥]pavilions, that he said unto his servants, [∥]Set yourselves in array. And they set themselves in array against the city.

13 ¶ And, behold, there [†]came a prophet unto Ahab king of Israel, saying, Thus saith the LORD, Hast thou seen all this great multitude? behold, I will deliver it into thine hand this day; and thou shalt know that I am the LORD. 14  And Ahab said, By whom? And he said, Thus saith the LORD, Even by the [∥]young men of the princes of the provinces. Then he said, Who shall [†]order the battle? And he answered, Thou. 15  Then he numbered the young men of the princes of the provinces, and they were two hundred and thirty two: and after them he numbered all the people, even all the children of Israel, being seven thousand. 16  And they went out at noon. But Ben-hadad was drinking himself drunk in the pavilions, he and the kings, the thirty and two kings that helped him. 17  And the young men of the princes of the provinces went out first; and Ben-hadad sent out, and they told him, saying, There are men come out of Samaria. 18  And he said, Whether they be come out for peace, take them alive; or whether they be come out for war, take them alive. 19  So these young men of the princes of the provinces came out of the city, and the army which followed them. 20  And they slew every one his man: and the Syrians fled; and Israel pursued them: and Ben-hadad the king of Syria escaped on an horse with the horsemen. 21  And the king of Israel went out, and smote the horses and chariots, and slew the Syrians with a great slaughter.

22 ¶ And the prophet came to the king of Israel, and said unto him, Go, strengthen thyself, and mark, and see what thou doest: for at the return of the year the king of Syria will come up against thee. 23  And the servants of the king of Syria said unto him, Their gods are gods of the hills; therefore they were stronger than we; but let us fight against them in the plain, and surely we shall be stronger than they. 24  And do this thing, Take the kings away, every man out of his place, and put captains in their rooms: 25  And number thee an army, like the army [†]that thou hast lost, horse for horse, and chariot for chariot: and we will fight against them in the plain, and surely we shall be stronger than they. And he hearkened unto their voice, and did so. 26  And it came to pass at the return of the year, that Ben-hadad numbered the Syrians, and went up to Aphek, [†]to fight against Israel. 27  And the children of Israel were numbered, and [∥]were all present, and went against them: and the children of Israel pitched before them like two little flocks of kids; but the Syrians filled the country.

28 ¶ And there came a man of God, and spake unto the king of Israel, and said, Thus saith the LORD, Because the Syrians have said, The LORD is God of the hills, but he is not God of the valleys, therefore will I deliver all this great multitude into thine hand, and ye shall know that I am the LORD. 29  And they pitched one over against the other seven days. And so it was, that in the seventh day the battle was joined: and the children of Israel slew of the Syrians an hundred thousand footmen in one day. 30  But the rest fled to Aphek, into the city; and there a wall fell upon twenty and seven thousand of the men that were left. And Ben-hadad fled, and came into the city, [∥][†]into an inner chamber.

31 ¶ And his servants said unto him, Behold now, we have heard that the kings of the house of Israel are merciful kings: let us, I pray thee, put sackcloth on our loins, and ropes upon our heads, and go out to the king of Israel: peradventure he will save thy life. 32  So they girded sackcloth on their loins, and put ropes on their heads, and came to the king of Israel, and said, Thy servant Ben-hadad saith, I pray thee, let me live. And he said, Is he yet alive? he is my brother. 33  Now the men did diligently observe whether any thing would come from him, and did hastily catch it: and they said, Thy brother Ben-hadad. Then he said, Go ye, bring him. Then Ben-hadad came forth to him; and he caused him to come up into the chariot. 34 And Ben-hadad said unto him, The cities, which my father took from thy father, I will restore; and thou shalt make streets for thee in Damascus, as my father made in Samaria. Then said Ahab, I will send thee away with this covenant. So he made a covenant with him, and sent him away.

35 ¶ And a certain man of the sons of the prophets said unto his neighbour in the word of the LORD, Smite me, I pray thee. And the man refused to smite him. 36  Then said he unto him, Because thou hast not obeyed the voice of the LORD, behold, as soon as thou art departed from me, a lion shall slay thee. And as soon as he was departed from him, a lion found him, and slew him. 37  Then he found another man, and said, Smite me, I pray thee. And the man smote him, [†]so that in smiting he wounded him. 38  So the prophet departed, and waited for the king by the way, and disguised himself with ashes upon his face. 39  And as the king passed by, he cried unto the king: and he said, Thy servant went out into the midst of the battle; and, behold, a man turned aside, and brought a man unto me, and said, Keep this man: if by any means he be missing, then shall thy life be for his life, or else thou shalt [†]pay a talent of silver. 40  And as thy servant was busy here and there, [†]he was gone. And the king of Israel said unto him, So shall thy judgment be; thyself hast decided it. 41  And he hasted, and took the ashes away from his face; and the king of Israel discerned him that he was of the prophets. 42  And he said unto him, Thus saith the LORD, [*]Because thou hast let go out of thy hand a man whom I appointed to utter destruction, therefore thy life shall go for his life, and thy people for his people. 43  And the king of Israel went to his house heavy and displeased, and came to Samaria.

21

1  And it came to pass after these things, that Naboth the Jezreelite had a vineyard, which was in Jezreel, hard by the palace of Ahab king of Samaria. 2  And Ahab spake unto Naboth, saying, Give me thy vineyard, that I may have it for a garden of herbs, because it is near unto my house: and I will give thee for it a better vineyard than it; or, if it [†]seem good to thee, I will give thee the worth of it in money. 3  And Naboth said to Ahab, The LORD forbid it me, that I should give the inheritance of my fathers unto thee. 4  And Ahab came into his house heavy and displeased because of the word which Naboth the Jezreelite had spoken to him: for he had said, I will not give thee the inheritance of my fathers. And he laid him down upon his bed, and turned away his face, and would eat no bread.

5 ¶ But Jezebel his wife came to him, and said unto him, Why is thy spirit so sad, that thou eatest no bread? 6  And he said unto her, Because I spake unto Naboth the Jezreelite, and said unto him, Give me thy vineyard for money; or else, if it please thee, I will give thee another vineyard for it: and he answered, I will not give thee my vineyard. 7  And Jezebel his wife said unto him, Dost thou now govern the kingdom of Israel? arise, and eat bread, and let thine heart be merry: I will give thee the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite. 8  So she wrote letters in Ahab’s name, and sealed them with his seal, and sent the letters unto the elders and to the nobles that were in his city, dwelling with Naboth. 9  And she wrote in the letters, saying, Proclaim a fast, and set Naboth [†]on high among the people: 10  And set two men, sons of Belial, before him, to bear witness against him, saying, Thou didst blaspheme God and the king. And then carry him out, and stone him, that he may die. 11  And the men of his city, even the elders and the nobles who were the inhabitants in his city, did as Jezebel had sent unto them, and as it was written in the letters which she had sent unto them. 12  They proclaimed a fast, and set Naboth on high among the people. 13  And there came in two men, children of Belial, and sat before him: and the men of Belial witnessed against him, even against Naboth, in the presence of the people, saying, Naboth did blaspheme God and the king. Then they carried him forth out of the city, and stoned him with stones, that he died. 14  Then they sent to Jezebel, saying, Naboth is stoned, and is dead.

15 ¶ And it came to pass, when Jezebel heard that Naboth was stoned, and was dead, that Jezebel said to Ahab, Arise, take possession of the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, which he refused to give thee for money: for Naboth is not alive, but dead. 16  And it came to pass, when Ahab heard that Naboth was dead, that Ahab rose up to go down to the vineyard of Naboth the Jezreelite, to take possession of it.

17 ¶ And the word of the LORD came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, 18  Arise, go down to meet Ahab king of Israel, which is in Samaria: behold, he is in the vineyard of Naboth, whither he is gone down to possess it. 19  And thou shalt speak unto him, saying, Thus saith the LORD, Hast thou killed, and also taken possession? And thou shalt speak unto him, saying, Thus saith the LORD, In the place where dogs licked the blood of Naboth shall dogs lick thy blood, even thine. 20  And Ahab said to Elijah, Hast thou found me, O mine enemy? And he answered, I have found thee: because thou hast sold thyself to work evil in the sight of the LORD. 21  Behold, [*]I will bring evil upon thee, and will take away thy posterity, and will cut off from Ahab [*]him that pisseth against the wall, and [*]him that is shut up and left in Israel, 22  And will make thine house like the house of [*]Jeroboam the son of Nebat, and like the house of [*]Baasha the son of Ahijah, for the provocation wherewith thou hast provoked me to anger, and made Israel to sin. 23  And [*]of Jezebel also spake the LORD, saying, The dogs shall eat Jezebel by the [∥]wall of Jezreel. 24  Him that dieth of Ahab in the city the dogs shall eat; and him that dieth in the field shall the fowls of the air eat.

25 ¶ But there was none like unto Ahab, which did sell himself to work wickedness in the sight of the LORD, whom Jezebel his wife [∥]stirred up. 26  And he did very abominably in following idols, according to all things as did the Amorites, whom the LORD cast out before the children of Israel. 27  And it came to pass, when Ahab heard those words, that he rent his clothes, and put sackcloth upon his flesh, and fasted, and lay in sackcloth, and went softly. 28  And the word of the LORD came to Elijah the Tishbite, saying, 29  Seest thou how Ahab humbleth himself before me? because he humbleth himself before me, I will not bring the evil in his days: but in his son’s days will I bring the evil upon his house.

22

1  And they continued three years without war between Syria and Israel. 2  And it came to pass in the third year, that [*]Jehoshaphat the king of Judah came down to the king of Israel. 3  And the king of Israel said unto his servants, Know ye that Ramoth in Gilead is ours, and we be [†]still, and take it not out of the hand of the king of Syria? 4  And he said unto Jehoshaphat, Wilt thou go with me to battle to Ramoth-gilead? And Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, [*]I am as thou art, my people as thy people, my horses as thy horses. 5  And Jehoshaphat said unto the king of Israel, Enquire, I pray thee, at the word of the LORD to day. 6  Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, about four hundred men, and said unto them, Shall I go against Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? And they said, Go up; for the Lord shall deliver it into the hand of the king. 7  And Jehoshaphat said, Is there not here a prophet of the LORD besides, that we might enquire of him? 8  And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, There is yet one man, Micaiah the son of Imlah, by whom we may enquire of the LORD: but I hate him; for he doth not prophesy good concerning me, but evil. And Jehoshaphat said, Let not the king say so. 9  Then the king of Israel called an [∥]officer, and said, Hasten hither Micaiah the son of Imlah. 10  And the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah sat each on his throne, having put on their robes, in a [†]void place in the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets prophesied before them. 11  And Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made him horns of iron: and he said, Thus saith the LORD, With these shalt thou push the Syrians, until thou have consumed them. 12  And all the prophets prophesied so, saying, Go up to Ramoth-gilead, and prosper: for the LORD shall deliver it into the king’s hand. 13  And the messenger that was gone to call Micaiah spake unto him, saying, Behold now, the words of the prophets declare good unto the king with one mouth: let thy word, I pray thee, be like the word of one of them, and speak that which is good. 14  And Micaiah said, As the LORD liveth, what the LORD saith unto me, that will I speak.

15 ¶ So he came to the king. And the king said unto him, Micaiah, shall we go against Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall we forbear? And he answered him, Go, and prosper: for the LORD shall deliver it into the hand of the king. 16  And the king said unto him, How many times shall I adjure thee that thou tell me nothing but that which is true in the name of the LORD? 17  And he said, I saw all Israel scattered upon the hills, as sheep that have not a shepherd: and the LORD said, These have no master: let them return every man to his house in peace. 18  And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, Did I not tell thee that he would prophesy no good concerning me, but evil? 19  And he said, Hear thou therefore the word of the LORD: I saw the LORD sitting on his throne, and all the host of heaven standing by him on his right hand and on his left. 20  And the LORD said, Who shall [∥]persuade Ahab, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-gilead? And one said on this manner, and another said on that manner. 21  And there came forth a spirit, and stood before the LORD, and said, I will persuade him. 22  And the LORD said unto him, Wherewith? And he said, I will go forth, and I will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets. And he said, Thou shalt persuade him, and prevail also: go forth, and do so. 23  Now therefore, behold, the LORD hath put a lying spirit in the mouth of all these thy prophets, and the LORD hath spoken evil concerning thee. 24  But Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah went near, and smote Micaiah on the cheek, and said, [*]Which way went the Spirit of the LORD from me to speak unto thee? 25  And Micaiah said, Behold, thou shalt see in that day, when thou shalt go [∥]into [†]an inner chamber to hide thyself. 26  And the king of Israel said, Take Micaiah, and carry him back unto Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king’s son; 27  And say, Thus saith the king, Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I come in peace. 28  And Micaiah said, If thou return at all in peace, the LORD hath not spoken by me. And he said, Hearken, O people, every one of you.

29  So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth-gilead. 30  And the king of Israel said unto Jehoshaphat, [∥]I will disguise myself, and enter into the battle; but put thou on thy robes. And the king of Israel disguised himself, and went into the battle. 31  But the king of Syria commanded his thirty and two captains that had rule over his chariots, saying, Fight neither with small nor great, save only with the king of Israel. 32  And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, Surely it is the king of Israel. And they turned aside to fight against him: and Jehoshaphat cried out. 33  And it came to pass, when the captains of the chariots perceived that it was not the king of Israel, that they turned back from pursuing him. 34 And a certain man drew a bow [†]at a venture, and smote the king of Israel between the [†]joints of the harness: wherefore he said unto the driver of his chariot, Turn thine hand, and carry me out of the host; for I am [†]wounded. 35  And the battle [†]increased that day: and the king was stayed up in his chariot against the Syrians, and died at even: and the blood ran out of the wound into the [†]midst of the chariot. 36  And there went a proclamation throughout the host about the going down of the sun, saying, Every man to his city, and every man to his own country.

37 ¶ So the king died, and [†]was brought to Samaria; and they buried the king in Samaria. 38 And one washed the chariot in the pool of Samaria; and the dogs licked up his blood; and they washed his armour; according [*]unto the word of the LORD which he spake. 39  Now the rest of the acts of Ahab, and all that he did, and the ivory house which he made, and all the cities that he built, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Israel? 40  So Ahab slept with his fathers; and Ahaziah his son reigned in his stead.

41 ¶ And [*]Jehoshaphat the son of Asa began to reign over Judah in the fourth year of Ahab king of Israel. 42  Jehoshaphat was thirty and five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty and five years in Jerusalem. And his mother’s name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. 43  And he walked in all the ways of Asa his father; he turned not aside from it, doing that which was right in the eyes of the LORD: nevertheless the high places were not taken away; for the people offered and burnt incense yet in the high places. 44  And Jehoshaphat made peace with the king of Israel. 45  Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, and his might that he shewed, and how he warred, are they not written in the book of the chronicles of the kings of Judah? 46  And the remnant of the sodomites, which remained in the days of his father Asa, he took out of the land. 47  There was then no king in Edom: a deputy was king. 48  Jehoshaphat [∥]made ships of Tharshish to go to Ophir for gold: but they went not; for the ships were broken at Ezion-geber. 49  Then said Ahaziah the son of Ahab unto Jehoshaphat, Let my servants go with thy servants in the ships. But Jehoshaphat would not.

50 ¶ And Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David his father: and Jehoram his son reigned in his stead.

51 ¶ Ahaziah the son of Ahab began to reign over Israel in Samaria the seventeenth year of Jehoshaphat king of Judah, and reigned two years over Israel. 52  And he did evil in the sight of the LORD, and walked in the way of his father, and in the way of his mother, and in the way of Jeroboam the son of Nebat, who made Israel to sin: 53  For he served Baal, and worshipped him, and provoked to anger the LORD God of Israel, according to all that his father had done.

† 1.1 Heb. entered into days.

† 1.2 Heb. Let them seek.

† 1.2 Heb a damsel, a virgin.

† 1.2 Heb. be a cherisher unto him.

† 1.5 Heb. reign.

† 1.6 Heb. from his days.

† 1.7 Heb. his words were with Joab.

† 1.7 Heb. helped after Adonijah.

∥ 1.9 Or, the well Rogel.

* 1.11 2 Sam. 3 4.

† 1.14 Heb. fill up.

† 1.16 Heb. What to thee?

† 1.21 Heb. sinners.

† 1.25 Heb. Let king Adonijah live.

† 1.28 Heb. before the king.

† 1.33 Heb. which belongeth to me.

∥ 1.40 Or, flutes.

* 2.3 Deut. 29. 9. Josh. 1. 7.

∥ 2.3 Or, do wisely.

* 2.4 2 Sam. 7. 12.

† 2.4 Heb. be cut off from thee from the throne.

* 2.5 2 Sam. 3. 27.

* 2.5 2 Sam. 20. 10.

† 2.5 Heb. put.

* 2.7 2 Sam. 19. 31.

* 2.8 2 Sam. 16. 5.

† 2.8 Heb. strong.

* 2.8 2 Sam. 19. 23.

* 2.10 Acts 2. 29. &c 13. 36.

* 2.11 2 Sam. 5. 4. 1 Chr. 29. 26, 27.

* 2.12 2 Chr. 29. 23.

† 2.16 Heb. turn not away my face.

* 2.24 2 Sam. 7. 12, 13.

† 2.26 Heb. a man of death.

* 2.27 1 Sam. 2. 31, 35.

* 2.32 2 Sam. 3. 27.

* 2.32 2 Sam. 20. 10.

* 2.46 2 Chr. 1. 1.

* 3.1 ch. 7. 8.

‡ 3.4 [1611 up on]

∥ 3.6 Or, bounty.

* 3.9 2 Chr. 1. 10.

† 3.9 Heb. hearing.

† 3.11 Heb. many days.

† 3.11 Heb. to hear.

‡ 3.12 [1611 word]

* 3.13 Wisd. 7. 11. Matt. 6. 33.

∥ 3.13 Or, hath not been.

* 3.14 ch. 15. 5.

† 3.26 Heb. were hot.

† 3.28 Heb. in the midst of him.

∥ 4.2 Or, the chief officer.

∥ 4.3 Or, secretaries.

∥ 4.3 Or, remembrancer.

* 4.6 ch. 5. 14.

∥ 4.6 Or, levy.

∥ 4.8 Or, Ben-hur.

∥ 4.9 Or, Ben-dekar.

∥ 4.10 Or, Ben-hesed.

∥ 4.11 Or, Ben-abinadab.

∥ 4.13 Or, Ben-geber.

∥ 4.14 Or, to Mahanaim.

* 4.21 Ecclus. 47. 13.

† 4.22 Heb. bread.

† 4.22 Heb. cors.

† 4.25 Heb. confidently.

* 4.26 2 Chr. 9. 25.

∥ 4.28 Or, mules, or, swift beasts.

* 4.29 Ecclus. 47. 14, 15, 16.

* 5.2 2 Chr. 2. 3.

† 5.5 Heb. say.

* 5.5 2 Sam. 7. 13. 1 Chr. 22. 10.

† 5.6 Heb. say.

† 5.8 Heb. heard.

† 5.9 Heb. send.

† 5.11 Heb. cors.

* 5.12 ch. 3. 12.

† 5.13 Heb tribute of men.

* 5.14 ch. 4. 6

∥ 5.18 Or, Giblites, as Ezek. 27. 9.

* 6.1 2 Chr. 3. 1.

‡ 6.1 [1611 fourscore]

† 6.1 Heb. built.

∥ 6.4 Or, windows broad within, and narrow without: or, skewed and closed.

∥ 6.5 Or, upon, or, joining to.

† 6.5 Heb. floors.

† 6.5 Heb. ribs.

† 6.6 Heb. narrowings, or, rebatements.

† 6.8 Heb. shoulder.

∥ 6.9 Or, the vault-beams and the cielings with cedar.

* 6.12 2 Sam. 7. 13. 1 Chr. 22. 10.

∥ 6.15 ver. 16.

∥ 6.18 Or, gourds.

† 6.18 Heb. openings of flowers.

† 6.20 Heb. shut up.

∥ 6.23 Or, oily.

† 6.23 Heb. trees of oil.

* 6.27 Ex. 25. 20.

∥ 6.27 Or, the cherubims stretched forth their wings.

† 6.29 Heb. openings of flowers.

∥ 6.31 Or, fivesquare.

∥ 6.32 Or, leaves of the doors.

† 6.32 Heb. openings of flowers.

∥ 6.33 Or, foursquare.

∥ 6.38 Or, with all the appurtenances thereof, and with all the ordinances thereof.

* 7.1 ch. 9. 10.

† 7.3 Heb. ribs.

† 7.4 Heb. sight against sight.

∥ 7.5 Or, spaces and pillars were square in prospect.

∥ 7.6 Or, according to them.

∥ 7.6 Or, according to them.

† 7.7 Heb. from floor to floor.

* 7.8 ch. 3. 1

† 7.14 Heb. the son of a widow woman.

† 7.15 Heb. fashional.

* 7.21 2 Chr. 3. 17.

∥ 7.21 That is, He shall establish.

∥ 7.21 That is, In it is strength.

† 7.23 Heb from his brim to his brim.

* 7.24 2 Chr. 4. 3.

† 7.32 Heb. in the base.

† 7.36 Heb. nakedness.

† 7.39 Heb. shoulder.

† 7.42 Heb. upon the face of.

† 7.45 Heb. made bright, or, scoured.

† 7.46 Heb. in the thickness of the ground.

† 7.47 Heb. for the exceeding multitude.

† 7.47 Heb. searched.

† 7.50 Heb. ash pans.

† 7.51 Heb. [holy] things of David.

* 7.51 2 Chr. 5. 1.

* 8.1 2 Chr. 5. 2.

† 8.1 Heb. princes.

† 8.8 Heb. heads.

∥ 8.8 2 Chr. 5. 9.

* 8.9 Deut. 10. 5.

∥ 8.9 Or, where.

* 8.10 Ex. 40. 34.

* 8.12 2 Chr. 6. 1.

* 8.16 2 Sam. 7. 8.

* 8.22 2 Chr. 6. 13.

* 8.23 2 Mac. 2. 8.

* 8.25 2 Sam. 7, 12. ch. 2. 4.

† 8.25 Heb. There shall not be cut off unto thee a man from my sight.

† 8.25 Heb. only if.

* 8.29 Deut. 12. 11.

∥ 8.29 Or, in this place.

∥ 8.30 Or, in this place.

† 8.31 Heb. and he require an oath of him.

∥ 8.33 Or, towards.

∥ 8.37 Or, jurisdiction.

† 8.43 Heb. thy name is called upon this house.

† 8.44 Heb. the way of the city.

∥ 8.45 Or, right.

* 8.46 2 Chr. 6. 36. Eccles. 7. 22. 1 John 1. 8, 10.

† 8.47 Heb. bring back to their heart.

∥ 8.49 Or, right.

* 8.53 Ex. 19. 6.

† 8.56 Heb. fallen.

† 8.59 Heb. the thing of a day in his day.

‡ 8.61 [1611 your]

* 8.62 2 Chr. 7. 4.

* 8.64 2 Chr. 7. 7.

∥ 8.66 Or, thanked.

* 9.1 2 Chr. 7. 11.

* 9.2 ch. 3. 5.

* 9.3 ch. 8. 29.

* 9.5 2 Sam. 7 12. 1 Chr. 22. 10.

* 9.7 Jer. 7. 14.

* 9.8 Deut. 29. 24. Jer. 22. 8.

* 9.10 2 Chr. 8. 1.

‡ 9.11 [1611 omits king]

† 9.12 Heb. were not right in his eyes.

∥ 9.13 That is, displeasing, or, dirty.

† 9.19 Heb. the desire of Solomon which he desired.

* 9.22 Lev. 25. 39.

* 9.24 2 Chr. 8. 11.

† 9.25 Heb. upon it.

† 9.26 Heb. lip.

* 10.1 2 Chr. 9. 1. Matt. 12. 42. Luke 11. 31.

† 10.3 Heb. words.

† 10.5 Heb. standing.

∥ 10.5 Or, butlers

† 10.6 Heb. word.

∥ 10.6 Or, sayings.

† 10.7 Heb. thou hast added wisdom and goodness to the fame.

∥ 10.12 Or, rails.

† 10.12 Heb. a prop.

* 10.12 2 Chr. 9. 10.

† 10.13 Heb. according to the hand of king Solomon.

∥ 10.15 Or, captains.

* 10.17 ch. 7. 2.

† 10.19 Heb. on the hinder part thereof.

† 10.19 Heb. kands.

† 10.20 Heb. so.

∥ 10.21 Or, there was no silver in them.

∥ 10.22 Or, elephants' teeth.

† 10.24 Heb. sought the face of.

* 10.26 2 Chr. 1. 14.

† 10.27 Heb. gave.

* 10.28 2 Chr. 1 16. &c 9. 28.

† 10.28 Heb. And the going forth of the horses which was Solomon's.

† 10.29 Heb. by their hand.

* 11.1 Deut. 17. 17. Ecclus. 47. 19.

∥ 11.1 Or, besides.

* 11.2 Ex. 34. 16.

* 11.5 Judg. 2 13.

† 11.6 Heb. ful filled not after.

* 11.9 ch. 3. 5. &c 9. 2.

* 11.10 ch. 6. 12.

† 11.11 Heb. is with thee.

* 11.11 ch. 12. 15.

* 11.15 2 Sam. 8. 14.

† 11.21 Heb. Send me away.

† 11.22 Heb. Not.

* 11.24 2 Sam. 8 3. &c 10. 18.

* 11.26 2 Chr. 13. 6.

† 11.27 Heb. closed.

† 11.28 Heb. did work.

† 11.28 Heb. burden.

* 11.35 ch. 12. 15.

† 11.36 Heb. lamp, or, candle.

∥ 11.41 Or, words, or, things.

† 11.42 Heb. days.

* 11.42 2 Chr. 9. 80.

* 11.43 Matt. 1. 7, called Roboam.

* 12.1 2 Chr. 10 1.

* 12.2 ch. 11. 40.

* 12.4 ch. 4. 7.

† 12.13 Heb. hardly.

* 12.15 ch 11. 11.

† 12.18 Heb. strengthened himself.

∥ 12.19 Or, fell away.

* 12.20 ch. 11. 13.

* 12.22 2 Chr. 11. 2.

* 12.28 Ex. 32. 8.

∥ 12.32 Or, went up to the altar, &c.

∥ 12.32 Or, to sacrifice.

∥ 12.33 Or, went up to the altar, &c.

† 12.33 Heb. to burn incense.

∥ 13.1 Or, to offer.

* 13.2 2 Kings 23. 17.

† 13.6 Heb. the face of the Lord.

‡ 13.6 [1611 omits him]

‡ 13.11 [1611 son]

† 13.17 Heb. a word was.

† 13.26 Heb. broken.

† 13.28 Heb. broken.

† 13.33 Heb. returned and made.

† 13.33 Heb. filled his hand.

* 14.2 ch. 11. 31.

† 14.3 Heb. in thine hand.

∥ 14.3 Or, cakes.

∥ 14.3 Or, bottle.

† 14.4 Heb. stood for his hoariness.

† 14.6 Heb. hard.

* 14.10 ch. 15. 29.

* 14.10 ch. 21. 21. 2 Kings 9. 8.

† 14.20 Heb. lay down.

* 14.21 2 Chr. 12. 13.

∥ 14.23 Or, standing images, or, statues.

* 14.26 ch. 10. 17.

† 14.27 Heb. runners.

* 15.2 2 Chr. 11. 22.

∥ 15.4 Or, candle.

* 15.5 2 Sam. 11. 4. &c 12. 9.

* 15.7 2 Chr. 13. 3.

* 15.8 2 Chr. 14. 1.

∥ 15.10 That is, grandmother's.

* 15.13 2 Chr. 15. 16.

† 15.13 Heb. cut off.

† 15.15 Heb. holy.

* 15.18 2 Chr. 16. 2.

‡ 15.19 [1611 the]

† 15.19 Heb. go up.

† 15.22 Heb. free.

* 15.24 Matt 1. 8. called Josaphat.

† 15.25 Heb. reigned.

‡ 15.27 [1611 belongeth]

* 15.29 ch. 14. 10

* 16.3 ch. 15. 29.

* 16.4 ch. 14. 11.

* 16.5 2 Chr. 16. 1.

‡ 16.8 [1611 twentieth]

† 16.9 Heb. which was over.

∥ 16.11 Or, both his kinsmen and his friends.

† 16.12 Heb. by the hand of.

‡ 16.19 [1611 omits to]

‡ 16.23 [1611 one]

† 16.24 Heb. Shomeron.

† 16.31 Heb. was it a light thing, &c.

* 16.34 Josh. 6 26.

† 17.1 Heb. Elijahu. Luke 4. 25, he is called Elias

* 17.1 Ecclus 48 3 James 5 17.

† 17.7 Heb. at the end of days.

* 17.9 Luke 4. 26, called Surepta.

† 17.14 Heb. giveth.

∥ 17.15 Or, a full year.

† 17.16 Heb. by the hand of.

† 17.21 Heb. measured.

† 17.21 Heb. into his inward parts.

† 18.3 Heb. Obadiahu.

† 18.3 Heb. over his house.

† 18.4 Heb. Izebel.

† 18.5 Heb. that we cut not off ourselves from the beasts.

∥ 18.21 Or, thoughts.

† 18.24 Heb. The word is good.

∥ 18.26 Or, answer.

∥ 18.26 Or, heard.

∥ 18.26 Or, leaped up and down at the altar.

† 18.27 Heb. with a great voice.

∥ 18.27 Or, he meditateth.

† 18.27 Heb. hath a pursuit.

‡ 18.28 [1611 loud]

† 18.28 Heb. poured out blood upon them.

† 18.29 Heb. ascending.

† 18.29 Heb. attention.

* 18.31 Gen. 32. 28 2 Kings 17. 34.

† 18.35 Heb. went.

∥ 18.40 Or, Apprehend.

∥ 18.41 Or, a sound of a noise of rain.

† 18.44 Heb. Tie, or, Bind.

† 18.46 Heb. till thou come to Jezreel.

† 19.4 Heb. for his life.

† 19.6 Heb. bolster.

* 19.10 Rom. 11. 3.

* 19.16 Luke 4. 27. called Eliseus.

* 19.17 2 Kings 9 1. 3. Ecclus. 48. 8.

* 19.18 Rom. 11. 4.

∥ 19.18 Or, I will leave.

† 19.20 Heb. Go return.

† 20.6 Heb. desirable.

† 20.7 Heb. I kept not back from him.

† 20.10 Heb. are at my feet.

† 20.12 Heb. word.

∥ 20.12 Or, tents.

∥ 20.12 Or, Place the engines: And they placed engines.

† 20.13 Heb. approached.

∥ 20.14 Or, servants.

† 20.14 Heb. bind. or, tie.

† 20.25 Heb. that was fallen,

† 20.26 Heb. to the war with Israel.

∥ 20.27 Or, were victualled.

∥ 20.30 Or, from chamber to chamber.

† 20.30 Heb. into a chamber within a chamber.

† 20.37 Heb. smiting and wounding.

† 20.39 Heb. weigh.

† 20.40 Heb. he was not.

* 20.42 ch 22. 38.

† 21.2 Heb. be good in thine eyes.

† 21.9 Heb. in the top of the people.

* 21.21 ch. 14. 10. 2 Kings 9. 8.

* 21.21 1 Sam. 25. 22.

* 21.21 ch. 14. 10.

* 21.22 ch. 15. 29.

* 21.22 ch. 16. 3.

* 21.23 2 Kings 9. 36.

∥ 21.23 Or, ditch.

∥ 21.25 Or, incited.

* 22.2 2 Chr. 18 1, &c.

† 22.3 Heb. silent from taking it.

* 22.4 2 Kings 3. 7.

∥ 22.9 Or, eunuch.

† 22.10 Heb. floor.

∥ 22.20 Or, deceive.

* 22.24 2 Chr. 18. 23.

∥ 22.25 Or, from chamber to chamber.

† 22.25 Heb a chamber in a chamber.

∥ 22.30 Or, when he was to disguise himself, and enter into the battle.

† 22.34 Heb. in his simplicity.

† 22.34 Heb. joints and the breast-plate.

† 22.34 Heb. made sick.

† 22.35 Heb. ascended.

† 22.35 Heb. bosom.

† 22.37 Heb. came.

* 22.38 ch. 21. 19.

* 22.41 2 Chr. 20. 31.

∥ 22.48 Or, had ten ships.

1 Maccabees

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

The First Book of the Maccabees

1

1 [a]And it happened, after that Alexander son of Philip, the Macedonian, who came out of the land of [*][b]Chettiim, had smitten Darius king of the Persians and [c]Medes, that he reigned in his stead, the first over Greece,

2 And made many wars, and won many [d]strong holds, and slew the kings of the earth,

3 And went through to the ends of the earth, and took spoils of many nations, insomuch that the earth was quiet before him; whereupon [*]he was exalted and his heart was lifted up.

4 And he gathered a mighty strong host and ruled over countries, and nations, and [*]kings, who became tributaries unto him.

5 And after these things he [e]fell sick, and perceived [*]that he should die.

6 Wherefore he called his servants, such as were honourable, and [f]had been brought up with him from his youth, and parted his kingdom among them, while he was yet alive.

7 So Alexander reigned twelve years, and then [*]died.

8 And his servants bare rule every one in his place.

9 And after his death they all put [ff]crowns upon themselves; so did their sons after them many years: and evils were multiplied in the earth.

10 And there came out of them [g]a wicked root [h]Antiochus surnamed Epiphanes, son of Antiochus the king, [*]who had been [i]an hostage at Rome, and he reigned in [*]the hundred and thirty and seventh year [*]of the kingdom of the Greeks.

11 [*]In those days went there out of Israel [ii]wicked men, who persuaded many, saying, Let us go and make a covenant with the heathen that are round about us: for since we departed from them [*]we have had much sorrow.

12 So this device pleased them well.

13 Then [ii]certain of the people were so forward herein, that they went to the king, who gave them licence to do after the ordinances of the heathen:

14 Whereupon [j]they [*]built a place of exercise at Jerusalem according to the customs of the heathen:

15 And [k]made themselves uncircumcised, and forsook the holy covenant, and [l]joined themselves to the heathen, and [m]were sold to do mischief.

16 [*]Now when the kingdom was established before Antiochus, he thought to reign over Egypt that he might have the dominion of two realms.

17 Wherefore [n]he entered into Egypt [o]with a great multitude, with chariots, and [p]elephants, and horsemen, and a great [pp]navy,

18 And made war against [q]Ptolemee king of Egypt: but Ptolemee was afraid of him, and fled; and [r]many were wounded to death.

19 Thus they got the strong cities in the land of Egypt and he took the spoils thereof.

20 And after that Antiochus had smitten Egypt, he returned again in [*]the hundred forty and third year, and [s]went up against Israel and Jerusalem [o]with a great multitude,

21 And [t]entered proudly into the sanctuary, and took away [u]the golden altar, and [w]the candlestick of light, and [w]all the vessels thereof,

22 And [x]the table of the shewbread, and [y]the pouring vessels, and [y]the vials. and [y]the censers of gold, and [z]the veil, and [a]the crown, and the golden ornaments that were before the temple, [*]all which he pulled off.

23 He took also the silver and the gold, and the [*]precious vessels: also he took the hidden treasures which he found.

24 And when he had taken all away, he went into his own land, [c]having made a great massacre, and [d]spoken very proudly.

25 Therefore there was a great mourning in Israel, in every place where they were;

26 So that the princes and elders mourned, the virgins and young men were made feeble, and the beauty of women was changed.

27 [e]Every bridegroom took up lamentation, and she that sat in the marriage chamber was in heaviness,

28 The land also was moved for the inhabitants thereof, and all the house of Jacob was covered with confusion.

29 [*]And after [f]two years fully expired [ff]the king sent his chief collector of tribute unto the cities of Juda, who came unto Jerusalem [g]with a great multitude,

30 And spake peaceable words unto them, but all was deceit: for when they had given him credence, he fell suddenly upon the city, and smote it very sore, and destroyed much people of Israel.

31 And when he had taken the spoils of the city, he set it on fire, and pulled down the houses and walls thereof on every side.

32 But the women and children took they captive, and possessed the cattle.

33 Then builded they the city of David with a great and strong wall, and with mighty towers, and made it [gg]a strong hold for them.

34 And they put therein a [h]sinful nation, [i]wicked men, and fortified themselves therein.

35 They stored it also with armour and victuals, and when they had gathered together the spoils of Jerusalem, they laid them up there, and so they became a sore snare:

36 For it was [j]a place to lie in wait against the sanctuary, and an evil adversary to Israel.

37 Thus [k]they shed innocent blood on every side of the sanctuary, and defiled it:

38 Insomuch [l]that the inhabitants of Jerusalem fled because of them: whereupon [ll]the city was made an habitation of strangers, and became strange to those that were born in her; and her own children left her.

39 [l]Her sanctuary was laid waste like a wilderness, [m][n]her feasts were turned into mourning, [n]her sabbaths into reproach her honour into contempt.

40 As had been her glory, so was her dishonour increased, and her excellency was turned into mourning.

41 Moreover king Antiochus wrote to his whole kingdom, that all should be one people,

42 And [o]every one should leave his laws: so all the heathen agreed according to the commandment of the king.

43 Yea, many also of the Israelites consented to his [p]religion, and sacrificed unto idols, and profaned the sabbath.

44 For the king had sent letters by messengers unto Jerusalem and the cities of Juda that they should follow [*]the strange laws of the land,

45 And [q]forbid burnt offerings, and sacrifice, and drink offerings, in the temple; and that they should [n]profane the sabbaths and festival days:

46 And [q]pollute the sanctuary and holy people:

47 [r]Set up altars, and [s]groves, and [t]chapels of idols, and [u]sacrifice swine’s flesh, and [x]unclean beasts:

48 That they should also leave their children uncircumcised, and make their souls abominable with all manner of uncleanness and profanation:

49 To the end they might forget the law, and change all the ordinances.

50 And [y]whosoever would not do according to the commandment of the king, [z]he said, he should die.

51 [a]In the selfsame manner wrote he to his whole kingdom, and appointed [b]overseers over all the people, commanding the cities of Juda to sacrifice, city by city.

52 Then many of the people were gathered unto them, to wit every one that forsook the law; and so they committed evils in the land;

53 [*]And drove the Israelites into [c]secret places, even wheresoever they could flee for succour.

54 Now the fifteenth day of the month [d]Casleu, in [*]the hundred forty and fifth year, they set up [d]the abomination of desolation upon the altar, and [e]builded idol altars throughout the cities of Juda on every side;

55 And burnt incense at the doors of their houses, and in the streets.

56 And when they had rent in pieces the books of the law which they found, they burnt them with fire.

57 And whosoever was found with any the book of the testament, or if any [f]committed to the law, [*]the king’s commandment was, that they should put him to death.

58 Thus did they by their authority unto the Israelites every month, to as many as were found in the cities.

59 Now [g]the five and twentieth day of the month they did sacrifice upon the idol altar, [g]which was upon the altar of God.

60 At which time according to the commandment [h]they put to death certain women, [*]that had caused their children to be circumcised.

61 And [h]they hanged the infants about their necks, and rifled their houses, and slew them that had circumcised them.

62 [*]Howbeit many in Israel were fully resolved and confirmed in themselves not to eat any [i]unclean thing.

63 Wherefore [k]they chose rather to die, [k]that they might not be defiled with meats, and that they might not profane the holy covenant: so then they died.

64 And there was very great wrath upon Israel.

2

1 In those days [*]arose Mattathias the son of John, the son of [a]Simeon, a priest of the sons of [b]Joarib, from Jerusalem, and dwelt in [c]Modin.

2 And he had five sons, [d]Joannan, [*]called [*]Caddis:

3 Simon; called Thassi:

4 [e]Judas, who was called Maccabeus:

5 [ee]Eleazar, called [*]Avaran: and Jonathan, [f]whose surname was Apphus.

6 And when he saw the blasphemies that were committed in Juda and Jerusalem,

7 He said, Woe is me! wherefore was I born to see this [g]misery of my people, and of [h]the holy city, and to dwell there, when it was delivered into the hand of the enemy, and the sanctuary into the hand of strangers?

8 Her temple is become as a man [i]without glory.

9 [k]Her glorious vessels are carried away into captivity, [l]her infants are slain in the streets, her young men with the sword of the enemy.

10 What nation hath not [m]had a part in her kingdom and gotten of her spoils?

11 [n]All her ornaments are taken away; of a free woman she is become a bondslave.

12 And, behold, our [*][o]sanctuary, even [p]our beauty and our glory, is laid waste, and [q]the Gentiles have profaned it.

13 To what end therefore shall we live any longer?

14 Then Mattathias and his sons [r]rent their clothes, and [r][s]put on sackcloth, and mourned very sore.

15 In the mean while [t]the king’s officers, such as compelled the people to [u]revolt, came into the city [c]Modin, to make them sacrifice.

16 And when many of Israel came unto them, Mattathias also and his sons came together.

17 Then answered [t]the king’s officers, and said to Mattathias on this wise, Thou art a ruler, and an honourable and great man in this city, and [v]strengthened with sons and brethren:

18 Now therefore come thou first, and fulfil the king’s commandment, like [w]as all the heathen have done, yea, and the men of Juda also, and such as remain at Jerusalem: so shalt thou and thy house be in the number of the king’s friends, and thou and thy children shall be honoured with silver and gold, and many [x]rewards.

19 Then Mattathias answered and spake with a loud voice, Though all the nations that are under [y]the king’s dominion obey him, and [u]fall away every one from the [z]religion of their fathers, and give consent to his commandments:

20 [a]Yet will I and my sons and my brethren walk in the covenant of our fathers.

21 [b]God forbid that we should forsake the law and the ordinances.

22 [c]We will not hearken to the king’s words, to go from our [d]religion, [e]either on the right hand, or the left.

23 Now when he had left speaking these words, there came one of the Jews in the sight of all to sacrifice on the altar which was at [f]Modin, according to the king’s commandment.

24 Which thing when Mattathias saw, he was inflamed with zeal, and [g]his reins trembled, neither could he forbear to shew his anger [h]according to judgment: wherefore he ran, and slew him upon the altar.

25 Also the king’s commissioner, who compelled men to sacrifice, he killed at that time, and the altar he pulled down.

26 Thus dealt he zealously for the law of God like as [i]Phinees did unto Zambri the son of Salom.

27 And Mattathias cried throughout the city with a loud voice, saying, Whosoever is zealous of the law, and maintaineth the covenant, let him follow me.

28 So [j]he and his sons fled into the mountains, and left all that ever they had in the city.

29 Then many that [k]sought after justice and [h]judgment [j]went down into the wilderness, to [*]dwell there:

30 Both they, [l]and their children, and their wives; and their cattle; because [*]afflictions increased sore upon them.

31 Now when it was told the king’s servants, and [m]the host that was at Jerusalem, in the city of David, that certain men, who had [n]broken the king’s commandment, were gone down into [o]the secret places in the wilderness,

32 They pursued after them a great number, and having overtaken them, they camped against them, and made war against them on the sabbath day.

33 And they said unto them, Let that which ye have done hitherto suffice; come forth, and do according to the commandment of the king, and ye shall live.

34 But they said, We will not come forth, neither will we do the king’s commandment, [p]to profane the sabbath day.

35 So then they gave [*]them the battle with all speed.

36 Howbeit they answered them not, neither cast they a stone at them, nor stopped [o]the places where they lay hid;

37 But said, Let us die all in our [*]innocency: heaven and earth will testify for us, that ye put us to death wrongfully.

38 [q]So they rose up against them in battle on the sabbath, and they slew them, [r]with their wives and children and their cattle, to the number of a thousand p[*]eople.

39 Now when Mattathias and his friends understood hereof, they mourned for them right sore.

40 And one of them said to another, If we all do as our brethren have done, and fight not for our lives and laws against the heathen, they will now quickly root us out of the earth.

41 At that time therefore they decreed, saying, [s]Whosoever shall come to make battle with us on the sabbath day, we will fight against him; neither will we die all, [t]as our brethren that were murdered in [o]the secret places.

42 Then came there unto him a company of [u]Assideans who were mighty men of Israel, even all such as were voluntarily devoted unto the law.

43 Also all they that fled for persecution joined themselves unto them, and were [v]a stay unto them.

44 So they joined their forces, and smote [w]sinful men in their anger, and [x]wicked men in their wrath: but the rest fled to the heathen for succour.

45 Then Mattathias and his friends went round about, and pulled down the altars:

46 And what children soever they found within the coast of Israel uncircumcised, those they circumcised [*][y]valiantly.

47 They pursued also after the proud men, and the work prospered in their hand.

48 So they recovered the law out of the hand of the Gentiles, and out of the hand of kings, neither [*]suffered they [w]the sinner to triumph.

49 Now when the time drew near that Mattathias should die, he said unto his sons, Now hath pride and rebuke gotten strength, and the time of destruction, and the wrath of indignation:

50 Now therefore, my sons, be ye zealous for the law, and give your lives for the covenant of your fathers.

51 Call to remembrance what acts our fathers did in their [*]time; so shall ye receive great honour and an everlasting name.

52 [z]Was not Abraham found faithful in temptation, [a]and it was imputed unto him for righteousness?

53 [b]Joseph in the time of his [c]distress kept the commandment a[d]nd was made lord of Egypt.

54 Phinees [e]our father [f][n]in being zealous and fervent obtained the covenant of an everlasting priesthood.

55 [g]Jesus for fulfilling the word was made a judge in Israel.

56 [h]Caleb for bearing witness before [i]the congregation received the heritage of the land.

57 David for being [k]merciful [l]possessed the throne of an everlasting kingdom.

58 [m]Elias [n]for being zealous and fervent for the law was taken up into heaven.

59 [o]Ananias, Azarias, and Misael, by believing were saved out of the flame.

60 [p]Daniel for his [q]innocency was delivered from the mouth of lions.

61 And thus consider ye throughout all ages, that none that put their trust in him shall be overcome.

62 [r]Fear not then the words of a sinful man: [s]for his glory shall be [t]dung and worms.

63 [s]To day he shall be lifted up and to morrow he shall not be found, because h[u][x]e is returned into his dust, a[x]nd his thought is come to nothing.

64 Wherefore, ye my sons, be valiant and [y]shew yourselves men in the behalf of the law; for by it shall ye obtain glory.

65 And behold, I know that your brother [z]Simon is a man of counsel, give ear unto him alway: he shall be a father unto you.

66 As for [a]Judas Maccabeus, he hath been mighty and strong, even [b]from his youth up: let him be your captain, and [*]fight the battle of the people.

67 Take also unto you all [c]those that observe the law, and avenge ye the wrong of your people.

68 Recompense fully the heathen, and take heed to the commandments of the law.

69 So [d]he blessed them, and [e]was gathered to his fathers.

70 And he died in [*]the hundred forty and sixth year, and his sons buried him in the sepulchres of his fathers at [f]Modin, and all Israel [g]made great lamentation for him.

3

1 Then [a]his son Judas, called Maccabeus, [aa]rose up in his stead.

2 And all his brethren helped him, and so did all they that held with his father, and they fought with cheerfulness the battle of Israel.

3 So he gat his people great honour, and put on a [b]breastplate as a giant, and girt his warlike [c]harness about him, and he made battles, protecting [d]the host with his sword.

4 In his acts he was like a lion, and like a lion’s whelp roaring for his prey.

5 For He pursued [e]the wicked, and sought them out, and [ee]burnt up those that vexed his people.

6 Wherefore [e]the wicked [f]shrunk for fear of him, and [ff]all the workers of iniquity were troubled, because [g]salvation prospered in his hand.

7 He grieved also many kings, and made Jacob glad with his acts, and [gg]his memorial is blessed for ever.

8 Moreover he went through the cities of Juda, destroying [e]the ungodly out of them, and [h]turning away wrath from Israel:

9 So that he was renowned unto the utmost part of the earth, and he [*]received unto him such as were [i]ready to perish.

10 Then [k]Apollonius gathered the Gentiles together, and a great host out of [l]Samaria, to fight against Israel.

11 Which thing when Judas perceived, he went forth to meet him, and so he smote him, and slew him: many also [m]fell down slain, but the rest fled.

12 Wherefore Judas took their spoils, and [k]Apollonius’ sword also, and therewith he fought all his life long.

13 Now when Seron, a prince of the army of Syria, heard say that Judas had gathered unto him a multitude and company of the faithful to go out with him to war;

14 He said, I will get me a name and honour in the kingdom; for I will go fight with Judas and them that are with him, who despise the king’s commandment.

15 So he [n]made him ready to go up, and there went with him a mighty [d]host of [e]the ungodly to help him, and to be avenged of the children of Israel.

16 And when he came near to the going up of [o]Bethhoron, Judas went forth to meet him [p]with a small company:

17 Who, when they saw [d]the host coming to meet them, said unto Judas, How shall we be able, being so [p]few, to fight against so great a multitude and so strong, seeing [q]we are ready to faint with fasting all this day?

18 Unto whom Judas answered, [r]It is no hard matter for many to be [s]shut up in the hands of a few; and with [t]the God of heaven it is all one, [r]to deliver with a great multitude, or a small company:

19 For the victory of battle standeth not in the multitude of an host; but strength cometh from heaven.

20 They come [*]against us [*]in much pride and iniquity to destroy us, and our wives and children, and to spoil us:

21 But we fight for our lives and our laws.

22 Wherefore the Lord himself will overthrow them before our face: and as for you, be ye not afraid of them.

23 Now as soon as he had left off speaking, he leapt suddenly upon them, and so Seron and his [d]host was overthrown before him.

24 And they pursued them [*]from [u]the going down of Bethhoron unto the plain, where were slain about eight hundred men of them; and the residue fled into the land of the Philistines.

25 Then began the fear of Judas and his brethren, and [w]an exceeding great dread, to fall upon the nations round about them:

26 Insomuch as his fame came unto the king, and all nations talked of the [x]battles of Judas.

27 Now when [y]king Antiochus heard these things, he was full of indignation: wherefore he sent and gathered together all the forces of his realm, even a very strong [d]army.

28 He opened also his treasure, and gave his soldiers [z]pay for a year, commanding them to be ready [*]whensoever he should need them.

29 Nevertheless, when he saw that the money of his treasures failed and t[*]hat the tributes in the country were small, because of the dissension and plague, which he had brought upon the land i[*]n taking away the laws which had been of old time;

30 He feared [*]that he should not be able to bear the charges [a]any longer, nor to have such gifts to give so liberally as he did before: for [b]he had abounded above the kings that were before him.

31 Wherefore, being greatly [c]perplexed in his mind, he determined to go into [d]Persia, there to take the tributes of the countries, and to gather much money.

32 So he left [e]Lysias, a nobleman, and one [ee]of the blood royal, to oversee the affairs of the king from the river Euphrates unto the borders of Egypt:

33 And to bring up [f]his son Antiochus, until he came again.

34 Moreover he delivered unto him the half of his forces, and [g]the elephants, and gave him charge of all things that he would have done, as also concerning them that dwelt in Juda and Jerusalem:

35 To wit, that he should send an army against them, to destroy and root out the strength of Israel, and [h]the remnant of Jerusalem, and [i]to take away their memorial from that place;

36 And that he should place strangers in all their quarters, and divide their land by lot.

37 So the king took the half of the forces that remained, and departed from [j]Antioch, [*]his royal city, [*]the hundred forty and seventh year; and having passed the river Euphrates, [d]he went through [k]the high countries.

38 Then Lysias chose [l]Ptolemee the son of Dorymenes, [m]Nicanor, and [n]Gorgias, mighty men of [nn]the king’s friends:

39 And with them he sent forty thousand footmen, and seven thousand horsemen, to go into the land of Juda, and to destroy it, as the king commanded.

40 So they went forth with all their power, and came and pitched by [o]Emmaus in the plain country.

41 And [oo]the merchants of the country, hearing the fame of them, took silver and gold very much, with [*]servants, and came into [p]the camp to buy the children of Israel for slaves: a power also of Syria and of the land [*]of the Philistines joined themselves unto them.

42 [q]Now when Judas and his brethren saw that miseries were multiplied, and that the forces did encamp themselves in their borders: for they knew how the king had given commandment to destroy the people, and utterly abolish them;

43 They said one to another, Let us restore the [r]decayed fortune of our people, and let us fight for our people and the sanctuary.

44 Then was the congregation gathered together, that they might be ready for battle, and that they might pray, and ask mercy and compassion.

45 Now [h][s]Jerusalem lay void as a wilderness, there was none of her children that [t]went in or out: [s]the sanctuary also was trodden down, and aliens kept [u]the strong hold; the heathen had their habitation in that place; and joy was taken from Jacob, and the pipe with [w]the harp ceased.

46 Wherefore the Israelites assembled themselves together, and came to [*]Maspha, over against Jerusalem; for in [x]Maspha was the place where they prayed aforetime in Israel.

47 Then [y]they fasted that day, and [z]put on sackcloth, and cast [y][a]ashes upon their heads, and [z][a]rent their clothes,

48 And laid open the book of the law, [*]wherein the heathen had sought to paint [b]the likeness of their images.

49 They brought also [c]the priests’ garments, and [d]the firstfruits, and [e]the tithes: and [f]the Nazarites they stirred up, [g]who had accomplished their days.

50 Then cried they with a loud voice toward heaven, saying, What shall we do with these, and whither shall we carry them away?

51 For thy [h]sanctuary is trodden down and profaned, and thy priests are in heaviness, and brought low.

52 And lo, the heathen are assembled together against us to destroy us: what things they imagine against us, thou knowest.

53 How shall we be able to stand against them, except thou, O God, be our help?

54 Then sounded they with [i]trumpets, and cried with a loud voice.

55 And [k]after this Judas ordained captains over the people, even [l]captains over thousands, and over hundreds, and over fifties, and over tens.

56 But as for [m]such as were building houses, or had betrothed wives, or were planting vineyards, or [n]were [o]fearful, those he commanded that they should return, every man to his own house, [m]according to the law.

57 So [p]the camp removed, and pitched upon the south side of [q]Emmaus.

58 And Judas said, [r]arm yourselves, and be valiant men, and see that ye be in readiness against the morning, that ye may fight with these nations, that are assembled together against us to destroy us and our [h]sanctuary:

59 For it is better for us to die in battle, than to behold the calamities of our people and our [h]sanctuary.

60 Nevertheless, [r]as the will [s]of God is in heaven, so let him do.

4

1 Then took [a]Gorgias [b]five thousand footmen, and a thousand of the best horsemen, and removed out of [c]the camp by night;

2 To the end he might rush in upon [c]the camp of the Jews, and smite them suddenly. And the men of [d]the fortress were his guides.

3 Now when Judas heard thereof he himself removed, and the valiant men with him, that he might smite t[e]he king’s army which was at Emmaus,

4 While as yet the forces were dispersed from [c]the camp.

5 In the mean season came [a]Gorgias by night into [c]the camp of Judas: and when he found no man there, he sought them in the mountains: for said he, These fellows flee from us

6 But as soon as it was day, Judas shewed himself in the plain with three thousand men, who nevertheless had neither [*]armour nor swords to their minds.

7 And they saw [c]the camp of the heathen, that it was strong and well [f]harnessed, and compassed round about with horsemen; and these were expert of war.

8 Then [ff]said Judas to the men that were with him, Fear ye not [b]their multitude, neither be ye afraid of their assault.

9 Remember how [g]our fathers were delivered in the Red sea, when Pharaoh pursued them with an army.

10 Now therefore let us [h]cry unto heaven, if peradventure the Lord will have mercy upon us, and remember the covenant of our fathers, and destroy this [c]host before our face this day:

11 [i]That so all the heathen may know that there is one who delivereth and saveth Israel.

12 Then the strangers lifted up their eyes, and saw them coming over against them.

13 [j]Wherefore they went out of [c]the camp to battle; but they that were with Judas [k]sounded their trumpets.

14 So they joined battle, and the heathen being discomfited fled into the plain.

15 Howbeit all the hindmost of them were slain with the sword: for they pursued them unto [*][l]Gazera, and unto the plains of [m]Idumea, and [n]Azotus, and [o]Jamnia, so that there were slain of them upon a three thousand men.

16 This done, Judas returned again with his host from pursuing them,

17 And said to the people, Be not greedy of the spoil inasmuch as there is a battle before us,

18 And [a]Gorgias and his host are here by us [p]in the mountain: but stand ye now against our enemies, and overcome them, and after this ye may boldly take the spoils.

19 As Judas was yet speaking these words, there appeared a part of them looking out of the mountain:

20 Who when they perceived that the Jews had put their host to flight and were burning t[c]he tents; for the smoke that was seen declared what was done:

21 When therefore they perceived these things, they were sore afraid, and seeing also [c]the host of Judas in the plain ready to fight,

22 They fled every one into the land of [q]strangers.

23 [r]Then Judas returned to spoil [c]the tents, where they got much gold, and silver, and [s]blue silk, and purple of the sea, and great riches.

24 After this they went home, and [r]sung a song of thanksgiving, and praised the Lord in heaven: [t]because [*]it is good, because his mercy endureth forever.

25 Thus Israel had a great deliverance that day.

26 Now all the strangers that had escaped came and told [u]Lysias what had happened:

27 Who, when he heard thereof, [v]was confounded and discouraged,[w] because neither such things as he would were done unto Israel, nor such things as the king commanded him were come to pass.

28 [*]The next year therefore following Lysias gathered together [b]threescore thousand choice men of foot, and five thousand horsemen, that he might subdue them.

29 So they came into [m]Idumea, and pitched their tents at [x]Bethsura, and Judas met them with [y]ten thousand men.

30 And when he saw that mighty [c]army, he prayed and said, Blessed art thou, O Saviour of Israel, [z]who didst quell the violence of the mighty man by the hand of thy servant David, and gavest the host of [*]strangers [a]into the hands of Jonathan the son of Saul, and his armourbearer;

31 [b]Shut up this army in the hand of thy people Israel, and let them be confounded in their power and horsemen:

32 Make them to be of no courage, and cause the boldness of their strength to [*]fall away, and let them quake at their destruction:

33 Cast them down with the sword of them that love thee, and let all those that know thy name praise thee with thanksgiving.

34 So they joined battle; and there were slain of the host of Lysias about five thousand men, even before them were they slain.

35 Now when Lysias saw his army put to flight, and the manliness of Judas’ soldiers, and how they were ready either to live or die valiantly, he went into [c]Antiochia, and gathered together a company of strangers, and having made his army greater than it was, he purposed to come again into Judea.

36 Then said Judas and his brethren, Behold, our enemies are discomfited: let us go up to cleanse and [*]dedicate the sanctuary.

37 [d]Upon this all the host assembled themselves together, and went up into mount Sion.

38 [d]And when they saw [e]the sanctuary desolate, and [f]the altar profaned, and [g]the gates burned up, and shrubs growing in [g]the courts as in a forest, or in one of the mountains, yea, and the priests’ [h]chambers pulled down;

39 [i]They rent their clothes, and [k]made great lamentation, and [i]cast ashes upon their heads,

40 And fell down flat to the ground upon their faces, and blew an alarm [l]with the trumpets, and [m]cried toward heaven.

41 Then Judas appointed certain men to fight against [n]those that were in the fortress, until he had cleansed the sanctuary.

42 So he chose priests of blameless conversation, such as had pleasure in the law:

43 Who cleansed the sanctuary, and bare out the defiled stones into an unclean place.

44 And when as they consulted what to do with the altar of burnt offerings, [f]which was profaned;

45 They thought it best to pull it down, lest it should be a reproach to them, because [f]the heathen had defiled it: wherefore they pulled it down,

46 And laid up the stones in the mountain of the temple in a convenient place, [o]until there should come a prophet to shew what should be done with them.

47 Then they took [p]whole stones according to the law, and [q]built a new altar according to the former;

48 And made up the sanctuary, and the things that were within the temple, and hallowed [g]the courts.

49 They made also new holy vessels, and into the temple they brought [r]the candlestick, and the altar [s]of burnt offerings, and [t]of incense, and [u]the table.

50 And [w]upon the altar [x]they burned incense, and [w]the lamps that were upon the candlestick they lighted, that they might give light in the temple.

51 Furthermore [y]they set the loaves upon the table, and [*]spread out [z]the veils, and finished all the works which they had begun to make.

52 Now [a]on the five and twentieth day of the ninth month, which is called the month [b]Casleu, in [*]the hundred forty and eighth year, they rose up betimes in the morning,

53 And offered sacrifice [c]according to the law upon the new altar of burnt offerings, [d]which they had made.

54 Look, at what time and [a]what day the heathen had profaned it, even in that was it dedicated with songs, and citherns, and [e]harps, and [f]cymbals.

55 Then all the people fell upon their faces, worshipping and praising [g]the God of heaven, who had given them good success.

56 And so they kept the dedication of the altar [h]eight days and offered burnt offerings with gladness, and sacrificed the sacrifice of d[*]eliverance and p[i]raise.

57 They decked also the forefront of the temple with crowns of gold, and with shields; and [j]the gates and [j]the chambers they [*]renewed, and [*]hanged doors upon them.

58 Thus was there very great gladness among the people, for that the reproach of the heathen was put away.

59 Moreover Judas and his brethren with the whole congregation of Israel ordained, that the days of [k]the dedication of the altar should be kept in their season from year to year by the space of eight days, [l]from the five and twentieth day of the month [b]Casleu, with mirth and gladness.

60 At that time also they builded up the mount Sion [m]with high walls and strong towers round about, lest the Gentiles should come and tread it down a[n]s they had done before.

61 And they set there a garrison to keep it, and fortified [o]Bethsura to preserve it; that the people might have a defence against [p]Idumea.

5

1 [*]Now when the nations round about heard that [a]the altar was built and t[b]he sanctuary renewed as before, it displeased them very much.

2 Wherefore they thought to destroy the generation of Jacob that was among them, and thereupon they began to slay and destroy the people.

3 Then Judas fought against [c]the children of Esau in [d]Idumea at [*]Arabattine, because they besieged Gael: and he gave them a great overthrow, and abated their courage, and took their spoils.

4 Also he remembered the [*]injury of the children of [*]Bean, who had been [e]a snare and [e]an offence unto the people, in that they lay in wait for them in the ways.

5 He shut them up therefore in the towers, and encamped against them, and [f]destroyed them utterly, and burned the towers of that place with fire, and all that were therein.

6 Afterward he passed over to [g]the children of Ammon, where he found a mighty power, and much people, with [gg]Timotheus their captain.

7 So he fought many battles with them, till at length they were discomfited before him; and he smote them.

8 And when he had taken [h]Jazar, with [i]the towns belonging thereto, he returned into Judea.

9 Then the heathen that were at [j]Galaad assembled themselves together against the Israelites that were in their quarters, to destroy them; but they fled to the fortress of Dathema.

10 And sent letters unto Judas and his brethren, The heathen that are round about us are assembled together against us to destroy us:

11 And they are preparing to come and take the fortress whereunto we are fled, [gg]Timotheus being captain of their [k]host.

12 Come now therefore, and deliver us from their hands, for many of us are slain:

13 Yea, all [kk]our brethren that were in the places of [*][l]Tobie are put to death: their wives and their children also they have carried away captives, and borne away their [m]stuff; and they have destroyed there about a thousand men.

14 While these letters were yet reading, behold, there came other messengers from Galilee [n]with their clothes rent, who reported on this wise,

15 And said, They of [o]Ptolemais, and of [p]Tyrus, and Sidon, and all [q]Galilee of the Gentiles, are assembled together against us to consume us.

16 Now when Judas and the people heard these words, there assembled a great congregation together, to consult what they should do for their brethren, that were in trouble, and assaulted of them.

17 Then said Judas unto [r]Simon his brother, Choose thee out men, and go and deliver thy brethren that are in [q]Galilee, for I and [s]Jonathan my brother will go into [j]the country of Galaad.

18 So he left [t]Joseph the son of Zacharias, and Azarias, captains of the people, with the remnant of the host in Judea to keep it.

19 Unto whom he gave commandment, saying, Take ye the charge of this people, and [u]see that ye make not war against the heathen until the time that we come again.

20 Now unto Simon were given three thousand men to go into [y]Galilee, and unto Judas eight thousand men for [j]the country of Galaad.

21 Then went Simon into Galilee, where he fought many battles with the heathen, so that the heathen were discomfited by him.

22 And he pursued them unto the gate of [o]Ptolemais; and there were slain of the heathen about three thousand men, whose spoils he took.

23 And [*]those that were in Galilee, and in [v]Arbattis, with their wives and their children, and all that they had, took he away with him, and brought them into Judea with great joy.

24 [w]Judas Maccabeus also and his brother Jonathan went over Jordan, and travelled three days’ journey in the wilderness,

25 Where they met with the [x]Nabathites, who came unto them in a peaceable manner, and told them every thing that had happened to their brethren in [j]the land of Galaad:

26 And how that many of them were shut up in [*]Bosora, and [y]Bosor, and Alema, [*]Casphor, [z]Maked, and [a]Carnaim; all these cities are strong and great:

27 And that they were shut up in the rest of the cities of the country of [j]Galaad, and that against to morrow [*]they had appointed to bring their host against the forts, and to take them, and to destroy them all in one day.

28 Hereupon Judas and his [b]host turned suddenly by the way of the wilderness unto [*]Bosora; and when he had won the city, [h]he slew all the males [c]with the edge of the sword, and took all their spoils, and burned the city with fire,

29 From whence he removed by night, and went till he came to [d]the fortress.

30 And betimes in the morning they [*]looked up, and, behold, there was an innumerable people bearing ladders and other engines of war, to take the fortress: for[*] they assaulted them.

31 When Judas therefore saw that the battle was begun, and that [e]the cry of the city went up to heaven, with trumpets, and a great sound,

32 He said unto his host, Fight this day for your brethren.

33 So he went forth behind them [f]in three companies, who sounded their trumpets, and cried with prayer.

34 Then [b]the host of Timotheus, knowing that it was Maccabeus, fled from him: wherefore he smote them with a great slaughter; so that there were killed of them that day about eight thousand men.

35 This done, Judas turned aside to [g]Maspha; and after he had assaulted it he took and slew [h]all the males therein, and received the spoils thereof and and burnt it with fire.

36 From thence went he, and took [i]Casphon, [j]Maged, Bosor, and the other cities of the country of Galaad.

37 After these things gathered [k]Timotheus another [b]host and encamped against Raphon beyond the brook.

38 So Judas sent men to espy [b]the host, who brought him word, saying, All the heathen that be round about us are assembled unto them, even a very great host.

39 He hath also hired the [l]Arabians to help them and they have pitched their tents beyond the brook, ready to come and fight against thee. Upon this Judas went to meet them.

40 Then Timotheus said unto the captains of his host, When Judas and his [b]host come near the brook, if he pass over first unto us, we shall not be able to withstand him; for he will mightily prevail against us:

41 But if he be afraid, and camp beyond the river, we shall go over unto him, and prevail against him.

42 Now when Judas came near the brook, he caused [m]the scribes of the people to remain by the brook: unto whom he gave commandment, saying, Suffer no man to remain in the camp, but let all come to the battle.

43 So he went first over unto them, and all the people after him: [n]then all the heathen, being discomfited before him, cast away their weapons, and fled unto the temple that was at [a]Carnaim.

44 But [*]they took the city, and [o]burned the temple with all that were therein. Thus was [a]Carnaim subdued, neither could they stand any longer before Judas.

45 Then Judas gathered together all the Israelites that were in the country of Galaad, [p]from the least unto the greatest, even their wives, and their children, and their [q]stuff, a very great [r]host, to the end they might come into the land of Judea.

46 Now [s]when they came unto Ephron, (this was a great city in [t]the way as they should go, very well fortified) they could not turn from it, [u]either on the right hand or the left, but must needs pass through the midst of it.

47 Then they of the city shut them out, and stopped up the gates with stones.

48 Whereupon Judas sent unto them in peaceable manner, saying, [u]Let us pass through your land to go into our own country, and none shall do you any hurt; we will only pass through on foot: howbeit they would not open unto him.

49 Wherefore Judas commanded a proclamation to be made throughout [r]the host, that every man should pitch his tent in the place where he was.

50 So the soldiers pitched, and assaulted the city all that day and all that night, till at the length [x]the city was delivered into his hands:

51 [h]Who then slew all the males [c]with the edge of the sword, and rased the city, and took the spoils thereof, and passed through the city over them that were slain.

52 After this [y]went they over Jordan [z]into the great plain before [a]Bethsan.

53 And Judas gathered together those that [*]came behind, and [*]exhorted the people all the way through, till they came into the land of Judea.

54 So they went up to mount Sion with joy and gladness, where they offered [*]burnt offerings, because not one of them were slain [b]until they had returned in peace.

55 Now what time as [c]Judas and Jonathan were in the land of Galaad, and [d]Simon his brother in Galilee before [e]Ptolemais,

56 [f]Joseph the son of Zacharias, and Azarias, captains of the garrisons, heard of the valiant acts and warlike deeds which they had done.

57 Wherefore they said, [g]Let us also get us a name, and go fight against the heathen that are round about us.

58 So when they had given charge unto the garrison that was with them, they went toward [h]Jamnia.

59 Then came [i]Gorgias and his men out of [h]the city [*]to fight against them.

60 And so it was, that [f]Joseph and Azarias were put to flight, and pursued unto the borders of Judea: and there were slain that day of the people of Israel about two thousand men.

61 Thus was there a great overthrow among the children of Israel, [g]because they were not obedient unto Judas and his brethren, but thought to do some valiant act.

62 Moreover these men came not of the seed of those, by whose hand deliverance was given unto Israel.

63 Howbeit the man Judas and his brethren were greatly renowned in the sight of all Israel, and of all the heathen, wheresoever their name was heard of;

64 Insomuch as the people assembled unto them with joyful acclamations.

65 Afterward [k]went Judas forth with his brethren, and fought against [l]the children of Esau in the land toward the south, where he smote [m]Hebron, and the [*]towns thereof, and pulled down the fortress of it, and burned the towers thereof round about.

66 From thence he removed to go into the land of [*]the Philistines, and passed through [n]Samaria.

67 At that time certain priests, desirous to shew their valour, were slain in battle, for that they went out to fight unadvisedly.

68 So Judas turned to [o]Azotus in the land of the Philistines, and when he had pulled down their altars, and burned their carved images with fire, and spoiled their cities, he returned into the land of Judea.

6

1 About that time [a]king Antiochus travelling through [a]the high countries heard say, that [b]Elymais in the country of [bb]Persia was a city greatly renowned for riches, silver, and gold;

2 And that there was in it a very rich temple, wherein were [*]coverings of gold, and breastplates, and [*]shields, which [c]Alexander, son of Philip, the Macedonian king, [c]who reigned first among the Grecians, had left there.

3 Wherefore [d]he came and sought to take the city, and to spoil it; but he was not able, because they of the city, having had warning thereof,

4 Rose up against him in battle: so he fled, and departed thence with great heaviness, and returned to [w]Babylon.

5 Moreover there came one who brought him tidings [dd]into Persia, that the armies, which went against the land of Judea, were put to flight:

6 And that [e]Lysias, who went forth first with a great power was driven away of the Jews; and that they were made strong by the armour, and power, and s[f]tore of spoils, which they had gotten of the armies, whom they had destroyed:

7 Also that [g]they had pulled down [h]the abomination, which he had set up upon the altar in Jerusalem, and that [i]they had compassed about the sanctuary with high walls, as before, and his city [k]Bethsura.

8 Now when the king heard these words, he was astonished and sore moved: [l]whereupon he laid him down upon his bed, and fell sick for grief, [m]because it had not befallen him as he looked for.

9 And there he continued many days: [n]for his grief was ever more and more, and he made account that he should die.

10 Wherefore he called for all his friends, and said unto them, The sleep is gone from mine eyes, and my heart faileth for very care.

11 And I thought with myself, Into what tribulation am I come, and how great a flood of misery is it, wherein now I am! for I was [o]bountiful and beloved in my power.

12 But now I remember the evils that I did at Jerusalem, and that [p]I took all the vessels of gold and silver that were therein, and [q]sent to destroy the inhabitants of Judea without a cause.

13 I perceive therefore that for this cause these [r]troubles are come upon me, and, behold, I perish through great grief in a strange land.

14 Then called he for [s]Philip, one of his friends, who he made ruler over all his realm,

15 And gave him [t]the crown, and his robe, and his [u]signet, to the end [*]he should bring up his son Antiochus, and nourish him up for the kingdom.

16 [v]So king Antiochus died [w]there in [*]the hundred forty and ninth year.

17 Now when [x]Lysias knew that the king was dead, he set up Antiochus his son, [x]whom he had brought up being young, to reign in his stead, and his name he called [y]Eupator.

18 About this time they that were in [z]the tower shut up the Israelites round about the sanctuary, and sought always their hurt, and the strengthening of the heathen.

19 Wherefore Judas, purposing to destroy them, called all the people together to besiege them.

20 So they came together, and besieged them in [*]the hundred and fiftieth year, and he made [a]mounts for shot against them, and other engines.

21 Howbeit certain of them that were besieged got forth, unto whom some [b]ungodly men of Israel joined themselves:

22 And they went unto [c]the king, and said, How long will it be ere thou execute judgment, and avenge our brethren?

23 We have been willing to serve thy father, and to do as he would have us, and to obey his commandments;

24 For which cause [b]they of our nation besiege [d]the tower, and are alienated from us: moreover [e]as many of us as they could light on they slew, and spoiled our inheritance.

25 Neither have they stretched out their hand against us only, but also against their borders.

26 And, behold, this day are they besieging[d] the tower at Jerusalem, to take it:[f] the sanctuary also and Bethsura have they fortified.

27 Wherefore if thou dost not prevent them quickly, they will do the greater things than these, neither shalt thou be able to rule them.

28 Now [g]when the king heard this, he was angry, and gathered together all his friends, and the captains of his army, and those that had charge of the horse.

29 There came also unto him from other kingdoms, and from [h]isles of the sea, bands of hired soldiers.

30 [i]So that the number of his army was an hundred thousand footmen, and twenty thousand horsemen, and two and thirty [k]elephants exercised in battle.

31 These went through [l]Idumea, and [m]pitched against Bethsura, which they assaulted many days, making engines of war; but they of Bethsura came out, and burned them with fire, and fought valiantly.

32 Upon this Judas removed from [d]the tower, and pitched in Bathzacharias, over against the king’s camp.

33 Then the king rising very early marched [t]fiercely with his host toward Bathzacharias, where his armies made them ready to battle, and sounded the trumpets.

34 And to the end they might provoke [k]the elephants to fight, they shewed them [n]the blood of grapes and mulberries.

35 Moreover they divided the beasts among the armies, and for every [k]elephant they appointed a thousand men, armed with coats of mail, and with helmets of brass on their heads; and beside this, for every beast were ordained five hundred horsemen of the best.

36 These were ready at every occasion: wheresoever the beast was, and whithersoever the beast went, they went also, neither departed they from him.

37 And upon the beasts were there strong towers of wood, which covered every one of them, and were girt fast unto them with devices: there were also upon every one two and thirty strong men, that fought upon them, beside the Indian that ruled him.

38 As for the remnant of the horsemen, they set them on this side and that side at the two parts of the host g[*]iving them signs what to do, and being h[o]arnessed all over amidst the ranks.

39 Now when the sun shone upon the shields of gold and brass, the mountains glistered therewith, and shined like lamps of fire.

40 So part of the king’s army being spread upon the high mountains, and part on the valleys below, they marched on safely and in order.

41 Wherefore all that heard the noise of their multitude, and the marching of the company, and the rattling of the [p]harness, were moved: for the army was very great and mighty.

42 Then Judas and his host drew near, and entered into battle, and there were slain of the king’s army six hundred men.

43 Eleazar also, surnamed [q]Savaran, perceiving that one of the beasts, armed with royal [p]harness, was higher than all the rest, and supposing that the king was upon him,

44 [r]Put himself in [r]jeopardy, to the end he might deliver his people, and [s]get him a perpetual name:

45 Wherefore he ran upon him courageously through the midst of the battle, slaying on the right hand and on the left, [*]so that they were divided from him on both sides.

46 Which done, he crept under the [k]elephant, and thrust him under, and slew him: whereupon the elephant fell down upon him, and there he died.

47 Howbeit the rest of the Jews seeing the strength of the king, and [t]the violence of his forces, turned away from them.

48 Then the king’s army went up to Jerusalem to meet them, and the king pitched his tents [*]against Judea, and against mount Sion.

49 But [u]with them that were in Bethsura he made peace: for they came out of the city, [*]because they had no victuals there to endure the siege, it being [w]a year of rest to the land.

50 So the king took Bethsura, and set a garrison there to keep it.

51 As for the sanctuary, he besieged it many days: and [*]set there artillery with engines and instruments to cast fire and stones, and pieces to cast darts and slings.

52 Whereupon [*]they also made engines against their engines, and held them battle a long season.

53 Yet at the last, their vessels being without victuals, (for that it was [w]the seventh year, and they in Judea that were delivered from the Gentiles, had eaten up the residue of the s[x]tore;)

54 There were but a few left in the sanctuary, because the famine did so prevail against them, that they were fain to disperse themselves, every man to his own place.

55 At that time [y]Lysias heard say, that [z]Philip, whom Antiochus the king, whiles he lived, had appointed to bring up his son Antiochus, that he might be king,

56 Was returned out of [a]Persia and Media, and the king’s host also that went with him, and that he sought to take unto him the ruling of the affairs.

57 Wherefore he went in all haste, and said to the king and the captains of the host and the company, We decay daily, and our victuals are but small, and the place we lay siege unto is strong, and the affairs of the kingdom lie upon us:

58 Now therefore let us [*]be friends with these men, and make peace with them, and with all their nation;

59 And covenant with them, that they shall live after their laws, as they did before: for they are therefore displeased, and have done all these things, because we [b]abolished their laws.

60 [c]So the king and the princes [d]were content: wherefore he sent unto them to make peace; and they accepted thereof.

61 Also the king and the princes made an oath unto them: whereupon they went out of the strong hold.

62 Then the king entered into mount Sion; but when he saw the strength of the place, he [e]broke his oath that he had made, and gave commandment to pull down [f]the wall round about.

63 Afterward departed he in all haste, [g]and returned unto [h]Antiochia, where he found [z]Philip to be master of the city: so [i]he fought against him, and took the city by force.

7

1 In [*]the hundred and one and fiftieth year [a]Demetrius the son of [a]Seleucus departed from [aa]Rome, and came up with a few men unto [*]a city of the sea coast, and reigned there.

2 And as he entered into the [*]palace of his ancestors, so it was, that [b]his forces had taken Antiochus and Lysias, to bring them unto him.

3 Wherefore, when he knew it, he said, Let me not see their faces.

4 So his host slew them. Now when Demetrius was set upon the throne of his kingdom,

5 There came unto him all [c]the wicked and [c]ungodly men of Israel, having [d]Alcimus, who was desirous to be high priest, for their captain:

6 And they accused the people to the king, saying, Judas and his brethren [e]have slain all thy friends, and driven us out of our own land.

7 Now therefore send some man whom thou trustest, and let him go and see what havock he hath made among us, and in the king’s land, and let him punish them with all them that aid them.

8 Then the king chose [f]Bacchides, [g]a friend of the king, who ruled [h]beyond the flood, and was a great man in the kingdom, and faithful to the king,

9 And him he sent with that wicked Alcimus, whom he made high priest, and commanded that he should take vengeance of the children of Israel.

10 So they departed, and came with a great power into the land of Judea, where they sent messengers to Judas and his brethren with peaceable words deceitfully.

11 But they gave no heed to their words; for they saw that they were come with a great power.

12 Then did there assemble unto Alcimus and [f]Bacchides a company of [*]scribes, to require justice.

13 Now the [i]Assideans were the first among the children of Israel that sought peace of them:

14 For said they, [ii]One that is a priest of the seed of Aaron is come with this army, and he will do us no wrong.

15 So he spake unto them, peaceably, and sware unto them, saying, we will procure the harm neither of you nor your friends.

16 Whereupon they believed him: howbeit he took of them threescore men, and slew them in one day, according to the words which [j]he wrote,

17 [k]The flesh of thy saints have they cast out, and their blood have they shed round about Jerusalem, and there was none to bury them.

18 Wherefore the fear and dread of them fell upon all the people, who said, There is neither truth nor [*]righteousness in them; for they have broken the covenant and oath that they made.

19 After this, removed[f] Bacchides from Jerusalem, and pitched his tents in Bezeth, where he sent and took many of the men that had[l] forsaken him, and certain of the people also, and when he had slain them,[m] he cast them into the great pit.

20 Then committed he the country to Alcimus, and left with him a power to aid him: so [f]Bacchides went to the king.

21 But Alcimus [*]contended for the high priesthood.

22 And unto him resorted all such as troubled the people, who, after they had gotten the land of Juda into their power, did much hurt in Israel.

23 Now when Judas saw all the mischief that Alcimus and his company had done among the Israelites, even above the heathen,

24 He went out into all the coasts of Judea round about, and took vengeance of them that had [*]revolted from him, so that they durst no more [*]go forth into the country.

25 On the other side, when Alcimus saw that Judas and his company [*]had gotten the upper hand, and knew that he was not able [*]to abide their force, [n]he went again to the king, and said all the worst of them that he could.

26 Then [o]the king sent [p]Nicanor, one of his honourable princes, a man that bare deadly hate unto Israel, with commandment to destroy the people.

27 [q][*]So Nicanor came to Jerusalem with a great force; and sent unto Judas and his brethren deceitfully with [*]friendly words, saying,

28 Let there be no battle between me and you; I will come with a few men, that I may [*]see you in peace.

29 He came therefore to Judas, and they saluted one another peaceably. Howbeit the enemies were prepared to take away Judas by violence.

30 Which thing after it was known to Judas, to wit, that he came unto him with deceit, he was sore afraid of him, and would see his face no more.

31 [p]Nicanor also, when he saw that his counsel was discovered, went out to [*]fight against Judas beside [*]Capharsalama:

32 Where there were slain of [p]Nicanor’s side about five thousand men, and the rest fled into the city of David.

33 After this went [p]Nicanor up [r]to mount Sion, and [s]there came out of the sanctuary certain of the priests and certain of the elders of the people, to salute him peaceably, and to shew him the burnt sacrifice that was offered [t]for the king.

34 But he mocked them, and laughed at them, and [*]abused them shamefully, and spake proudly,

35 And sware in his wrath, saying, Unless Judas and his host be now delivered into my hands, if ever I come again [*]in safety, I will burn up this house: and with that he went out in a great rage.

36 Then the priests [s]entered in, and stood [u]before the altar and the temple, weeping, and saying,

37 Thou, O Lord, [x]didst choose this house to be called by thy name, and to be [y]a house of prayer and petition for thy people:

38 Be avenged of this man and his host, and let them fall by the sword: remember their blasphemies, and suffer them not to continue any longer.

39 So [z]Nicanor went out of Jerusalem, and pitched his tents in [a]Bethhoron, where an host out of Syria met him.

40 But Judas pitched in [g]Adasa with three thousand men, and there [b]he prayed, saying,

41 O Lord, when they that were sent from the king of the Assyrians blasphemed, [c]thine angel went out, and smote an hundred fourscore and five thousand of them.

42 Even so destroy thou this host before us this day, that the rest may know that [d]he hath spoken blasphemously against thy sanctuary, and judge thou him according to his wickedness.

43 So the thirteenth day of the month [e]Adar the hosts joined battle: but Nicanor’s host was discomfited, and [f]he himself was first slain in the battle.

44 Now when Nicanor’s host saw that he was slain, they cast away their weapons, and fled.

45 Then [*]they pursued after them a day’s journey, from [g]Adasa unto [h]Gazera, sounding an alarm after them [i]with their trumpets.

46 Whereupon they came forth out of all the towns of Judea round about, and closed them in; so that they, turning back upon them that pursued them, were all slain with the sword, and not one of them was left.

47 Afterwards they took the spoils, and the prey, and smote off Nicanors head, and his right hand, [k]which he stretched out so [d]proudly, and brought them away, and hanged them up [l]toward Jerusalem.

48 For this cause the people rejoiced greatly, and they kept that day a day of great gladness.

49 Moreover [m]they ordained to keep yearly this day, being the thirteenth of [e]Adar.

50 Thus [n]the land of Juda was in rest a little while.

8

1 Now Judas had heard of [a]the Romans, that they were mighty and valiant men, and such as would lovingly accept all that joined themselves unto them, and make a league of amity with all that came unto them;

2 And that they were men of great valour. It was told him also of their wars and noble acts which they had done among the [*][b]Galatians, and how they had conquered them, and brought them under tribute;

3 And what they had done in the country of Spain, for the winning of the mines of the silver and gold which is there;

4 And that by their policy and patience they had conquered [*]all the place, though it were very far from them; and the kings also that came against them from the uttermost part of the earth, till they had discomfited them, and given them a great overthrow, so that the rest did give them tribute every year:

5 Beside this, how they had discomfited in battle Philip, and Perseus, king of the [*]Citims, with others that lifted up themselves against them, and had overcome them:

6 How also Antiochus the great king of [c]Asia, that came against them in battle, having an hundred and twenty [d]elephants, with horsemen, and chariots, and a very great army, was discomfited by them;

7 And how they took him alive, and covenanted that he and such as reigned after him should pay a great tribute, and give [e]hostages, and that which was agreed upon,

8 And the country of India, and Media and Lydia and of the goodliest countries, which they took of him, and gave to king Eumenes:

9 Moreover how the Grecians had determined to come and destroy them;

10 And that they, having knowledge thereof sent against them a certain captain, and fighting with them s[ee]lew many of them, and carried away captives their wives and their children, and spoiled them, and took possession of their lands, and pulled down their strong holds, and brought them to be their servants unto this day:

11 It was told him besides, how they destroyed and brought under their dominion all other kingdoms and isles that at any time resisted them;

12 But with their friends and such as relied upon them they kept amity: and that they had conquered kingdoms both far and nigh, insomuch as all that heard of their name were afraid of them:

13 Also that, whom they would help to a kingdom, those reign; and whom again they would, they displace: finally, that they were greatly exalted:

14 Yet for all this none of them [f]wore a crown or was clothed in purple, to be magnified thereby:

15 Moreover how they had made for themselves a [i]senate house, wherein three hundred and twenty men sat in council daily, consulting alway for the people, to the end they might be well ordered:

16 And that they committed their government to [ff]one man every year, who ruled over all their country, and that all were obedient to that one, and that there was neither envy nor emmulation among them.

17 In consideration of these things, Judas chose [g]Eupolemus the son of John, the son of Accos, and Jason the son of Eleazar, and sent them to [a]Rome, to make a league of amity and confederacy with them,

18 And to intreat them that they would take [p]the yoke from them; for they saw that the kingdom of [h]the Grecians did oppress Israel with servitude.

19 They went therefore to Rome, which was a very great journey, and came into the [i]senate, where they [j]spake and said.

20 Judas [k]Maccabeus with his brethren, and the people of the Jews, have sent us unto you, to make a confederacy and peace with you, and that we might be registered your confederates and friends.

21 So [l]that matter pleased the Romans well.

22 And this is the copy of the epistle which the senate wrote back again [ll]in tables of brass, and sent to Jerusalem, that there they might have by them a memorial of peace and confederacy:

23 [m]Good success be to the Romans, and to the people of the Jews, [n]by sea and by land for ever: the sword also and enemy be far from them,

24 If there come first any war upon the Romans or any of their confederates throughout all their dominion,

25 The people of the Jews shall help them, as the time shall be appointed, with all their heart:

26 Neither shall they give any thing unto them that make war upon them, or aid them with victuals, weapons, money, or ships, as it hath seemed good unto the Romans; but they shall keep their covenants without taking any thing therefore.

27 In the same manner also, if war come first upon the nation of the Jews, the Romans shall help them with all their heart, according as the time shall be appointed them:

28 Neither shall victuals be given to them that take part against them, or weapons, or money, or ships, as it hath seemed good to the Romans; but they shall keep their covenants, and that without deceit.

29 According to these articles did the Romans make a covenant with the people of the Jews.

30 Howbeit if hereafter the one party or the other shall think to meet to add or diminish any thing, they may do it at their pleasures, and whatsoever they shall add or take away shall be ratified.

31 And as touching the evils that [o]Demetrius doeth to the Jews, we have written unto him, saying, Wherefore thou made [p]thy yoke heavy upon [q]our friends and confederates the Jews?

32 If therefore they [r]complain any more against thee, we will do them justice, and fight with thee [n]by sea and by land.

9

1 Furthermore, [a]when Demetrius heard the Nicanor and his host were slain in battle, [*]he sent [aa]Bacchides and Alcimus into the land of Judea [b]the second time, and with them [*]the chief strength of his host:

2 Who went forth by the way that leadeth to [*]Galgala, and pitched their tents before Masaloth, which is in [c]Arbela, and after they had won it, they slew much [d]people.

3 Also the first month of [*]the hundred fifty and second year they encamped before Jerusalem:

4 From whence they removed, and went to [*]Berea, with twenty thousand footmen and two thousand horsemen.

5 Now Judas had pitched his tents at [e]Eleasa, and three thousand chosen men with him:

6 Who seeing the multitude of the other army to be so great were sore afraid; whereupon many conveyed themselves out of the host, insomuch as abode of them no more but eight hundred men.

7 When Judas therefore saw that his host slipt away, and that the battle pressed upon him, he was sore troubled in mind, and much distressed, for that he had no time to gather them together.

8 Nevertheless unto them that remained he said, Let us arise and go up against our enemies, if peradventure we may be able to fight with them.

9 But they dehorted him, saying, We shall never be able: [*]let us now rather save our lives, and hereafter we will return with our brethren, and fight against them: for we are but few.

10 Then Judas said, [f]God forbid that I should do this thing, and flee away from them: if our time be come, let us die manfully for our brethren, and [*]let us not stain our honour.

11 With that the host of Bacchides removed out of their tents, and stood over against [*]them, their horsemen being divided into two [g]troops, and their slingers and archers going before the host and they that marched in the foreward were all mighty men.

12 As for Bacchides, he was in [h]the right wing: so the host drew near on the two [g]parts, and sounded their trumpets.

13 They also of Judas’ side, even they sounded their trumpets also, so that the earth shook at the noise of the armies, and the battle continued from morning till night.

14 Now when Judas perceived that Bacchides and the strength of his army were on [h]the right side, he took with him all the hardy men,

15 Who discomfited [h]the right wing, and pursued them unto the mount [i]Azotus.

16 But when they of the left wing saw that they of the right wing were discomfited, they followed upon Judas and those that were with him hard at the heels from behind:

17 Whereupon there was a sore battle, insomuch as [j]many were slain on both parts.

18 Judas also was killed, and the remnant fled.

19 Then [k]Jonathan and Simon took Judas their brother, and buried him in the sepulchre of his fathers in [l]Modin.

20 Moreover they bewailed him, and [m]all Israel made great lamentation for him, and mourned many days, saying,

21 How is the valiant man fallen, that delivered Israel!

22 [mm]As for the other things concerning Judas and his wars, and the noble acts which he did, and his greatness, [n]they are not written: for they were very many.

23 Now after the death of Judas [o]the wicked began to put forth their heads in all the coasts of Israel, and there arose up all [p]such as wrought iniquity.

24 In those days also was there a very great famine, by reason whereof the country revolted, and went with [*]them.

25 Then Bacchides chose [o]the wicked men, and made them lords of the country.

26 And they made enquiry and search for Judas’ friends, and brought them unto Bacchides, who took vengeance of them, and [*]used them despitefully.

27 So was there a great affliction in Israel, the like whereof was not since the time that [q]a prophet was not seen among them.

28 For this cause [r]all Judas’ friends came together, and said unto [k]Jonathan,

29 Since thy brother Judas died, we have no man like him to go forth against our enemies, and Bacchides, and against them [s]of our nation that are adversaries to us.

30 Now therefore we have chosen thee this day to be our prince and captain in his stead, that thou mayest fight our battles.

31 Upon this Jonathan took the governance upon him at that time, and rose up instead of his brother Judas.

32 But when Bacchides gat knowledge thereof, he sought for to slay him

33 Then [k]Jonathan, and Simon his brother, and all that were with him, perceiving that, fled into [t]the wilderness of [u]Thecoe, and pitched their tents by the water of the pool Asphar.

34 [*]Which when Bacchides understood, he came [w]near to Jordan with all his host upon the sabbath day.

35 Now Jonathan had sent his brother [*][x]John, a captain of the people, to pray his friends the [y]Nabathites, [*]that they might leave with them their [z]carriage, which was much.

36 But the children of [*]Jambri came out of [b]Medaba, and took [c]John, and all that he had, and went their way with it.

37 After this came word to Jonathan and Simon his brother, that the children of Jambri made a great marriage, and were bringing the bride from [*]Nadabatha with a great train, as being the daughter of one of the great princes of [d]Chanaan.

38 Therefore they remembered John their brother, and went up, and hid themselves under the covert of the mountain:

39 Where they lifted up their eyes, and looked, and, behold, there was much ado and great [e]carriage: and the bridegroom came forth, and his friends and brethren, to meet them with [*]drums, and [*][f]instruments of musick, and many weapons.

40 Then [g]Jonathan and they that were with him rose up against them from [h]the place where they lay in ambush, and made a slaughter of them in such sort, as [i]many fell down dead, and the remnant fled into the mountain, and they took all their spoils.

41 Thus was the marriage turned into mourning, and the noise of their [f]melody into lamentation.

42 So when they had avenged fully the blood of their brother, they turned again to [k]the marsh of Jordan.

43 Now when Bacchides heard hereof, [l]he came on the sabbath day unto the banks of Jordan with a great power.

44 Then Jonathan said to his company, [ll]Let us go up now and fight for our lives, for it standeth not with us to day, as [m]in time past:

45 For, behold, the battle is before us and behind us, and the water of Jordan on this side and that side,[k] the marsh likewise and wood, neither is there place for us to turn aside.

46 Wherefore [n]cry ye now unto heaven, that ye may be delivered from the hand of your enemies.

47 With that they joined battle, and Jonathan stretched forth his hand to smite Bacchides, but he turned back from him.

48 Then Jonathan and they that were with him leapt into Jordan, and swam over unto the other bank: howbeit the other passed not over Jordan unto them.

49 So there were slain of Bacchides’ side that day about [*]a thousand men.

50 Afterward returned Bacchides to Jerusalem and [*]repaired the strong cites in Judea; the fort in [o]Jericho, and [p]Emmaus, and [q]Bethhoron, and [r]Bethel, and [s]Thamnatha, [t]Pharathoni, and [*][u]Taphon, these did he strengthen [v]with high walls, with gates and with bars.

51 And in them he set a garrison, that they might work malice upon Israel.

52 He fortified also [*]the city [w]Bethsura, and [x]Gazera, and [y]the tower, and put forces in them, and [z]provision of victuals.

53 Besides, he took the chief men’s sons in the country for [a]hostages, and put them into [y]the tower at Jerusalem to be kept.

54 Moreover in [*]the hundred fifty and third year, in the second month, [b]Alcimus commanded that [c]the wall of the inner court of the sanctuary should be pulled down; he pulled down also [d]the works of the prophets

55 And as he began to pull down, even at that time was Alcimus plagued, and his enterprizes hindered: for his mouth was stopped, and he was taken with a palsy, so that he could no more speak any thing, nor [e]give order concerning his house.

56 So Alcimus died at that time with great torment.

57 Now when [f]Bacchides saw that Alcimus was dead, he returned to the king: whereupon [g]the land of Judea was in rest two years.

58 [*]Then all [h]the ungodly men held a council, saying, Behold, Jonathan and his company are at ease, and dwell without care: now therefore we will bring Bacchides hither, who shall take them all in one night.

59 So they went and consulted with him.

60 Then removed he, and came with a great host, and sent letters privily to his adherents in Judea, that they should take Jonathan and those that were with him: howbeit they could not, because their counsel was known unto them.

61 Wherefore they took of the men of the country, that were authors of that mischief, about fifty persons, and slew them.

62 Afterward [i]Jonathan, and Simon, and they that were with him, got them away to [l]Bethbasi, which is in the wilderness, and they [k]repaired the decays thereof, and made it strong.

63 Which thing when Bacchides knew, he gathered together all his host, and sent word [*]to them that were of Judea.

64 Then went he and laid siege against Bethbasi; and they fought against it a long season and made engines of war.

65 But Jonathan left his brother Simon in [l]the city, and went forth himself into the country, and with a certain number went he forth.

66 And he smote [*]Odonarkes and his brethren, and the children of Phasiron in their tent.

67 And when he began to smite them, and came up with his forces, Simon and his company went out of [l]the city, and burned up [m]the engines of war,

68 And fought against Bacchides, who was discomfited by them, and they afflicted him sore: for his counsel and travail was in vain.

69 Wherefore he was very wroth at [h]the wicked men that gave him counsel [n]to come into the country, inasmuch as he slew many of them, and purposed to return into his own country.

70 Whereof when Jonathan had knowledge, he sent ambassadors unto him, [o]to the end he should make peace with him, and deliver them the prisoners.

71 Which thing he accepted, and did according to his demands, and sware unto him that he would never do him harm all the days of his life.

72 When therefore he had restored unto him [p]the prisoners that he had taken aforetime out of the land of Judea, he returned and went his way into his own land, neither [*]came he any more into their borders.

73 Thus the sword ceased from Israel: but Jonathan dwelt at [q]Machmas, and began to [*]govern the people; and he destroyed [h]the ungodly men out of Israel.

10

1 In [*]the hundred and sixtieth year Alexander, [*]the son of Antiochus surnamed Epiphanes, went up and took P[a]tolemais: for the people had received him, by means whereof he reigned there,

2 Now when [b]king Demetrius heard thereof, he gathered together an exceeding great host, and went forth against him to fight.

3 Moreover Demetrius sent letters unto [c]Jonathan with loving words, so as he magnified him.

4 For said he, [u]Let us first [d]make peace with him, before he join with Alexander against us:

5 Else [e]he will remember all the evils that we have done against him, and against his brethren and his people.

6 Wherefore he gave him authority to gather together an host, and to provide weapons, that he might aid him in battle: he commanded also that [f]the [g]hostages that were in [h]the tower should be delivered him.

7 Then came [c]Jonathan to Jerusalem, and read the letters in the audience of all the people, and of them that were in [h]the tower:

8 Who [i]were sore afraid, when they heard that the king had given him authority to gather together an host.

9 Whereupon they of [h]the tower delivered their [g]hostages unto Jonathan, and he delivered them unto their parents.

10 This done, Jonathan settled himself in Jerusalem, and began to build and repair the city.

11 And he commanded the workmen [k]to build the walls and the mount Sion and about with square stones for fortification; and they did so.

12 Then the strangers, that were in the fortresses[l] which Bacchides had built, fled away;

13 Insomuch as every man left his place, and went into his own country.

14 Only at [m]Bethsura certain of [n]those that had forsaken the law and the commandments remained still: for it was their place of refuge.

15 Now when king Alexander had heard [o]what promises Demetrius had sent unto Jonathan: when also it was told him of the battles and noble acts which he and his brethren had done, and of the pains that they had endured,

16 He said, Shall we find such another man? now therefore we will make him our friend and confederate.

17 Upon this he wrote a letter, and sent it unto him, according to these words, saying,

18 King Alexander [oo]to his brother Jonathan sendeth greeting:

19 We have heard of thee, that thou art a man of great power, and meet to be our friend.

20 Wherefore now this day we ordain thee to be the high priest of thy nation, and to be called [p]the king’s friend; (and therewithal he sent him [pp]a purple robe and [q]a crown of gold:) and require thee [r]to take our part, and keep friendship with us.

21 So in [s]the seventh month of [*]the hundred and sixtieth year, [s]at the feast of the tabernacles, Jonathan put on [t]the holy robe, and gathered together forces, and provided much armour.

22 Whereof when Demetrius heard, he was very sorry, and said,

23 What have we done, [u]that Alexander hath [x]prevented us in making amity with the Jews to strengthen himself?

24 I also will write unto them words of encouragement, and promise them dignities and gifts, that I may have their aid.

25 He sent unto them therefore to this effect: King Demetrius unto the people of the Jews sendeth greeting:

26 Whereas ye have kept covenants with us, and continued in our friendship, not joining yourselves with our enemies, we have heard hereof, and are glad.

27 Wherefore now continue ye still to be faithful unto us, and we will well recompense you for the things ye do in our behalf,

28 And will grant you many [y]immunities, and give you rewards.

29 And now do I free you, and for your sake I release all the Jews, from [z]tributes, and from [z]the customs of salt, and from [z][a]crown taxes,

30 And from [b]that which appertaineth unto me to receive for the third part or the seed, and the half of the fruit of the trees, I release it from this day forth, so that they shall not be taken of the land of Judea, nor of [c]the three governments which are added thereunto out of the country of [d]Samaria and Galilee, from this day forth for evermore.

31 Let Jerusalem also be [e]holy and free, with the [q]borders thereof, both from [f]tenths and [f][g]tributes.

32 And as for [h]the tower which is at Jerusalem, I yield up authority over it, and give [i]the high priest, that he may set in it such men as he shall choose to keep it.

33 Moreover I freely set at liberty every one of the Jews, [j]that were carried captives out of the land of Judea into any part of my kingdom, and I will that all my officers remit the tributes even of their cattle.

34 Furthermore I will that all the feasts, and [k]sabbaths, and [k]new moons, and solemn days, and the three days before the feast, and the three days after the feast shall be all of [l]immunity and freedom for all the Jews in my realm.

35 Also no man shall have authority to meddle with or to [m]molest any of them in any matter.

36 I will further, [mm]that there be enrolled among the king’s forces about thirty thousand men of the Jews, unto whom pay shall be given, as belongeth to all king’s forces.

37 And of them some shall be placed in the king’s strong holds, of whom also some shall be set over the [n]affairs of the kingdom, which are of trust: and I will that their overseers and governors be of themselves, and that they [*]live after their own laws, even as the king hath commanded in the land of Judea.

38 And concerning [c]the three governments that are added to Judea from the country of [d]Samaria, let them be joined with Judea, that they may be reckoned to be under one, nor bound to obey other authority than [i]the high priest’s.

39 As for [o]Ptolemais, and the land pertaining thereto, I give it as a free gift to the sanctuary at Jerusalem for the necessary expences [*]of the sanctuary.

40 Moreover I give every year fifteen thousand shekels of silver out of the king’s accounts from the places appertaining.

41 And all the overplus, which [p]the officers payed not in as in former time, from henceforth shall be given toward the works of the temple.

42 And beside this, [pp]the five thousand shekels of silver, which they took from the [n]uses of the temple out of the accounts year by year, even those things shall be released, because they appertain to the priests that minister.

43 And whosoever they be that flee unto the temple at Jerusalem, or be within the [q]liberties hereof, being indebted unto the king, or for any other matter, let them be at liberty, and all that they have in my realm.

44 For the building also and [r]repairing of the works of the sanctuary expences shall be given of the king’s accounts.

45 Yea, and for [s]the building of the walls of Jerusalem, and the fortifying thereof round about, expences shall be given out of the king’s accounts, as also for the building of the walls in Judea.

46 Now when Jonathan and the people heard these words, they gave no credit unto them, nor received them, because [t]they remembered the great evil that he had done in Israel; for he had afflicted them very sore.

47 But with Alexander they were well pleased, because he was the first that entreated of true peace with them, and they were confederate with him always.

48 [*]Then gathered king Alexander great forces, and camped over against Demetrius.

49 And after the two kings had joined battle, Demetrius’ host fled: but Alexander followed after him, and prevailed against them.

50 And he continued the battle very sore until the sun went down: and that day was Demetrius slain.

51 Afterward Alexander sent ambassadors to [u]Ptolemee king of Egypt with a message to this effect:

52 Forasmuch as I am come again to my realm, and am set in the throne of my progenitors, and have gotten the dominion, and overthrown Demetrius, and recovered our country;

53 For after I had joined battle with him, both he and his host was discomfited by us, so that we sit in the throne of his kingdom:

54 Now therefore let us make a league of amity together, and give me now thy daughter to wife: and I will be thy son in law, and will give both thee and her as according to thy dignity.

55 Then Ptolemee the king gave answer, saying, Happy be the day wherein thou didst return into the land of thy fathers, and satest in the throne of their kingdom.

56 And now will I do to thee, as thou hast written: meet me therefore at [x]Ptolemais, that we may see one another; for I will marry my daughter to thee according to thy desire.

57 So Ptolemee went out of Egypt with his daughter Cleopatra, and they came unto [x]Ptolemais in [*]the hundred threescore and second year:

58 Where king Alexander meeting him, he gave unto him his daughter Cleopatra, and celebrated her marriage at [x]Ptolemais with great glory, as the manner of kings is.

59 Now king Alexander had written unto Jonathan, that he should come and meet him.

60 Who thereupon went honourably to [x]Ptolemais, where he met the two kings, and gave them and their friends silver and gold, and many presents, and [y]found favour in their sight.

61 At that time certain [z]pestilent fellows of Israel, [a]men of a wicked life, assembled themselves against him, to [b]accuse him: but the king would not hear them.

62 Yea more than that, the king commanded to take off his garments, and [c]clothe him in purple: and they did so.

63 And he made him sit by himself, and said unto his princes, [d]Go with him into the midst of the city, and make proclamation, that no man [b]complain against him of any matter, and that no man [e]trouble him for any manner of cause.

64 Now when his [b]accusers saw that he was honored according to the proclamation, and clothed in purple, they fled all away.

65 So the king honoured him, and [f]wrote him among his chief friends, and made him a [g]duke, and [*]partaker of his dominion.

66 Afterward Jonathan returned to Jerusalem with peace and gladness.

67 Furthermore in [*]the hundred threescore and fifth year came Demetrius son of [g]Demetrius out of [h]Crete into the land of his fathers:

68 Whereof when king Alexander heard tell, he was right sorry, and returned into [i]Antioch.

69 Then Demetrius made [j]Apollonius the governor of [k]Celosyria his general, who gathered together a great host, and camped in [l]Jamnia, and sent unto Jonathan the high priest, saying,

70 Thou alone liftest up thyself against us, and I am laughed to scorn for thy sake, and reproached: and why dost thou vaunt thy power against us [m]in the mountains?

71 Now therefore, if thou trustest in thine own strength, [m]come down to us into the plain field, and there let us try the matter together: for with me is the power of the cities.

72 Ask and learn who I am, and the rest that take our part, and they shall tell thee that thy foot is not able to stand before our face; for thy fathers have been [n]twice put to flight in their own land.

73 Wherefore now thou shalt not be able to abide the horsemen and so great a power in the plain, [nn]where is neither stone nor flint, nor place to flee unto.

74 So when Jonathan heard these words of [j]Apollonius, he was moved in his mind, and choosing ten thousand men he went out of Jerusalem, where [o]Simon his brother met him for to help him.

75 And he pitched his tents against [p]Joppa: but; they of Joppa shut him out of the city, because Apollonius had a garrison there.

76 Then Jonathan laid siege unto it: whereupon they of the city let him in for fear: and so Jonathan won Joppa.

77 Whereof when Apollonius heard, he took three thousand horsemen, with a great host of footmen, and went to [q]Azotus [*]as one that journeyed, and therewithal [*]drew him forth into [t]the plain. because he had a great number of horsemen, in whom he put his trust.

78 Then Jonathan followed after him to [q]Azotus, where the armies joined battle.

79 Now Apollonius had left a thousand horsemen in ambush.

80 And Jonathan knew that there was an [r]ambushment behind him; for they had compassed in his host, and cast darts at the people, from morning till evening.

81 But the people stood still, as Jonathan had commanded them: and so the [*][s]enemies’ horses were tired.

82 Then brought Simon forth his host, and set them against the footmen, (for the horsemen were spent) who were discomfited by him, and fled.

83 The horsemen also, being scattered in [t]the field, fled to [q]Azotus, and went into [u]Bethdagon, their [v]idol’s temple, for safety.

84 But Jonathan set fire on Azotus, and the cities round about it, and took their spoils; and [u]the temple of Dagon, with them that were fled into it, he burned with fire.

85 Thus there were burned and slain with the sword well nigh eight thousand men.

86 And from thence Jonathan removed his host, and camped against [w]Ascalon, where the men of the city came forth, and met him with great pomp.

87 After this returned Jonathan and his host unto Jerusalem, having any spoils.

88 Now when king Alexander heard these things, he honoured Jonathan [x]yet more.

89 And sent him [y]a buckle of gold, as the use is to be given to such as are of the king’s blood: he gave him also [z]Accaron with the borders thereof in possession.

11

1 [*]And [a]the king of Egypt gathered together a great host, [b]like the sand that lieth upon the sea shore, and many ships, and went about through deceit to get Alexander’s kingdom, and join it to his own.

2 Whereupon he took his journey into Spain [c]in peaceable manner, so as they of the cities opened unto him, and met him: for king Alexander had commanded them so to do, because he was his brother in law.

3 Now as [a]Ptolemee entered into the cities, he set in every one of them a garrison of soldiers to keep it.

4 And when he came near to [d]Azotus, they shewed him [e]the temple of Dagon that was burnt, and Azotus and [e]the suburbs thereof that were destroyed, and the bodies that were [f]cast abroad and them that he had burnt in the battle; for they had made heaps of them by the way where he should pass.

5 Also they told the king whatsoever Jonathan had done, to the intent he might blame him: but the king held his peace.

6 Then Jonathan met the king with great pomp at [g]Joppa, where they saluted one another, and [*]lodged.

7 Afterward Jonathan, when he had gone with the king to the river called [h]Eleutherus, returned again to Jerusalem.

8 [a]King Ptolemee therefore, having gotten the dominion of the cities by the sea unto [i]Seleucia upon the sea coast, [k]imagined wicked counsels against Alexander.

9 Whereupon he sent ambasadors unto king [l]Demetrius, saying, Come, let us make a league betwixt us, and I will give thee my daughter whom Alexander hath, and thou shalt reign in thy father’s kingdom:

10 For I repent that I gave my daughter unto him, for he sought to slay me.

11 Thus did he slander him, because he was desirous of his kingdom.

12 Wherefore he took his daughter from him, and gave her to Demetrius, and [m]forsook Alexander, so that their hatred was openly known.

13 Then Ptolemee entered into [n]Antioch, where he set two crowns upon his head, the crown of [nn]Asia, and of Egypt.

14 In the mean season was king Alexander in [o]Cilicia, because those that dwelt in those parts had revolted from him.

15 But when Alexander heard of this, he came to war against him: whereupon king Ptolemee brought forth his host, and met him with a mighty power, and put him to flight.

16 So Alexander fled into [p]Arabia there to be defended; but king Ptolemee was exalted:

17 For Zabdiel the [p]Arabian took off Alexander’s head, and sent it unto Ptolemee.

18 King Ptolemee also died the third day after, [*]and they that were in the strong holds were slain one of another.

19 By this means [pp]Demetrius reigned in [*]the hundred threescore and seventh year.

20 At the same time [q]Jonathan gathered together them that were in Judea to take t[r]he tower that was in Jerusalem: and he made many engines of war against it.

21 Then came [s]ungodly persons, who hated their own people, went unto the [t]king, and told him that Jonathan besieged [r]the tower,

22 Whereof when he heard, he was angry, and immediately removing, he came to [u]Ptolemais, and wrote unto Jonathan, that he should not lay siege to [r]the tower, but come and speak with him at Ptolemais in great haste.

23 Nevertheless Jonathan, when he heard this, commanded to besiege it still: and he chose certain of the elders of Israel and the priests, and [w]put himself in peril;

24 And took silver and gold, and raiment, and divers presents besides, and went to [u]Ptolemais unto the king, where he [x]found favour in his sight.

25 And though [y]certain ungodly men of the people had [y][z]made complaints against him,

26 Yet the king entreated him [a]as his predecessors had done before, and promoted him in the sight of all his friends,

27 And confirmed him in [b]the high priesthood, and in all the honours that he had before, and gave him preeminence among [c]his chief friends.

28 Then Jonathan desired the king, that he would make [d]Judea free from tribute, as also [e]the three governments, with the country of Samaria; and he promised him three hundred talents.

29 So the king consented, and wrote letters unto Jonathan of all these things after this manner:

30 King Demetrius [f]unto his brother Jonathan, and unto the nation of the Jews, sendeth greeting:

31 We send you here a copy of the letter which we did write unto our cousin Lasthenes concerning you, that ye might see it.

32 King Demetrius unto his father Lasthenes sendeth greeting:

33 We are determined to do good to the people of the Jews, who are our friends, and keep covenants with us, because of their good will toward us.

34 [*]Wherefore we have ratified unto them the borders of Judea, with [e]the three governments of Apherema and [g]Lydda and [h]Ramathem, that are added unto Judea from the country of Samaria, and [i]all things appertaining unto them, for all such as do sacrifice in Jerusalem, instead of the payments which the king received of them yearly aforetime [k]out of the fruits of the earth and [k]of trees.

35 And as for other things that belong unto us, of the [l]tithes and [l]customs pertaining unto us, as also [m]the saltpits, and the [m]crown taxes, which are due unto us, we discharge them of them all for their relief.

36 And nothing hereof shall be [n]revoked from this time forth for ever.

37 Now therefore see that thou make a copy of these things, and let it be delivered unto Jonathan, and set upon the holy mount in a conspicuous place.

38 After this, when king Demetrius saw that the land was quiet before him, and that no resistance was made against him, he sent away all his forces, every one to his own place, except certain bands of strangers, whom [o]he had gathered from [p]the isles of the heathen: wherefore all the forces of his fathers hated him.

39 Moreover there was one Tryphon, that had been of Alexander’s part afore, who, seeing that all the host murmured against Demetrius, went to Simalcue the [q]Arabian that brought up Antiochus the young son of Alexander,

40 And lay sore upon him to deliver him this young Antiochus, that he might reign in his father’s stead: he told him therefore all that Demetrius had done, and how his men of war were at enmity with him, and [r]there he remained a long season.

41 In the mean time Jonathan sent unto king Demetrius, that he would cast those of [s]the tower out of Jerusalem, and [t]those also in the fortresses: for they fought against Israel.

42 So Demetrius sent unto Jonathan, saying, I will not only do this for thee and thy people, but I will greatly honour thee and thy nation, if opportunity serve.

43 Now therefore thou shalt do well, if thou send me men to help me; for [u]all my forces are gone from me.

44 Upon this Jonathan sent him three thousand strong men unto [w]Antioch: and when they came to the king, the king was very glad of their coming.

45 Howbeit they that were of the city gathered themselves together into the midst of the city, to the number of an hundred and twenty thousand men, and would have slain the king.

46 Wherefore the king fled into the court, but they of the city kept the passages of the city, and began to fight.

47 Then the king called to the Jews for help, who came unto him all at once, and dispersing themselves through the city slew that day in the city to the number of an hundred thousand.

48 Also they set fire on the city, and gat many spoils that day, and delivered the king.

49 So when they of the city saw that the Jews had got the city as they would, their courage was abated: wherefore they made supplication to the king, and cried, saying,

50 [*]Grant us peace, and let the Jews cease from assaulting us and the city.

51 With that they cast away their weapons, and made peace; and the Jews were honoured in the sight of the king, and in the sight of all that were in his realm; and they returned to Jerusalem, having great spoils.

52 So king Demetrius sat on the throne of his kingdom, and [x]the land was quiet before him.

53 Nevertheless he dissembled in all that ever he spake, and estranged himself from Jonathan, neither rewarded he him according to the benefits which he had received of him, but troubled him very sore.

54 [*]After [y]this returned Tryphon, and with him [z]the young child Antiochus, who reigned, and was crowned.

55 Then there gathered unto him all the men of war, whom Demetrius had put away, and they fought against Demetrius, who turned his back and fled.

56 Moreover Tryphon took the [*]elephants, and won [w]Antioch.

57 At that time young Antiochus wrote unto Jonathan, saying, [a]I confirm thee in the high priesthood, and appoint thee ruler over [b]the four governments, and to be one of [c]the king’s friends.

58 Upon this he sent him golden vessels [*]to be served in, and gave him leave to drink in gold, and [cc]to be clothed in purple, and to wear [d]a golden buckle.

59 His brother [e]Simon also he made captain from the place called The ladder of [ee]Tyrus unto the borders of Egypt.

60 Then Jonathan [*]went forth, and passed through the cities beyond the water, and all the forces of Syria gathered themselves unto him for to help him: and when he came to [f]Ascalon, they of the city met him honourably.

61 From whence he went to [g]Gaza, but they of Gaza shut him out; wherefore he laid siege unto it, and burned [*]the suburbs thereof with fire, and spoiled them.

62 Afterward, when they of Gaza made supplication unto Jonathan, [*]he made peace with them, and took the sons of their chief men for [h]hostages, and sent them to Jerusalem, and passed through the country unto [i]Damascus.

63 Now [j]when Jonathan heard that Demetrius’ princes were come to [k]Cades, which is in Galilee, with a great power, purposing [*]to remove him out of the country,

64 He went to meet them, and left Simon his brother in the country.

65 Then Simon encamped against [m]Bethsura and fought against it a long season, and shut it up:

66 But they desired [mm]to have peace with him, which he granted them, and then [m]put them out from thence, and took the city, and set a garrison in it.

67 As for Jonathan and his host, they pitched at the water of [n]Gennesar, from whence betimes in the morning they gat them to the plain of [o]Nasor.

68 And, behold, the host of strangers met them in the plain, who, having laid[p] men in ambush for him in the mountains, came themselves over against him.

69 So when [p]they that lay in ambush rose out of their places and joined battle, all that were of Jonathan’s side fled;

70 Insomuch as there was not one of them left, except Mattathias the son of [q]Absalom, and Judas the son of Calphi, the captains of the host.

71 Then Jonathan [r]rent his clothes, and [s]cast earth upon his head, and prayed.

72 Afterwards turning again to battle, he put them to flight, and so they ran away.

73 Now when his own men that were fled saw this, they turned again unto him, and with him pursued them to [k]Cades, even [k]unto their own tents, and there they camped.

74 So there were slain of the heathen that day about three thousand men: but Jonathan returned to Jerusalem.

12

1 Now when Jonathan saw that time served him, he chose [a]certain men, and sent them to [a]Rome, for to confirm and renew [b]the friendship that they had with them.

2 He sent letters also to [bb]the Lacedemonians, and to other places, for the same purpose.

3 So they went unto [a]Rome, and [c]entered into the senate, and said, Jonathan the high priest, and the people of the Jews, sent us unto you, to the end ye should renew the friendship, which ye had with them, and league, as in former time.

4 Upon this the Romans gave them letters unto the governors of every place that they should bring them into the land of Judea peaceably.

5 And this is the copy of the letters [d]which Jonathan wrote to the Lacedemonians:

6 Jonathan the high priest, and [e]the elders of the nation, and the priests, and the other of the Jews, unto the Lacedemonians their brethren send greeting:

7 There were letters sent in times past unto [f]Onias the high priest from [*]Darius, who reigned then among you, to signify that ye are our brethren, as [g]the copy here underwritten doth specify.

8 At which time Onias entreated the ambassador that was sent honourably, and received the letters, wherein [h]declaration was made of the [*]league and friendship.

9 Therefore we also, albeit we need none of these things, that we have the holy books of scripture in our hands [i]to comfort us,

10 Have nevertheless attempted to send unto you for the renewing of brotherhood and friendship, lest we should become strangers unto you altogether: for there is a long time passed since ye sent unto us.

11 We therefore at all times [j]without ceasing, both in our feasts, and other convenient days, do remember you in the sacrifices which we offer, and in our prayers, as reason is, and as it becometh us to think upon our brethren:

12 And we are right glad of your honour.

13 As for ourselves, we have had great troubles and wars on every side, forsomuch as the kings that are round about us have fought against us.

14 Howbeit we would not [k]be troublesome unto you, nor to others of our confederates and friends, in these wars:

15 For we have help from heaven that succoureth us, so as we are delivered from our enemies, and our enemies are brought under foot.

16 For this cause we chose [kk]Numenius the son of Antiochus, and Antipater the son of Jason, and sent them unto the Romans, to renew the amity that we had with them, and the former league.

17 We commanded them also to go unto you, and to salute and to deliver you our letters concerning the renewing of our brotherhood.

18 Wherefore now ye shall do well to give us an answer thereto.

19 And this is [l]the copy of the letters [*]which Oniares sent.

20 Areus king of the Lacedemonians to Onias the high priest, greeting:

21 It is found in writing, that [ll]the Lacedemonians and Jews are brethren, and that they are of the stock of Abraham:

22 Now therefore, since this is come to our knowledge, ye shall do well to write unto us of your [*]prosperity.

23 We do write back again to you, that your cattle and goods are our’s, and our’s are your’s We do command therefore our ambassadors to make report unto you on this wise.

24 Now when Jonathan heard that Demebius’ princes were come to fight against him [m]with a greater host than afore,

25 He removed from Jerusalem, and met them in the land of [n]Amathis: for he gave them no respite [*]to enter his country.

26 He sent spies also unto their tents, who came again, and told him that they were appointed to come upon them in the night season.

27 Wherefore so soon as the sun was down, Jonathan commanded his men to watch, and to be in arms, that all the night long they might be ready to fight: also he [o]sent forth centinels round about the host.

28 But when the adversaries heard that Jonathan and his men were ready for battle, they feared, and trembled in their hearts, and [*]they kindled fires in their camp.

29 Howbeit Jonathan and his company knew it not till the morning: for they saw the lights burning.

30 Then Jonathan pursued after them, but overtook them not: for they were gone over the river [p]Eleutherus.

31 Wherefore Jonathan turned to the [q]Arabians, who were called [*]Zabadeans, and smote them, and took their spoils.

32 And removing thence, he came to [r]Damascus, and so passed through all the country,

33 [s]Simon also went forth, and passed through the country unto [t]Ascalon, and the holds there adjoining, from whence he turned aside to [u]Joppa, and won it.

34 For he had heard that they would deliver the hold unto [v]them that took Demetrius’ part; wherefore he set a garrison there to keep it.

35 After this came Jonathan home again, and calling the elders of the people together, he consulted with them about [vv]building strong holds in Judea,

36 And [w]making the walls of Jerusalem higher, and raising a great mount between [x]the tower and the city, for to separate it from the city, that so it might be alone, [y]that men might neither sell nor buy in it.

37 Upon this they came together to build up the city, [*]forasmuch as part of the wall toward the brook on the east side was fallen down, and they repaired that which was called Caphenatha.

38 Simon also set up [z]Adida in [z]Sephela, and made it strong [a]with gates and bars.

39 Now [b]Tryphon went about to get the kingdom of [c]Asia, and [d]to kill Antiochus the king, that he might set the crown upon his own [e]head.

40 Howbeit he was afraid that Jonathan would not suffer him, and that he would fight against him; wherefore he sought a way how to take Jonathan, that he might kill him. So he removed, and came to [f]Bethsan.

41 Then Jonathan went out to meet him with forty thousand men chosen for the [g]battle, and came to [f]Bethsan.

42 Now when Tryphon saw Jonathan came with so great a force, he durst not stretch his hand against him;

43 But received him honourably, and commended him unto all his friends, and gave him gifts, and commanded his men of war to be as obedient unto him, as to himself.

44 Unto Jonathan also he said, Why hast thou brought all this people to so great trouble, seeing there is no war betwixt us?

45 Therefore send them now home again, and choose a few men to wait on thee, and come thou with me to [h]Ptolemais, for [i]I will give it thee, and the rest of the strong holds and forces, and all that have any [j]charge: as for me, I will return and depart: for this is the cause of my coming.

46 So Jonathan believing him did as he bade him, and sent away his host, who went into the land of Judea.

47 And with himself he retained but three thousand men, of whom he [*]sent [m]two thousand into Galilee, and one thousand went with him.

48 Now as soon as Jonathan entered into [h]Ptolemais, they of Ptolemais shut the gates and took him, and all them that came with him they slew with the sword.

49 Then sent Tryphon an host of footmen and horsemen into Galilee, and into [l]the great plain, to destroy [m]all Jonathan’s company.

50 But when they knew that Jonathan and they that were with him were taken and [n]slain, they encouraged one another; and went close together, prepared to fight.

51 They therefore that followed upon them, perceiving that they were ready to fight for their lives, turned back again.

52 Whereupon they all came into the land of Judea peaceably, and there they bewailed Jonathan, and them that were with him, and they were sore afraid; wherefore all Israel made great lamentation.

53 Then all the heathen that were round about then sought to destroy them: for said they, They have no captain, nor any to help them: now therefore let us make war upon them, and [o]take away their memorial from among men.

13

1 Now when [a]Simon heard that [b]Tryphon had gathered together a great host to invade the land of Judea, and destroy it,

2 And saw that the people was [c]in great trembling and fear, he went up to Jerusalem, and gathered the people together,

3 And gave them exhortation, saying, Ye yourselves know what great things I, and my brethren, and my father’s house, have done for the laws and the sanctuary, the battles also and troubles which we have seen.

4 By reason whereof [d]all my brethren are slain for Israel’s sake, and I am left alone.

5 Now therefore be it far from me, that I should spare mine own life in any time of trouble: [e]for I am no better than my brethren.

6 Doubtless I will avenge my nation, and the sanctuary, and our wives, and our children: for all the heathen are gathered to destroy us of very malice.

7 Now as soon as the people heard these words, their spirit [f]revived.

8 And they answered with a loud voice, saying, Thou shalt be our leader instead of [g]Judas and [h]Jonathan thy brother.

9 Fight thou our battles, and whatsoever, thou commandest us, that will we do.

10 So then he gathered together all the men of war, and made haste [i]to finish the walls of Jerusalem, and he fortified it round about.

11 Also he sent Jonathan the son of [k]Absolom, and with him a great power, to [l]Joppa: who [m]casting out them that were therein remained there in it.

12 So Tryphon removed from [n]Ptolemaus with a great power to invade the land of Judea, and [o]Jonathan was with him in ward.

13 But Simon pitched his tents at [p]Adida, over against [p]the plain.

14 Now when Tryphon knew that Simon [q]was risen up instead of his brother Jonathan, and meant to join battle with him, he sent messengers unto him, saying,

15 Whereas we have Jonathan thy brother in hold, it is for money that he is owing unto the king’s treasure, [*]concerning the business that was committed unto him.

16 Wherefore now send an hundred talents of silver, and two of his sons for [r]hostages, that when he is at liberty he may not revolt from us, and we will let him go.

17 Hereupon Simon, albeit he perceived that they spake deceitfully unto him yet sent he the money and the children, lest peradventure he should procure to himself great hatred of the people:

18 Who might have said, Because I sent him not the money and the children, therefore is Jonathan dead.

19 So he sent them the children and the hundred talents: howbeit Tryphon dissembled neither would he let Jonathan go.

20 And after this came Tryphon to invade the land, and destroy it, going round about by the way that leadeth unto [s]Adora: but Simon and his host marched against him in every place, wheresoever he went.

21 Now they that were in [t]the tower sent messengers unto Tryphon, to the end that he should hasten his coming unto them by the wilderness, and [u]send them victuals.

22 Wherefore Tryphon made ready all his horsemen to come that night: but there fell a very great snow, by reason whereof he came not. So he departed, and came into the country of [w]Galaad.

23 And when he came near to [x]Bascama he slew Jonathan, who was buried there.

24 Afterward Tryphon returned and went into his own land.

25 [*]Then sent Simon, and took the bones of Jonathan his brother, and buried them in [y]Modin, the city of his fathers.

26 And [z]all Israel made great lamentation for him, and bewailed him many days.

27 Simon also built a monument upon the sepulchre of his father and his brethren, and raised it aloft to the sight, with hewn stone behind and before.

28 Moreover he set up seven pyramids, one against another, for his father, and his mother, and his four brethren.

29 And in these he made cunning devices, about the which he set great pillars, and upon the pillars he made [a]all their armour for a perpetual memory, and by the armour ships carved, that they might be seen of all [b]that sail on the sea.

30 This is the sepulchre which he made at [c]Modin, and it standeth yet [d]unto this day.

31 Now [e]Tryphon dealt deceitfully with the young king Antiochus, and slew him.

32 And he reigned in his stead, and crowned himself king of [f]Asia, and brought a great calamity upon the land.

33 Then Simon [g]built up the strong holds in Judea, and fenced them about with high towers, and [h]great walls, and gates, and bars, and laid up victuals [*]therein.

34 Moreover Simon chose men, and sent to [i]king Demetrius, to the end he should give the land an immunity, because [*]all that Tryphon did was to spoil.

35 Unto whom king Demetrius answered and wrote after this manner:

36 King Demetrius unto Simon [j][k]the high priest, and [k]friend of kings, as also unto the elders and nation of the Jews, sendeth greeting:

37 [l]The golden crown, and [m]the scarlet robe, which ye sent unto us, we have received: and we are ready to make a stedfast peace with you, yea, and to write unto our [n]officers, to confirm the [o]immunities which we have granted.

38 And whatsoever covenants we have made with you shall stand; and [g]the strong holds, which ye have builded, shall be your own.

39 As for any oversight or fault committed unto this day, we forgive it, and the [p]crown tax also, which ye owe us: and [pp]if there were any other tribute paid in Jerusalem, it shall no more be paid.

40 And look who are meet among you to be in our court, [q]let then be enrolled, and let there be peace betwixt us.

41 Thus the yoke of the heathen was taken away from Israel in [*]the hundred and seventieth year.

42 Then the people of Israel [r]began to write in their instruments and contracts, In the first year of Simon the high priest, the governor and leader of the Jews.

43 In those days Simon camped against [s]Gaza and besieged it round about; he made also an engine of war, and set it by the city, and battered a certain tower, and took it.

44 And they that were in the engine leaped into the city; whereupon there was a great uproar in the city:

45 Insomuch as the people of the city [t]rent their clothes, and climbed upon the walls with their wives and children, and cried with a loud voice, beseeching Simon [*]to grant them peace.

46 And they said, Deal not with us according to our wickedness, but according to thy mercy.

47 So Simon was appeased toward them, and fought no more against them, but put them out of the city, and cleansed the houses wherein the idols were, and so entered into it [u]with songs and thanksgiving.

48 Yea, he put all uncleanness out of it, and placed such men there as would keep the law, and made it stronger than it was before, and built therein [w]a dwellingplace for himself.

49 [*]They also of [x]the tower in Jerusalem were kept so strait, that they could neither [y]come forth, nor go into the country, [z]nor buy, nor sell: wherefore [a]they were in great distress for want of victuals, and a great number of them perished through famine.

50 Then cried they to Simon, beseeching him [*]to be at one with them: which thing he granted them; and when he had put them out from thence, [aa]he cleansed [x]the tower from pollutions:

51 And entered into it the three and twentieth day of the second month in [*]the hundred seventy and first year, with [b]thanksgiving, and [c]branches of palm trees, and with [d][f]harps, and [e]cymbals, and with [f]viols, and [b]hymns, and songs: because there was destroyed [g]a great enemy out of Israel.

52 He ordained also that that day should be kept every year with gladness. Moreover [h]the hill of the temple that was by [x]the tower he made stronger than it was, and there he dwelt himself with his company.

53 And when Simon saw that [i]John his son was a valiant man, he made him captain of all the hosts; and [j]he dwelt in [k]Gazera.

14

1 Now in [*]the hundred threescore and twelfth year king Demetrius gathered his forces together, and went into [a]Media t[b]o get him help to fight against Tryphone.

2 But when [c]Arsaces, the king of [cc]Persia and [a]Media, heard that Demetrius was entered within his borders, he sent one of his princes to take him alive:

3 Who went and smote the host of Demetrius, and took him, and brought him to Arsaces, by whom he was put in ward.

4 As for the land of Judea, [d]that was quiet all the days of Simon; for he sought the good of his nation in such wise, as that evermore his authority and honour pleased them well.

5 And as he was honourable in all his acts, so in this, that he took [e]Joppa for an haven, and made an entrance to the [f]isles of the sea,

6 And enlarged the bounds of his nation, and recovered the country,

7 And gathered together a great number of captives, and had the dominion of [g]Gazera, and [h]Bethsura, and [i]the tower, [k]out of the which he took all uncleaness, neither was there any that resisted him.

8 Then did they till their ground in peace, and [l]the earth gave her increase, and the trees of the field their fruit.

9 The ancient men sat all in the streets, communing together of [*]good things, and the young men [m]put on glorious and warlike apparel.

10 He provided victuals for the cities, and set in them all manner of munition, so that his honourable name was renowned unto the end of the world.

11 He made peace in the land, and Israel rejoiced with great joy:

12 For [n]every man sat under his vine and his fig tree, and there was none to [o]fray them:

13 Neither was there any left in the land to fight against them: yea, the kings themselves were overthrown in those days.

14 Moreover he strengthened all those of his people that were brought low: the law he searched out; and every contemner of the law and wicked person he took away.

15 He beautified the sanctuary, and multiplied vessels of the temple.

16 Now when it was heard at [p]Rome, and as far as [q]Sparta, that Jonathan was dead, [r]they were very sorry.

17 But as soon as they heard that his brother Simon was made high priest in his stead, and ruled the country, and the cities therein:

18 They wrote unto him [s]in tables of brass, to renew the friendship and league which they had made with [t]Judas and [u]Jonathan his brethren:

19 Which writings were read before the congregation at Jerusalem.

20 And this is the copy of the letters that the [q]Lacedemonians sent; The rulers of the [q]Lacedemonians, with the city, unto Simon [v]the high priest, and the elders, and priests, and residue of the people of the Jews, our brethren, [w]send greeting:

21 [x]The ambassadors that were sent unto our people certified us of your glory and honour: wherefore we were glad of their coming,

22 And did register the things that they spake in the [*]council of the people in this manner; [x]Numenius son of Antiochus, and Antipater son of Jason, the Jews’ ambassadors, came unto us to renew the friendship they had with us.

23 And it pleased the people to entertain the men honourably, and to put the copy of their [y]ambassage in publick records, to the end the people of the [q]Lacedemonians might have a memorial thereof: furthermore we have written a copy thereof unto Simon the high priest.

24 After this Simon sent [x]Numenius to [p]Rome with a great shield of gold of a thousand [z]pound weight to confirm the league with them.

25 Whereof when the people heard, they said, What thanks shall we give to Simon and [a]his sons?

26 For [aa]he and his brethren and the house of his father have established Israel, and chased away in fight their enemies from them, and confirmed their liberty.

27 So then they wrote it [b]in tables of brass, which they set upon pillars in mount Sion: and this is the copy of the writing; The eighteenth day of the month [bb]Elul, in [*]the hundred threescore and twelfth year, being [c]the third year of Simon the high priest,

28 At [*]Saramel in the great congregation of the priests, and people, and rulers of the nation, and elders of the country, were these things notified unto us.

29 Forasmuch as oftentimes there have been wars in the country, wherein for the maintenance of their sanctuary, and the law, [d]Simon the son of Mattathias, of the posterity of [e]Jarib, together with his brethren, [f]put themselves in jeopardy, and resisting the enemies of their nation did their nation great honour:

30 (For after that Jonathan, having gathered his nation together, and [g]been their high priest, [h]was added to his people,

31 [i]Their enemies prepared to invade their country, that they might destroy it, and lay hands on the sanctuary:

32 At which time Simon rose up, and fought for his nation, and spent much of his own substance, and armed [*]the valiant men of his nation and gave them w[j]ages,

33 And [k]fortified the cities of Judea, together with [l]Bethsura, that lieth upon the borders of Judea, where the [*][ll]armour of the enemies had been before; but he set a garrison of Jews there:

34 Moreover he fortified [m]Joppa, which lieth upon the sea, and [*][n]Gazera, that bordereth upon [n]Azotus, where the enemies had dwelt before: but he placed Jews there, and furnished them with all things convenient for the reparation thereof.)

35 The people therefore sang the acts of Simon, and unto what glory he thought to bring his nation, made him their governor and [o]chief priest, because he had done all these things, and for the justice and faith which he kept to his nation, and for that he sought by all means to exalt his people.

36 For in his time [oo]things prospered in his hands, so that [p]the heathen were taken out of their country, and [q]they also that were in the city of David in Jerusalem, who had made themselves [r]a tower, out of which they issued, and polluted all about the sanctuary, and did much hurt [*]in the holy place:

37 But he placed Jews therein. and [s]fortified it for the safety of the country and the city, and [t]raised up the walls of Jerusalem.

38 King Demetrius also [u]confirmed him in the high priesthood according to those things,

39 And made him one [w]of his friends, and honoured him with great honour.

40 For he had heard say, that [x]the Romans had called the Jews their friends and confederates and brethren; and that [y]they had entertained the ambassadors of Simon honourably;

41 Also that the Jews and priests were well pleased that Simon should be their governor and [o]high priest [z]for ever, [a]until there should arise [b]a faithful prophet;

42 Moreover that he should be their captain, and should take charge of the sanctuary, to set them over their works, and over the country, and over the armour, and over the fortresses, that, I say, he should take charge of the sanctuary;

43 Beside this, that he should be obeyed of every man, and that [c]all the writings in the country should be made in his name, and that [d]he should be clothed in purple, and wear gold:

44 Also that it should be lawful for none of the people or priests to [e]break any of these things, or to gainsay his words, or to gather an assembly in the country without him, or to be clothed in purple, or wear [f]a buckle of gold;

45 And whosoever should do otherwise, or [e]break any of these things, [g]he should be punished.

46 Thus it liked all the people to deal with Simon, and to do as hath been said.

47 Then Simon accepted hereof, and was well pleased [h]to be high priest, and captain and [i]governor of the Jews and priests, and to defend them all.

48 So they commanded that this writing should be put [k]in tables of brass, and that they should be set up within the compass of the sanctuary in a conspicuous place;

49 Also that the copies thereof should be laid up in [l]the treasury, to the end that Simon and [m]his sons might have them.

15

1 [*]Moreover Antiochus son of [a]Demetrius the king sent letters from [b]the isles of the sea unto Simon the priest and [c]prince of the Jews, and to all the people;

2 [d]The contents whereof were these: King Antiochus to Simon the high priest and [c]prince of his nation, and to the people of the Jews, greeting:

3 Forasmuch as [e]certain pestilent men [f]have usurped the kingdom of our fathers, and my purpose is to challenge it again, that I may restore it to the old estate, and to that end have gathered a multitude of foreign soldiers together, and prepared ships of war;

4 My meaning also being to go through the country, that I may be avenged of [g]them that have destroyed it, and made many cities in the kingdom desolate:

5 Now therefore [h]I confirm unto thee all the oblations which the kings before me granted thee, and whatsoever gifts besides they granted.

6 I give thee leave also to coin money for thy country with thine own stamp.

7 And as concerning Jerusalem and the sanctuary, let them [i]be free; and all the armour that thou hast made, and [k]fortresses that thou hast built, and keepest in thine hands, let them remain unto thee.

8 And if anything be, or shall be, owing to the king, [l]let it be forgiven thee from this time forth for evermore.

9 Furthermore, when we have obtained our kingdom, we will honour thee, and thy nation, and thy temple, with great honour, so that your honour shall be known throughout the world.

10 In [*]the hundred threescore and fourteenth year went Antiochus into the land of his fathers: at which time all the forces came together unto him, so that few were left with [g]Tryphon.

11 Wherefore being pursued by king Antiochus, he fled unto [m]Dora, which lieth by the sea side:

12 For he saw that troubles came upon him all at once, and that his forces had forsaken him.

13 Then camped Antiochus against [m]Dora, having with him an hundred and twenty thousand men of war, and eight thousand horsemen.

14 And when he had compassed the city round about, and joined ships close to the town on the sea side, he vexed the city by land and by sea, neither suffered he any [n]to go out or in.

15 In the mean season came [o]Numenius and his company from [p]Rome, having letters [q]to the kings and countries; wherein were written these things:

16 [r]Lucius, consul of the Romans unto king [rr]Ptolemee, greeting:

17 The Jews’ ambassadors, [s]our friends and confederates, came unto us to renew [t]the old friendship and league, [o]being sent from Simon the high priest, and from the people of the Jews:

18 And [o]they brought a shield of gold of a thousand pound.

19 We thought it good therefore to write [q]unto the kings and countries, that they should do them no harm, nor fight against them, their cities, or countries, nor yet aid their enemies against them.

20 It seemed also good to us to receive the shield of them.

21 If therefore there be [e]any pestilent fellows, that have fled from their country unto you, deliver them unto Simon the high priest, that he may punish them according to their own law.

22 The same things wrote he likewise unto [u]Demetrius the king, and Attalus, to [*]Ariarathes, and [w]Arsaces,

23 And to all the countries and to [*]Sampsames, and the [x]Lacedemonians, and to Delus, and Myndus, and Sicyon, and Caria, and [y]Samos, and [z]Pamphylia, and [a]Lycia, and Halicarnassus, and [b]Rhodus, and [*]Aradus, and [b]Cos, and Side, and Aradus, and Gortyna, and [c]Cnidus, and [d]Cyprus, and [e]Cyrene.

24 And the copy hereof they wrote to Simon the high priest.

25 [f]So Antiochus the king camped against Dora the second day, [*]assaulting it continually, and making engines, by which means he shut up Tryphon, that he could neither [f]go out nor in.

26 At that time Simon sent him two thousand chosen men to aid him; silver also, and gold, and much armour.

27 Nevertheless he would not receive them, but [g]brake [h]all the covenants which he had made with him afore, and became strange unto him.

28 Furthermore he sent unto him Athenobius, one of his friends, to commune with him, and say, Ye withhold [i]Joppa and [k]Gazera; with [l]the tower that is in Jerusalem, which are cities of my realm.

29 The borders thereof ye have wasted, and done great hurt in the land, and got the dominion of [m]many places within my kingdom.

30 Now therefore deliver the cities which ye have taken, and [m]the tributes of the places, whereof ye have gotten dominion [*]without the borders of Judea:

31 Or else give me for them five hundred talents of silver; and for the harm that ye have done, and the tributes of the cities, other five hundred talents: if not, we will come and [*]fight against you

32 So Athenobius [n]the king’s friend came to Jerusalem: and when he saw the glory of Simon, and the cupboard of gold and silver plate, and his great [o]attendance, he was astonished, and told him the king’s message.

33 Then answered Simon, and said unto him, We have neither taken other men’s land, nor holden that which appertaineth to others, but the inheritance of our fathers, which our enemies had wrongfully in possession a certain time.

34 Wherefore we, having opportunity, hold the inheritance of our fathers.

35 And whereas thou demandest [i]Joppa and [k]Gazera, albeit they did great harm unto the people in our country, yet will we give [p]thee an hundred talents for them. Hereunto Athenobius answered him not a word;

36 But returned in a rage to the king, and made report unto him of these speeches, and of the glory of Simon, and of all that he had seen: whereupon the king was exceeding wroth.

37 In the mean time fled [q]Tryphon by ship unto Orthosias.

38 Then the king made [r]Cendebeus captain of the sea coast, and gave him an host of footmen and horsemen,

39 And commanded him to remove his host toward Judea; also he commanded him to build up [*]Cedron, and to fortify the gates, and to war against the people; but as for the king himself, he pursued [q]Tryphon.

40 So [r]Cendebeus came to [s]Jamnia and began to provoke the people and to invade Judea, and to take the people prisoners, and slay them.

41 And when he had built up Cedrou, he set horsemen there, and an host of footmen, to the end that issuing out they might make outroads upon the ways of Judea, as the king had commanded him.

16

1 Then came up [a]John from [a][b]Gazera, and told Simon his father [c]what Cendebeus had done.

2 Wherefore Simon called his two eldest sons, Judas and [a]John, and said unto them, [d]I, and my brethren, and my father’s house, have ever from my youth unto this day fought against the enemies of Israel; and [e]things have prospered so well in our hands, that we have delivered Israel oftentimes.

3 But now I am old, and ye, by God’s mercy, are of a sufficient age: be ye instead of me and [f]my brother, and go and fight for our nation, and the help from heaven be with you.

4 So he chose out of the country twenty thousand men of war with horsemen, who went out against Cendebeus, and [g]rested that night at [h]Modin.

5 And when as they rose in the morning, and went into the plain, behold, a mighty great host both of footmen and horsemen came against them: howbeit there was a water brook betwixt them.

6 So he and his people pitched over against them: and when he saw that the people were afraid to go over the water brook, he went first over himself, and then the men seeing him passed through after him.

7 That done, he divided his men, and set the horsemen in the midst of the footmen: for the enemies’ horsemen were very many.

8 Then [i]sounded they with the holy trumpets: whereupon Cendebeus and his host were put to flight, so that [k]many of them were slain, and the remnant gat them to [l]the strong hold.

9 At that time was [m]Judas John’s brother wounded; but John still followed after them, until he came to [l]Cedron, which Cendebeus had built.

10 [*]So they fled even unto the towers in the fields of [*][n]Azotus; wherefore he burned it with fire: so that there were slain of them about two thousand men. Afterward he returned into the land of Judea in peace.

11 Moreover in [o]the plain of Jericho was Ptolemeus the son of Abubus made captain, and he had abundance of silver and gold:

12 For he was the high priest’s son in law.

13 Wherefore his heart being lifted up, he thought to get the country to himself, and thereupon consulted deceitfully against Simon and his sons to destroy them.

14 Now Simon was visiting the cities that were in the country, and taking care for the good ordering of them; at which time he came down himself to [p]Jericho with his sons, Mattathias and Judas, in [*]the hundred threescore and seventeenth year, in the eleventh month, called [q]Sabat:

15 Where the son of Abubus receiving them deceitfully into a little hold, called Docus, which he had built, made them a great banquet: howbeit he had hid men there.

16 So when Simon and his sons [r]had drunk largely, Ptolemee and his men rose up, and took their weapons, and came upon Simon into the banqueting place, and slew him, and his two sons, and certain of his servants.

17 In which doing he committed a great treachery, and recompensed evil for good.

18 Then Ptolemee wrote these things, and sent to [s]the king, that he should send him an host to aid him, and he would deliver him the country and cities.

19 He sent others also to [b]Gazera to kill John: and unto the [*]tribunes he sent letters to come unto him, that he might give them [t]silver, and gold, and rewards.

20 And others he sent to take Jerusalem, and the mountain of the temple.

21 Now one had run afore to [b]Gazera and told John that his father and brethren were slain, and, [u]quoth he, Ptolemee hath sent to slay thee also.

22 Hereof when he heard, he was sore astonished: so he laid hands on them that were come to destroy him, and slew them; for he knew that they sought to make him away.

23 [x]As concerning the rest of the acts of John, and his wars, and worthy deeds which he did, and the building of the walls which he made, and his doings,

24 Behold, these are written in the chronicles of his priesthood, from the time he was made high priest after his father.

a 1.1 Comp. Josh. 1. 1. Baruch 1. 1. 2 Macc 2. 19.

* 1.1 Or, Chethiim. So ch. 8. 5.

b 1.1 Gen. 10. 4 (Heb.). Num. 24. 24. 1 Chr. 1. 7 (Heb.). Isai. 23. 1, 12. Jer. 2. 10. Ezek. 27. 6. Dan. 11. 30.

c 1.1 See Acts 2. 9.

d 1.2 2 Cor. 10. 4.

* 1.3 Or, his heart was exalted and lifted up.

* 1.4 Or, kingdoms which became, &c.

e 1.5 So Rev. 2. 22 (Gk.).

* 1.5 Gr. that he dieth.

f 1.6 So 2 Macc. 9. 29. Acts 13. 1.

* 1.7 B.C. 323.

ff 1.9 ch. 6. 15.

g 1.10 Comp. Deut 29. 18. with Isai. 11. 10. 2 Esdr. 3. 22. & 8. 53.

h 1.10 2 Macc. 4. 7. & 10. 9, 13. So ch. 3. 27, &c. 2 Macc. 1. 14.

* 1.10 About B.C. 176.

i 1.10 ch. 8. 7. & 9. 53. & 10. 6, 9. & 11. 62. & 13. 16. See ch. 8. 1.

* 1.10 B.C. 175.

* 1.10 [Began B.C. 312].

* 1.11 B.C. 174.

ii 1.11 So ver. 34. ch. 10. 61. & 11. 21. Comp. ch. 7. 5. & 10. 14.

* 1.11 Gr. many evils have found us. ch. 6. 13. See Gen. 44. 34 marg.

ii 1.13 So ver. 34. ch. 10. 61. & 11. 21. Comp. ch. 7. 5. & 10. 14.

j 1.14 2 Macc. 4. 9, 12.

* 1.14 Or, set up an open school at Jerusalem.

k 1.15 1 Cor. 7. 18.

l 1.15 So 2 Cor. 6. 14. See Deut. 7. 3.

m 1.15 See 1 Kin. 21. 20.

* 1.16 B.C. 170.

n 1.17 Dan. 11. 25. 2 Macc. 5. 1?

o 1.17 ver. 20, 29.

p 1.17 ch. 3. 34. & 6. 30, 34, 35, 46. & 8. 6. 2 Macc. 11. 4. & 13. 2, 15. & 14. 12. Comp. ch. 11. 56. 20, 21. 2 Macc. 15. 20, 21.

pp 1.17 2 Macc. 12. 9. & 14. 1.

q 1.18 2 Macc. 4. 21. & 9. 29. & 10. 13. See Esth. 12. 1.

r 1.18 ch. 3. 11. & 8. 10. & 9. 17, 40. & 16. 8 in the Gk.

* 1.20 B. C. 170 [–169].

s 1.20 2 Macc. 5. 11–16.

o 1.20 ver. 20, 29.

t 1.21 Dan. 8. 12. & 11. 31. 2 Macc. 5. 15, 16, 21. So ch. 6. 12.

u 1.21 Ex. 30. 1–3.

w 1.21 Ex. 25. 31–39. Comp. 2 Esdr. 10. 22.

w 1.21 Ex. 25. 31–39. Comp. 2 Esdr. 10. 22.

x 1.22 Ex. 25. 23–30.

y 1.22 1 Esdr. 2. 13 (Gk.). So Ezra 1. 9–11. & 8. 27.

y 1.22 1 Esdr. 2. 13 (Gk.). So Ezra 1. 9–11. & 8. 27.

y 1.22 1 Esdr. 2. 13 (Gk.). So Ezra 1. 9–11. & 8. 27.

z 1.22 Ex. 26. 31–33.

a 1.22 Zech. 6. 11, 14.

* 1.22 Or, he b pilled all things.

* 1.23 Gr. desirable. Dan. 11. 8. Hos. 13. 15. Nah. 2. 9. See Ezra 8. 27.

c 1.24 Comp. 2 Macc. 5. 12–14.

d 1.24 So 2 Macc. 5. 17, 21. Comp. Dan. 11. 36.

e 1.27 Comp. Joel 2. 16.

* 1.29 B.C. 168.

f 1.29 Jer 28. 3 & marg.

ff 1.29 2 Macc. 5. 24–26.

g 1.29 ver. 17, 20.

gg 1.33 ch. 3. 45. & 4. 2, 41. & 6. 18, 24, 26, 32. & 9. 52, 53. & 10. 6, 7, 9, 32. & 11. 20, 21, 22, 41. & 12. 36. & 13. 21, 49, 50, 52. & 14. 7, 36. & 15. 28. 2 Macc. 15. 31, 35 in the Gk. So 2 Macc. 4. 12, 27. & 5. 5.

h 1.34 Comp. Gal. 2. 15.

i 1.34 So ver. 11. ch. 2. 44, 48. & 3. 5, 6, 8, 15.

j 1.36 ch. 9. 40. Comp. ch. 13. 51.

k 1.37 Comp. Ps 79. 1–3.

l 1.38 ch. 3. 45. & 4. 38.

ll 1.38 So 2 Macc. 11. 2.

l 1.39 ch. 3. 45. & 4. 38.

m 1.39 See Tobit 2. 6.

n 1.39 ver. 45. ch. 2. 34. 2 Macc. 6. 6.

n 1.39 ver. 45. ch. 2. 34. 2 Macc. 6. 6.

o 1.42 So ch. 2. 18. 2 Macc. 4. 10. & 6. 1.

p 1.43 So ch. 2. 19, 22.

* 1.44 Or, the laws and rites of the strangers of the land.

q 1.45 Dan. 11. 31. 2 Macc. 6. 2.

n 1.45 ver. 45. ch. 2. 34. 2 Macc. 6. 6.

q 1.46 Dan. 11. 31. 2 Macc. 6. 2.

r 1.47 ver. 54 (Gk.). So 2 Macc. 6. 5.

s 1.47 2 Macc. 10. 2. & 11. 3 in the Gk. See Ex. 34. 13.

t 1.47 ch. 10. 83 (Gk.). See 1 Esdr. 2. 10. & Amos 7. 13 (Engl.).

u 1.47 So Isai. 66. 3. See 2 Macc. 6. 18.

x 1.47 ver. 62. See Acts 10. 14.

y 1.50 2 Macc. 6. 9. So ch. 6. 12.

z 1.50 ch. 16. 21. 2 Macc. 6. 24. & 11. 14. See Ex. 18. 4.

a 1.51 2 Macc. 6. 8.

b 1.51 So 2 Macc. 5. 22.

* 1.53 Or, and they made Israel hide themselves in holes, in every place of succour.

c 1.53 ch. 2. 31, 36 (Gk.), 41. See 2 Macc. 6. 11.

d 1.54 ch. 4. 52, 59. 2 Macc. 1. 9, 18. & 10. 5. See Neh. 1. 1.

* 1.54 B.C. 168 [–167].

d 1.54 ch. 4. 52, 59. 2 Macc. 1. 9, 18. & 10. 5. See Neh. 1. 1.

e 1.54 ver. 47 (Gk.).

f 1.57 See Rom. 1. 32 marg.

* 1.57 Gr. the king’s commandment put him to death.

g 1.59 Comp. ver. 54. ch. 4. 38, 44, 45, 52.

g 1.59 Comp. ver. 54. ch. 4. 38, 44, 45, 52.

h 1.60 2 Macc. 6. 10.

* 1.60 Gr. that had circumcised their children. Gk. as 2 Macc. 6. 10. But comp. ver. 61 (Gk.).

h 1.61 2 Macc. 6. 10.

* 1.62 About B.C. 167.

i 1.62 ver. 47.

k 1.63 2 Macc. 6. 19. & 7. 1.

k 1.63 2 Macc. 6. 19. & 7. 1.

* 2.1 Or, Mattathias the son of John, &c. arose from Jerusalem, or, out of Jerusalem.

a 2.1 ver. 65(Gk.). See 2 Pet. 1. 1 marg.

b 2.1 1 Chr. 24. 7. So ch. 14. 29.

c 2.1 ver. 15, 23, 70. ch. 9. 19. & 13. 25, 30. & 16. 4. 2 Macc. 13. 14.

d 2.2 ch. 9. 35, 36, 38. Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 22. & 10. 19?

* 2.2 Or, who was called: and so afterward in the rest.

* 2.2 [Or,] Gaddis.

e 2.4 ver. 66. ch. 8. 20. 2 Macc. 5. 27.

ee 2.5 2 Macc. 8. 23.

* 2.5 Or, Avaron, or, Abaron: Comp. ch. 6. 43.

f 2.5 Gk. as ver. 2 marg.

g 2.7 See Wisd. 3. 3.

h 2.7 Song 5. ch. 10. 31. See Neh. 11. 1. & 2 Macc. 1. 12.

i 2.8 So ch. 1. 40.

k 2.9 ch. 1. 23.

l 2.9 2 Macc. 5. 13. So ch. 1. 24.

m 2.10 Tobit 14. 13 marg.

n 2.11 So Ezek. 16. 39.

* 2.12 Or, holy thing. ch. 10. 39 (Gk.).

o 2.12 ch. 3. 51, 58, 59. Heb. 9. 2.

p 2.12 Ps. 50. 2.

q 2.12 ch. 1. 21, 54.

r 2.14 ch. 3. 47. & 11. 71. See Gen. 44. 13.

r 2.14 ch. 3. 47. & 11. 71. See Gen. 44. 13.

s 2.14 See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

t 2.15 ver. 17. Gk. as Susanna 33. Mark 3. 21.

u 2.15 Acts 21. 21. 2 Thess. 2. 3 in the Gk. So ver. 19.

c 2.15 ver. 15, 23, 70. ch. 9. 19. & 13. 25, 30. & 16. 4. 2 Macc. 13. 14.

t 2.17 ver. 17. Gk. as Susanna 33. Mark 3. 21.

v 2.17 So ver. 43 (Gk.). Comp. Ps. 127. 5.

w 2.18 ch. 1. 41, 42.

x 2.18 1 Esdr. 9. 51, 54. 2 Macc. 3. 2 in the Gk.

y 2.19 ch. 7. 2 marg.

u 2.19 Acts 21. 21. 2 Thess. 2. 3 in the Gk. So ver. 19.

z 2.19 ver. 22. So ch. 1. 45. See Rom. 9. 4.

a 2.20 Josh. 24. 15.

b 2.21 Matt. 16. 22 (Gk.).

c 2.22 See Acts 5. 29.

d 2.22 ver. 19.

e 2.22 See Deut. 5. 32.

f 2.23 See ver. 1.

g 2.24 So Ps. 73. 21.

h 2.24 Deut. 13. 6–9. Or as ver. 29.

i 2.26 Num. 25. 7. 8, 14. So ver. 54.

j 2.28 So 2 Macc. 5. 27.

k 2.29 So Isai. 16. 5.

h 2.29 Deut. 13. 6–9. Or as ver. 29.

j 2.29 So 2 Macc. 5. 27.

* 2.29 Gr. sit, [or,] abide. See Acts 18. 11.

l 2.30 ver. 38.

* 2.30 Gr. evils were multiplied upon them.

m 2.31 ch. 1. 33, 34.

n 2.31 ch. 6. 59 (Gk.).

o 2.31 ver. 36 (Gk.), 41. ch. 1. 53.

p 2.34 ch. 1. 39.

* 2.35 That is, the Jews. So ver. 38.

o 2.36 ver. 36 (Gk.), 41. ch. 1. 53.

* 2.37 Gr. simplicity. ver. 60. Wisd. 1. 1. Eph. 6. 5 (Gk.). Col. 3. 22 (Gk.).

q 2.38 2 Macc. 6. 11.

r 2.38 ver. 30.

* 2.38 Gr. souls of men. ch. 9. 2. See 1 Chr. 5. 21 marg.

s 2.41 Comp. ch. 9. 43, 44. 2 Macc. 15. 1–4.

t 2.41 ver. 38.

o 2.41 ver. 36 (Gk.), 41. ch. 1. 53.

u 2.42 ch. 7. 13. 2 Macc. 14. 6. See Ps. 50. 5 (Heb.).

v 2.43 So ver. 17 (Gk.).

w 2.44 So ch. 1. 34. ver. 48.

x 2.44 ch. 3. 5, 6.

* 2.46 Or, by force.

y 2.46 Rev. 18. 2 (Gk.).

* 2.48 Gr. gave they the horn to the sinner. Comp. 1 Sam. 2. 1. Ecclus. 47. 5, 11.

w 2.48 So ch. 1. 34. ver. 48.

* 2.51 Gr. generations.

z 2.52 Gen. 22. 9–12.

a 2.52 See Gen. 15. 6.

b 2.53 Gen. 39. 8, 9.

c 2.53 See Rom. 2. 9.

d 2.53 Gen. 41. 40.

e 2.54 Comp. ver. 1 with 1 Chr. 24. 4, 7.

f 2.54 Numb. 25. 13. Ecclus. 45. 23, 24. So ver. 26.

n 2.54 ver. 54.

g 2.55 Josh. 1. 2. Ecclus. 46. 7.

h 2.56 Numb. 14. 6, 7, 24. Josh. 14. 6–13. Ecclus. 46. 7.

i 2.56 Acts 7. 38 (Gk.).

k 2.57 See Hos. 6. 4 marg., or comp. 2 Sam. 2. 4–6.

l 2.57 2 Sam. 7. 16.

m 2.58 See 2 Kin. 2. 11.

n 2.58 ver. 54.

o 2.59 Dan. 1. 6, 7. & 3. 16–18, 26. Song 66.

p 2.60 Dan. 6. 22.

q 2.60 ver. 37.

r 2.62 Comp. Isai. 51. 12.

s 2.62 See Ecclus. 10. 10.

t 2.62 So 2 Esdr. 16. 23. See 2 Kin. 9. 37.

s 2.63 See Ecclus. 10. 10.

u 2.63 Gen. 3. 19.

x 2.63 Ps. 146. 4.

x 2.63 Ps. 146. 4.

y 2.64 2 Sam. 10. 12. 1 Cor. 16. 13 in the Gk.

z 2.65 ver. 3 (Gk. as ver. 1). ch. 5. 17, &c. Comp. ch. 13. 1.

a 2.66 ver. 4. 2 Macc. 5. 27.

b 2.66 See Ecclus. 6. 18.

* 2.66 Or, fight ye the battle of the people.

c 2.67 Rom. 2. 13. James 4. 11 in the Gk.

d 2.69 Gen. 49. 28.

e 2.69 Bel and Drag. 1. So ch. 14. 30. See Judith 16. 22.

* 2.70 B.C. 166.

f 2.70 See ver. 1.

g 2.70 ch. 4. 39.

a 3.1 To ver. 9, comp. 2 Macc. 8. 1–7.

aa 3.1 ch. 13. 14.

b 3.3 1 Sam. 17. 5 (Gk.).

c 3.3 ch. 6. 41, 43. So ch. 4. 7. & 6. 38 (Engl.). See 1 Kin. 20. 11.

d 3.3 See ch. 5. 45.

e 3.5 ver. 6. ch. 2. 44. So ver. 8, 15. See ch. 1. 34.

ee 3.5 ch. 5. 5. 2 Macc. 10. 36.

e 3.6 ver. 6. ch. 2. 44. So ver. 8, 15. See ch. 1. 34.

f 3.6 2 Macc. 6. 12 (Gk.).

ff 3.6 So ch. 9. 23. See Ps. 94. 4.

g 3.6 So ch. 14. 36. & 16. 2.

gg 3.7 See Ecclus. 45. 1.

e 3.8 ver. 6. ch. 2. 44. So ver. 8, 15. See ch. 1. 34.

h 3.8 So Num. 25. 11.

* 3.9 Gr. gathered together. ver. 10, 27.

i 3.9 See Job 29. 13 & Gk.

k 3.10 2 Macc. 4. 21. & 5. 24?

l 3.10 ch. 5. 66. & 10. 30, 38. 2 Macc. 15. 1. See 1 Kin. 16. 24.

m 3.11 See ch. 1. 18.

k 3.12 2 Macc. 4. 21. & 5. 24?

n 3.15 Gk. as Tobit 14. 2 marg. So ch. 9. 1, 72 marg. & 10. 88. See Luke 19. 11.

d 3.15 See ch. 5. 45.

e 3.15 ver. 6. ch. 2. 44. So ver. 8, 15. See ch. 1. 34.

o 3.16 ver. 24. Judith 4. 4. ch. 7. 39. & 9. 50. See Josh. 10. 10.

p 3.16 Gk. as ver. 16.

d 3.17 See ch. 5. 45.

p 3.17 Gk. as ver. 16.

q 3.17 Matt. 15. 32.

r 3.18 See 1 Sam. 14. 6.

s 3.18 ch. 4. 31. See 1 Sam. 17. 46 marg.

t 3.18 ch. 4. 55. See ver. 60. Comp. Judith 5. 8.

r 3.18 See 1 Sam. 14. 6.

* 3.20 Or, unto us.

* 3.20 Gr. in multitude of pride, or, envy and iniquity.

d 3.23 See ch. 5. 45.

* 3.24 Gr. in the going down.

u 3.24 Josh. 10. 11.

w 3.25 So 1 Pet. 3. 6. See Deut. 2. 25.

x 3.26 ch. 12. 41. 2 Macc. 8. 20. See Judith 5. 23.

y 3.27 ch. 1. 10.

d 3.27 See ch. 5. 45.

z 3.28 1 Esdr. 4. 56. ch. 14. 32 in the Gk. See Luke 3. 14.

* 3.28 Gr. at every need. See ch. 13. 37.

* 3.29 Gr. that the collectors of tribute in the country were few.

* 3.29 Or, for the taking away of the laws.

* 3.30 Gr. that he should not have.

a 3.30 Gk. as Ps. 62. 11.

b 3.30 Comp. Dan. 11. 24.

c 3.31 Ecclus. 18. 7 (Gk.).

d 3.31 ch. 6. 1, 5, 56. & 14. 2. 2 Macc. 1. 13, 19, 33.

e 3.32 See ch. 6. 17. Comp. 2 Macc. 10. 11.

ee 3.32 So 2 Macc. 11. 1, 35.

f 3.33 2 Macc. 10. 10. Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 25.

g 3.34 See ch. 1. 17.

h 3.35 Comp. ver. 45.

i 3.35 ch. 12. 53.

j 3.37 ch. 4. 35 (Gk.). & 6. 63 (Gk.). & 10. 68. & 11. 13, 44, 56. 2 Macc. 4. (9, 19), 33. & 5. 21 (Gk.). & 8. 35. & 11. 36. & 13. 23, 26. See Acts 11. 26.

* 3.37 Gr. a city of his kingdom. Josh. 10. 2 marg. 1 Sam. 27. 5 (Heb.).

* 3.37 [B.C. 166–5].

d 3.37 ch. 6. 1, 5, 56. & 14. 2. 2 Macc. 1. 13, 19, 33.

k 3.37 ch. 6. 1. 2 Macc. 9. 25. So 2 Macc. 9. 23. Acts 19. 1.

l 3.38 See 2 Macc. 4. 45.

m 3.38 ch. 7. 26, 27, 31, 32, 33, 44, 47. 2 Macc. 8. 9, 34. & 9. 3. & 12. 2. & 14. 12, &c.

n 3.38 ch. 4. 1, 5, 18. & 5. 59. 2 Macc. 8. 9. & 10. 14. & 12. 32, 35, 36, 37.

nn 3.38 See ch. 10. 20.

o 3.40 ver. 57. ch. 4. 3. & 9. 50. Luke 24. 13.

oo 3.41 2 Macc. 8. 10, 11, 25, 34.

* 3.41 Or, fetters.

p 3.41 See ch. 5. 45.

* 3.41 Or, of strangers. ch. 4. 22. & 5. 66, 68. 1 Sam. 14. 1. & 17. 1, &c. (Gk.). So ch. 4. 30.

q 3.42 Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 12, &c.

r 3.43 2 Cor. 10. 4, 8. & 13. 10 in the Gk.

h 3.45 Comp. ver. 45.

s 3.45 ch. 1. 38, 39. & 4. 38. 2 Macc. 8. 2, 3.

t 3.45 ch. 15. 25. So ch. 13. 49. & 15. 14. See Num. 27. 17.

s 3.45 ch. 1. 38, 39. & 4. 38. 2 Macc. 8. 2, 3.

u 3.45 See ch. 1. 33.

w 3.45 See Ecclus. 39. 15.

* 3.46 Or, Mitzpa.

x 3.46 Judg. 20. 1. 1 Sam. 7. 5. See Josh. 18. 26.

y 3.47 See Esther 4. 1, 3.

z 3.47 See ch. 2. 14.

y 3.47 See Esther 4. 1, 3.

a 3.47 ch. 4. 39. So ch. 11. 71. 2 Macc. 10. 25. & 14. 15.

z 3.47 See ch. 2. 14.

a 3.47 ch. 4. 39. So ch. 11. 71. 2 Macc. 10. 25. & 14. 15.

* 3.48 Or, for the which the heathen had made diligent search, that they might paint therein the likeness of their idols.

b 3.48 Comp. Lev. 26. 1. Num. 33. 52.

c 3.49 See Ecclus. 45. 10.

d 3.49 Ecclus. 35. 8.

e 3.49 Ecclus. 35. 9.

f 3.49 Numb. 6. 2, 13. Comp. Amos 2. 11.

g 3.49 Acts 21. 26, 27.

h 3.51 See ch. 2. 12.

i 3.54 Num. 10. 8, 9. ch. 4. 13, 40. & 7. 45. & 16. 8. So Ecclus. 50. 16.

k 3.55 Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 22.

l 3.55 1 Sam. 17. 18.

m 3.56 Deut. 20. 5–8.

n 3.56 Judg. 7. 3. Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 13.

o 3.56 See Wisd. 9. 14.

m 3.56 Deut. 20. 5–8.

p 3.57 See ch. 5. 45.

q 3.57 See ver. 40.

r 3.58 2 Sam. 10. 12. Comp. Eph. 6. 14 (Gk.).

h 3.58 See ch. 2. 12.

h 3.59 See ch. 2. 12.

r 3.60 2 Sam. 10. 12. Comp. Eph. 6. 14 (Gk.).

s 3.60 Comp. ver. 18. ch. 4. 10, 40, 55. & 9. 46. 2 Macc. 7. 11, 34. & 9. 4 (Gk.). & 15. 34.

a 4.1 ver. 5, 18. See ch. 3. 38.

b 4.1 Comp. ch. 3. 39.

c 4.1 See ch. 5. 45.

c 4.2 See ch. 5. 45.

d 4.2 See ch. 1. 33.

e 4.3 See ch. 3. 40.

c 4.4 See ch. 5. 45.

a 4.5 ver. 5, 18. See ch. 3. 38.

c 4.5 See ch. 5. 45.

* 4.6 Or, targets. ch. 6. 2 (Gk.).

c 4.7 See ch. 5. 45.

f 4.7 ch. 6. 38 (Engl.). See ch. 3. 3.

ff 4.8 So 2 Macc. 8. 16.

b 4.8 Comp. ch. 3. 39.

g 4.9 Ex. 14. 30.

h 4.10 So ver. 40. See ch. 3. 60.

c 4.10 See ch. 5. 45.

i 4.11 So 1 Sam. 17. 46.

j 4.13 Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 23–26?

c 4.13 See ch. 5. 45.

k 4.13 See ch. 3. 54.

* 4.15 [Gr. Assaremoth].

l 4.15 ch. 7. 45. & 9. 52. & 13. 53. & 14. 7, 34. & 15. 28, 35. & 16. 1, 19, 21. See Josh. 10. 33.

m 4.15 ver. 29, 61. See Mark 3. 8.

n 4.15 Judith 2. 28. ch. 5. 68. & 9. 15? & 10. 77, 78, 83, 84. & 11. 4. & 14. 34. & 16. 10. See 1 Sam. 5. 1.

o 4.15 Josh. 15. 11? 2 Chr. 26. 6. Judith 2. 28? ch. 5. 58. & 10. 69. & 15. 40. So 2 Macc. 12. 8, 9, 40.

a 4.18 ver. 5, 18. See ch. 3. 38.

p 4.18 ver. 5.

c 4.20 See ch. 5. 45.

c 4.21 See ch. 5. 45.

q 4.22 See ch. 3. 41.

r 4.23 Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 27.

c 4.23 See ch. 5. 45.

s 4.23 Ecclus. 45. 10.

r 4.24 Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 27.

t 4.24 Ps. 136. 1. So Song 67.

* 4.24 [Or, he]. See Ps. 106. 1.

u 4.26 ch. 3. 38.

v 4.27 See Acts 2. 6.

w 4.27 So ch. 6. 8.

* 4.28 About B.C. 165.

b 4.28 Comp. ch. 3. 39.

m 4.29 ver. 29, 61. See Mark 3. 8.

x 4.29 ver. 61. ch. 6. 7, 26, 31. & 9. 52. & 10. 14. & 11. 65. & 14. 7, 33. 2 Macc. 11. 5. & 13. 19, 22. See 2 Chr. 11. 7.

y 4.29 Comp. ver. 6.

c 4.30 See ch. 5. 45.

z 4.30 1 Sam. 17. 50, 51.

* 4.30 Or, Philistines. So ver. 22. See ch. 3. 41.

a 4.30 1 Sam. 14. 13, 14.

b 4.31 See ch. 3. 18.

* 4.32 Gr. melt. Wisd. 16. 29.

c 4.35 See ch. 3. 37.

* 4.36 Or, repair. Gk. as ver. 54, 57. ch. 5. 1. & 10. 44. So ch. 10. 10.

d 4.37 Comp. 2 Macc. 10. 1–3.

d 4.38 Comp. 2 Macc. 10. 1–3.

e 4.38 ch. 1. 39. & 3. 45.

f 4.38 ch. 1. 59.

g 4.38 ver. 48. 2 Chr. 4. 9.

g 4.38 ver. 48. 2 Chr. 4. 9.

h 4.38 ver. 57. Jer. 35. 4 in the Gk. So 1 Kin. 6. 5, 6.

i 4.39 See ch. 3. 47.

k 4.39 ch. 2. 70.

i 4.39 See ch. 3. 47.

l 4.40 ch. 7. 45 (Gk.). See ch. 3. 54.

m 4.40 See ver. 10.

n 4.41 See ch. 1. 33, 34.

f 4.44 ch. 1. 59.

f 4.45 ch. 1. 59.

o 4.46 ch. 9. 27. & 14. 41. See Ps. 74. 9. Comp. Ezra 2. 63.

p 4.47 Deut. 27. 5, 6. Josh. 8. 31 in the Gk. So Ex. 20. 25.

q 4.47 2 Macc. 10. 3.

g 4.48 ver. 48. 2 Chr. 4. 9.

r 4.49 Ex. 25. 31.

s 4.49 But comp. ver. 47.

t 4.49 Ex. 30. 1–3.

u 4.49 Ex. 25. 23.

w 4.50 Ex. 30. 7, 8. 2 Macc. 1. 8.

x 4.50 Comp. 2 Macc. 10. 3.

w 4.50 Ex. 30. 7, 8. 2 Macc. 1. 8.

y 4.51 Ex. 25. 30. 2 Macc. 1. 8.

* 4.51 Or, spread abroad the hangings, or, hanged up the vails.

z 4.51 See Ex. 26. 31.

a 4.52 ch. 1. 59. 2 Macc. 10. 3, 5.

b 4.52 See ch. 1. 54.

* 4.52 [B.C. 165–4].

c 4.53 Ex. 29. 38, 39. 2 Macc. 1. 8.

d 4.53 ver. 47.

a 4.54 ch. 1. 59. 2 Macc. 10. 3, 5.

e 4.54 See Ecclus. 39. 15.

f 4.54 ch. 13. 51. See Judith 16. 2.

g 4.55 Comp. Judith 5. 8. See ch. 3. 18.

h 4.56 2 Macc. 10. 6.

* 4.56 Or, peace offerings. See Ecclus. 35. 1.

i 4.56 Ecclus. 35. 2. See 2 Chr. 29. 31.

j 4.57 See ver. 38.

j 4.57 See ver. 38.

* 4.57 Or, dedicated. ver. 36, 54. ch. 5. 1.

* 4.57 Or, made doors for them.

k 4.59 So 2 Macc. 1. 18. & 2. 16. & 10. 8. John 10. 22.

l 4.59 ver. 52.

b 4.59 See ch. 1. 54.

m 4.60 ch. 6. 7?, 62.

n 4.60 ch. 1. 31.

o 4.61 See ver. 29.

p 4.61 See ver. 15.

* 5.1 About B.C. 164.

a 5.1 ch. 4. 47.

b 5.1 ch. 4. 36, 54.

c 5.3 ver. 65. Judith 7. 8, 18.

d 5.3 Comp. 2 Macc. 10. 15–17. See Mark 3. 8.

* 5.3 Or, Arabathane, or, Arabattan, or, Akrabattine. See Josh. 15. 3 marg.

* 5.4 Or, malice. 1 Cor. 5. 8.

* 5.4 Or, Akan. Gen. 36. 27. See Numb. 33. 31, 32.

e 5.4 Ps. 69. 22 (Gk.).

e 5.4 Ps. 69. 22 (Gk.).

f 5.5 Num. 21. 2 (Gk.). &c. Comp. ch 3. 5. 2 Macc. 10. 36.

g 5.6 2 Macc. 4. 26. & 5. 7. See Judith 1. 12.

gg 5.6 See 2 Macc. 12. 2.

h 5.8 See Num. 21. 32. Comp. 2 Macc. 10. 32?

i 5.8 See ver. 65 marg.

j 5.9 Gen. 31. 47, 48. Num. 32. 1. Judith 1. 8. & 15. 5. ver. 25, 27. ch. 13. 22. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 2.

gg 5.11 See 2 Macc. 12. 2.

k 5.11 ver. 45.

kk 5.13 Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 17.

* 5.13 [Or, Tubin].

l 5.13 See Judg. 11. 3.

m 5.13 ver. 45. See Judith 15. 11 (Engl.).

n 5.14 2 Kin. 18. 37. So ch. 13. 45.

o 5.15 ver. 22, 55. ch. 10. 1, 39, 56, 57, 58, 60. & 11. 22, 24. & 12. 45, 48. & 13. 12. 2 Macc. 13. 24. 25. Acts 21. 7. So Judg. 1. 31.

p 5.15 1 Esdr. 5. 55. 2 Esdr. 1. 11.

q 5.15 So Isai. 9. 1. Matt. 4. 16. Comp. Judith 1. 8.

r 5.17 ch. 2. 3, 65, &c.

q 5.17 So Isai. 9. 1. Matt. 4. 16. Comp. Judith 1. 8.

s 5.17 ch. 2. 5.

j 5.17 Gen. 31. 47, 48. Num. 32. 1. Judith 1. 8. & 15. 5. ver. 25, 27. ch. 13. 22. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 2.

t 5.18 ver. 56, 60.

u 5.19 Comp. ver. 57, 61.

y 5.20 Gk. as ver. 36. Isai. 34. 6. & 63. 1. Jer. 48. 24.

j 5.20 Gen. 31. 47, 48. Num. 32. 1. Judith 1. 8. & 15. 5. ver. 25, 27. ch. 13. 22. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 2.

o 5.22 ver. 22, 55. ch. 10. 1, 39, 56, 57, 58, 60. & 11. 22, 24. & 12. 45, 48. & 13. 12. 2 Macc. 13. 24. 25. Acts 21. 7. So Judg. 1. 31.

* 5.23 That is, captive Jews.

v 5.23 Comp. ch. 9. 2?

w 5.24 ver. 17.

x 5.25 ch. 9. 35. Comp. ch. 12. 31 marg. See Isai. 60. 7.

j 5.25 Gen. 31. 47, 48. Num. 32. 1. Judith 1. 8. & 15. 5. ver. 25, 27. ch. 13. 22. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 2.

* 5.26 Or, Bosorra. 1 Chr. 1. 44 (Gk.).

y 5.26 Gk. as ver. 36. Isai. 34. 6. & 63. 1. Jer. 48. 24.

* 5.26 Or, Chascor, [or, Casphon, as ver. 36]. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 13?

z 5.26 So Deut. 3. 14. Josh. 12. 5. & 13. 11, 13. 2 Sam. 10. 6?

a 5.26 See Gen. 14. 5.

j 5.27 Gen. 31. 47, 48. Num. 32. 1. Judith 1. 8. & 15. 5. ver. 25, 27. ch. 13. 22. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 2.

* 5.27 That is, the heathen.

b 5.28 ver. 45.

* 5.28 Or, Bosor. ver. 26.

h 5.28 ver. 28, 51.

c 5.28 ver. 51. See Judith 2. 27.

d 5.29 ver. 9.

* 5.30 Gr. lift up their eyes. So Gen. 13. 10, &c.

* 5.30 [That is,] the heathen assaulted the Jews.

e 5.31 See Ex. 2. 23.

f 5.33 Judg. 7. 16 (Gk.). See Job 1. 17.

b 5.34 ver. 45.

g 5.35 Gen. 31. 49. Judg. 11. 29, 34 (Gk.).

h 5.35 ver. 28, 51.

i 5.36 See ver. 26.

j 5.36 Matt. 15. 39?

k 5.37 ver. 6, 11. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 20, 21.

b 5.37 ver. 45.

b 5.38 ver. 45.

l 5.39 ch. 11. 16, 17, 39. & 12. 31. 2 Macc. 5. 8. & 12. 10.

b 5.40 ver. 45.

m 5.42 See ch. 7. 12.

n 5.43 Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 22, 26.

a 5.43 See Gen. 14. 5.

* 5.44 [That is,] Judas and his company.

o 5.44 2 Macc. 12. 21, 26.

a 5.44 See Gen. 14. 5.

p 5.45 See Jer. 6. 13.

q 5.45 See ver. 13.

r 5.45 Ecclus. 43. 8 (Gk.). ver. 11, 28, 34, 37, 38, 49. ch. 3. 3, 15, 17, 23, 27, 41, 57. ch. 4. 1, &c. in the Gk. See Judith 7. 7.

s 5.46 2 Macc. 12. 27.

t 5.46 1 Esdr. 8. 61 (Gk.).

u 5.46 So Deut. 2. 27, 28.

u 5.48 So Deut. 2. 27, 28.

r 5.49 Ecclus. 43. 8 (Gk.). ver. 11, 28, 34, 37, 38, 49. ch. 3. 3, 15, 17, 23, 27, 41, 57. ch. 4. 1, &c. in the Gk. See Judith 7. 7.

x 5.50 2 Macc. 12. 28.

h 5.51 ver. 28, 51.

c 5.51 ver. 51. See Judith 2. 27.

y 5.52 ver. 24.

z 5.52 Judith 1. 8. ch. 12. 49.

a 5.52 ch. 12. 40, 41. So 2 Macc. 12. 29. See Josh. 17. 11.

* 5.53 Or, went hindmost. So Num. 10. 25.

* 5.53 Or, comforted, or, encouraged. Ecclus. 30. 23. ch. 12. 50. 2 Cor. 1. 4. So ch. 10. 24.

* 5.54 Or, peace offerings. Joseph. Antiq. [lib.] 12. [cap.] 12.

b 5.54 ch. 7. 35. See 1 Kin. 22. 27. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 31.

c 5.55 ver. 24–54.

d 5.55 ver. 21–23.

e 5.55 See ver. 15.

f 5.56 ver. 18.

g 5.57 Comp. ver. 19.

h 5.58 See ch. 4. 15. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 32.

i 5.59 See ch. 3. 38.

h 5.59 See ch. 4. 15. Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 32.

* 5.59 Gr. to meet them in battle. So ver. 39. ch. 6. 48. & 7. 31. & 9. 11. & 10. 2 in the Gk.

f 5.60 ver. 18.

g 5.61 Comp. ver. 19.

k 5.65 Comp. 2 Macc. 12. 33.

l 5.65 See ver. 3.

m 5.65 Josh. 21. 11.

* 5.65 Gr. daughters. ver. 8. See Num. 21. 25.

* 5.66 Gr. strangers. ver. 68. See ch. 3. 41.

n 5.66 See ch. 3. 10.

o 5.68 See ch. 4. 15.

a 6.1 See ch. 3. 31, 37. To ver. 4, comp. 2 Macc. 1. 13–16.

a 6.1 See ch. 3. 31, 37. To ver. 4, comp. 2 Macc. 1. 13–16.

b 6.1 See Tobit 2. 10. Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 1.

bb 6.1 See ch. 3. 31.

* 6.2 Or, shields. ch. 4. 6 (Gk.).

* 6.2 Or, armour. ver. 6. Rom. 13. 12.

c 6.2 ch. 1. 1.

c 6.2 ch. 1. 1.

d 6.3 2 Macc. 9. 2, 3.

w 6.4 ver. 4. Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 28.

dd 6.5 Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 3.

e 6.6 ch. 3. 38–4. 35.

f 6.6 Gen. 26. 14. Tobit 7. 8 (Engl.).

g 6.7 ch. 4. 36–59.

h 6.7 ch. 1. 54.

i 6.7 ch. 4. 60?

k 6.7 ch. 4. 61. See ch. 4. 29.

l 6.8 Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 5.

m 6.8 So ch. 4. 27.

n 6.9 Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 11–17.

o 6.11 See Luke 6. 35.

p 6.12 ch. 1. 21–23.

q 6.12 ch. 1. 50, 57.

r 6.13 ch. 1. 11 marg. Comp. 2 Macc. 7. 37.

s 6.14 ver. 55, 63. 2 Macc. 9. 29.

t 6.15 ch. 1. 9. Comp. ch. 8. 14.

u 6.15 See Gen. 41. 42.

* 6.15 Or, he should take his son Antiochus to him.

v 6.16 2 Macc. 10. 9.

w 6.16 ver. 4. Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 28.

* 6.16 B.C. 164. [Nisan]. Comp. 2 Macc. 11. 21, 33.

x 6.17 ch. 3. 32, 33. ver. 55. & 7. 2. 2 Macc. 10. 11. & 11. 1. & 12. 1, 27. & 13. 2, 4, 26, & 14. 2.

x 6.17 ch. 3. 32, 33. ver. 55. & 7. 2. 2 Macc. 10. 11. & 11. 1. & 12. 1, 27. & 13. 2, 4, 26, & 14. 2.

y 6.17 See 2 Macc. 10. 10.

z 6.18 ver. 24. See ch. 1. 33.

* 6.20 B.C. 163. Comp. 2 Macc. 13. 1.

a 6.20 See ver. 51.

b 6.21 See ch. 7. 5. So ver. 24. Comp. ch. 1. 11.

c 6.22 ver. 17.

b 6.24 See ch. 7. 5. So ver. 24. Comp. ch. 1. 11.

d 6.24 ver. 18.

e 6.24 ch. 5. 22, 44, 51? & 7. 6.

d 6.26 ver. 18.

f 6.26 ch. 4. 61.

g 6.28 2 Macc. 13. 1.

h 6.29 ch. 11. 38. & 14. 5. & 15. 1.

i 6.30 Comp. 2 Macc. 13. 2.

k 6.30 ver. 34, 35, 46. See ch. 1. 17.

l 6.31 See Mark 3. 8.

m 6.31 2 Macc. 13. 19–21.

d 6.32 ver. 18.

t 6.33 Gk. as ver. 33.

k 6.34 ver. 34, 35, 46. See ch. 1. 17.

n 6.34 See Ecclus. 39. 26.

k 6.35 ver. 34, 35, 46. See ch. 1. 17.

* 6.38 Or, stirring them up, and being compassed with the ranks, or, defended with the valleys. Comp. ch. 10. 82 (Gk.).

o 6.38 ch. 4. 7 (Engl.).

p 6.41 See ch. 3. 3.

q 6.43 Comp. ch. 2. 5.

p 6.43 See ch. 3. 3.

r 6.44 So ch. 11. 23 (Gk.). & 14. 29 (Gk. & Engl.). See Luke 8. 23 (Engl.).

r 6.44 So ch. 11. 23 (Gk.). & 14. 29 (Gk. & Engl.). See Luke 8. 23 (Engl.).

s 6.44 So Judith 11. 9.

* 6.45 Or, so that he cut them in pieces.

k 6.46 ver. 34, 35, 46. See ch. 1. 17.

t 6.47 Gk. as ver. 33.

* 6.48 Or, in Judea. Gk. as ver. 53.

u 6.49 2 Macc. 13. 22.

* 6.49 Add out of Josephus, and yielded themselves.

w 6.49 ver. 53. See Lev. 25. 4, 5. & 2 Chr. 36. 21.

* 6.51 Or, made there mounts for shot. ver. 20. So Jer. 32. 24. & 33. 4.

* 6.52 That is, the Jews.

w 6.53 ver. 53. See Lev. 25. 4, 5. & 2 Chr. 36. 21.

x 6.53 ch. 9. 52 (Gk.).

y 6.55 2 Macc. 13. 23. See ver. 17. Comp. 2 Macc. 11. 13–15.

z 6.55 See ver. 14, 15.

a 6.56 ver. 1, 4.

* 6.58 Gr. give hands. ch. 11. 50, 62 (Gk.). & 13. 45 (Gk.). 2 Macc. 11. 26. & 12. 11. & 13. 22. & 14. 19. See 2 Kin. 10. 15.

b 6.59 ch. 2. 31 (Gk.).

c 6.60 Comp. 2 Macc. 13. 23. 24.

d 6.60 ch. 8. 21. Acts 6. 5 in the Gk.

e 6.62 ch. 11. 36 (Gk.). & 14. 44, 45. & 15. 27. 2 Macc. 13. 25 (Gk.). & 14. 28 (Gk.). See Mark 7. 9 marg.

f 6.62 ch. 4. 60. Comp. ch. 10. 11.

g 6.63 Comp. 2 Macc. 13. 26.

h 6.63 See ch. 3. 37.

z 6.63 See ver. 14, 15.

i 6.63 Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 29.

* 7.1 B.C. 162. 2 Macc. 14. 4.

a 7.1 2 Macc. 14. 1, 26. See 2 Macc. 3. 3.

a 7.1 2 Macc. 14. 1, 26. See 2 Macc. 3. 3.

aa 7.1 See ch. 8. 1.

* 7.1 a Tripolis, Joseph. Ant. lib. 12. cap. 16.

* 7.2 Gr. house of the kingdom of his father. ch. 2. 19.

b 7.2 2 Macc. 14. 2.

c 7.5 ch. 6. 21. & 9. 23, 25, 58, 69, 73.

c 7.5 ch. 6. 21. & 9. 23, 25, 58, 69, 73.

d 7.5 2 Macc. 14. 3, 13, 26. So ch. 9. 1, 54–56.

e 7.6 See ch. 6. 24.

f 7.8 ver. 12, 19, 20. ch. 9. 1, 25, 26, 43, 57, 58, 68. 2 Macc. 8. 30.

g 7.8 See ch. 10. 20.

h 7.8 Deut. 1. 7.

f 7.12 ver. 12, 19, 20. ch. 9. 1, 25, 26, 43, 57, 58, 68. 2 Macc. 8. 30.

* 7.12 Or, officers, governors, chief men, or, men in authority. ch. 5. 42.

i 7.13 See ch. 2. 42.

ii 7.14 So 2 Macc. 14. 7.

j 7.16 Comp. Heb. 2. 6. & 4. 3, 4.

k 7.17 Cited from Ps. 79. 2, 3.

* 7.18 Gr. judgment. ch. 6. 22.

f 7.19 ver. 12, 19, 20. ch. 9. 1, 25, 26, 43, 57, 58, 68. 2 Macc. 8. 30.

l 7.19 ver. 24. (Gk.).

m 7.19 So Jer. 41. 7, 9.

f 7.20 ver. 12, 19, 20. ch. 9. 1, 25, 26, 43, 57, 58, 68. 2 Macc. 8. 30.

* 7.21 Or, laboured to defend his high priesthood. Comp. ver. 9.

* 7.24 Or, fled from him to the enemy. ver. 19. ch. 9. 24 in the Gk.

* 7.24 Or, invade the country.

* 7.25 Or, were grown very strong.

* 7.25 Gr. to abide them.

n 7.25 So 2 Macc. 14. 3–10.

o 7.26 2 Macc. 14. 12, 13.

p 7.26 See ch. 3. 38.

q 7.27 To ver. 38, comp. 2 Macc. 14. 21–36.

* 7.27 About B.C. 161.

* 7.27 Gr. peaceable. ver. 10, 15.

* 7.28 Gr. see your faces. ver. 30. Comp. ver. 3.

p 7.31 See ch. 3. 38.

* 7.31 Gr. meet Judas in battle. See ch. 5. 59.

* 7.31 Or, Carphasalama.

p 7.32 See ch. 3. 38.

p 7.33 See ch. 3. 38.

r 7.33 ch. 4. 60. & 6. 48, 62. Comp. ch. 6. 51.

s 7.33 Comp. 2 Macc. 14. 31.

t 7.33 So Baruch 1. 11. See Ezra 6. 10.

* 7.34 Gr. defiled them.

* 7.35 Gr. in peace. See ch. 5. 54.

s 7.36 Comp. 2 Macc. 14. 31.

u 7.36 So Joel 2. 17.

x 7.37 See Deut. 12. 5.

y 7.37 Isai. 56. 7.

z 7.39 Comp. 2 Macc. 15. 1.

a 7.39 See ch. 3. 16.

g 7.40 ver. 40. 1 Chr. 7. 28 marg. Comp. ch. 9. 5.

b 7.40 To ver. 50, 2 Macc. 15. 22–37.

c 7.41 See Tobit 1. 18.

d 7.42 ver. 34.

e 7.43 See Ezra 6. 15.

f 7.43 Comp. 2 Macc. 15. 28 (Gk.).

* 7.45 That is, the Jews.

g 7.45 ver. 40. 1 Chr. 7. 28 marg. Comp. ch. 9. 5.

h 7.45 See ch. 4. 15.

i 7.45 ch. 4. 40 (Gk.). See ch. 3. 54.

k 7.47 2 Macc. 14. 32. Comp. 2 Kin. 19. 21, 22.

d 7.47 ver. 34.

l 7.47 Comp. 2 Macc. 15. 30.

m 7.49 Comp. 2 Macc. 15. 36.

e 7.49 See Ezra 6. 15.

n 7.50 So ch. 9. 57. & 14. 4.

a 8.1 Comp. ch. 1. 10. & 7. 1. & 12. 1, 3, 16. & 14. 16, 24, 40. & 15. 15, 16. 2 Macc. 4. 11. & 8. 10, 36. & 11. 34.

* 8.2 Or, French men.

b 8.2 See Acts 16. 6. Comp. 2 Macc. 8. 20.

* 8.4 Or, every place.

* 8.5 Or, Macedonians. So ch. 1. 1.

c 8.6 2 Esdr. 15. 46. & 16. 1. ch. 11. 13. & 12. 39. & 13. 32. 2 Macc. 3. 3. & 10. 24. Comp. Acts 2. 9.

d 8.6 See ch. 1. 17.

e 8.7 See ch. 1. 10.

ee 8.10 See ch. 1. 18.

f 8.14 Comp. ch. 1. 9. & 6. 15.

i 8.15 Gk. as ver. 15. ch. 12. 3.

ff 8.16 Comp. ch. 15. 16.

g 8.17 2 Macc. 4. 11.

a 8.17 Comp. ch. 1. 10. & 7. 1. & 12. 1, 3, 16. & 14. 16, 24, 40. & 15. 15, 16. 2 Macc. 4. 11. & 8. 10, 36. & 11. 34.

p 8.18 ver. 18.

h 8.18 ch. 1. 1, 10.

i 8.19 Gk. as ver. 15. ch. 12. 3.

j 8.19 1 Sam. 9. 17 (Gk.). See Judg. 18. 14.

k 8.20 ch. 2. 4.

l 8.21 See ch. 6. 60.

ll 8.22 See ch. 14. 18.

m 8.23 Comp. ch. 12. 1.

n 8.23 ver. 32.

o 8.31 ch. 7. 1, 26.

p 8.31 ver. 18.

q 8.31 ch. 14. 40. & 15. 17.

r 8.32 See Rom. 11. 2.

n 8.32 ver. 32.

a 9.1 ch. 7. 43, 44.

* 9.1 Gr. he added, or, proceeded to send. ver. 72. ch. 10. 88. See ch. 3. 15.

aa 9.1 ch. 7. 5, 8.

b 9.1 ch. 7. 20, 25. ver. 25, 26. See ch. 7. 8.

* 9.1 Or, the right wing. Comp. ver. 12, 15.

* 9.2 Or, Galilea.

c 9.2 Comp. ch. 5. 23?

d 9.2 Comp. ch. 2. 38 (Gk.).

* 9.3 [B.C. 161–160].

* 9.4 Or, Berretho, Jos[eph].

e 9.5 As ch. 7. 40, 45?

* 9.9 We follow here the Roman copy.

f 9.10 See Luke 20. 16.

* 9.10 Gr. let us not leave any just cause behind us, why our glory should be spoken against.

* 9.11 That is, the Jews.

g 9.11 Gk. as ver. 12.

h 9.12 ver. 1 (Gk.), 15. So ver. 14.

g 9.12 Gk. as ver. 12.

h 9.14 ver. 1 (Gk.), 15. So ver. 14.

h 9.15 ver. 1 (Gk.), 15. So ver. 14.

i 9.15 Josh. 19. 34? See ch. 4. 15?

j 9.17 See ch. 1. 18.

k 9.19 ver. 33, 37, 62. ch. 2. 3, 5. & 10. 74. & 11. 59. & 12. 33, 38. & 13. 1.

l 9.19 See ch. 2. 1.

m 9.20 ch. 13. 26.

mm 9.22 So ch. 16. 23, 24.

n 9.22 Comp. John 21. 25.

o 9.23 See ch. 7. 5.

p 9.23 So Matt. 7. 23. See ch. 3. 6.

* 9.24 That is, Bacchides and his company.

o 9.25 See ch. 7. 5.

* 9.26 Gr. mocked them. Matt. 2. 16, &c.

q 9.27 See ch. 4. 46.

r 9.28 ch. 3. 2.

k 9.28 ver. 33, 37, 62. ch. 2. 3, 5. & 10. 74. & 11. 59. & 12. 33, 38. & 13. 1.

s 9.29 Comp. ch. 1. 11.

k 9.33 ver. 33, 37, 62. ch. 2. 3, 5. & 10. 74. & 11. 59. & 12. 33, 38. & 13. 1.

t 9.33 2 Chr. 20. 20.

u 9.33 See 2 Sam. 14. 2. Comp. ver. 50.

* 9.34 Or, Which when Bacchides understood on the sabbath day, he came near.

w 9.34 Gk. as Matt. 4. 25, &c. Comp. ver. 43.

* 9.35 Jos[eph]. Antiq. lib. 13. cap. 1.

x 9.35 ch. 2. 2.

y 9.35 ch. 5. 25. Comp. ch. 12. 31 marg.

* 9.35 Gr. that he might leave with them their z carriage, or, a stuff.

z 9.35 ver. 39. See Judith 2. 17.

* 9.36 [Gr. Ambri].

b 9.36 See 1 Chr. 19. 7.

c 9.36 Comp. ver. 42.

* 9.37 Or, Medaba.

d 9.37 Comp. Judith. 5. 2, 3.

e 9.39 ver. 35.

* 9.39 Or, timbrels. 1 Esdr. 5. 2 (Gk.). Judith 3. 7. & 16. 2. See Ex. 15. 20.

* 9.39 Or, musicians.

f 9.39 1 Esdr. 4. 63. & 5. 2, 59. ver. 41 (Gk.).

g 9.40 See Song 26.

h 9.40 ch. 11. 68, 69. So ch. 1. 36.

i 9.40 See ch. 1. 18.

f 9.41 1 Esdr. 4. 63. & 5. 2, 59. ver. 41 (Gk.).

k 9.42 ver. 45. See Josh. 3. 15.

l 9.43 ver. 34.

ll 9.44 Comp. ch. 2. 41.

m 9.44 Susanna 15 marg.

k 9.45 ver. 45. See Josh. 3. 15.

n 9.46 See ch. 3. 60.

* 9.49 two thousand men. Joseph. Ant[iq.] lib. 13. cap. 1.

* 9.50 Or, built. ver. 62. ch. 10. 12. Judges 21. 23 in the Gk.

o 9.50 Ecclus. 24. 14. ch. 16. 14. 2 Macc. 12. 15. See Ezra 2. 34.

p 9.50 See ch. 3. 40.

q 9.50 See ch. 3. 16.

r 9.50 Josh. 16. 2.

s 9.50 See 2 Chr. 28. 18.

t 9.50 See 2 Sam. 23. 30.

* 9.50 Joseph. Tecoa. [Comp. ver. 33].

u 9.50 See Josh. 15. 34?

v 9.50 ch. 13. 33. So ch. 12. 38. Neh. 3. 3.

* 9.52 Gr. the city in Bethsura.

w 9.52 See ch. 4. 29.

x 9.52 See ch. 4. 15.

y 9.52 See ch. 1. 33.

z 9.52 ch. 6. 53 (Gk.).

a 9.53 ch. 10. 6. See ch. 1. 10.

y 9.53 See ch. 1. 33.

* 9.54 About B.C. 160.

b 9.54 See ch. 7. 5.

c 9.54 Ezek. 42. 20.

d 9.54 Comp. Ezek. 44. 17, 19.

e 9.55 So 2 Sam. 17. 23. 2 Kin. 20. 1 in the Gk. Comp. 2 Esdr. 14. 13.

f 9.57 Comp. ver. 1.

g 9.57 See ch. 7. 50.

* 9.58 About B.C. 158.

h 9.58 See ch. 7. 5.

i 9.62 See ver. 19.

l 9.62 ver. 62.

k 9.62 ver. 50.

* 9.63 That is, to such of the country as were his friends to take his part. Comp. ver. 58.

l 9.65 ver. 62.

* 9.66 Or, Odomarra.

l 9.67 ver. 62.

m 9.67 ver. 64.

h 9.69 See ch. 7. 5.

n 9.69 ver. 58.

o 9.70 Comp. ch. 10. 4.

p 9.72 So ch. 10. 33.

* 9.72 Gr. added he to come any more. See ver. 1.

q 9.73 See 1 Sam. 13. 2.

* 9.73 Gr. judge. 2 Kin. 23. 22, &c.

h 9.73 See ch. 7. 5.

* 10.1 B.C. 153.

* 10.1 Jos[eph.] the son of Antiochus Epiphanes.

a 10.1 ver. 39, 56, 57, 58, 60. See ch. 5. 15.

b 10.2 ch. 7. 1. & 9. 1, &c.

c 10.3 ch. 9. 73.

u 10.4 ver. 4 (Gk.).

d 10.4 Comp. ch. 9. 70.

e 10.5 ver. 46. ch. 7. & ch. 9.

f 10.6 ch. 9. 53.

g 10.6 See ch. 1. 10.

h 10.6 ver. 32. See ch. 1. 33.

c 10.7 ch. 9. 73.

h 10.7 ver. 32. See ch. 1. 33.

i 10.8 Mark 4. 41. Luke 2. 9 in the Gk.

h 10.9 ver. 32. See ch. 1. 33.

g 10.9 See ch. 1. 10.

k 10.11 ver. 45. Comp. ch. 6. 62. & 12. 36. & 13. 10. & 14. 37.

l 10.12 ch. 9. 50, 51. Comp. ch. 11. 41.

m 10.14 ch. 9. 52. Comp. ch. 11. 65.

n 10.14 See ch. 1. 11.

o 10.15 ver. 3, 6.

oo 10.18 ch. 11. 30. 2 Macc. 11. 22.

p 10.20 ver. 65. ch. 3. 38. & 7. 8. & 11. 27, 57. & 13. 36. & 14. 39. & 15. 32.

pp 10.20 See ver. 62.

q 10.20 So ch. 11. 58. & 14. 43. Comp. ch. 13. 37. 2 Macc. 14. 4.

r 10.20 See Matt. 16. 23.

s 10.21 Lev. 23. 34.

* 10.21 B.C. 153.

s 10.21 Lev. 23. 34.

t 10.21 Ex. 28. 2. So Ecclus. 50. 11.

u 10.23 ver. 4 (Gk.).

x 10.23 See Wisd. 4. 7 (Engl.).

y 10.28 ch. 13. 37. So ver. 34. ch. 13. 34.

z 10.29 So ch. 11. 35. Comp. ch. 11. 28.

z 10.29 So ch. 11. 35. Comp. ch. 11. 28.

z 10.29 So ch. 11. 35. Comp. ch. 11. 28.

a 10.29 ch. 13. 39.

b 10.30 Luke 15. 12 (Gk.).

c 10.30 ver. 38. ch. 11. 34. So ch. 11. 28.

d 10.30 See ch. 3. 10.

e 10.31 See ch. 2. 7. Comp. ch. 15. 7.

q 10.31 So ch. 11. 58. & 14. 43. Comp. ch. 13. 37. 2 Macc. 14. 4.

f 10.31 ch. 11. 35 (Gk.).

f 10.31 ch. 11. 35 (Gk.).

g 10.31 Matt. 17. 25.

h 10.32 ver. 6, 7, 9. See ch. 1. 33.

i 10.32 Comp. ver. 20, 21.

j 10.33 Comp. ch. 1. 32. So ch. 9. 72.

k 10.34 Judith 8. 6. See Isai. 1. 13.

k 10.34 Judith 8. 6. See Isai. 1. 13.

l 10.34 See ver. 28.

m 10.35 See ver. 63.

mm 10.36 So ch. 13. 40.

n 10.37 ver. 42. ch. 11. 63. & 12. 45. & 13. 15. Acts 6. 3 in the Gk. See ch. 13. 37. Comp. ver. 41 (Gk.).

* 10.37 Gr. walk. Ps. 78. 10, &c.

c 10.38 ver. 38. ch. 11. 34. So ch. 11. 28.

d 10.38 See ch. 3. 10.

i 10.38 Comp. ver. 20, 21.

o 10.39 Comp. ver. 1. Also ch. 11. 57. & 12. 45.

* 10.39 Or, of the holy things. ch. 2. 12 (Gk.). Comp. 2 Macc. 9. 16.

p 10.41 So Judith 12. 10. Comp. ver. 37. 42 (Gk.).

pp 10.42 Comp. ch. 11. 34.

n 10.42 ver. 42. ch. 11. 63. & 12. 45. & 13. 15. Acts 6. 3 in the Gk. See ch. 13. 37. Comp. ver. 41 (Gk.).

q 10.43 Gk. as ver. 31.

r 10.44 ch. 4. 36.

s 10.45 ver. 11.

t 10.46 See ver. 5.

* 10.48 About B.C. 150.

u 10.51 ch. 1. 18. See Esther 11. 1.

x 10.56 See ver. 1.

x 10.57 See ver. 1.

* 10.57 [B.C. 151–150.]

x 10.58 See ver. 1.

x 10.60 See ver. 1.

y 10.60 ch. 11. 24. See Baruch 1. 12.

z 10.61 ch. 15. 3, 21. Acts 24. 5.

a 10.61 ch. 11. 21 (Gk.). See ch. 1. 11.

b 10.61 ver. 63 2 Macc. 4. 36 in the Gk. See Rom. 11. 2. So ver. 64.

c 10.62 Dan. 5. 29 (Gk.). ver. 20. See Esther 8. 15.

d 10.63 Comp. Gen. 41. 43. Esther 6. 9.

b 10.63 ver. 63 2 Macc. 4. 36 in the Gk. See Rom. 11. 2. So ver. 64.

e 10.63 Song 27. ver. 35 (Gk.). ch. 12. 14 (Gk.). Acts 15. 19.

b 10.64 ver. 63 2 Macc. 4. 36 in the Gk. See Rom. 11. 2. So ver. 64.

f 10.65 See ver. 20.

g 10.65 Gen. 36. 40–43. 1 Chr. 1. 51–54 (Engl.).

* 10.65 Or, governor of a province. Comp. 1 Esdr. 1. 4 (Gk.), and places in marg.

* 10.67 About B.C. 148.

g 10.67 ver. 50.

h 10.67 See Acts 2. 11. Comp. ch. 11. 38. & 15. 1.

i 10.68 See ch. 3. 37.

j 10.69 2 Macc. 3. 5. & 4. 4?

k 10.69 See 1 Esdr. 2. 17.

l 10.69 See ch. 4. 15.

m 10.70 Comp. Deut. 11. 11. 1 Kin. 20. 23.

m 10.71 Comp. Deut. 11. 11. 1 Kin. 20. 23.

n 10.72 ch. 5. 60. & 9. 17, 18.

nn 10.73 Comp. 2 Macc. 1. 16.

j 10.74 2 Macc. 3. 5. & 4. 4?

o 10.74 See ch. 9. 19.

p 10.75 See ch. 11. 6.

q 10.77 See ch. 4. 15.

* 10.77 Or, as though he would pass through it.

* 10.77 Or, led his company.

t 10.77 Gk. as ver. 77.

q 10.78 See ch. 4. 15.

r 10.80 Acts 23. 16 (Gk.). 2 Chr. 13. 13. & 20. 22 (Engl.).

* 10.81 Jos[eph.] Antiq. lib. 13. cap. 8.

s 10.81 ver. 79, 82.

t 10.83 Gk. as ver. 77.

q 10.83 See ch. 4. 15.

u 10.83 So ver. 84. ch. 11. 4. See Judg. 16. 23.

v 10.83 See ch. 1. 47.

u 10.84 So ver. 84. ch. 11. 4. See Judg. 16. 23.

w 10.86 See Judith 2. 28.

x 10.88 ver. 65. Gk. as ch. 9. 1.

y 10.89 ch. 11. 58. & 14. 44.

z 10.89 Josh. 15. 45, 46 (Gk.). See Josh. 15. 11. Comp. Zech. 9. 7.

* 11.1 About B.C. 146.

a 11.1 ch. 10. 51–58. See Esther 11. 1.

b 11.1 See Song 13.

c 11.2 ch. 1. 30. & 7. 15 in the Gk.

a 11.3 ch. 10. 51–58. See Esther 11. 1.

d 11.4 See ch. 4. 15.

e 11.4 ch. 10. 84. So ver. 61.

e 11.4 ch. 10. 84. So ver. 61.

f 11.4 Matt. 9. 36 (Gk.).

g 11.6 ch. 12. 33. & 13. 11. & 14. 5. See Josh. 19. 46.

* 11.6 Gr. slept. ch. 16. 4.

h 11.7 ch. 12. 30.

a 11.8 ch. 10. 51–58. See Esther 11. 1.

i 11.8 Acts 13. 4.

k 11.8 See Luke 3. 15 marg.

l 11.9 ch. 10. 67.

m 11.12 So Dan. 3. 19 (Gk.). Comp. Gen. 31. 2, 5.

n 11.13 ver. 44, 56. See ch. 3. 37.

nn 11.13 See ch. 8. 6.

o 11.14 See Judith 2. 21.

p 11.16 ver. 39. See ch. 5. 39.

p 11.17 ver. 39. See ch. 5. 39.

* 11.18 Gr. and those that were in the holds were slain of those that were in the holds.

pp 11.19 2 Macc. 1. 7.

* 11.19 About B.C. 145.

q 11.20 ver. 7.

r 11.20 ver. 41. See ch. 1. 33.

s 11.21 ch. 10. 61 (Gk.). See ch. 1. 11.

t 11.21 ver. 19.

r 11.21 ver. 41. See ch. 1. 33.

u 11.22 See ch. 5. 15.

r 11.22 ver. 41. See ch. 1. 33.

w 11.23 See ch. 6. 44.

u 11.24 See ch. 5. 15.

x 11.24 ch. 10. 60.

y 11.25 So ch. 10. 61.

y 11.25 So ch. 10. 61.

z 11.25 See Rom. 11. 2.

a 11.26 ch. 10. 62–65. ver. 6.

b 11.27 ch. 10. 20. & 14. 38. ver. 57.

c 11.27 See ch. 10. 20.

d 11.28 Comp. ch. 10. 29.

e 11.28 See ch. 10. 30.

f 11.30 See ch. 10. 18.

* 11.34 Joseph. Antiq. lib. 13. cap. 8.

e 11.34 See ch. 10. 30.

g 11.34 See Acts 9. 32.

h 11.34 1 Sam. 1. 19?

i 11.34 Comp. ch. 10. 42.

k 11.34 So ch. 10. 30.

k 11.34 So ch. 10. 30.

l 11.35 ch. 10. 31 (Gk.).

l 11.35 ch. 10. 31 (Gk.).

m 11.35 ch. 10. 29.

m 11.35 ch. 10. 29.

n 11.36 See ch. 6. 62.

o 11.38 Comp. ch. 10. 67.

p 11.38 See ch. 6. 29.

q 11.39 See ver. 16.

r 11.40 Comp. ver. 54, 56. ch. 12. 39, &c.

s 11.41 ver. 20–22.

t 11.41 ch. 9. 50–52. Comp. ch. 10. 12–14.

u 11.43 Comp. ver. 38.

w 11.44 See ver. 13.

* 11.50 Or, Be friends with us. ver. 62 (Gk.). See ch. 6. 58.

x 11.52 ver. 38.

* 11.54 About B.C. 144.

y 11.54 Comp. ver. 40.

z 11.54 ver. 39.

* 11.56 Gr. beasts. 2 Macc. 15. 20, 21. See ch. 1. 17.

w 11.56 See ver. 13.

a 11.57 See ver. 27.

b 11.57 Comp. ch. 10. 39 and ver. 28, 34.

c 11.57 See ch. 10. 20.

* 11.58 Gr. and service.

cc 11.58 ch. 10. 20. & 14. 43.

d 11.58 ch. 10. 89. & 14. 44.

e 11.59 See ch. 9. 19.

ee 11.59 See 2 Macc. 4. 18.

* 11.60 Or, went beyond the river, and passed through the cities, or, went and passed beyond the river and through the cities, Gr.

f 11.60 See Judith 2. 28.

g 11.61 ch. 13. 43. See Josh. 15. 47.

* 11.61 Or, the places there-about. Gk. as ver. 4.

* 11.62 Gr. he gave them the right hand. ver. 50 (Gk.). 2 Macc. 11. 26. See ch. 6. 58. Comp. ver. 66 (Gk.).

h 11.62 See ch. 1. 10.

i 11.62 See Isai. 7. 8.

j 11.63 Comp. ch. 12. 24.

k 11.63 ver. 73. Tobit 1. 2 marg. See Josh. 19. 37.

* 11.63 Or, to remove him from the l affairs of the kingdom.

m 11.65 Comp. ch. 10. 14. & 14. 7. See ch. 4. 29.

mm 11.66 ch. 13. 50.

m 11.66 Comp. ch. 10. 14. & 14. 7. See ch. 4. 29.

n 11.67 See Luke 5. 1.

o 11.67 Josh. 19. 36 (Gk.). See Josh. 11. 1.

p 11.68 ch. 9. 40.

p 11.69 ch. 9. 40.

q 11.70 ch. 13. 11. So 2 Macc. 11. 17.

r 11.71 See ch. 2. 14

s 11.71 See ch. 3. 47.

k 11.73 ver. 73. Tobit 1. 2 marg. See Josh. 19. 37.

k 11.73 ver. 73. Tobit 1. 2 marg. See Josh. 19. 37.

a 12.1 ver. 16. So ver. 3. See ch. 8. 1.

a 12.1 ver. 16. So ver. 3. See ch. 8. 1.

b 12.1 ch. 8. 23–32.

bb 12.2 So 2 Macc. 5. 9. See ch. 14. 16.

a 12.3 ver. 16. So ver. 3. See ch. 8. 1.

c 12.3 ch. 8. 19.

d 12.5 ver. 2.

e 12.6 2 Macc. 1. 10 (Gk.). Comp. ch. 14. 20. See Judith 4. 8.

f 12.7 Ecclus. 50. 1? or see 2 Macc. 3. 1.

* 12.7 Areus : See Joseph. Ant[iq.] lib. 13. cap. 8. [Comp. ver. 20].

g 12.7 ver. 20–23.

h 12.8 Matt. 18. 31 (Gk.). See 2 Macc. 1. 18.

* 12.8 Or,kindred. Jos[eph.] Ant[iq.]

i 12.9 Rom. 15. 4.

j 12.11 See 1 Thess. 1. 3.

k 12.14 See ch. 10. 63.

kk 12.16 ch. 14. 22, 24. & 15. 15.

l 12.19 ver. 7.

* 12.19 Read out of Jos[eph.] which Areus sent toOnias. [Comp. ver. 7].

ll 12.21 2 Macc. 5. 9.

* 12.22 Gr. peace. Tobit 13. 14.

m 12.24 ch. 11. 63.

n 12.25 See 1 Kin. 8. 65.

* 12.25 Or, to set foot in his country: or, to invade his country. ch. 13 20. & 14. 31. &. 15. 40.

o 12.27 See John 10. 4.

* 12.28 Joseph. Ant[iq.] lib. 13. [cap.] 9. they went away.

p 12.30 ch. 11. 7.

q 12.31 See ch. 5. 39.

* 12.31 Jos[eph.] Gr. Nabatheans, or, Zabatheans. Comp. ch. 5. 25. & 9. 35.

r 12.32 See Isai. 7. 8.

s 12.33 See ch. 9. 19.

t 12.33 See Judith 2. 28.

u 12.33 ch. 11. 6. See ch. 13. 11.

v 12.34 ver. 24. Comp. ch. 13. 11.

vv 12.35 ch. 13. 33.

w 12.36 See ch. 10. 11. Comp. ch. 13. 10.

x 12.36 See ch. 1. 33.

y 12.36 ch. 13. 49. Comp. ch. 13. 21.

* 12.37 Or, according to the Roman reading, and he came near to the wall of the brook toward the east.

z 12.38 ch. 13. 13. So Ezra 2. 33. Neh. 7. 37. & 11. 34.

z 12.38 ch. 13. 13. So Ezra 2. 33. Neh. 7. 37. & 11. 34.

a 12.38 See ch. 9. 50.

b 12.39 ch. 11. 39, 54, 56. & 13. 1, &c.

c 12.39 See ch. 8. 6.

d 12.39 ch. 13. 31.

e 12.39 Supplied from ch. 11. 13.

f 12.40 ch. 5. 52. See Josh. 17. 11.

g 12.41 See ch. 3. 26.

f 12.41 ch. 5. 52. See Josh. 17. 11.

h 12.45 See ch. 5. 15.

i 12.45 ch. 10. 39.

j 12.45 See ch. 10. 37.

* 12.47 Gr. k left two thousand in Galilee.

m 12.47 ver. 47.

h 12.48 See ch. 5. 15.

l 12.49 Judith 1. 8. ch. 5. 52.

m 12.49 ver. 47.

n 12.50 Comp. ch. 13. 12, 23.

o 12.53 ch. 3. 35.

a 13.1 See ch. 9. 19. Comp. ch. 2. 65.

b 13.1 See ch. 11. 39.

c 13.2 So Heb. 12. 21 (Gk.).

d 13.4 ch. 6. 43–46. & 9. 18, 36. & 12. 50 (comp. ver. 12, &c.). ver. 23.

e 13.5 Comp. 1 Kin. 19. 4.

f 13.7 2 Tim. 1. 6 (Gk.).

g 13.8 ch. 3. 1.

h 13.8 ch. 9. 28–31.

i 13.10 ch. 12. 36, 37. & 14. 37.

k 13.11 See ch. 11. 70.

l 13.11 ch. 11. 6. & 12. 33. & 14. 5, 34. & 15. 28, 35. See Josh. 19. 46.

m 13.11 Comp. ch. 12. 34.

n 13.12 See ch. 5. 15.

o 13.12 Comp. ch. 12. 50. ver. 4.

p 13.13 ch. 12. 38.

p 13.13 ch. 12. 38.

q 13.14 ch. 3. 1.

* 13.15 Or, for the affairs, or, offices that he had, [or], for the necessary uses which he had. See ch. 10. 37. Comp. ver. 37 (Gk.).

r 13.16 See ch. 1. 10.

s 13.20 2 Chr. 11. 9?

t 13.21 See ch. 1. 33.

u 13.21 So ver. 49. Comp. ch. 12. 36.

w 13.22 See ch. 5. 9.

x 13.23 1 Sam. 11. 8 ?

* 13.25 About B.C. 143.

y 13.25 ver. 30. See ch. 2. 1.

z 13.26 ch. 9. 20.

a 13.29 Comp. Ezek. 32. 27.

b 13.29 Ecclus. 43. 24.

c 13.30 ver. 25.

d 13.30 So Matt. 27. 8. & 28. 15. Acts 2. 29.

e 13.31 ch. 12. 39.

f 13.32 See ch. 8.

g 13.33 ver. 38. ch. 12. 35. So ch. 14. 3 & 15. 7.

h 13.33 See ch. 9. 50.

* 13.33 Gr. in the strong holds.

i 13.34 ch. 11. 55.

* 13.34 Gr. all Tryphon’s doings were robberies.

j 13.36 ch. 14. 38.

k 13.36 See ch. 10. 20.

k 13.36 See ch. 10. 20.

l 13.37 2 Macc. 14. 4. Comp. ch. 10. 20.

m 13.37 Rather comp. ver. 51 (Gk.).

n 13.37 ch. 3. 28, marg. 2 Macc. 7. 24. & 12. 39. & 15. 5, 28 in the Gk. See ch. 10. 37.

o 13.37 See ch. 10. 28.

g 13.38 ver. 38. ch. 12. 35. So ch. 14. 3 & 15. 7.

p 13.39 ch. 10. 29. & 11. 35.

pp 13.39 So ch. 15. 8.

q 13.40 So ch. 10. 36.

* 13.41 [B.C. 143–2].

r 13.42 ch. 14. 27, 43.

s 13.43 ch. 11. 61, 62. See Josh. 15. 47. But comp. ch. 14. 34 marg. with ver. 48, 53. ch. 14. 7.

t 13.45 So ch. 5. 14.

* 13.45 Gr. to give them his right hand. See ch. 6. 58. Comp. ver. 50.

u 13.47 So ver. 51.

w 13.48 Comp. ver. 43, 53.

* 13.49 About B.C. 142.

x 13.49 See ch. 1. 33.

y 13.49 See ch. 3. 45.

z 13.49 ch. 12. 36.

a 13.49 ver. 21.

* 13.50 Or, to make peace with them. ch. 11. 66. Comp. ver. 45. See 2 Macc. 1. 5 (Engl.).

aa 13.50 ch. 14. 7.

x 13.50 See ch. 1. 33.

* 13.51 [B.C. 142–141.]

b 13.51 2 Macc. 10. 7, 38 in the Gk. So ver. 47.

c 13.51 John 12. 13. Comp. ver. 37 (Gk.).

d 13.51 See Ecclus. 39. 15.

f 13.51 1 Chr. 15. 16, 28 (Gk.).

e 13.51 See ch. 4. 54.

f 13.51 1 Chr. 15. 16, 28 (Gk.).

b 13.51 2 Macc. 10. 7, 38 in the Gk. So ver. 47.

g 13.51 ch. 1. 34–36.

h 13.52 Comp. ch. 14. 37.

x 13.52 See ch. 1. 33.

i 13.53 ch. 16. 1, 2, 9, 19, 21–24.

j 13.53 ch 16. 1. Comp. ver. 48.

k 13.53 See ch. 4. 15.

* 14.1 About B.C. 141.

a 14.1 See Tobit 1. 14.

b 14.1 ch. 13. 32.

c 14.2 ch. 15. 22.

cc 14.2 2 Macc. 1. 13, 19, 20, 33. See ch. 3. 31.

a 14.2 See Tobit 1. 14.

d 14.4 See ch. 7. 50.

e 14.5 ver. 34. ch. 15. 28. See ch. 13. 11.

f 14.5 See ch. 6. 29.

g 14.7 See ch. 4. 15. Comp. ch. 13. 43.

h 14.7 ch. 11. 65, 66. ver. 33. See ch. 4. 29.

i 14.7 See ch. 1. 33.

k 14.7 ch. 13. 50.

l 14.8 See Ps. 67. 6.

* 14.9 Or, the wealth of the land. Gk. as ver. 4.

m 14.9 Comp. Job 40. 10.

n 14.12 See 1 Kin. 4. 25.

o 14.12 See Ecclus. 22. 20 (Engl.).

p 14.16 ver. 24, 40. See ch. 8. 1.

q 14.16 So ch. 12. 2, 5, 6, 20, 21. & 15. 23. ver. 20, 23 in the Gk.

r 14.16 ch. 12. 23.

s 14.18 ver. 27, 48. ch. 8. 22.

t 14.18 ch. 8. 20, 21.

u 14.18 ch. 12. 1–23.

q 14.20 So ch. 12. 2, 5, 6, 20, 21. & 15. 23. ver. 20, 23 in the Gk.

q 14.20 So ch. 12. 2, 5, 6, 20, 21. & 15. 23. ver. 20, 23 in the Gk.

v 14.20 Comp. ch. 12. 6.

w 14.20 See Acts 15. 23.

x 14.21 ch. 12. 16. & 15. 15.

* 14.22 [Or, publick records]. ver. 23.

x 14.22 ch. 12. 16. & 15. 15.

y 14.23 Luke 14. 32 (Engl.).

q 14.23 So ch. 12. 2, 5, 6, 20, 21. & 15. 23. ver. 20, 23 in the Gk.

x 14.24 ch. 12. 16. & 15. 15.

p 14.24 ver. 24, 40. See ch. 8. 1.

z 14.24 1 Esdr. 5. 45. ch 15. 18. Luke 19. 13 marg.

a 14.25 ver. 49. ch. 13. 53. & 16. 1, 2, 9, 13, 14.

aa 14.26 So ch. 16. 2.

b 14.27 See ver. 18.

bb 14.27 Neh. 6. 15.

* 14.27 [B.C. 141–140].

c 14.27 ch. 13. 42.

* 14.28 Or, Jerusalem, peradventure by corruption and transposition of letters; or, as some think, the common hall where they met to consult of matters of estate.

d 14.29 ch. 2. 3.

e 14.29 So ch. 2. 1.

f 14.29 See ch. 6. 44.

g 14.30 ch. 10. 20, 21.

h 14.30 See Judith 16. 22.

i 14.31 ch. 13. 1.

* 14.32 Or, the men of war.

j 14.32 See ch. 3. 28.

k 14.33 See ch. 13. 33.

l 14.33 See ver. 7.

* 14.33 Or, weapons. ch. 5. 43. & 10. 6.

ll 14.33 ver. 42. ch. 15. 7. Comp. ch. 10. 14.

m 14.34 ver. 5. See ch. 13. 11.

* 14.34 Or, Gaza. ch. 13. 43.

n 14.34 See ch. 4. 15.

n 14.34 See ch. 4. 15.

o 14.35 ch. 13. 36, 42. ver. 41 in the Gk. So ver. 20, 38, 47.

oo 14.36 ch. 16. 2. So ch. 3. 6.

p 14.36 ch. 13. 47.

q 14.36 ch. 13. 50.

r 14.36 See ch. 1. 33.

* 14.36 Or, unto religion.

s 14.37 Comp. ch. 13. 52.

t 14.37 ch. 13. 10.

u 14.38 ch. 13. 36. See ch. 11. 27.

w 14.39 See ch. 10. 20.

x 14.40 ch. 8. 31. & 15. 17. So ver. 18.

y 14.40 ver. 24.

o 14.41 ch. 13. 36, 42. ver. 41 in the Gk. So ver. 20, 38, 47.

z 14.41 So 2 Sam. 7. 13. 1 Chr. 17. 12.

a 14.41 See ch. 4. 46.

b 14.41 Comp. Deut. 18. 15.

c 14.43 ch. 13. 42.

d 14.43 ch. 10. 20. & 11. 58.

e 14.44 See ch. 6. 62.

f 14.44 ch. 10. 89. & 11. 58.

e 14.45 See ch. 6. 62.

g 14.45 Matt. 5. 21, 22 (Gk.).

h 14.47 See ver. 35.

i 14.47 ch. 15. 1, 2 (Gk.). 2 Cor. 11. 32.

k 14.48 See ver. 18.

l 14.49 John 8. 20. So Mark 12. 41. Luke 21. 1. See 2 Macc. 3. 6.

m 14.49 See ver. 25.

* 15.1 About B.C. 140.

a 15.1 ch. 7. 1. & 10. 50.

b 15.1 See ch. 6. 29. Comp. ch. 10. 67.

c 15.1 See ch. 14. 47.

d 15.2 2 Macc. 11. 16. See Acts 23. 25.

c 15.2 See ch. 14. 47.

e 15.3 ver. 21. ch. 10. 61. Acts 24. 5.

f 15.3 ch. 13. 32.

g 15.4 ch. 13. 34. ver. 10.

h 15.5 Comp. ch. 10. 40–43.

i 15.7 So ch. 10. 31

k 15.7 See ch. 13. 33.

l 15.8 So ch. 10. 29. & 13. 39.

* 15.10 About B.C. 139.

g 15.10 ch. 13. 34. ver. 10.

m 15.11 ver. 13, 25. See Josh. 11. 2.

m 15.13 ver. 13, 25. See Josh. 11. 2.

n 15.14 So ver. 25 (Gk.). See ch. 3. 45.

o 15.15 ch. 14. 24.

p 15.15 See ch. 8. 1.

q 15.15 ver. 22, 23.

r 15.16 Comp. ch. 8. 16.

rr 15.16 2 Macc. 1. 10.

s 15.17 See ch. 14. 40.

t 15.17 ch. 8. 23–32.

o 15.17 ch. 14. 24.

o 15.18 ch. 14. 24.

q 15.19 ver. 22, 23.

e 15.21 ver. 21. ch. 10. 61. Acts 24. 5.

u 15.22 ch. 10. 67. & 14. 1.

* 15.22 Or, Arathes.

w 15.22 ch. 14. 2, 3.

* 15.23 Or, Sampsaces [Lat. Lampsacus].

x 15.23 See ch. 14. 16.

y 15.23 Acts 20. 15.

z 15.23 Acts 2. 10. & 13. 13. & 14. 24. & 15. 38. & 27. 5.

a 15.23 Acts 27. 5.

b 15.23 Acts 21. 1.

* 15.23 Or, Basilis.

b 15.23 Acts 21. 1.

c 15.23 Acts 27. 7.

d 15.23 See Acts 4. 36.

e 15.23 See Acts 2. 10.

f 15.25 See ver. 14.

* 15.25 Gr. bringing his forces to it.

f 15.25 See ver. 14.

g 15.27 See ch. 6. 62.

h 15.27 ver. 3–9.

i 15.28 ch. 14. 5. ver. 35. See ch. 13. 11.

k 15.28 ch. 14. 7. ver. 35. See ch. 4. 15.

l 15.28 ch. 13. 50, 51. See ch. 1. 33.

m 15.29 ch. 11. 28, 34.

m 15.30 ch. 11. 28, 34.

* 15.30 Or, except the borders, &c.

* 15.31 Or, subdue you in fight.

n 15.32 See ch. 10. 20.

o 15.32 So 1 Kin. 10. 5 marg.

i 15.35 ch. 14. 5. ver. 35. See ch. 13. 11.

k 15.35 ch. 14. 7. ver. 35. See ch. 4. 15.

p 15.35 Comp. ver. 31.

q 15.37 ver. 25, 39.

r 15.38 ch. 16. 1, 4, 8.

* 15.39 [Or, Gedor]. Josh. 15. 58. So ver. 41. ch. 16. 9.

q 15.39 ver. 25, 39.

r 15.40 ch. 16. 1, 4, 8.

s 15.40 See ch. 4. 15.

a 16.1 See ch. 13. 53.

a 16.1 See ch. 13. 53.

b 16.1 ver. 19, 21. See ch. 4. 15.

c 16.1 ch. 15. 40, 41.

a 16.2 See ch. 13. 53.

d 16.2 So ch. 14. 26.

e 16.2 See ch. 14. 36.

f 16.3 Comp. ch. 13. 23.

g 16.4 ch. 11. 6 marg.

h 16.4 See ch. 2. 1.

i 16.8 See ch. 3. 54.

k 16.8 See ch. 1. 18.

l 16.8 ch. 15. 39, 41.

m 16.9 ver. 2, 14.

l 16.9 ch. 15. 39, 41.

* 16.10 Or, Which when he had set [on] fire, they fled unto the towers in the fields of Azotus; and there were slain, &c.

* 16.10 About B.C. 135.

n 16.10 See ch. 4. 15.

o 16.11 2 Kin. 25. 5.

p 16.14 See ch. 9. 50.

* 16.14 [B.C. 135].

q 16.14 Zech. 1. 7 (Gk.).

r 16.16 Gen. 43. 34. John 2. 10 in the Gk.

s 16.18 ch. 15. 25, 38.

b 16.19 ver. 19, 21. See ch. 4. 15.

* 16.19 Gr. captains of thousands. Judith 14. 12. Mark 6. 21. Acts 25. 23. Rev. 6. 15. & 19. 18 in the Gk.

t 16.19 ver. 11.

b 16.21 ver. 19, 21. See ch. 4. 15.

u 16.21 See ch. 1. 50.

x 16.23 So ch. 9. 22.

1 Peter

1
2
3
4
5

THE FIRST EPISTLE GENERAL OF PETER

1

1  Peter, an apostle of Jesus Christ, to the strangers scattered throughout Pontus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Asia, and Bithynia, 2 Elect according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, through sanctification of the Spirit, unto obedience and sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ: Grace unto you, and peace, be multiplied.

3  Blessed be the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, which according to his [†]abundant mercy hath begotten us again unto a lively hope by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from the dead, 4  To an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven [∥]for you, 5  Who are kept by the power of God through faith unto salvation ready to be revealed in the last time. 6  Wherein ye greatly rejoice, though now for a season, if need be, ye are in heaviness through manifold temptations: 7  That the trial of your faith, being much more precious than of gold that perisheth, though it be tried with fire, might be found unto praise and honour and glory at the appearing of Jesus Christ: 8  Whom having not seen, ye love; in whom, though now ye see him not, yet believing, ye rejoice with joy unspeakable and full of glory: 9  Receiving the end of your faith, even the salvation of your souls. 10  Of which salvation the prophets have enquired and searched diligently, who prophesied of the grace that should come unto you: 11  Searching what, or what manner of time the Spirit of Christ which was in them did signify, when it testified beforehand the sufferings of Christ, and the glory that should follow. 12  Unto whom it was revealed, that not unto themselves, but unto us they did minister the things, which are now reported unto you by them that have preached the gospel unto you with the Holy Ghost sent down from heaven; which things the angels desire to look into. 13  Wherefore gird up the loins of your mind, be sober, and hope [†]to the end for the grace that is to be brought unto you at the revelation of Jesus Christ; 14  As obedient children, not fashioning yourselves according to the former lusts in your ignorance: 15  But as he which hath called you is holy, so be ye holy in all manner of conversation; 16  Because it is written, [*]Be ye holy; for I am holy. 17  And if ye call on the Father, who without respect of persons judgeth according to every man’s work, pass the time of your sojourning here in fear: 18  Forasmuch as ye know that ye were not redeemed with corruptible things, as silver and gold, from your vain conversation received by tradition from your fathers; 19  But with the precious blood of Christ, as of a lamb without blemish and without spot: 20  Who verily was foreordained before the foundation of the world, but was manifest in these last times for you, 21  Who by him do believe in God, that raised him up from the dead, and gave him glory; that your faith and hope might be in God. 22  Seeing ye have purified your souls in obeying the truth through the Spirit unto unfeigned love of the brethren, see that ye love one another with a pure heart fervently: 23  Being born again, not of corruptible seed, but of incorruptible, by the word of God, which liveth and abideth for ever. 24 [∥] For all flesh is as grass, and all the glory of man as the flower of grass. The grass withereth, and the flower thereof falleth away: 25  But the word of the Lord endureth for ever. And this is the word which by the gospel is preached unto you.

2

1  Wherefore laying aside all malice, and all guile, and hypocrisies, and envies, and [‡]all evil speakings, 2  As newborn babes, desire the sincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby: 3  If so be ye have tasted that the Lord is gracious. 4  To whom coming, as unto a living stone, disallowed indeed of men, but chosen of God, and precious, 5  Ye also, as lively stones, [∥]are built up a spiritual house, an holy priesthood, to offer up spiritual [‡]sacrifices, acceptable to God by Jesus Christ. 6  Wherefore [‡]also it is contained in the scripture, [*]Behold, I lay in Sion a chief corner stone, elect, precious: and he that believeth on him shall not be confounded. 7  Unto you therefore which believe he is [∥]precious: but unto them which be disobedient, [*]the stone which the builders disallowed, the same is made the head of the corner, 8 [*] And a stone of stumbling, and a rock of offence, even to them which stumble at the word, being disobedient: whereunto also they were appointed. 9  But ye are a chosen generation, a royal priesthood, an holy nation, [∥]a peculiar people; that ye should shew forth the [∥]praises of him who hath called you out of darkness into his marvellous light: 10 [*] Which in time past were not a people, but are now the people of God: which had not obtained mercy, but now have obtained mercy.

11  Dearly beloved, I beseech you as strangers and pilgrims, abstain from fleshly lusts, which war against the soul; 12  Having your conversation honest among the Gentiles: that, [∥]whereas they speak against you as evildoers, they may by your good works, which they shall behold, glorify God in the day of visitation.

13  Submit yourselves to every ordinance of man for the Lord’s sake: whether it be to the king, as supreme; 14  Or unto governors, as unto them that are sent by him for the punishment of evildoers, and for the praise of them that do well. 15  For so is the will of God, that with well doing ye may put to silence the ignorance of foolish men: 16  As free, and not [†]using your liberty for a cloke of maliciousness, but as the servants of God. 17 [∥] Honour all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Honour the king. 18  Servants, be subject to your masters with all fear; not only to the good and gentle, but also to the froward. 19  For this is thankworthy, if a man for conscience toward God endure grief, suffering wrongfully. 20  For what glory is it, if, when ye be buffeted for your faults, ye shall take it patiently? but if, when ye do well, and suffer for it, ye take it patiently, this is [∥]acceptable with God. 21  For even hereunto were ye called: because Christ also suffered [∥]for us, leaving us an example, that ye should follow his steps: 22  Who did no sin, neither was guile found in his mouth: 23  Who, when he was reviled, reviled not again; when he suffered, he threatened not; but [∥]committed himself to him that judgeth righteously: 24  Who his own self bare our sins in his own body [∥]on the tree, that we, being dead to sins, should live unto righteousness: by whose stripes ye were healed. 25  For ye were as sheep going astray; but are now returned unto the Shepherd and Bishop of your souls.

3

1  Likewise, ye wives, be in subjection to your own husbands; that, if any obey not the word, they also may without the word be won by the conversation of the wives; 2  While they behold your chaste conversation coupled with fear. 3  Whose adorning let it not be that outward adorning of plaiting the hair, and of wearing of gold, or of putting on of apparel; 4  But let it be the hidden man of the heart, in that which is not corruptible, even the ornament of a meek and quiet spirit, which is in the sight of God of great price. 5  For after this manner in the old time the holy women also, who trusted in God, adorned themselves, being in subjection unto their own husbands: 6  Even as Sara obeyed Abraham, calling him lord: whose [†]daughters ye are, as long as ye do well, and are not afraid with any amazement. 7  Likewise, ye husbands, dwell with them according to knowledge, giving honour unto the wife, as unto the weaker vessel, and as being heirs together of the grace of life; that your prayers be not hindered. 8  Finally, be ye all of one mind, having compassion one of another, [∥]love as brethren, be pitiful, be courteous: 9  Not rendering evil for evil, or railing for railing: but contrariwise blessing; knowing that ye are thereunto called, that ye should inherit a blessing. 10  For [*]he that will love life, and see good days, let him refrain his tongue from evil, and his lips that they speak no guile: 11  Let him eschew evil, and do good; let him seek peace, and ensue it. 12  For the eyes of the Lord are over the righteous, and his ears are open unto their prayers: but the face of the Lord is [†]against them that do evil.

13  And who is he that will harm you, if ye be followers of that which is good? 14  But and if ye suffer for righteousness’ sake, happy are ye: and [*]be not afraid of their terror, neither be troubled; 15  But sanctify the Lord God in your hearts: and be ready always to give an answer to every man that asketh you a reason of the hope that is in you with meekness and [∥]fear: 16  Having a good conscience; that, whereas they speak evil of you, as of evildoers, they may be ashamed that falsely accuse your good conversation in Christ. 17  For it is better, if the will of God be so, that ye suffer for well doing, than for evil doing. 18  For Christ also hath once suffered for sins, the just for the unjust, that he might bring us to God, being put to death in the flesh, but quickened by the Spirit: 19  By which also he went and preached unto the spirits in prison; 20  Which sometime were disobedient, when once the longsuffering of God waited in the days of Noah, while the ark was a preparing, wherein few, that is, eight souls were saved by water. 21  The like figure whereunto even baptism doth also now save us (not the putting away of the filth of the flesh, but the answer of a good conscience toward God,) by the resurrection of Jesus Christ: 22  Who is gone into heaven, and is on the right hand of God; angels and authorities and powers being made subject unto him.

4

1  Forasmuch then as Christ hath suffered for us in the flesh, arm yourselves likewise with the same mind: for he that hath suffered in the flesh hath ceased from sin; 2  That he no longer should live the rest of his time in the flesh to the lusts of men, but to the will of God. 3  For the time past of our life may suffice us to have wrought the will of the Gentiles, when we walked in lasciviousness, lusts, excess of wine, revellings, banquetings, and abominable idolatries: 4  Wherein they think it strange that ye run not with them to the same excess of riot, speaking evil of you: 5  Who shall give account to him that is ready to judge the quick and the dead. 6  For for this cause was the gospel preached also to them that are dead, that they might be judged according to men in the flesh, but live according to God in the spirit.

7  But the end of all things is at hand: be ye therefore sober, and watch unto prayer. 8  And above all things have fervent charity among yourselves: for charity [∥]shall cover the multitude of sins. 9  Use hospitality one to another without grudging. 10  As every man hath received the gift, even so minister the same one to another, as good stewards of the manifold grace of God. 11  If any man speak, let him speak as the oracles of God; if any man minister, let him do it as of the ability which God giveth: that God in all things may be glorified through Jesus Christ, to whom be praise and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.

12  Beloved, think it not strange concerning the fiery trial which is to try you, as though some strange thing happened unto you: 13  But rejoice, inasmuch as ye are partakers of Christ’s sufferings; that, when his glory shall be revealed, ye may be glad also with exceeding joy. 14  If ye be reproached for the name of Christ, happy are ye; for the spirit of glory and of God resteth upon you: on their part he is evil spoken of, but on your part he is glorified. 15  But let none of you suffer as a murderer, or as a thief, or as an evildoer, or as a busybody in other men’s matters. 16  Yet if any man suffer as a Christian, let him not be ashamed; but let him glorify God on this behalf. 17  For the time is come that judgment must begin at the house of God: and if it first begin at us, what shall the end be of them that obey not the gospel of God? 18  And if the righteous scarcely be saved, where shall the ungodly and the sinner appear? 19  Wherefore let them that suffer according to the will of God commit the keeping of their souls to him in well doing, as unto a faithful Creator.

5

1  The elders which are among you I exhort, who am also an elder, and a witness of the sufferings of Christ, and also a partaker of the glory that shall be revealed: 2  Feed the flock of God [∥]which is among you, taking the oversight thereof, not by constraint, but willingly; not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind; 3  Neither as [∥]being lords over God’s heritage, but being ensamples to the flock. 4  And when the chief Shepherd shall appear, ye shall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away. 5  Likewise, ye younger, submit yourselves unto the elder. Yea, all of you be subject one to another, and be clothed with humility: for God resisteth the proud, and giveth grace to the humble.

6  Humble yourselves therefore under the mighty hand of God, that he may exalt you in due time: 7  Casting all your care upon him; for he careth for you. 8  Be sober, be vigilant; because your adversary the devil, as a roaring lion, walketh about, seeking whom he may devour: 9  Whom resist stedfast in the faith, knowing that the same afflictions are accomplished in your brethren that are in the world. 10  But the God of all grace, who hath called us [‡]unto his eternal glory by Christ Jesus, after that ye have suffered a while, make you perfect, stablish, strengthen, settle you. 11  To him be glory and dominion for ever and ever. Amen.

12  By Silvanus, a faithful brother unto you, as I suppose, I have written briefly, exhorting, and testifying that this is the true grace of God wherein ye stand. 13  The church that is at Babylon, elected together with you, saluteth you; and so doth Marcus my son. 14  Greet ye one another with a kiss of charity. Peace be with you all that are in Christ Jesus. Amen.

† 1.3 Gr. much.

∥ 1.4 Or, for us.

† 1.13 Gr. perfectly.

* 1.16 Lev. 11. 44. & 19. 2. & 20. 7.

∥ 1.24 Or, For that.

‡ 2.1 [1611 omits all]

∥ 2.5 Or, be ye built.

‡ 2.5 [1611 sacrifice]

‡ 2.6 [1611 omits also]

* 2.6 Is. 28. 16.

∥ 2.7 Or, an honour.

* 2.7 Ps. 118. 22 Matt 21. 42. Acts 4. 11.

* 2.8 Is. 8. 14.

∥ 2.9 Or, a purchased people.

∥ 2.9 Or, virtues.

* 2.10 Hos. 2. 23.

∥ 2.12 Or, wherein.

† 2.16 Gr. having.

∥ 2.17 Or, Esteem.

∥ 2.20 Or, thank.

∥ 2.21 Some read, for you.

∥ 2.23 Or, committed his cause.

∥ 2.24 Or, to.

† 3.6 Gr. children.

∥ 3.8 Or, loving to the brethren.

* 3.10 Ps. 34. 12.

† 3.12 Gr. upon.

* 3.14 Is. 8. 12, 13.

∥ 3.15 Or, reverence.

∥ 4.8 Or, will.

∥ 5.2 Or, as much as in you is.

∥ 5.3 Or, overruling.

‡ 5.10 [1611 into]

1 Samuel

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16
17
18
19
20

21
22
23
24
25
26
27
28
29
30

31

The First Book of Samuel Otherwise Called the First Book of the Kings

1

1  Now there was a certain man of Ramathaim-zophim, of mount Ephraim, and his name was Elkanah, the son of Jeroham, the son of Elihu, the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph, an Ephrathite: 2  And he had two wives; the name of the one was Hannah, and the name of the other Peninnah: and Peninnah had children, but Hannah had no children. 3  And this man went up out of his city [*][†]yearly to worship and to sacrifice unto the LORD of hosts in Shiloh. And the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, the priests of the LORD, were there.

4 ¶ And when the time was that Elkanah offered, he gave to Peninnah his wife, and to all her sons and her daughters, portions: 5  But unto Hannah he gave [∥]a worthy portion; for he loved Hannah: but the LORD had shut up her womb. 6  And her adversary also [†]provoked her sore, for to make her fret, because the LORD had shut up her womb. 7 And as he did so year by year, [∥][†]when she went up to the house of the LORD, so she provoked her; therefore she wept, and did not eat. 8  Then said Elkanah her husband to her, Hannah, why weepest thou? and why eatest thou not? and why is thy heart grieved? am not I better to thee than ten sons?

9 ¶ So Hannah rose up after they had eaten in Shiloh, and after they had drunk. Now Eli the priest sat upon a seat by a post of the temple of the LORD. 10 And she was [†]in bitterness of soul, and prayed unto the LORD, and wept sore. 11  And she vowed a vow, and said, O LORD of hosts, if thou wilt indeed look on the affliction of thine handmaid, and remember me, and not forget thine handmaid, but wilt give unto thine handmaid [†]a man child, then I will give him unto the LORD all the days of his life, and [*]there shall no razor come upon his head. 12  And it came to pass, as she [†]continued praying before the LORD, that Eli marked her mouth. 13  Now Hannah, she spake in her heart; only her lips moved, but her voice was not heard: therefore Eli thought she had been drunken. 14  And Eli said unto her, How long wilt thou be drunken? put away thy wine from thee. 15  And Hannah answered and said, No, my lord, I am a woman [†]of a sorrowful spirit: I have drunk neither wine nor strong drink, but have poured out my soul before the LORD. 16  Count not thine handmaid for a daughter of Belial: for out of the abundance of my [∥]complaint and grief have I spoken hitherto. 17  Then Eli answered and said, Go in peace: and the God of Israel grant thee thy petition that thou hast asked of him. 18  And she said, Let thine handmaid find grace in thy sight. So the woman went her way, and did eat, and her countenance was no more sad.

19 ¶ And they rose up in the morning early, and worshipped before the LORD, and returned, and came to their house to Ramah: and Elkanah knew Hannah his wife; and the LORD remembered her. 20  Wherefore it came to pass, when [†]the time was come about after Hannah had conceived, that she bare a son, and called his name [∥]Samuel, saying, Because I have asked him of the LORD. 21  And the man Elkanah, and all his house, went up to offer unto the LORD the yearly sacrifice, and his vow. 22  But Hannah went not up; for she said unto her husband, I will not go up until the child be weaned, and then I will bring him, that he may appear before the LORD, and there abide for ever. 23  And Elkanah her husband said unto her, Do what seemeth thee good; tarry until thou have weaned him; only the LORD establish his word. So the woman abode, and gave her son suck until she weaned him.

24 ¶ And when she had weaned him, she took him up with her, with three bullocks, and one ephah of flour, and a bottle of wine, and brought him unto the house of the LORD in Shiloh: and the child was young. 25  And they slew a bullock, and brought the child to Eli. 26  And she said, Oh my lord, as thy soul liveth, my lord, I am the woman that stood by thee here, praying unto the LORD. 27  For this child I prayed; and the LORD hath given me my petition which I asked of him: 28  Therefore also I have [∥]lent him to the LORD; as long as he liveth [∥]he shall be lent to the LORD. And he worshipped the LORD there.

2

1  And Hannah prayed, and said, My heart rejoiceth in the LORD, mine horn is exalted in the LORD: my mouth is enlarged over mine enemies; because I rejoice in thy salvation. 2  There is none holy as the LORD: for there is none beside thee: neither is there any rock like our God. 3  Talk no more so exceeding proudly; let not [†]arrogancy come out of your mouth: for the LORD is a God of knowledge, and by him actions are weighed. 4  The bows of the mighty men are broken, and they that stumbled are girded with strength. 5  They that were full have hired out themselves for bread; and they that were hungry ceased: so that the barren hath born seven; and she that hath many children is waxed feeble. 6 [*] The LORD killeth, and maketh alive: he bringeth down to the grave, and bringeth up. 7  The LORD maketh poor, and maketh rich: he bringeth low, and lifteth up. 8  He [*]raiseth up the poor out of the dust, and lifteth up the beggar from the dunghill, to set them among princes, and to make them inherit the throne of glory: for the pillars of the earth are the LORD’s, and he hath set the world upon them. 9  He will keep the feet of his saints, and the wicked shall be silent in darkness; for by strength shall no man prevail. 10  The adversaries of the LORD shall be broken to pieces; [*]out of heaven shall he thunder upon them: the LORD shall judge the ends of the earth; and he shall give strength unto his king, and exalt the horn of his anointed.

11  And Elkanah went to Ramah to his house. And the child did minister unto the LORD before Eli the priest.

12 ¶ Now the sons of Eli were sons of Belial; they knew not the LORD. 13  And the priests’ custom with the people was, that, when any man offered sacrifice, the priest’s servant came, while the flesh was in seething, with a fleshhook of three teeth in his hand; 14  And he struck it into the pan, or kettle, or caldron, or pot; all that the fleshhook brought up the priest took for himself. So they did in Shiloh unto all the Israelites that came thither. 15  Also before they burnt the fat, the priest’s servant came, and said to the man that sacrificed, Give flesh to roast for the priest; for he will not have sodden flesh of thee, but raw. 16 And if any man said unto him, Let them not fail to burn the fat [†]presently, and then take as much as thy soul desireth; then he would answer him, Nay; but thou shalt give it me now: and if not, I will take it by force. 17  Wherefore the sin of the young men was very great before the LORD: for men abhorred the offering of the LORD.

18 ¶ But Samuel ministered before the LORD, being a child, [*]girded with a linen ephod. 19  Moreover his mother made him a little coat, and brought it to him from year to year, when she came up with her husband to offer the yearly sacrifice.

20 ¶ And Eli blessed Elkanah and his wife, and said, The LORD give thee seed of this woman for the [∥]loan which is lent to the LORD. And they went unto their own home. 21  And the LORD visited Hannah, so that she conceived, and bare three sons and two daughters. And the child Samuel grew before the LORD.

22 ¶ Now Eli was very old, and heard all that his sons did unto all Israel; and how they lay with the women that [†]assembled at the door of the tabernacle of the congregation. 23  And he said unto them, Why do ye such things? for [∥]I hear of your evil dealings by all this people. 24  Nay, my sons; for it is no good report that I hear: ye make the LORD’s people [∥]to transgress. 25  If one man sin against another, the judge shall judge him: but if a man sin against the LORD, who shall intreat for him? Notwithstanding they hearkened not unto the voice of their father, because the LORD would slay them. 26  And the child Samuel grew on, and was in favour both with the LORD, and also with men.

27 ¶ And there came a man of God unto Eli, and said unto him, Thus saith the LORD, Did I plainly appear unto the house of thy father, when they were in Egypt in Pharaoh’s house? 28  And did I choose him out of all the tribes of Israel to be my priest, to offer upon mine altar, to burn incense, to wear an ephod before me? and [*]did I give unto the house of thy father all the offerings made by fire of the children of Israel? 29  Wherefore kick ye at my sacrifice and at mine offering, which I have commanded in my habitation; and honourest thy sons above me, to make yourselves fat with the chiefest of all the offerings of Israel my people? 30  Wherefore the LORD God of Israel saith, I said indeed that thy house, and the house of thy father, should walk before me for ever: but now the LORD saith, Be it far from me; for them that honour me I will honour, and they that despise me shall be lightly esteemed. 31  Behold, the days come, that I will cut off thine arm, and the arm of thy father’s house, that there shall not be an old man in thine house. 32  And thou shalt see [∥]an enemy in my habitation, in all the wealth which God shall give Israel: and there shall not be an old man in thine house for ever. 33  And the man of thine, whom I shall not cut off from mine altar, shall be to consume thine eyes, and to grieve thine heart: and all the increase of thine house shall die [†]in the flower of their age. 34 And this shall be a sign unto thee, that shall come upon thy two sons, on Hophni and Phinehas; in one day they shall die both of them. 35  And I will raise me up a faithful priest, that shall do according to that which is in mine heart and in my mind: and I will build him a sure house; and he shall walk before mine anointed for ever. 36 And it shall come to pass, that every one that is left in thine house shall come and crouch to him for a piece of silver and a morsel of bread, and shall say, [†]Put me, I pray thee, into [∥]one of the priests’ offices, that I may eat a piece of bread.

3

1  And the child Samuel ministered unto the LORD before Eli. And the word of the LORD was precious in those days; there was no open vision. 2  And it came to pass at that time, when Eli was laid down in his place, and his eyes began to wax dim, that he could not see; 3  And ere the lamp of God went out in the temple of the LORD, where the ark of God was, and Samuel was laid down to sleep; 4  That the LORD called Samuel: and he answered, Here am I. 5  And he ran unto Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou calledst me. And he said, I called not; lie down again. And he went and lay down. 6  And the LORD called yet again, Samuel. And Samuel arose and went to Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou didst call me. And he answered, I called not, my son; lie down again. 7 [∥] Now Samuel did not yet know the LORD, neither was the word of the LORD yet revealed unto him. 8  And the LORD called Samuel again the third time. And he arose and went to Eli, and said, Here am I; for thou didst call me. And Eli perceived that the LORD had called the child. 9  Therefore Eli said unto Samuel, Go, lie down: and it shall be, if he call thee, that thou shalt say, Speak, LORD; for thy servant heareth. So Samuel went and lay down in his place. 10  And the LORD came, and stood, and called as at other times, Samuel, Samuel. Then Samuel answered, Speak; for thy servant heareth.

11 ¶ And the LORD said to Samuel, Behold, I will do a thing in Israel, at which both the ears of [*]every one that heareth it shall tingle. 12  In that day I will perform against Eli all things which I have spoken concerning his house: [†]when I begin, I will also make an end. 13 [∥][*] For I have told him that I will judge his house for ever for the iniquity which he knoweth; because his sons made themselves [∥]vile, and he [†]restrained them not. 14  And therefore I have sworn unto the house of Eli, that the iniquity of Eli’s house shall not be purged with sacrifice nor offering for ever.

15 ¶ And Samuel lay until the morning, and opened the doors of the house of the LORD. And Samuel feared to shew Eli the vision. 16  Then Eli called Samuel, and said, Samuel, my son. And he answered, Here am I. 17  And he said, What is the thing that the Lord hath said unto thee? I pray thee hide it not from me: God do so to thee, and [†]more also, if thou hide any [∥]thing from me of all the things that he said unto thee. 18  And Samuel told him [†]every whit, and hid nothing from him. And he said, It is the LORD: let him do what seemeth him good.

19 ¶ And Samuel grew, and the LORD was with him, and did let none of his words fall to the ground. 20  And all Israel from Dan even to Beer-sheba knew that Samuel was [∥]established to be a prophet of the LORD. 21  And the LORD appeared again in Shiloh: for the LORD revealed himself to Samuel in Shiloh by the word of the LORD.

4

1  And the word of Samuel [∥][†]came to all Israel. Now Israel went out against the Philistines to battle, and pitched beside Eben-ezer: and the Philistines pitched in Aphek. 2  And the Philistines put themselves in array against Israel: and when [†]they joined battle, Israel was smitten before the Philistines: and they slew of [†]the army in the field about four thousand men.

3 ¶ And when the people were come into the camp, the elders of Israel said, Wherefore hath the LORD smitten us to day before the Philistines? Let us [†]fetch the ark of the covenant of the LORD out of Shiloh unto us, that, when it cometh among us, it may save us out of the hand of our enemies. 4  So the people sent to Shiloh, that they might bring from thence the ark of the covenant of the LORD of hosts, which dwelleth between the cherubims: and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, were there with the ark of the covenant of God. 5  And when the ark of the covenant of the LORD came into the camp, all Israel shouted with a great shout, so that the earth rang again. 6  And when the Philistines heard the noise of the shout, they said, What meaneth the noise of this great shout in the camp of the Hebrews? And they understood that the ark of the LORD was come into the camp. 7  And the Philistines were afraid, for they said, God is come into the camp. And they said, Woe unto us! for there hath not been such a thing [†]heretofore. 8  Woe unto us! who shall deliver us out of the hand of these mighty Gods? these are the Gods that smote the Egyptians with all the plagues in the wilderness. 9  Be strong, and quit yourselves like men, O ye Philistines, that ye be not servants unto the Hebrews, [*]as they have been to you: [†]quit yourselves like men, and fight.

10 ¶ And the Philistines fought, and Israel was smitten, and they fled every man into his tent: and there was a very great slaughter; for there fell of Israel thirty thousand footmen. 11  And the ark of God was taken; and the two sons of Eli, Hophni and Phinehas, [†]were slain.

12 ¶ And there ran a man of Benjamin out of the army, and came to Shiloh the same day with his clothes rent, and with earth upon his head. 13  And when he came, lo, Eli sat upon a seat by the wayside watching: for his heart trembled for the ark of God. And when the man came into the city, and told it, all the city cried out. 14  And when Eli heard the noise of the crying, he said, What meaneth the noise of this tumult? And the man came in hastily, and told Eli. 15  Now Eli was ninety and eight years old; and [*]his eyes [†]were dim, that he could not see. 16  And the man said unto Eli, I am he that came out of the army, and I fled to day out of the army. And he said, What [†]is there done, my son? 17  And the messenger answered and said, Israel is fled before the Philistines, and there hath been also a great slaughter among the people, and thy two sons also, Hophni and Phinehas, are dead, and the ark of God is taken. 18  And it came to pass, when he made mention of the ark of God, that he fell from off the seat backward by the side of the gate, and his neck brake, and he died: for he was an old man, and heavy. And he had judged Israel forty years.

19 ¶ And his daughter in law, Phinehas’ wife, was with child, near [∥]to be delivered: and when she heard the tidings that the ark of God was taken, and that her father in law and her husband were dead, she bowed herself and travailed; for her pains [†]came upon her. 20  And about the time of her death the women that stood by her said unto her, Fear not; for thou hast born a son. But she answered not, [†]neither did she regard it. 21  And she named the child [∥]I-chabod, saying, The glory is departed from Israel: because the ark of God was taken, and because of her father in law and her husband. 22  And she said, The glory is departed from Israel: for the ark of God is taken.

5

1  And the Philistines took the ark of God, and brought it from Eben-ezer unto Ashdod. 2  When the Philistines took the ark of God, they brought it into the house of Dagon, and set it by Dagon.

3 ¶ And when they of Ashdod arose early on the morrow, behold, Dagon was fallen upon his face to the earth before the ark of the LORD. And they took Dagon, and set him in his place again. 4  And when they arose early on the morrow morning, behold, Dagon was fallen upon his face to the ground before the ark of the LORD; and the head of Dagon and both the palms of his hands were cut off upon the threshold; only [∥]the stump of Dagon was left to him. 5  Therefore neither the priests of Dagon, nor any that come into Dagon’s house, tread on the threshold of Dagon in Ashdod unto this day.

6  But the hand of the LORD was heavy upon them of Ashdod, and he destroyed them, and smote them with [*]emerods, even Ashdod and the coasts thereof. 7  And when the men of Ashdod saw that it was so, they said, The ark of the God of Israel shall not abide with us: for his hand is sore upon us, and upon Dagon our god. 8  They sent therefore and gathered all the lords of the Philistines unto them, and said, What shall we do with the ark of the God of Israel? And they answered, Let the ark of the God of Israel be carried about unto Gath. And they carried the ark of the God of Israel about thither. 9 And it was so, that, after they had carried it about, the hand of the LORD was against the city with a very great destruction: and he smote the men of the city, both small and great, and they had emerods in their secret parts.

10 ¶ Therefore they sent the ark of God to Ekron. And it came to pass, as the ark of God came to Ekron, that the Ekronites cried out, saying, They have brought about the ark of the God of Israel to us, to slay us and our people. 11  So they sent and gathered together all the lords of the Philistines, and said, Send away the ark of the God of Israel, and let it go again to his own place, that it slay us not, and our people: for there was a deadly destruction throughout all the city; the hand of God was very heavy there. 12  And the men that died not were smitten with the emerods: and the cry of the city went up to heaven.

6

1  And the ark of the LORD was in the country of the Philistines seven months. 2  And the Philistines called for the priests and the diviners, saying, What shall we do to the ark of the LORD? tell us wherewith we shall send it to his place. 3  And they said, If ye send away the ark of the God of Israel, send it not empty; but in any wise return him a trespass offering: then ye shall be healed, and it shall be known to you why his hand is not removed from you. 4  Then said they, What shall be the trespass offering which we shall return to him? They answered, Five golden emerods, and five golden mice, according to the number of the lords of the Philistines: for one plague was on [†]you all, and on your lords. 5  Wherefore ye shall make images of your emerods, and images of your mice that mar the land; and ye shall give glory unto the God of Israel: peradventure he will lighten his hand from off you, and from off your gods, and from off your land. 6  Wherefore then do ye harden your hearts, as the Egyptians and Pharaoh hardened their hearts? when he had wrought [∥]wonderfully among them, [*]did they not let [†]the people go, and they departed? 7  Now therefore make a new cart, and take two milch kine, on which there hath come no yoke, and tie the kine to the cart, and bring [‡]their calves home from them: 8  And take the ark of the LORD, and lay it upon the cart; and put the jewels of gold, which ye return him for a trespass offering, in a coffer by the side thereof; and send it away, that it may go. 9  And see, if it goeth up by the way of his own coast to Beth-shemesh, then [∥]he hath done us this great evil: but if not, then we shall know that it is not his hand that smote us; it was a chance that happened to us.

10 ¶ And the men did so; and took two milch kine, and tied them to the cart, and shut up their calves at home: 11  And they laid the ark of the LORD upon the cart, and the coffer with the mice of gold and the images of their emerods. 12  And the kine took the straight way to the way of Beth-shemesh, and went along the highway, lowing as they went, and turned not aside to the right hand or to the left; and the lords of the Philistines went after them unto the border of Beth-shemesh. 13 And they of Beth-shemesh were reaping their wheat harvest in the valley: and they lifted up their eyes, and saw the ark, and rejoiced to see it. 14  And the cart came into the field of Joshua, a Beth-shemite, and stood there, where there was a great stone: and they clave the wood of the cart, and offered the kine a burnt offering unto the LORD. 15  And the Levites took down the ark of the LORD, and the coffer that was with it, wherein the jewels of gold were, and put them on the great stone: and the men of Beth-shemesh offered burnt offerings and sacrificed sacrifices the same day unto the LORD. 16  And when the five lords of the Philistines had seen it, they returned to Ekron the same day. 17 And these are the golden emerods which the Philistines returned for a trespass offering unto the LORD; for Ashdod one, for Gaza one, for Askelon one, for Gath one, for Ekron one; 18  And the golden mice, according to the number of all the cities of the Philistines belonging to the five lords, both of fenced cities, and of country villages, even unto the [∥]great stone of Abel, whereon they set down the ark of the LORD: which stone remaineth unto this day in the field of Joshua, the Beth-shemite.

19 ¶ And he smote the men of Beth-shemesh, because they had looked into the ark of the LORD, even he smote of the people fifty thousand and threescore and ten men: and the people lamented, because the LORD had smitten many of the people with a great slaughter. 20  And the men of Beth-shemesh said, Who is able to stand before this holy LORD God? and to whom shall he go up from us?

21 ¶ And they sent messengers to the inhabitants of Kirjath-jearim, saying, The Philistines have brought again the ark of the LORD; come ye down, and fetch it up to you.

7

1  And the men of Kirjath-jearim came, and fetched up the ark of the LORD, and brought it into the house of Abinadab in the hill, and sanctified Eleazar his son to keep the ark of the LORD. 2  And it came to pass, while the ark abode in Kirjath-jearim, that the time was long; for it was twenty years: and all the house of Israel lamented after the LORD.

3 ¶ And Samuel spake unto all the house of Israel, saying, If ye do return unto the LORD with all your hearts, then [*]put away the strange gods and [*]Ashtaroth from among you, and prepare your hearts unto the LORD, and [*]serve him only: and he will deliver you out of the hand of the Philistines. 4  Then the children of Israel did put away [*]Baalim and Ashtaroth, and served the LORD only. 5  And Samuel said, Gather all Israel to Mizpeh, and I will pray for you unto the LORD. 6  And they gathered together to Mizpeh, and drew water, and poured it out before the LORD, and fasted on that day, and said there, We have sinned against the LORD. And Samuel judged the children of Israel in Mizpeh.

7  And when the Philistines heard that the children of Israel were gathered together to Mizpeh, the lords of the Philistines went up against Israel. And when the children of Israel heard it, they were afraid of the Philistines. 8  And the children of Israel said to Samuel, [†]Cease not to cry unto the LORD our God for us, that he will save us out of the hand of the Philistines.

9 ¶ And Samuel took a sucking lamb, and offered it for a burnt offering wholly unto the LORD: and Samuel cried unto the LORD for Israel; and the LORD [∥]heard him. 10  And as Samuel was offering up the burnt offering, the Philistines drew near to battle against Israel: but the LORD thundered with a great thunder on that day upon the Philistines, and discomfited them; and they were smitten before Israel. 11  And the men of Israel went out of Mizpeh, and pursued the Philistines, and smote them, until they came under Beth-car. 12  Then Samuel took a stone, and set it between Mizpeh and Shen, and called the name of it [∥]Eben-ezer, saying, Hitherto hath the LORD helped us.

13 ¶ So the Philistines were subdued, and they came no more into the coast of Israel: and the hand of the LORD was against the Philistines all the days of Samuel. 14  And the cities which the Philistines had taken from Israel were restored to Israel, from Ekron even unto Gath; and the coasts thereof did Israel deliver out of the hands of the Philistines. And there was peace between Israel and the Amorites. 15  And Samuel judged Israel all the days of his life. 16  And he went from year to year [†]in circuit to Beth-el, and Gilgal, and Mizpeh, and judged Israel in all those places. 17  And his return was to Ramah; for there was his house; and there he judged Israel; and there he built an altar unto the LORD.

8

1  And it came to pass, when Samuel was old, that he made his sons judges over Israel. 2  Now the name of his firstborn was Joel; and the name of his second, Abiah: they were judges in Beer-sheba. 3  And his sons walked not in his ways, but turned aside after lucre, and [*]took bribes, and perverted judgment.

4  Then all the elders of Israel gathered themselves together, and came to Samuel unto Ramah, 5  And said unto him, Behold, thou art old, and thy sons walk not in thy ways: now [*]make us a king to judge us like all the nations.

6 ¶ But the thing [†]displeased Samuel, when they said, Give us a king to judge us. And Samuel prayed unto the LORD. 7  And the LORD said unto Samuel, Hearken unto the voice of the people in all that they say unto thee: for they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me, that I should not reign over them. 8  According to all the works which they have done since the day that I brought them up out of Egypt even unto this day, wherewith they have forsaken me, and served other gods, so do they also unto thee. 9  Now therefore [∥]hearken unto their voice: [∥]howbeit yet protest solemnly unto them, and shew them the manner of the king that shall reign over them.

10 ¶ And Samuel told all the words of the LORD unto the people that asked of him a king. 11  And he said, This will be the manner of the king that shall reign over you: He will take your sons, and appoint them for himself, for his chariots, and to be his horsemen; and some shall run before his chariots. 12  And he will appoint him captains over thousands, and captains over fifties; and will set them to ear his ground, and to reap his harvest, and to make his instruments of war, and instruments of his chariots. 13  And he will take your daughters to be confectionaries, and to be cooks, and to be bakers. 14  And he will take your fields, and your vineyards, and your oliveyards, even the best of them, and give them to his servants. 15  And he will take the tenth of your seed, and of your vineyards, and give to his [†]officers, and to his servants. 16  And he will take your menservants, and your maidservants, and your goodliest young men, and your asses, and put them to his work. 17  He will take the tenth of your sheep: and ye shall be his servants. 18  And ye shall cry out in that day because of your king which ye shall have chosen you; and the LORD will not hear you in that day.

19 ¶ Nevertheless the people refused to obey the voice of Samuel; and they said, Nay; but we will have a king over us; 20  That we also may be like all the nations; and that our king may judge us, and go out before us, and fight our battles. 21  And Samuel heard all the words of the people, and he rehearsed them in the ears of the LORD. 22  And the LORD said to Samuel, Hearken unto their voice, and make them a king. And Samuel said unto the men of Israel, Go ye every man unto his city.

9

1  Now there was a man of Benjamin, whose name was [*]Kish, the son of Abiel, the son of Zeror, the son of Bechorath, the son of Aphiah, [∥]a Benjamite, a mighty man of [∥]power. 2  And he had a son, whose name was Saul, a choice young man, and a goodly: and there was not among the children of Israel a goodlier person than he: from his shoulders and upward he was higher than any of the people.

3  And the asses of Kish Saul’s father were lost. And Kish said to Saul his son, Take now one of the servants with thee, and arise, go seek the asses. 4  And he passed through mount Ephraim, and passed through the land of Shalisha, but they found them not: then they passed through the land of Shalim, and there they were not: and he passed through the land of the Benjamites, but they found them not. 5  And when they were come to the land of Zuph, Saul said to his servant that was with him, Come, and let us return; lest my father leave caring for the asses, and take thought for us. 6  And he said unto him, Behold now, there is in this city a man of God, and he is an honourable man; all that he saith cometh surely to pass: now let us go thither; peradventure he can shew us our way that we should go. 7  Then said Saul to his servant, But, behold, if we go, what shall we bring the man? for the bread [†]is spent in our vessels, and there is not a present to bring to the man of God: what [†]have we? 8  And the servant answered Saul again, and said, Behold, [†]I have here at hand the fourth part of a shekel of silver: that will I give to the man of God, to tell us our way. 9 (Beforetime in Israel, when a man went to enquire of God, thus he spake, Come, and let us go to the seer: for he that is now called a Prophet was beforetime called a Seer.) 10  Then said Saul to his servant, [†]Well said; come, let us go. So they went unto the city where the man of God was.

11 ¶ And as they went up [†]the hill to the city, they found young maidens going out to draw water, and said unto them, Is the seer here? 12  And they answered them, and said, He is; behold, he is before you: make haste now, for he came to day to the city; for there is a [∥]sacrifice of the people to day in the high place: 13  As soon as ye be come into the city, ye shall straightway find him, before he go up to the high place to eat: for the people will not eat until he come, because he doth bless the sacrifice; and afterwards they eat that be bidden. Now therefore get you up; for about [†]this time ye shall find him. 14  And they went up into the city: and when they were come into the city, behold, Samuel came out against them, for to go up to the high place.

15 ¶ [*]Now the LORD had [†]told Samuel in his ear a day before Saul came, saying, 16  To morrow about this time I will send thee a man out of the land of Benjamin, and thou shalt anoint him to be captain over my people Israel, that he may save my people out of the hand of the Philistines: for I have looked upon my people, because their cry is come unto me. 17  And when Samuel saw Saul, the LORD said unto him, Behold the man whom I spake to thee of! this same shall [†]reign over my people.

18  Then Saul drew near to Samuel in the gate, and said, Tell me, I pray thee, where the seer’s house is. 19  And Samuel answered Saul, and said, I am the seer: go up before me unto the high place; for ye shall eat with me to day, and to morrow I will let thee go, and will tell thee all that is in thine heart. 20  And as for thine asses that were lost [†]three days ago, set not thy mind on them; for they are found. And on whom is all the desire of Israel? Is it not on thee, and on all thy father’s house? 21  And Saul answered and said, Am not I a Benjamite, of the smallest of the tribes of Israel? and my family the least of all the families of the tribe of Benjamin? wherefore then speakest thou [†]so to me? 22  And Samuel took Saul and his servant, and brought them into the parlour, and made them sit in the chiefest place among them that were bidden, which were about thirty persons. 23  And Samuel said unto the cook, Bring the portion which I gave thee, of which I said unto thee, Set it by thee. 24  And the cook took up the shoulder, and that which was upon it, and set it before Saul. And Samuel said, Behold that which is [∥]left! set it before thee, and eat: for unto this time hath it been kept for thee since I said, I have invited the people. So Saul did eat with Samuel that day.

25 ¶ And when they were come down from the high place into the city, Samuel communed with Saul upon the top of the house. 26  And they arose early: and it came to pass about the spring of the day, that Samuel called Saul to the top of the house, saying, Up, that I may send thee away. And Saul arose, and they went out both of them, he and Samuel, abroad. 27  And as they were going down to the end of the city, Samuel said to Saul, Bid the servant pass on before us, (and he passed on,) but stand thou still [†]a while, that I may shew thee the word of God.

10

1  Then Samuel took a vial of oil, and poured it upon his head, and kissed him, and said, Is it not because the LORD hath anointed thee to be captain over his inheritance? 2  When thou art departed from me to day, then thou shalt find two men by [*]Rachel’s sepulchre in the border of Benjamin at Zelzah; and they will say unto thee, The asses which thou wentest to seek are found: and, lo, thy father hath left [†]the care of the asses, and sorroweth for you, saying, What shall I do for my son? 3  Then shalt thou go on forward from thence, and thou shalt come to the plain of Tabor, and there shall meet thee three men going up to God to Beth-el, one carrying three kids, and another carrying three loaves of bread, and another carrying a bottle of wine: 4  And they will [†]salute thee, and give thee two loaves of bread; which thou shalt receive of their hands. 5  After that thou shalt come to the hill of God, where is the garrison of the Philistines: and it shall come to pass, when thou art come thither to the city, that thou shalt meet a company of prophets coming down from the high place with a psaltery, and a tabret, and a pipe, and a harp, before them; and they shall prophesy: 6  And the Spirit of the LORD will come upon thee, and thou shalt prophesy with them, and shalt be turned into another man. 7  And [†]let it be, when these signs are come unto thee, [†]that thou do as occasion serve thee; for God is with thee. 8  And thou shalt go down before me to Gilgal; and, behold, I will come down unto thee, to offer burnt offerings, and to sacrifice sacrifices of peace offerings: [*]seven days shalt thou tarry, till I come to thee, and shew thee what thou shalt do.

9 ¶ And it was so, that when he had turned his [†]back to go from Samuel, God [†]gave him another heart: and all those signs came to pass that day. 10  And when they came thither to the hill, behold, a company [‡]of prophets met him; and the Spirit of God came upon him, and he prophesied among them. 11  And it came to pass, when all that knew him beforetime saw that, behold, he prophesied among the prophets, then the people said [†]one to another, What is this that is come unto the son of Kish? [*]Is Saul also among the prophets? 12  And one [†]of the same place answered and said, But who is their father? Therefore it became a proverb, Is Saul also among the prophets? 13  And when he had made an end of prophesying, he came to the high place.

14 ¶ And Saul’s uncle said unto him and to his servant, Whither went ye? And he said, To seek the asses: and when we saw that they were no where, we came to Samuel. 15  And Saul’s uncle said, Tell me, I pray thee, what Samuel said unto you. 16  And Saul said unto his uncle, He told us plainly that the asses were found. But of the matter of the kingdom, whereof Samuel spake, he told him not.

17 ¶ And Samuel called the people together unto the LORD to Mizpeh; 18  And said unto the children of Israel, Thus saith the LORD God of Israel, I brought up Israel out of Egypt, and delivered you out of the hand of the Egyptians, and out of the hand of all kingdoms, and of them that oppressed you: 19  And ye have this day rejected your God, who himself saved you out of all your adversities and your tribulations; and ye have said unto him, Nay, but set a king over us. Now therefore present yourselves before the LORD by your tribes, and by your thousands. 20  And when Samuel had caused all the tribes of Israel to come near, the tribe of Benjamin was taken. 21  When he had caused the tribe of Benjamin to come near by their families, the family of Matri was taken, and Saul the son of Kish was taken: and when they sought him, he could not be found. 22  Therefore they enquired of the LORD further, if the man should yet come thither. And the LORD answered, Behold, he hath hid himself among the stuff. 23  And they ran and fetched him thence: and when he stood among the people, he was higher than any of the people from [‡]his shoulders and upward. 24  And Samuel said to all the people, See ye him whom the LORD hath chosen, that there is none like him among all the people? And all the people shouted, and said, [†]God save the king. 25  Then Samuel told the people the manner of the kingdom, and wrote it in a book, and laid it up before the LORD. And Samuel sent all the people away, every man to his house.

26 ¶ And Saul also went home to Gibeah; and there went with him a band of men, whose hearts God had touched. 27  But the children of Belial said, How shall this man save us? And they despised him, and brought him no presents. But [∥]he held his peace.

11

1  Then Nahash the Ammonite came up, and encamped against Jabesh-gilead: and all the men of Jabesh said unto Nahash, Make a covenant with us, and we will serve thee. 2  And Nahash the Ammonite answered them, On this condition will I make a covenant with you, that I may thrust out all your right eyes, and lay it for a reproach upon all Israel. 3  And the elders of Jabesh said unto him, [†]Give us seven days’ respite, that we may send messengers unto all the coasts of Israel: and then, if there be no man to save us, we will come out to thee.

4 ¶ Then came the messengers to Gibeah of Saul, and told the tidings in the ears of the people: and all the people lifted up their voices, and wept.

5  And, behold, Saul came after the herd out of the field; and Saul said, What aileth the people that they weep? And they told him the tidings of the men of Jabesh. 6  And the Spirit of God came upon Saul when he heard those tidings, and his anger was kindled greatly. 7  And he took a yoke of oxen, and hewed them in pieces, and sent them throughout all the coasts of Israel by the hands of messengers, saying, Whosoever cometh not forth after Saul and after Samuel, so shall it be done unto his oxen. And the fear of the LORD fell on the people, and they came out [†]with one consent. 8  And when he numbered them in Bezek, the children of Israel were three hundred thousand, and the men of Judah thirty thousand. 9  And they said unto the messengers that came, Thus shall ye say unto the men of Jabesh-gilead, To morrow, by that time the sun be hot, ye shall have [∥]help. And the messengers came and shewed it to the men of Jabesh; and they were glad. 10  Therefore the men of Jabesh said, To morrow we will come out unto you, and ye shall do with us all that seemeth good unto you. 11 And it was so on the morrow, that Saul put the people in three companies; and they came into the midst of the host in the morning watch, and slew the Ammonites until the heat of the day: and it came to pass, that they which remained were scattered, so that two of them were not left together.

12 ¶ And the people said unto Samuel, Who is he that said, Shall Saul reign over us? bring the men, that we may put them to death. 13  And Saul said, There shall not a man be put to death this day: for to day the LORD hath wrought salvation in Israel. 14  Then said Samuel to the people, Come, and let us go to Gilgal, and renew the kingdom there. 15  And all the people went to Gilgal; and there they made Saul king before the LORD in Gilgal; and there they sacrificed sacrifices of peace offerings before the LORD; and there Saul and all the men of Israel rejoiced greatly.

12

1  And Samuel said unto all Israel, Behold, I have hearkened unto your voice in all that ye said unto me, and have made a king over you. 2  And now, behold, the king walketh before you: and I am old and grayheaded; and, behold, my sons are with you: and I have walked before you from my childhood unto this day. 3 Behold, [*]here I am: witness against me before the LORD, and before his anointed: whose ox have I taken? or whose ass have I taken? or whom have I defrauded? whom have I oppressed? or of whose hand have I received any [†]bribe [∥]to blind mine eyes therewith? and I will restore it you. 4  And they said, Thou hast not defrauded us, nor oppressed us, neither hast thou taken ought of any man’s hand. 5  And he said unto them, The LORD is witness against you, and his anointed is witness this day, that ye have not found ought in my hand. And they answered, He is witness.

6 ¶ And Samuel said unto the people, It is the LORD that [∥]advanced Moses and Aaron, and that brought your fathers up out of the land of Egypt. 7  Now therefore stand still, that I may reason with you before the LORD of all the [†]righteous acts of the LORD, which he did [†]to you and to your fathers. 8 [*] When Jacob was come into Egypt, and your fathers cried unto the LORD, then the LORD [*]sent Moses and Aaron, which brought forth your fathers out of Egypt, and made them dwell in this place. 9  And when they forgat the LORD their God, [*]he sold them into the hand of Sisera, captain of the host of Hazor, and into the hand of the Philistines, and into the hand of the king of Moab, and they fought against them. 10  And they cried unto the LORD, and said, We have sinned, because we have forsaken the LORD, and have served Baalim and Ashtaroth: but now deliver us out of the hand of our enemies, and we will serve thee. 11  And the LORD sent Jerubbaal, and Bedan, and [*]Jephthah, and Samuel, and delivered you out of the hand of your enemies on every side, and ye dwelled safe. 12  And when ye saw that Nahash the king of the children of Ammon came against you, ye said unto me, Nay; but a king shall reign over us: when the LORD your God was your king. 13  Now therefore behold the king whom ye have chosen, and whom ye have desired! and, behold, the LORD hath set a king over you. 14  If ye will fear the LORD, and serve him, and obey his voice, and not rebel against the [†]commandment of the LORD, then shall both ye and also the king that reigneth over you [†]continue following the LORD your God: 15  But if ye will not obey the voice of the LORD, but rebel against the commandment of the LORD, then shall the hand of the LORD be against you, as it was against your fathers.

16 ¶ Now therefore stand and see this great thing, which the LORD will do before your eyes. 17  Is it not wheat harvest to day? I will call unto the LORD, and he shall send thunder and rain; that ye may perceive and see that your wickedness is great, which ye have done in the sight of the LORD, in asking you a king. 18  So Samuel called unto the LORD; and the LORD sent thunder and rain that day: and all the people greatly feared the LORD and Samuel. 19  And all the people said unto Samuel, Pray for thy servants unto the LORD thy God, that we die not: for we have added unto all our sins this evil, to ask us a king.

20 ¶ And Samuel said unto the people, Fear not: ye have done all this wickedness: yet turn not aside from following the LORD, but serve the LORD with all your heart; 21  And turn ye not aside: for then should ye go after vain things, which cannot profit nor deliver; for they are vain. 22  For the LORD will not forsake his people for his great name’s sake: because it hath pleased the LORD to make you his people. 23  Moreover as for me, God forbid that I should sin against the LORD [†]in ceasing to pray for you: but I will teach you the good and the right way: 24  Only fear the LORD, and serve him in truth with all your heart: for consider [∥]how great things he hath done for you. 25  But if ye shall still do wickedly, ye shall be consumed, both ye and your king.

13

1  Saul [†]reigned one year; and when he had reigned two years over Israel, 2  Saul chose him three thousand men of Israel; whereof two thousand were with Saul in Michmash and in mount Beth-el, and a thousand were with Jonathan in Gibeah of Benjamin: and the rest of the people he sent every man to his tent. 3  And Jonathan smote the garrison of the Philistines that was in [∥]Geba, and the Philistines heard of it. And Saul blew the trumpet throughout all the land, saying, Let the Hebrews hear. 4  And all Israel heard say that Saul had smitten a garrison of the Philistines, and that Israel also [†]was had in abomination with the Philistines. And the people were called together after Saul to Gilgal.

5 ¶ And the Philistines gathered themselves together to fight with Israel, thirty thousand chariots, and six thousand horsemen, and people as the sand which is on the sea shore in multitude: and they came up, and pitched in Michmash, eastward from Beth-aven. 6  When the men of Israel saw that they were in a strait, (for the people were distressed,) then the people did hide themselves in caves, and in thickets, and in rocks, and in high places, and in pits. 7 And some of the Hebrews went over Jordan to the land of Gad and Gilead. As for Saul, he was yet in Gilgal, and all the people [†]followed him trembling.

8 ¶ [*]And he tarried seven days, according to the set time that Samuel had appointed: but Samuel came not to Gilgal; and the people were scattered from him. 9  And Saul said, Bring hither a burnt offering to me, and peace offerings. And he offered the burnt offering. 10  And it came to pass, that as soon as he had made an end of offering the burnt offering, behold, Samuel came; and Saul went out to meet him, that he might [†]salute him.

11 ¶ And Samuel said, What hast thou done? And Saul said, Because I saw that the people were scattered from me, and that thou camest not within the days appointed, and that the Philistines gathered themselves together at Michmash; 12  Therefore said I, The Philistines will come down now upon me to Gilgal, and I have not [†]made supplication unto the LORD: I forced myself therefore, and offered a burnt offering. 13  And Samuel said to Saul, Thou hast done foolishly: thou hast not kept the commandment of the LORD thy God, which he commanded thee: for now would the LORD have established thy kingdom upon Israel for ever. 14  But now thy kingdom shall not continue: the LORD hath sought him a man after his own heart, and the LORD hath commanded him to be captain over his people, because thou hast not kept that which the LORD commanded thee.

15  And Samuel arose, and gat him up from Gilgal unto Gibeah of Benjamin. And Saul numbered the people that were [†]present with him, about six hundred men. 16  And Saul, and Jonathan his son, and the people that were present with them, abode in Gibeah of Benjamin: but the Philistines encamped in Michmash.

17 ¶ And the spoilers came out of the camp of the Philistines in three companies: one company turned unto the way that leadeth to Ophrah, unto the land of Shual: 18  And another company turned the way to Beth-horon: and another company turned to the way of the border that looketh to the valley of Zeboim toward the wilderness.

19 ¶ Now there was no smith found throughout all the land of Israel: for the Philistines said, Lest the Hebrews make them swords or spears: 20  But all the Israelites went down to the Philistines, to sharpen every man his share, and his coulter, and his axe, and his mattock. 21  Yet they had [†]a file for the mattocks, and for the coulters, and for the forks, and for the axes, and [†]to sharpen the goads. 22  So it came to pass in the day of battle, that there was neither sword nor spear found in the hand of any of the people that were with Saul and Jonathan: but with Saul and with Jonathan his son was there found. 23  And the [∥]garrison of the Philistines went out to the passage of Michmash.

14

1  Now [∥]it came to pass upon a day, that Jonathan the son of Saul said unto the young man that bare his armour, Come, and let us go over to the Philistines’ garrison, that is on the other side. But he told not his father. 2  And Saul tarried in the uttermost part of Gibeah under a pomegranate tree which is in Migron: and the people that were with him were about six hundred men; 3  And Ahiah, the son of Ahitub, [*]I-chabod’s brother, the son of Phinehas, the son of Eli, the LORD’s priest in Shiloh, wearing an ephod. And the people knew not that Jonathan was gone.

4 ¶ And between the passages, by which Jonathan sought to go over unto the Philistines’ garrison, there was a sharp rock on the one side, and a sharp rock on the other side: and the name of the one was Bozez, and the name of the other Seneh. 5  The [†]forefront of the one was situate northward over against Michmash, and the other southward over against Gibeah. 6  And Jonathan said to the young man that bare his armour, Come, and let us go over unto the garrison of these uncircumcised: it may be that the LORD will work for us: for there is no restraint to the LORD [*]to save by many or by few. 7  And his armourbearer said unto him, Do all that is in thine heart: turn thee; behold, I am with thee according to thy heart. 8  Then said Jonathan, Behold, we will pass over unto these men, and we will discover ourselves unto them. 9  If they say thus unto us, [†]Tarry until we come to you; then we will stand still in our place, and will not go up unto them. 10  But if they say thus, Come up unto us; then we will go up: for [*]the LORD hath delivered them into our hand: and this shall be a sign unto us. 11  And both of them discovered themselves unto the garrison of the Philistines: and the Philistines said, Behold, the Hebrews come forth out of the holes where they had hid themselves. 12  And the men of the garrison answered Jonathan and his armourbearer, and said, Come up to us, and we will shew you a thing. And Jonathan said unto his armourbearer, Come up after me: for the LORD hath delivered them into the hand of Israel. 13  And Jonathan climbed up upon his hands and upon his feet, and his armourbearer after him: and they fell before Jonathan; and his armourbearer slew after him. 14  And that first slaughter, which Jonathan and his armourbearer made, was about twenty men, within as it were [∥]an half acre of land, which a yoke of oxen might plow. 15  And there was trembling in the host, in the field, and among all the people: the garrison, and the spoilers, they also trembled, and the earth quaked: so it was [†]a very great trembling.

16  And the watchmen of Saul in Gibeah of Benjamin looked; and, behold, the multitude melted away, and they went on beating down one another. 17  Then said Saul unto the people that were with him, Number now, and see who is gone from us. And when they had numbered, behold, Jonathan and his armourbearer were not there. 18  And Saul said unto Ahiah, Bring hither the ark of God. For the ark of God was at that time with the children of Israel.

19 ¶ And it came to pass, while Saul talked unto the priest, that the [∥]noise that was in the host of the Philistines went on and increased: and Saul said unto the priest, Withdraw thine hand. 20  And Saul and all the people that were with him [†]assembled themselves, and they came to the battle: and, behold, [*]every man’s sword was against his fellow, and there was a very great discomfiture. 21  Moreover the Hebrews that were with the Philistines before that time, which went up with them into the camp from the country round about, even they also turned to be with the Israelites that were with Saul and Jonathan. 22  Likewise all the men of Israel which had hid themselves in mount Ephraim, when they heard that the Philistines fled, even they also followed hard after them in the battle. 23  So the LORD saved Israel that day: and the battle passed over unto Beth-aven.

24 ¶ And the men of Israel were distressed that day: for Saul had adjured the people, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth any food until evening, that I may be avenged on mine enemies. So none of the people tasted any food. 25 And all they of the land came to a wood; and there was honey upon the ground. 26  And when the people were come into the wood, behold, the honey dropped; but no man put his hand to his mouth: for the people feared the oath. 27  But Jonathan heard not when his father charged the people with the oath: wherefore he put forth the end of the rod that was in his hand, and dipped it in an honeycomb, and put his hand to his mouth; and his eyes were enlightened. 28  Then answered one of the people, and said, Thy father straitly charged the people with an oath, saying, Cursed be the man that eateth any food this day. And the people were [∥]faint. 29  Then said Jonathan, My father hath troubled the land: see, I pray you, how mine eyes have been enlightened, because I tasted a little of this honey. 30  How much more, if haply the people had eaten freely to day of the spoil of their enemies which they found? for had there not been now a much greater slaughter among the Philistines? 31  And they smote the Philistines that day from Michmash to Aijalon: and the people were very faint. 32  And the people flew upon the spoil, and took sheep, and oxen, and calves, and slew them on the ground: and the people did eat them [*]with the blood.

33 ¶ Then they told Saul, saying, Behold, the people sin against the LORD, in that they eat with the blood. And he said, Ye have [∥]transgressed: roll a great stone unto me this day. 34  And Saul said, Disperse yourselves among the people, and say unto them, Bring me hither every man his ox, and every man his sheep, and slay them here, and eat; and sin not against the LORD in eating with the blood. And all the people brought every man his ox [†]with him that night, and slew them there. 35  And Saul built an altar unto the LORD: [†]the same was the first altar that he built unto the LORD.

36 ¶ And Saul said, Let us go down after the Philistines by night, and spoil them until the morning light, and let us not leave a man of them. And they said, Do whatsoever seemeth good unto thee. Then said the priest, Let us draw near hither unto God. 37  And Saul asked counsel of God, Shall I go down after the Philistines? wilt thou deliver them into the hand of Israel? But he answered him not that day. 38  And Saul said, Draw ye near hither, [*]all the [†]chief of the people: and know and see wherein this sin hath been this day. 39 For, as the LORD liveth, which saveth Israel, though it be in Jonathan my son, he shall surely die. But there was not a man among all the people that answered him. 40  Then said he unto all Israel, Be ye on one side, and I and Jonathan my son will be on the other side. And the people said unto Saul, Do what seemeth good unto thee. 41  Therefore Saul said unto the LORD God of Israel, [∥]Give a perfect lot. And Saul and Jonathan were taken: but the people [†]escaped. 42  And Saul said, Cast lots between me and Jonathan my son. And Jonathan was taken. 43  Then Saul said to Jonathan, Tell me what thou hast done. And Jonathan told him, and said, I did but taste a little honey with the end of the rod that was in mine hand, and, lo, I must die. 44  And Saul answered, God do so and more also: for thou shalt surely die, Jonathan. 45  And the people said unto Saul, Shall Jonathan die, who hath wrought this great salvation in Israel? God forbid: as the LORD liveth, there shall not one hair of his head fall to the ground; for he hath wrought with God this day. So the people rescued Jonathan, that he died not. 46  Then Saul went up from following the Philistines: and the Philistines went to their own place.

47 ¶ So Saul took the kingdom over Israel, and fought against all his enemies on every side, against Moab, and against the children of Ammon, and against Edom, and against the kings of Zobah, and against the Philistines: and whithersoever he turned himself, he vexed them. 48  And he [∥]gathered an host, and smote the Amalekites, and delivered Israel out of the hands of them that spoiled them. 49  Now the sons of Saul were Jonathan, and Ishui, and Melchi-shua: and the names of his two daughters were these; the name of the firstborn Merab, and the name of the younger Michal: 50  And the name of Saul’s wife was Ahinoam, the daughter of Ahimaaz: and the name of the captain of his host was Abner, the son of Ner, Saul’s uncle. 51  And Kish was the father of Saul; and Ner the father of Abner was the son of Abiel. 52  And there was sore war against the Philistines all the days of Saul: and when Saul saw any strong man, or any valiant man, he took him unto him.

15

1  Samuel also said unto Saul, [*]The LORD sent me to anoint thee to be king over his people, over Israel: now therefore hearken thou unto the voice of the words of the LORD. 2  Thus saith the LORD of hosts, I remember that which Amalek did to Israel, [*]how he laid wait for him in the way, when he came up from Egypt. 3  Now go and smite Amalek, and utterly destroy all that they have, and spare them not; but slay both man and woman, infant and suckling, ox and sheep, camel and ass. 4  And Saul gathered the people together, and numbered them in Telaim, two hundred thousand footmen, and ten thousand men of Judah. 5  And Saul came to a city of Amalek, and [∥]laid wait in the valley.

6 ¶ And Saul said unto the Kenites, Go, depart, get you down from among the Amalekites, lest I destroy you with them: for ye shewed kindness to all the children of Israel, when they came up out of Egypt. So the Kenites departed from among the Amalekites. 7  And Saul smote the Amalekites from Havilah until thou comest to Shur, that is over against Egypt. 8  And he took Agag the king of the Amalekites alive, and utterly destroyed all the people with the edge of the sword. 9  But Saul and the people spared Agag, and the best of the sheep, and of the oxen, and [∥]of the fatlings, and the lambs, and all that was good, and would not utterly destroy them: but every thing that was vile and refuse, that they destroyed utterly.

10 ¶ Then came the word of the LORD unto Samuel, saying, 11  It repenteth me that I have set up Saul to be king: for he is turned back from following me, and hath not performed my commandments. And it grieved Samuel; and he cried unto the LORD all night. 12  And when Samuel rose early to meet Saul in the morning, it was told Samuel, saying, Saul came to Carmel, and, behold, he set him up a place, and is gone about, and passed on, and gone down to Gilgal. 13  And Samuel came to Saul: and Saul said unto him, Blessed be thou of the LORD: I have performed the commandment of the LORD. 14  And Samuel said, What meaneth then this bleating of the sheep in mine ears, and the lowing of the oxen which I hear? 15  And Saul said, They have brought them from the Amalekites: for the people spared the best of the sheep and of the oxen, to sacrifice unto the LORD thy God; and the rest we have utterly destroyed. 16  Then Samuel said unto Saul, Stay, and I will tell thee what the LORD hath said to me this night. And he said unto him, Say on. 17  And Samuel said, When thou wast little in thine own sight, wast thou not made the head of the tribes of Israel, and the LORD anointed thee king over Israel? 18  And the LORD sent thee on a journey, and said, Go and utterly destroy the sinners the Amalekites, and fight against them until [†]they be consumed. 19  Wherefore then didst thou not obey the voice of the LORD, but didst fly upon the spoil, and didst evil in the sight of the LORD? 20  And Saul said unto Samuel, Yea, I have obeyed the voice of the LORD, and have gone the way which the LORD sent me, and have brought Agag the king of Amalek, and have utterly destroyed the Amalekites. 21  But the people took of the spoil, sheep and oxen, the chief of the things which should have been utterly destroyed, to sacrifice unto the LORD thy God in Gilgal. 22  And Samuel said, Hath the LORD as great delight in burnt offerings and sacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the LORD? Behold, [*]to obey is better than sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of rams. 23  For rebellion is as the sin of [†]witchcraft, and stubbornness is as iniquity and idolatry. Because thou hast rejected the word of the LORD, he hath also rejected thee from being king.

24 ¶ And Saul said unto Samuel, I have sinned: for I have transgressed the commandment of the LORD, and thy words: because I feared the people, and obeyed their voice. 25  Now therefore, I pray thee, pardon my sin, and turn again with me, that I may worship the LORD. 26  And Samuel said unto Saul, I will not return with thee: for thou hast rejected the word of the LORD, and the LORD hath rejected thee from being king over Israel. 27  And as Samuel turned about to go away, he laid hold upon the skirt of his mantle, and it rent. 28  And Samuel said unto him, The LORD hath rent the kingdom of Israel from thee this day, and hath given it to a neighbour of thine, that is better than thou. 29  And also the [∥]Strength of Israel will not lie nor repent: for he is not a man, that he should repent. 30  Then he said, I have sinned: yet honour me now, I pray thee, before the elders of my people, and before Israel, and turn again with me, that I may worship the LORD thy God. 31  So Samuel turned again after Saul; and Saul worshipped the LORD.

32 ¶ Then said Samuel, Bring ye hither to me Agag the king of the Amalekites. And Agag came unto him delicately. And Agag said, Surely the bitterness of death is past. 33  And Samuel said, [*]As thy sword hath made women childless, so shall thy mother be childless among women. And Samuel hewed Agag in pieces before the LORD in Gilgal.

34 ¶ Then Samuel went to Ramah; and Saul went up to his house to Gibeah of Saul. 35  And Samuel came no more to see Saul until the day of his death: nevertheless Samuel mourned for Saul: and the LORD repented that he had made Saul king over Israel.

16

1  And the LORD said unto Samuel, How long wilt thou mourn for Saul, seeing I have rejected him from reigning over Israel? fill thine horn with oil, and go, I will send thee to Jesse the Beth-lehemite: for I have provided me a king among his sons. 2  And Samuel said, How can I go? if Saul hear it, he will kill me. And the LORD said, Take an heifer [†]with thee, and say, I am come to sacrifice to the LORD. 3  And call Jesse to the sacrifice, and I will shew thee what thou shalt do: and thou shalt anoint unto me him whom I name unto thee. 4  And Samuel did that which the LORD spake, and came to Beth-lehem. And the elders of the town trembled at his [†]coming, and said, Comest thou peaceably? 5  And he said, Peaceably: I am come to sacrifice unto the LORD: sanctify yourselves, and come with me to the sacrifice. And he sanctified Jesse and his sons, and called them to the sacrifice.

6 ¶ And it came to pass, when they were come, that he looked on Eliab, and said, Surely the LORD’s anointed is before him. 7  But the LORD said unto Samuel, Look not on his countenance, or on the height of his stature; because I have refused him: for the Lord seeth not as man seeth; for man looketh on the [†]outward appearance, but the LORD looketh on the [*]heart. 8  Then Jesse called Abinadab, and made him pass before Samuel. And he said, Neither hath the LORD chosen this. 9  Then Jesse made Shammah to pass by. And he said, Neither hath the LORD chosen this. 10  Again, Jesse made seven of his sons to pass before Samuel. And Samuel said unto Jesse, The LORD hath not chosen these. 11  And Samuel said unto Jesse, Are here all thy children? And he said, There remaineth yet the youngest, and, behold, he keepeth the sheep. And Samuel said unto Jesse, [*]Send and fetch him: for we will not sit [†]down till he come hither. 12  And he sent, and brought him in. Now he was ruddy, and withal [†]of a beautiful countenance, and goodly to look to. And the LORD said, Arise, anoint him: for this is he. 13  Then Samuel took the horn of oil, and anointed him in the midst of his brethren: and the Spirit of the LORD came upon David from that day forward. So Samuel rose up, and went to Ramah.

14 ¶ But the Spirit of the LORD departed from Saul, and an evil spirit from the LORD [∥]troubled him. 15  And Saul’s servants said unto him, Behold now, an evil spirit from God troubleth thee. 16  Let our lord now command thy servants, which are before thee, to seek out a man, who is a cunning player on an harp: and it shall come to pass, when the evil spirit from God is upon thee, that he shall play with his hand, and thou shalt be well. 17  And Saul said unto his servants, Provide me now a man that can play well, and bring him to me. 18  Then answered one of the servants, and said, Behold, I have seen a son of Jesse the Beth-lehemite, that is cunning in playing, and a mighty valiant man, and a man of war, and prudent in [∥]matters, and a comely person, and the LORD is with him.

19 ¶ Wherefore Saul sent messengers unto Jesse, and said, Send me David thy son, which is with the sheep. 20  And Jesse took an ass laden with bread, and a bottle of wine, and a kid, and sent them by David his son unto Saul. 21  And David came to Saul, and stood before him: and he loved him greatly; and he became his armourbearer. 22  And Saul sent to Jesse, saying, Let David, I pray thee, stand before me; for he hath found favour in my sight. 23 And it came to pass, when the evil spirit from God was upon Saul, that David took an harp, and played with his hand: so Saul was refreshed, and was well, and the evil spirit departed from him.

17

1  Now the Philistines gathered together their armies to battle, and were gathered together at Shochoh, which belongeth to Judah, and pitched between Shochoh and Azekah, in [∥]Ephes-dammim. 2  And Saul and the men of Israel were gathered together, and pitched by the valley of Elah, and [†]set the battle in array against the Philistines. 3  And the Philistines stood on a mountain on the one side, and Israel stood on a mountain on the other side: and there was a valley between them.

4 ¶ And there went out a champion out of the camp of the Philistines, named Goliath, of Gath, whose height was six cubits and a span. 5 And he had an helmet of brass upon his head, and he was [†]armed with a coat of mail; and the weight of the coat was five thousand shekels of brass. 6 And he had greaves of brass upon his legs, and a [∥]target of brass between his shoulders. 7  And the staff of his spear was like a weaver’s beam; and his spear’s head weighed six hundred shekels of iron: and one bearing a shield went before him. 8  And he stood and cried unto the armies of Israel, and said unto them, Why are ye come out to set your battle in array? am not I a Philistine, and ye servants to Saul? choose you a man for you, and let him come down to me. 9  If he be able to fight with me, and to kill me, then will we be your servants: but if I prevail against him, and kill him, then shall ye be our servants, and serve us. 10  And the Philistine said, I defy the armies of Israel this day; give me a man, that we may fight together. 11  When Saul and all Israel heard those words of the Philistine, they were dismayed, and greatly afraid.

12 ¶ Now David was [*]the son of that Ephrathite of Beth-lehem-judah, whose name was Jesse; and he had eight sons: and the man went among men for an old man in the days of Saul. 13  And the three eldest sons of Jesse went and followed Saul to the battle: and the names of his three sons that went to the battle were Eliab the firstborn, and next unto him Abinadab, and the third Shammah. 14  And David was the youngest: and the three eldest followed Saul. 15  But David went and returned from Saul to feed his father’s sheep at Beth-lehem. 16  And the Philistine drew near morning and evening, and presented himself forty days. 17  And Jesse said unto David his son, Take now for thy brethren an ephah of this parched corn, and these ten loaves, and run to the camp to thy brethren; 18  And carry these ten [†]cheeses unto the [†]captain of their thousand, and look how thy brethren fare, and take their pledge. 19  Now Saul, and they, and all the men of Israel, were in the valley of Elah, fighting with the Philistines.

20 ¶ And David rose up early in the morning, and left the sheep with a keeper, and took, and went, as Jesse had commanded him; and he came to the [∥]trench, as the host was going forth to the [∥]fight, and shouted for the battle. 21  For Israel and the Philistines had put the battle in array, army against army. 22  And David left [†]his carriage in the hand of the keeper of the carriage, and ran into the army, and came and [†]saluted his brethren. 23  And as he talked with them, behold, there came up the champion, the Philistine of Gath, Goliath by name, out of the armies of the Philistines, and spake according to the same words: and David heard them. 24  And all the men of Israel, when they saw the man, fled [†]from him, and were sore afraid. 25  And the men of Israel said, Have ye seen this man that is come up? surely to defy Israel is he come up: and it shall be, that the man who killeth him, the king will enrich him with great riches, and [*]will give him his daughter, and make his father’s house free in Israel. 26  And David spake to the men that stood by him, saying, What shall be done to the man that killeth this Philistine, and taketh away the reproach from Israel? for who is this uncircumcised Philistine, that he should defy the armies of the living God? 27  And the people answered him after this manner, saying, So shall it be done to the man that killeth him.

28 ¶ And Eliab his eldest brother heard when he spake unto the men; and Eliab’s anger was kindled against David, and he said, Why camest thou down hither? and with whom hast thou left those few sheep in the wilderness? I know thy pride, and the naughtiness of thine heart; for thou art come down that thou mightest see the battle. 29  And David said, What have I now done? Is there not a cause?

30 ¶ And he turned from him toward another, and spake after the same [†]manner: and the people answered him again after the former manner.

31  And when the words were heard which David spake, they rehearsed them before Saul: and he [†]sent for him.

32 ¶ And David said to Saul, Let no man’s heart fail because of him; thy servant will go and fight with this Philistine. 33  And Saul said to David, Thou art not able to go against this Philistine to fight with him: for thou art but a youth, and he a man of war from his youth. 34  And David said unto Saul, Thy servant kept his father’s sheep, and there came a lion, and a bear, and took a [∥]lamb out of the flock: 35  And I went out after him, and smote him, and delivered it out of his mouth: and when he arose against me, I caught him by his beard, and smote him, and slew him. 36  Thy servant slew both the lion and the bear: and this uncircumcised Philistine shall be as one of them, seeing he hath defied the armies of the living God. 37  David said moreover, The LORD that delivered me out of the paw of the lion, and out of the paw of the bear, he will deliver me out of the hand of this Philistine. And Saul said unto David, Go, and the LORD be with thee.

38 ¶ And Saul [†]armed David with his armour, and he put an helmet of brass upon his head; also he armed him with a coat of mail. 39  And David girded his sword upon his armour, and he assayed to go; for he had not proved it. And David said unto Saul, I cannot go with these; for I have not proved them. And David put them off him.

40  And he took his staff in his hand, and chose him five smooth stones out of the [∥]brook, and put them in a shepherd’s [†]bag which he had, even in a scrip; and his sling was in his hand: and he drew near to the Philistine. 41  And the Philistine came on and drew near unto David; and the man that bare the shield went before him. 42  And when the Philistine looked about, and saw David, he disdained him: for he was but a youth, and ruddy, and of a fair countenance. 43  And the Philistine said unto David, Am I a dog, that thou comest to me with staves? And the Philistine cursed David by his gods. 44  And the Philistine said to David, Come to me, and I will give thy flesh unto the fowls of the air, and to the beasts of the field. 45  Then said David to the Philistine, Thou comest to me with a sword, and with a spear, and with a shield: but I come to thee in the name of the LORD of hosts, the God of the armies of Israel, whom thou hast defied. 46  This day will the LORD [†]deliver thee into mine hand; and I will smite thee, and take thine head from thee; and I will give the carcases of the host of the Philistines this day unto the fowls of the air, and to the wild beasts of the earth; that all the earth may know that there is a God in Israel. 47  And all this assembly shall know that the LORD saveth not with sword and spear: for the battle is the LORD’s, and he will give you into our hands.

48  And it came to pass, when the Philistine arose, and came and drew nigh to meet David, that David hasted, and ran toward the army to meet the Philistine. 49  And David put his hand in his bag, and took thence a stone, and slang it, and smote the Philistine in his forehead, that the stone sunk into his forehead; and he fell upon his face to the earth. 50  So [*]David prevailed over the Philistine with a sling and with a stone, and smote the Philistine, and slew him; but there was no sword in the hand of David. 51  Therefore David ran, and stood upon the Philistine, and took his sword, and drew it out of the sheath thereof, and slew him, and cut off his head therewith. And when the Philistines saw their champion was dead, they fled. 52  And the men of Israel and of Judah arose, and shouted, and pursued the Philistines, until thou come to the valley, and to the gates of Ekron. And the wounded of the Philistines fell down by the way to Shaaraim, even unto Gath, and unto Ekron. 53  And the children of Israel returned from chasing after the Philistines, and they spoiled their tents. 54  And David took the head of the Philistine, and brought it to Jerusalem; but he put his armour in his tent.

55 ¶ And when Saul saw David go forth against the Philistine, he said unto Abner, the captain of the host, Abner, whose son is this youth? And Abner said, As thy soul liveth, O king, I cannot tell. 56  And the king said, Enquire thou whose son the stripling is. 57  And as David returned from the slaughter of the Philistine, Abner took him, and brought him before Saul with the head of the Philistine in his hand. 58  And Saul said to him, Whose son art thou, thou young man? And David answered, I am the son of thy servant Jesse the Beth-lehemite.

18

1  And it came to pass, when he [‡]had made an end of speaking unto Saul, that the soul of Jonathan was knit with the soul of David, and Jonathan loved him as his own soul. 2  And Saul took him that day, and would let him go no more home to his father’s house. 3  Then Jonathan and David made a covenant, because he loved him as his own soul. 4  And Jonathan stripped himself of the robe that was upon him, and gave it to David, and his garments, even to his sword, and to his bow, and to his girdle.

5 ¶ And David went out whithersoever Saul sent him, and [∥]behaved himself wisely: and Saul set him over the men of war, and he was accepted in the sight of all the people, and also in the sight of Saul’s servants.

6  And it came to pass as they came, when David was returned from the slaughter of the [∥]Philistine, that the women came out of all cities of Israel, singing and dancing, to meet king Saul, with tabrets, with joy, and with [†]instruments of musick. 7  And the women answered one another as they played, and said, [*]Saul hath slain his thousands, and David his ten thousands. 8  And Saul was very wroth, and the saying [†]displeased him; and he said, They have ascribed unto David ten thousands, and to me they have ascribed but thousands: and what can he have more but the kingdom? 9  And Saul eyed David from that day and forward.

10 ¶ And it came to pass on the morrow, that the evil spirit from God came upon Saul, and he prophesied in the midst of the house: and David played with his hand, as at other times: and there was a javelin in Saul’s hand. 11  And Saul cast the javelin; for he said, I will smite David even to the wall with it. And David avoided out of his presence twice.

12 ¶ And Saul was afraid of David, because the LORD was with him, and was departed from Saul. 13  Therefore Saul removed him from him, and made him his captain over a thousand; and he went out and came in before the people. 14  And David [∥]behaved himself wisely in all his ways; and the LORD was with him. 15  Wherefore when Saul saw that he behaved himself very wisely, he was afraid of him. 16  But all Israel and Judah loved David, because he went out and came in before them.

17 ¶ And Saul said to David, Behold my elder daughter Merab, her will I give thee to wife: only be thou [†]valiant for me, and fight the LORD’s battles. For Saul said, Let not mine hand be upon him, but let the hand of the Philistines be upon him. 18  And David said unto Saul, Who am I? and what is my life, or my father’s family in Israel, that I should be son in law to the king? 19  But it came to pass at the time when Merab Saul’s daughter should have been given to David, that she was given unto Adriel the Meholathite to wife. 20  And Michal Saul’s daughter loved David: and they told Saul, and the thing [†]pleased him. 21  And Saul said, I will give him her, that she may be a snare to him, and that the hand of the Philistines may be against him. Wherefore Saul said to David, Thou shalt this day be my son in law in the one of the twain.

22 ¶ And Saul commanded his servants, saying, Commune with David secretly, and say, Behold, the king hath delight in thee, and all his servants love thee: now therefore be the king’s son in law. 23  And Saul’s servants spake those words in the ears of David. And David said, Seemeth it to you a light thing to be a king’s son in law, seeing that I am a poor man, and lightly esteemed? 24  And the servants of Saul told him, saying, [†]On this manner spake David. 25  And Saul said, Thus shall ye say to David, The king desireth not any dowry, but an hundred foreskins of the Philistines, to be avenged of the king’s enemies. But Saul thought to make David fall by the hand of the Philistines. 26  And when his servants told David these words, it pleased David well to be the king’s son in law: and the days were not [†]expired. 27  Wherefore David arose [‡]and went, he and his men, and slew of the Philistines two hundred men; and David brought their foreskins, and they gave them in full tale to the king, that he might be the king’s son in law. And Saul gave him Michal his daughter to wife.

28 ¶ And Saul saw and knew that the LORD was with David, and that Michal Saul’s daughter loved him. 29  And Saul was yet the more afraid of David; and Saul became David’s enemy continually. 30  Then the princes of the Philistines went forth: and it came to pass, after they went forth, that David behaved himself more wisely than all the servants of Saul; so that his name was much [†]set by.

19

1  And Saul spake to Jonathan his son, and to all his servants, that they should kill David. 2  But Jonathan Saul’s son delighted much in David: and Jonathan told David, saying, Saul my father seeketh to kill thee: now therefore, I pray thee, take heed to thyself until the morning, and abide in a secret place, and hide thyself: 3  And I will go out and stand beside my father in the field where thou art, and I will commune with my father of thee; and what I see, that I will tell thee.

4 ¶ And Jonathan spake good of David unto Saul his father, and said unto him, Let not the king sin against his servant, against David; because he hath not sinned against thee, and because his works have been to thee-ward very good: 5  For he did put his [*]life in his hand, and slew the Philistine, and the LORD wrought a great salvation for all Israel: thou sawest it, and didst rejoice: wherefore then wilt thou sin against innocent blood, to slay David without a cause? 6  And Saul hearkened unto the voice of Jonathan: and Saul sware, As the LORD liveth, he shall not be slain. 7  And Jonathan called David, and Jonathan shewed him all those things. And Jonathan brought David to Saul, and he was in his presence, as [†]in times past.

8 ¶ And there was war again: and David went out, and fought with the Philistines, and slew them with a great slaughter; and they fled from [†]him. 9  And the evil spirit from the LORD was upon Saul, as he sat in his house with his javelin in his hand: and David played with his hand. 10  And Saul sought to smite David even to the wall with the javelin; but he slipped away out of Saul’s presence, and he smote the javelin into the wall: and David fled, and escaped that night.

11  Saul also sent messengers unto David’s house, to watch him, and to slay him in the morning: and Michal David’s wife told him, saying, If thou save not thy life to night, to morrow thou shalt be slain.

12 ¶ So Michal let David down through a window: and he went, and fled, and escaped. 13  And Michal took an image, and laid it in the bed, and put a pillow of goats’ hair for his bolster, and covered it with a cloth. 14  And when Saul sent messengers to take David, she said, He is sick. 15  And Saul sent the messengers again to see David, saying, Bring him up to me in the bed, that I may slay him. 16  And when the messengers were come in, behold, there was an image in the bed, with a pillow of goats’ hair for his bolster. 17  And Saul said unto Michal, Why hast thou deceived me so, and sent away mine enemy, that he is escaped? And Michal answered Saul, He said unto me, Let me go; why should I kill thee?

18 ¶ So David fled, and escaped, and came to Samuel to Ramah, and told him all that Saul had done to him. And he and Samuel went and dwelt in Naioth. 19  And it was told Saul, saying, Behold, David is at Naioth in Ramah. 20  And Saul sent messengers to take David: and when they saw the company of the prophets prophesying, and Samuel standing as appointed over them, the Spirit of God was upon the messengers of Saul, and they also prophesied. 21  And when it was told Saul, he sent other messengers, and they prophesied likewise. And Saul sent messengers again the third time, and they prophesied also. 22  Then went he also to Ramah, and came to a great well that is in Sechu: and he asked and said, Where are Samuel and David? And one said, Behold, they be at Naioth in Ramah. 23  And he went thither to Naioth in Ramah: and the Spirit of God was upon him also, and he went on, and prophesied, until he came to Naioth in Ramah. 24  And he stripped off his clothes also, and prophesied before Samuel in like manner, and [†]lay down naked all that day and all that night. Wherefore they say, [*]Is Saul also among the prophets?

20

1  And David fled from Naioth in Ramah, and came and said before Jonathan, What have I done? what is mine iniquity? and what is my sin before thy father, that he seeketh my life? 2  And he said unto him, God forbid; thou shalt not die: behold, my father will do nothing either great or small, but that he will [†]shew it me: and why should my father hide this thing from me? it is not so. 3  And David sware moreover, and said, Thy father certainly knoweth that I have found grace in thine eyes; and he saith, Let not Jonathan know this, lest he be grieved: but truly as the LORD liveth, and as thy soul liveth, there is but a step between me and death. 4  Then said Jonathan unto David, [∥]Whatsoever thy soul [†]desireth, I will even do it for thee. 5  And David said unto Jonathan, Behold, to morrow is the new moon, and I should not fail to sit with the king at meat: but let me go, that I may hide myself in the [‡]field unto the third day at even. 6  If thy father at all miss me, then say, David earnestly asked leave of me that he might run to Beth-lehem his city: for there is a yearly sacrifice there for all the family. 7  If he say thus, It is well; thy servant shall have peace: but if he be very wroth, then be sure that evil is determined by him. 8  Therefore thou shalt deal kindly with thy servant; for [*]thou hast brought thy servant into a covenant of the LORD with thee: notwithstanding, if there be in me iniquity, slay me thyself; for why shouldest thou bring me to thy father?

9  And Jonathan said, Far be it from thee: for if I knew certainly that evil were determined by my father to come upon thee, then would not I tell it thee? 10  Then said David to Jonathan, Who shall tell me? or what if thy father answer thee roughly?

11 ¶ And Jonathan said unto David, Come, and let us go out into the field. And they went out both of them into the field. 12  And Jonathan said unto David, O LORD God of Israel, when I have [†]sounded my father about to morrow any time, or the third day, and, behold, if there be good toward David, and I then send not unto thee, and [†]shew it thee; 13  The LORD do so and much more to Jonathan: but if it please my father to do thee evil, then I will shew it thee, and send thee away, that thou mayest go in peace: and the LORD be with thee, as he hath been with my father. 14  And thou shalt not only while yet I live shew me the kindness of the LORD, that I die not: 15 But also thou shalt not cut off thy kindness from my house for ever: no, not when the LORD hath cut off the enemies of David every one from the face of the earth. 16  So Jonathan [†]made a covenant with the house of David, saying, Let the LORD even require it at the hand of David’s enemies. 17  And Jonathan caused David to swear again, [∥]because he loved him: for he loved him as he loved his own soul. 18  Then Jonathan said to David, To morrow is the new moon: and thou shalt be missed, because thy seat will be [†]empty. 19 And when thou hast stayed three days, then thou shalt go down [∥][†]quickly, and come to the place where thou didst hide thyself [†]when the business was in hand, and shalt remain by the stone [∥]Ezel. 20  And I will shoot three arrows on the side thereof, as though I shot at a mark. 21  And, behold, I will send a lad, saying, Go, find out the arrows. If I expressly say unto the lad, Behold, the arrows are on this side of thee, take them; then come thou: for there is peace to thee, and [†]no hurt; as the LORD liveth. 22  But if I say thus unto the young man, Behold, the arrows are beyond thee; go thy way: for the LORD hath sent thee away. 23 And as touching the matter which thou and I have spoken of, behold, the LORD be between thee and me for ever.

24 ¶ So David hid himself in the field: and when the new moon was come, the king sat him down to eat meat. 25  And the king sat upon his seat, as at other times, even upon a seat by the wall: and Jonathan arose, and Abner sat by Saul’s side, and David’s place was empty. 26  Nevertheless Saul spake not any thing that day: for he thought, Something hath befallen him, he is not clean; surely he is not clean. 27  And it came to pass on the morrow, which was the second day of the month, that David’s place was empty: and Saul said unto Jonathan his son, Wherefore cometh not the son of Jesse to meat, neither yesterday, nor to day? 28  And Jonathan answered Saul, David earnestly asked leave of me to go to Beth-lehem: 29  And he said, Let me go, I pray thee; for our family hath a sacrifice in the city; and my brother, he hath commanded me to be there: and now, if I have found favour in thine eyes, let me get away, I pray thee, and see my brethren. Therefore he cometh not unto the king’s table. 30  Then Saul’s anger was kindled against Jonathan, and he said unto him, [∥][†]Thou son of the perverse rebellious woman, do not I know that thou hast chosen the son of Jesse to thine own confusion, and unto the confusion of thy mother’s nakedness? 31  For as long as the son of Jesse liveth upon the ground, thou shalt not be established, nor thy kingdom. Wherefore now send and fetch him unto me, for he [†]shall surely die. 32  And Jonathan answered Saul his father, and said unto him, Wherefore shall he be slain? what hath he done? 33  And Saul cast a javelin at him to smite him: whereby Jonathan knew that it was determined of his father to slay David. 34  So Jonathan arose from the table in fierce anger, and did eat no meat the second day of the month: for he was grieved for David, because his father had done him shame.

35 ¶ And it came to pass in the morning, that Jonathan went out into the field at the time appointed with David, and a little lad with him. 36  And he said unto his lad, Run, find out now the arrows which I shoot. And as the lad ran, he shot an arrow [†]beyond him. 37  And when the lad was come to the place of the arrow which Jonathan had shot, Jonathan cried after the lad, and said, Is not the arrow beyond thee? 38  And Jonathan cried after the lad, Make speed, haste, stay not. And Jonathan’s lad gathered up the arrows, and came to his master. 39  But the lad knew not any thing: only Jonathan and David knew the matter. 40  And Jonathan gave his [†]artillery unto [†]his lad, and said unto him, Go, carry them to the city.

41 ¶ And as soon as the lad was gone, David arose out of a place toward the south, and fell on his face to the ground, and bowed himself three times: and they kissed one another, and wept one with another, until David exceeded. 42  And Jonathan said to David, Go in peace, [∥]forasmuch as we have sworn both of us in the name of the LORD, saying, The LORD be between me and thee, and between my seed and thy seed for ever. And he arose and departed: and Jonathan went into the city.

21

1  Then came David to Nob to Ahimelech the priest: and Ahimelech was afraid at the meeting of David, and said unto him, Why art thou alone, and no man with thee? 2  And David said unto Ahimelech the priest, The king hath commanded me a business, and hath said unto me, Let no man know any thing of the business whereabout I send thee, and what I have commanded thee: and I have appointed my servants to such and such a place. 3  Now therefore what is under thine hand? give me five loaves of bread in mine hand, or what there is [†]present. 4  And the priest answered David, and said, There is no common bread under mine hand, but there is [*]hallowed bread; if the young men have kept themselves at least from women. 5  And David answered the priest, and said unto him, Of a truth women have been kept from us about these three days, since I came out, and the vessels of the young men are holy, and the bread is in a manner common, [∥]yea, though it were sanctified this day in the vessel. 6  So the priest gave him hallowed bread: for there was no bread there but the shewbread, that was taken from before the LORD, to put hot bread in the day when it was taken away. 7  Now a certain man of the servants of Saul was there that day, detained before the LORD; and his name was Doeg, an Edomite, the chiefest of the herdmen that belonged to Saul.

8 ¶ And David said unto Ahimelech, And is there not here under thine hand spear or sword? for I have neither brought my sword nor my weapons with me, because the king’s business required haste. 9  And the priest said, The sword of Goliath the Philistine, whom thou slewest in [*]the valley of Elah, behold, it is here wrapped in a cloth behind the ephod: if thou wilt take that, take it: for there is no other save that here. And David said, There is none like that; give it me.

10 ¶ And David arose, and fled that day for fear of Saul, and went to Achish the king of Gath. 11  And the servants of Achish said unto him, Is not this David the king of the land? did they not sing one to another of him in dances, saying, [*]Saul hath slain his thousands, and David his ten thousands? 12  And David laid up these words in his heart, and was sore afraid of Achish the king of Gath. 13  And he changed his behaviour before them, and feigned himself mad in their hands, and [∥]scrabbled on the doors of the gate, and let his spittle fall down upon his beard. 14  Then said Achish unto his servants, Lo, ye see the man [∥]is mad: wherefore then have ye brought him to me? 15  Have I need of mad men, that ye have brought this fellow to play the mad man in my presence? shall this fellow come into my house?

22

1  David therefore departed thence, and escaped to the cave Adullam: and when his brethren and all his father’s house heard it, they went down thither to him. 2  And every one that was in distress, and every one that [†]was in debt, and every one that was [†]discontented, gathered themselves unto him; and he became a captain over them: and there were with him about four hundred men.

3 ¶ And David went thence to Mizpeh of Moab: and he said unto the king of Moab, Let my father and my mother, I pray thee, come forth, and be with you, till I know what God will do for me. 4  And he brought them before the king of Moab: and they dwelt with him all the while that David was in the hold.

5 ¶ And the prophet Gad said unto David, Abide not in the hold; depart, and get thee into the land of Judah. Then David departed, and came into the forest of Hareth.

6 ¶ When Saul heard that David was discovered, and the men that were with him, (now Saul abode in Gibeah under a [∥]tree in Ramah, having his spear in his hand, and all his servants were standing about him;) 7  Then Saul said unto his servants that stood about him, Hear now, ye Benjamites; will the son of Jesse give every one of you fields and vineyards, and make you all captains of thousands, and captains of hundreds; 8  That all of you have conspired against me, and there is none that [†]sheweth me that my son hath made a league with the son of Jesse, and there is none of you that is sorry for me, or sheweth unto me that my son hath stirred up my servant against me, to lie in wait, as at this day?

9 ¶ Then answered Doeg the Edomite, which was set over the servants of Saul, and said, I saw the son of Jesse coming to Nob, to Ahimelech the son of Ahitub. 10  And he enquired of the LORD for him, and gave him victuals, and gave him the sword of Goliath the Philistine. 11  Then the king sent to call Ahimelech the priest, the son of Ahitub, and all his father’s house, the priests that were in Nob: and they came all of them to the king. 12  And Saul said, Hear now, thou son of Ahitub. And he answered, [†]Here I am, my lord. 13  And Saul said unto him, Why have ye conspired against me, thou and the son of Jesse, in that thou hast given him bread, and a sword, and hast enquired of God for him, that he should rise against me, to lie in wait, as at this day? 14  Then Ahimelech answered the king, and said, And who is so faithful among all thy servants as David, which is the king’s son in law, and goeth at thy bidding, and is honourable in thine house? 15  Did I then begin to enquire of God for him? be it far from me: let not the king impute any thing unto his servant, nor to all the house of my father: for thy servant knew nothing of all this, [†]less or more. 16  And the king said, Thou shalt surely die, Ahimelech, thou, and all thy father’s house.

17 ¶ And the king said unto the [∥][†]footmen that stood about him, Turn, and slay the priests of the LORD; because their hand also is with David, and because they knew when he fled, and did not shew it to me. But the servants of the king would not put forth their hand to fall upon the priests of the LORD. 18  And the king said to Doeg, Turn thou, and fall upon the priests. And Doeg the Edomite turned, and he fell upon the priests, and slew on that day fourscore and five persons that did wear a linen ephod. 19  And Nob, the city of the priests, smote he with the edge of the sword, both men and women, children and sucklings, and oxen, and asses, and sheep, with the edge of the sword.

20 ¶ And one of the sons of Ahimelech the son of Ahitub, named Abiathar, escaped, and fled after David. 21  And Abiathar shewed David that Saul had slain the LORD’s priests. 22  And David said unto Abiathar, I knew it that day, when Doeg the Edomite was there, that he would surely tell Saul: I have occasioned the death of all the persons of thy father’s house. 23  Abide thou with me, fear not: for he that seeketh my life seeketh thy life: but with me thou shalt be in safeguard.

23

1  Then they told David, saying, Behold, the Philistines fight against Keilah, and they rob the threshingfloors. 2  Therefore David enquired of the LORD, saying, Shall I go and smite these Philistines? And the LORD said unto David, Go, and smite the Philistines, and save Keilah. 3  And David’s men said unto him, Behold, we be afraid here in Judah: how much more then if we come to Keilah against the armies of the Philistines? 4  Then David enquired of the LORD yet again. And the LORD answered him and said, Arise, go down to Keilah; for I will deliver the Philistines into thine hand. 5  So David and his men went to Keilah, and fought with the Philistines, and brought away their cattle, and smote them with a great slaughter. So David saved the inhabitants of Keilah. 6  And it came to pass, when Abiathar the son of Ahimelech [*]fled to David to Keilah, that he came down with an ephod in his hand.

7 ¶ And it was told Saul that David was come to Keilah. And Saul said, God hath delivered him into mine hand; for he is shut in, by entering into a town that hath gates and bars. 8  And Saul called all the people together to war, to go down to Keilah, to besiege David and his men.

9 ¶ And David knew that Saul secretly practised mischief against him; and he said to Abiathar the priest, Bring hither the ephod. 10  Then said David, O LORD God of Israel, thy servant hath certainly heard that Saul seeketh to come to Keilah, to destroy the city for my sake. 11  Will the men of Keilah deliver me up into his hand? will Saul come down, as thy servant hath heard? O LORD God of Israel, I beseech thee, tell thy servant. And the LORD said, He will come down. 12  Then said David, Will the men of Keilah [†]deliver me and my men into the hand of Saul? And the LORD said, They will deliver thee up.

13 ¶ Then David and his men, which were about six hundred, arose and departed out of Keilah, and went whithersoever they could go. And it was told Saul that David was escaped from Keilah; and he forbare to go forth.

14  And David abode in the wilderness in strong holds, and remained in a mountain in the wilderness of Ziph. And Saul sought him every day, but God delivered him not into his hand. 15  And David saw that Saul was come out to seek his life: and David was in the wilderness of Ziph in a wood.

16 ¶ And Jonathan Saul’s son arose, and went to David into the wood, and strengthened his hand in God. 17  And he said unto him, Fear not: for the hand of Saul my father shall not find thee; and thou shalt be king over Israel, and I shall be next unto thee; and that also Saul my father knoweth. 18  And they two made a covenant before the LORD: and David abode in the wood, and Jonathan went to his house.

19 ¶ Then came up the Ziphites to Saul to Gibeah, saying, Doth not David hide himself with us in strong holds in the wood, in the hill of Hachilah, which is [†]on the south of [∥]Jeshimon? 20  Now therefore, O king, come down according to all the desire of thy soul to come down; and our part shall be to deliver him into the king’s hand. 21  And Saul said, Blessed be ye of the LORD; for ye have compassion on me. 22  Go, I pray you, prepare yet, and know and see his place where his [†]haunt is, and who hath seen him there: for it is told me that he dealeth very subtilly. 23  See therefore, and take knowledge of all the lurking places where he hideth himself, and come ye again to me with the certainty, and I will go with you: and it shall come to pass, if he be in the land, that I will search him out throughout all the thousands of Judah. 24  And they arose, and went to Ziph before Saul: but David and his men were in the wilderness of Maon, in the plain on the south of Jeshimon. 25  Saul also and his men went to seek him. And they told David: wherefore he came down into a rock, and abode in the wilderness of Maon. And when Saul heard that, he pursued after David in the wilderness of Maon. 26  And Saul went on this side of the mountain, and David and his men on that side of the mountain: and David made haste to get away for fear of Saul; for Saul and his men compassed David and his men round about to take them.

27 ¶ But there came a messenger unto Saul, saying, Haste thee, and come; for the Philistines have [†]invaded the land. 28  Wherefore Saul returned from pursuing after David, and went against the Philistines: therefore they called that place [∥]Sela-hammahlekoth.

29 ¶ And David went up from thence, and dwelt in strong holds at En-gedi.

24

1  And it came to pass, when Saul was returned from [†]following the Philistines, that it was told him, saying, Behold, David is in the wilderness of En-gedi. 2  Then Saul took three thousand chosen men out of all Israel, and went to seek David and his men upon the rocks of the wild goats. 3  And he came to the sheepcotes by the way, where was a cave; and Saul went in to cover his feet: and David and his men remained in the sides of the cave. 4  And the men of David said unto him, Behold the day of which the LORD said unto thee, Behold, I will deliver thine enemy into thine hand, that thou mayest do to him as it shall seem good unto thee. Then David arose, and cut off the skirt of [†]Saul’s robe privily. 5  And it came to pass afterward, that David’s heart smote him, because he had cut off Saul’s skirt. 6  And he said unto his men, The LORD forbid that I should do this thing unto my master, the LORD’s anointed, to stretch forth mine hand against him, seeing he is the anointed of the LORD. 7  So David [†]stayed his servants with these words, and suffered them not to rise against Saul. But Saul rose up out of the cave, and went on his way. 8  David also arose afterward, and went out of the cave, and cried after Saul, saying, My lord the king. And when Saul looked behind him, David stooped with his face to the earth, and bowed himself.

9 ¶ And David said to Saul, Wherefore hearest thou men’s words, saying, Behold, David seeketh thy hurt? 10  Behold, this day thine eyes have seen how that the LORD had delivered thee to day into mine hand in the cave: and some bade me kill thee: but mine eye spared thee; and I said, I will not put forth mine hand against my lord; for he is the LORD’s anointed. 11  Moreover, my father, see, yea, see the skirt of thy robe in my hand: for in that I cut off the skirt of thy robe, and killed thee not, know thou and see that there is neither evil nor transgression in mine hand, and I have not sinned against thee; yet thou huntest my soul to take it. 12  The LORD judge between me and thee, and the LORD avenge me of thee: but mine hand shall not be upon thee. 13  As saith the proverb of the ancients, Wickedness proceedeth from the wicked: but mine hand shall not be upon thee. 14  After whom is the king of Israel come out? after whom dost thou pursue? after a dead dog, after a flea. 15  The LORD therefore be judge, and judge between me and thee, and see, and plead my cause, and [†]deliver me out of thine hand.

16 ¶ And it came to pass, when David had made an end of speaking these words unto Saul, that Saul said, Is this thy voice, my son David? And Saul lifted up his voice, and wept. 17  And he said to David, Thou art more righteous than I: for thou hast rewarded me good, whereas I have rewarded thee evil. 18  And thou hast shewed this day how that thou hast dealt well with me: forasmuch as when the LORD had [†]delivered me into thine hand, thou killedst me not. 19  For if a man find his enemy, will he let him go well away? wherefore the LORD reward thee good for that thou hast done unto me this day. 20  And now, behold, I know well that thou shalt surely be king, and that the kingdom of Israel shall be established in thine hand. 21  Swear now therefore unto me by the LORD, that thou wilt not cut off my seed after me, and that thou wilt not destroy my name out of my father’s house. 22  And David sware unto Saul. And Saul went home; but David and his men gat them up unto the hold.

25

1  And [*]Samuel died; and all the Israelites were gathered together, and lamented him, and buried him in his house at Ramah. And David arose, and went down to the wilderness of Paran.

2 And there was a man in Maon, whose [∥]possessions were in Carmel; and the man was very great, and he had three thousand sheep, and a thousand goats: and he was shearing his sheep in Carmel. 3  Now the name of the man was Nabal; and the name of his wife Abigail: and she was a woman of good understanding, and of a beautiful countenance: but the man was churlish and evil in his doings; and he was of the house of Caleb.

4 ¶ And David heard in the wilderness that Nabal did shear his sheep. 5  And David sent out ten young men, and David said unto the young men, Get you up to Carmel, and go to Nabal, and [†]greet him in my name: 6  And thus shall ye say to him that liveth in prosperity, Peace be both to thee, and peace be to thine house, and peace be unto all that thou hast. 7  And now I have heard that thou hast shearers: now thy shepherds which were with us, we [†]hurt them not, neither was there ought missing unto them, all the while they were in Carmel. 8  Ask thy young men, and they will shew thee. Wherefore let the young men find favour in thine eyes: for we come in a good day: give, I pray thee, whatsoever cometh to thine hand unto thy servants, and to thy son David. 9  And when David’s young men came, they spake to Nabal according to all those words in the name of David, and [†]ceased.

10 ¶ And Nabal answered David’s servants, and said, Who is David? and who is the son of Jesse? there be many servants now a days that break away every man from his master. 11  Shall I then take my bread, and my water, and my [†]flesh that I have killed for my shearers, and give it unto men, whom I know not whence they be?

12  So David’s young men turned their way, and went again, and came and told him all those sayings. 13  And David said unto his men, Gird ye on every man his sword. And they girded on every man his sword; and David also girded on his sword: and there went up after David about four hundred men; and two hundred abode by the stuff.

14 ¶ But one of the young men told Abigail, Nabal’s wife, saying, Behold, David sent messengers out of the wilderness to salute our master; and he [†]railed on them. 15  But the men were very good unto us, and we were not [†]hurt, neither missed we any thing, as long as we were conversant with them, when we were in the fields: 16  They were a wall unto us both by night and day, all the while we were with them keeping [‡]the sheep. 17  Now therefore know and consider what thou wilt do; for evil is determined against our master, and against all his household: for he is such a son of Belial, that a man cannot speak to him.

18 ¶ Then Abigail made haste, and took two hundred loaves, and two bottles of wine, and five sheep ready dressed, and five measures of parched corn, and an hundred [∥]clusters of raisins, and two hundred cakes of figs, and laid them on asses. 19  And she said unto her servants, Go on before me; behold, I come after you. But she told not her husband Nabal. 20 And it was so, as she rode on the ass, that she came down by the covert of the hill, and, behold, David and his men came down against her; and she met them. 21  Now David had said, Surely in vain have I kept all that this fellow hath in the wilderness, so that nothing was missed of all that pertained unto him: and he hath requited me evil for good. 22  So and more also do God unto the enemies of David, if I leave of all that pertain to him by the morning light any that pisseth against the wall. 23  And when Abigail saw David, she hasted, and lighted off the ass, and fell before David on her face, and bowed herself to the ground, 24  And fell at his feet, and said, Upon me, my lord, upon me let this iniquity be: and let thine handmaid, I pray thee, speak in thine [†]audience, and hear the words of thine handmaid. 25  Let not my lord, I pray thee, [†]regard this man of Belial, even Nabal: for as his name is, so is he; Nabal is his name, and folly is with him: but I thine handmaid saw not the young men of my lord, whom thou didst send. 26  Now therefore, my lord, as the LORD liveth, and as thy soul liveth, seeing the LORD hath withholden thee from coming to shed blood, and from [†]avenging thyself with thine own hand, now let thine enemies, and they that seek evil to my lord, be as Nabal. 27  And now this [∥]blessing which thine handmaid hath brought unto my lord, let it even be given unto the young men that [†]follow my lord. 28  I pray thee, forgive the trespass of thine handmaid: for the LORD will certainly make my lord a sure house; because my lord fighteth the battles of the LORD, and evil hath not been found in thee all thy days. 29  Yet a man is risen to pursue thee, and to seek thy soul: but the soul of my lord shall be bound in the bundle of life with the LORD thy God; and the souls of thine enemies, them shall he sling out, [†]as out of the middle of a sling. 30  And it shall come to pass, when the LORD shall have done to my lord according to all the good that he hath spoken concerning thee, and shall have appointed thee ruler over Israel; 31  That this shall be [†]no grief unto thee, nor offence of heart unto my lord, either that thou hast shed blood causeless, or that my lord hath avenged himself: but when the LORD shall have dealt well with my lord, then remember thine handmaid.

32 ¶ And David said to Abigail, Blessed be the LORD God of Israel, which sent thee this day to meet me: 33  And blessed be thy advice, and blessed be thou, which hast kept me this day from coming to shed blood, and from avenging myself with mine own hand. 34  For in very deed, as the LORD God of Israel liveth, which hath kept me back from hurting thee, except thou hadst hasted and come to meet me, surely there had not been left unto Nabal by the morning light any that pisseth against the wall. 35  So David received of her hand that which she had brought him, and said unto her, Go up in peace to thine house; see, I have hearkened to thy voice, and have accepted thy person.

36 ¶ And Abigail came to Nabal; and, behold, he held a feast in his house, like the feast of a king; and Nabal’s heart was merry within him, for he was very drunken: wherefore she told him nothing, less or more, until the morning light. 37  But it came to pass in the morning, when the wine was gone out of Nabal, and his wife had told him these things, that his heart died within him, and he became as a stone. 38  And it came to pass about ten days after, that the LORD smote Nabal, that he died.

39 ¶ And when David heard that Nabal was dead, he said, Blessed be the LORD, that hath pleaded the cause of my reproach from the hand of Nabal, and hath kept his servant from evil: for the LORD hath returned the wickedness of Nabal upon his own head. And David sent and communed with Abigail, to take her to him to wife. 40  And when the servants of David were come to Abigail to Carmel, they spake unto her, saying, David sent us unto thee, to take thee to him to wife. 41  And she arose, and bowed herself on her face to the earth, and said, Behold, let thine handmaid be a servant to wash the feet of the servants of my lord. 42  And Abigail hasted, and arose, and rode upon an ass, with five damsels of hers that went [†]after her; and she went after the messengers of David, and became his wife. 43  David also took Ahinoam [*]of Jezreel; and they were also both of them his wives.

44 ¶ But Saul had given [*]Michal his daughter, David’s wife, to Phalti the son of Laish, which was of Gallim.

26

1  And the Ziphites came unto Saul to Gibeah, saying, [*]Doth not David hide himself in the hill of Hachilah, which is before Jeshimon? 2  Then Saul arose, and went down to the wilderness of Ziph, having three thousand chosen men of Israel with him, to seek David in the wilderness of Ziph. 3  And Saul pitched in the hill of Hachilah, which is before Jeshimon, by the way. But David abode in the wilderness, and he saw that Saul came after him into the wilderness. 4  David therefore sent out spies, and understood that Saul was come in very deed.

5 ¶ And David arose, and came to the place where Saul had pitched: and David beheld the place where Saul lay, and [*]Abner the son of Ner, the captain of his host: and Saul lay in the [∥]trench, and the people pitched round about him.

6  Then answered David and said to Ahimelech the Hittite, and to Abishai the son of Zeruiah, brother to Joab, saying, Who will go down with me to Saul to the camp? And Abishai said, I will go down with thee. 7  So David and Abishai came to the people by night: and, behold, Saul lay sleeping within the trench, and his spear stuck in the ground at his bolster: but Abner and the people lay round about him. 8  Then said Abishai to David, God hath [†]delivered thine enemy into thine hand this day: now therefore let me smite him, I pray thee, with the spear even to the earth at once, and I will not smite him the second time. 9  And David said to Abishai, Destroy him not: for who can stretch forth his hand against the LORD’s anointed, and be guiltless? 10  David said furthermore, As the LORD liveth, the LORD shall smite him; or his day shall come to die; or he shall descend into battle, and perish. 11  The LORD forbid that I should stretch forth mine hand against the LORD’s anointed: but, I pray thee, take thou now the spear that is at his bolster, and the cruse of water, and let us go. 12  So David took the spear and the cruse of water from Saul’s bolster; and they gat them away, and no man saw it, nor knew it, neither awaked: for they were all asleep; because a deep sleep from the LORD was fallen upon them.

13 ¶ Then David went over to the other side, and stood on the top of an hill afar off; a great space being between them: 14  And David cried to the people, and to Abner the son of Ner, saying, Answerest thou not, Abner? Then Abner answered and said, Who art thou that criest to the king? 15  And David said to Abner, Art not thou a valiant man? and who is like to thee in Israel? wherefore then hast thou not kept thy lord the king? for there came one of the people in to destroy the king thy lord. 16  This thing is not good that thou hast done. As the LORD liveth, ye are [†]worthy to die, because ye have not kept your master, the LORD’s anointed. And now see where the king’s spear is, and the cruse of water that was at his bolster. 17  And Saul knew David’s voice, and said, Is this thy voice, my son David? And David said, It is my voice, my lord, O king. 18  And he said, Wherefore doth my lord thus pursue after his servant? for what have I done? or what evil is in mine hand? 19  Now therefore, I pray thee, let my lord the king hear the words of his servant. If the LORD have stirred thee up against me, let him [†]accept an offering: but if they be the children of men, cursed be they before the LORD; for they have driven me out this day from [†]abiding in the inheritance of the LORD, saying, Go, serve other gods. 20  Now therefore, let not my blood fall to the earth before the face of the LORD: for the king of Israel is come out to seek a flea, as when one doth hunt a partridge in the mountains.

21 ¶ Then said Saul, I have sinned: return, my son David: for I will no more do thee harm, because my soul was precious in thine eyes this day: behold, I have played the fool, and have erred exceedingly. 22  And David answered and said, Behold the king’s spear! and let one of the young men come over and fetch it. 23  The LORD render to every man his righteousness and his faithfulness: for the LORD delivered thee into my hand to day, but I would not stretch forth mine hand against the LORD’s anointed. 24  And, behold, as thy life was much set by this day in mine eyes, so let my life be much set by in the eyes of the LORD, and let him deliver me out of all tribulation. 25  Then Saul said to David, Blessed be thou, my son David: thou shalt both do great things, and also shalt still prevail. So David went on his way, and Saul returned to his place.

27

1  And David said in his heart, I shall now [†]perish one day by the hand of Saul: there is nothing better for me than that I should speedily escape into the land of the Philistines; and Saul shall despair of me, to seek me any more in any coast of Israel: so shall I escape out of his hand. 2  And David arose, and he passed over with the six hundred men that were with him unto Achish, the son of Maoch, king of Gath. 3  And David dwelt with Achish at Gath, he and his men, every man with his household, even David with his two wives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the Carmelitess, Nabal’s wife. 4  And it was told Saul that David was fled to Gath: and he sought no more again for him.

5 ¶ And David said unto Achish, If I have now found grace in thine eyes, let them give me a place in some town in the country, that I may dwell there: for why should thy servant dwell in the royal city with thee? 6  Then Achish gave him Ziklag that day: wherefore Ziklag pertaineth unto the kings of Judah unto this day. 7  And [†]the time that David dwelt in the country of the Philistines was [†]a full year and four months.

8 ¶ And David and his men went up, and invaded the Geshurites, and the [∥]Gezrites, and the Amalekites: for those nations were of old the inhabitants of the land, as thou goest to Shur, even unto the land of Egypt. 9  And David smote the land, and left neither man nor woman alive, and took away the sheep, and the oxen, and the asses, and the camels, and the apparel, and returned, and came to Achish. 10  And Achish said, [∥]Whither have ye made a road to day? And David said, Against the south of Judah, and against the south of the Jerahmeelites, and against the south of the Kenites. 11  And David saved neither man nor woman alive, to bring tidings to Gath, saying, Lest they should tell on us, saying, So did David, and so will be his manner all the while he dwelleth in the country of the Philistines. 12  And Achish believed David, saying, He hath made his people Israel [†]utterly to abhor him; therefore he shall be my servant for ever.

28

1  And it came to pass in those days, that the Philistines gathered their armies together for warfare, to fight with Israel. And Achish said unto David, Know thou assuredly, that thou shalt go out with me to battle, thou and thy men. 2  And David said to Achish, Surely thou shalt know what thy servant can do. And Achish said to David, Therefore will I make thee keeper of mine head for ever.

3 ¶ Now [*]Samuel was dead, and all Israel had lamented him, and buried him in Ramah, even in his own city. And Saul had put away those that had familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land. 4  And the Philistines gathered themselves together, and came and pitched in Shunem: and Saul gathered all Israel together, and they pitched in Gilboa. 5  And when Saul saw the host of the Philistines, he was afraid, and his heart greatly trembled. 6  And when Saul enquired of the LORD, the LORD answered him not, neither by dreams, nor by Urim, nor by prophets.

7 ¶ Then said Saul unto his servants, Seek me a woman that hath a familiar spirit, that I may go to her, and enquire of her. And his [‡]servants said to him, Behold, there is a woman that hath a familiar spirit at Endor. 8  And Saul disguised himself, and put on other raiment, and he went, and two men with him, and they came to the woman by night: and he said, I pray thee, divine unto me by the familiar spirit, and bring me him up, whom I shall name unto thee. 9  And the woman said unto him, Behold, thou knowest what Saul hath done, how he hath cut off those that have familiar spirits, and the wizards, out of the land: wherefore then layest thou a snare for my life, to cause me to die? 10  And Saul sware to her by the LORD, saying, As the LORD liveth, there shall no punishment happen to thee for this thing. 11  Then said the woman, Whom shall I bring up unto thee? And he said, Bring me up Samuel. 12  And when the woman saw Samuel, she cried with a loud voice: and the woman spake to Saul, saying, Why hast thou deceived me? for thou art Saul. 13  And the king said unto her, Be not afraid: for what sawest thou? And the woman said unto Saul, I saw gods ascending out of the earth. 14  And he said unto her, [†]What form is he of? And she said, An old man cometh up; and he is covered with a mantle. And Saul perceived that it was Samuel, and he stooped with his face to the ground, and bowed himself.

15 ¶ And Samuel said to Saul, Why hast thou disquieted me, to bring me up? And Saul answered, I am sore distressed; for the Philistines make war against me, and God is departed from me, and answereth me no more, neither [†]by prophets, nor by dreams: therefore I have called thee, that thou mayest make known unto me what I shall do. 16  Then said Samuel, Wherefore then dost thou ask of me, seeing the LORD is departed from thee, and is become thine enemy? 17  And the LORD hath done [∥]to him, [*]as he spake by [†]me: for the LORD hath rent the kingdom out of thine hand, and given it to thy neighbour, even to David: 18  Because thou obeyedst not the voice of the LORD, nor executedst his fierce wrath upon Amalek, therefore hath the LORD done this thing unto thee this day. 19  Moreover the LORD will also deliver Israel with thee into the hand of the Philistines: and to morrow shalt thou and thy sons be with me: the LORD also shall deliver the host of Israel into the hand of the Philistines.

20  Then Saul [†]fell straightway all along on the earth, and was sore afraid, because of the words of Samuel: and there was no strength in him; for he had eaten no bread all the day, nor all the night.

21 ¶ And the woman came unto Saul, and saw that he was sore troubled, and said unto him, Behold, thine handmaid hath obeyed thy voice, and I have put my life in my hand, and have hearkened unto thy words which thou spakest unto me. 22  Now therefore, I pray thee, hearken thou also unto the voice of thine handmaid, and let me set a morsel of bread before thee; and eat, that thou mayest have strength, when thou goest on thy way. 23  But he refused, and said, I will not eat. But his servants, together with the woman, compelled him; and he hearkened unto their voice. So he arose from the earth, and sat upon the bed. 24  And the woman had a fat calf in the house; and she hasted, and killed it, and took flour, and kneaded it, and did bake unleavened bread thereof: 25  And she brought it before Saul, and before his servants; and they did eat. Then they rose up, and went away that night.

29

1  Now the Philistines gathered together all their armies to Aphek: and the Israelites pitched by a fountain which is in Jezreel. 2  And the lords of the Philistines passed on by hundreds, and by thousands: but David and his men passed on in the rereward with Achish. 3  Then said the princes of the Philistines, What do these Hebrews here? And Achish said unto the princes of the Philistines, Is not this David, the servant of Saul the king of Israel, which hath been with me these days, or these years, and I have found no fault in him since he fell unto me unto this day? 4  And the princes of the Philistines were wroth with him; and the princes of the Philistines said unto him, [*]Make this fellow return, that he may go again to his place which thou hast appointed him, and let him not go down with us to battle, lest in the battle he be an adversary to us: for wherewith should he reconcile himself unto his master? should it not be with the heads of these men? 5  Is not this David, of whom they sang one to another in dances, saying, [*]Saul slew his thousands, and David his ten thousands?

6 ¶ Then Achish called David, and said unto him, Surely, as the LORD liveth, thou hast been upright, and thy going out and thy coming in with me in the host is good in my sight: for I have not found evil in thee since the day of thy coming unto me unto this day: nevertheless [†]the lords favour thee not. 7  Wherefore now return, and go in peace, that thou [†]displease not the lords of the Philistines.

8 ¶ And David said unto Achish, But what have I done? and what hast thou found in thy servant so long as I have been [†]with thee unto this day, that I may not go fight against the enemies of my lord the king? 9  And Achish answered and said to David, I know that thou art good in my sight, as an angel of God: notwithstanding the princes of the Philistines have said, He shall not go up with us to the battle. 10  Wherefore now rise up early in the morning with thy master’s servants that are come with thee: and as soon as ye be up early in the morning, and have light, depart. 11  So David and his men rose up early to depart in the morning, to return into the land of the Philistines. And the Philistines went up to Jezreel.

30

1  And it came to pass, when David and his men were come to Ziklag on the third day, that the Amalekites had invaded the south, and Ziklag, and smitten Ziklag, and burned it with fire; 2  And had taken the women captives, that were therein: they slew not any, either great or small, but carried them away, and went on their way.

3 ¶ So David and his men came to the city, and, behold, it was burned with fire; and their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, were taken captives. 4  Then David and the people that were with him lifted up their voice and wept, until they had no more power to weep. 5  And David’s two wives were taken captives, Ahinoam the Jezreelitess, and Abigail the wife of Nabal the Carmelite. 6  And David was greatly distressed; for the people spake of stoning him, because the soul of all the people was [†]grieved, every man for his sons and for his daughters: but David encouraged himself in the LORD his God.

7  And David said to Abiathar the priest, Ahimelech’s son, I pray thee, bring me hither the ephod. And Abiathar brought thither the ephod to David. 8  And David enquired at the LORD, saying, Shall I pursue after this troop? shall I overtake them? And he answered him, Pursue: for thou shalt surely overtake them, and without fail recover all. 9  So David went, he and the six hundred men that were with him, and came to the brook Besor, where those that were left behind stayed. 10  But David pursued, he and four hundred men: for two hundred abode behind, which were so faint that they could not go over the brook Besor.

11 ¶ And they found an Egyptian in the field, and brought him to David, and gave him bread, and he did eat; and they made him drink water; 12  And they gave him a piece of a cake of figs, and two clusters of raisins: and when he had eaten, his spirit came again to him: for he had eaten no bread, nor drunk any water, three days and three nights. 13  And David said unto him, To whom belongest thou? and whence art thou? And he said, I am a young man of Egypt, servant to an Amalekite; and my master left me, because three days agone I fell sick. 14  We made an invasion upon the south of the Cherethites, and upon the coast which belongeth to Judah, and upon the south of Caleb; and we burned Ziklag with fire. 15  And David said to him, Canst thou bring me down to this company? And he said, Swear unto me by God, that thou wilt neither kill me, nor deliver me into the hands of my master, and I will bring thee down to this company.

16 ¶ And when he had brought him down, behold, they were spread abroad upon all the earth, eating and drinking, and dancing, because of all the great spoil that they had taken out of the land of the Philistines, and out of the land of Judah. 17  And David smote them from the twilight even unto the evening of [†]the next day: and there escaped not a man of them, save four hundred young men, which rode upon camels, and fled. 18  And David recovered all that the Amalekites had carried away: and David rescued his two wives. 19  And there was nothing lacking to them, neither small nor great, neither sons nor daughters, neither spoil, nor any thing that they had taken to them: David recovered all. 20  And David took all the flocks and the herds, which they drave before those other cattle, and said, This is David’s spoil.

21 ¶ And David came to the two hundred men, which were so faint that they could not follow David, whom they had made also to abide at the brook Besor: and they went forth to meet David, and to meet the people that were with him: and when David came near to the people, he [∥]saluted them. 22  Then answered all the wicked men and men of Belial, of [†]those that went with David, and said, Because they went not with us, we will not give them ought of the spoil that we have recovered, save to every man his wife and his children, that they may lead them away, and depart. 23  Then said David, Ye shall not do so, my brethren, with that which the LORD hath given us, who hath preserved us, and delivered the company that came against us into our hand. 24  For who will hearken unto you in this matter? but as his part is that goeth down to the battle, so shall his part be that tarrieth by the stuff: they shall part alike. 25 And it was so from that day [†]forward, that he made it a statute and an ordinance for Israel unto this day.

26 ¶ And when David came to Ziklag, he sent of the spoil unto the elders of Judah, even to his friends, saying, Behold a [†]present for you of the spoil of the enemies of the LORD; 27 To them which were in Beth-el, and to them which were in south Ramoth, and to them which were in Jattir, 28 And to them which were in Aroer, and to them which were in Siphmoth, and to them which were in Eshtemoa, 29 And to them which were in Rachal, and to them which were in the cities of the Jerahmeelites, and to them which were in the cities of the Kenites, 30 And to them which were in Hormah, and to them which were in Chor-ashan, and to them which were in Athach, 31 And to them which were in Hebron, and to all the places where David himself and his men were wont to haunt.

31

1  Now [*]the Philistines fought against Israel: and the men of Israel fled from before the Philistines, and fell down [∥]slain in mount Gilboa. 2  And the Philistines followed hard upon Saul and upon his sons; and the Philistines slew Jonathan, and Abinadab, and Malchi-shua, Saul’s sons. 3  And the battle went sore against Saul, and the [†]archers [†]hit him; and he was sore wounded of the archers. 4  Then said Saul unto his armourbearer, Draw thy sword, and thrust me through therewith; lest these uncircumcised come and thrust me through, and [∥]abuse me. But his armourbearer would not; for he was sore afraid. Therefore Saul took a sword, and fell upon it. 5  And when his armourbearer saw that Saul was dead, he fell likewise upon his sword, and died with him. 6  So Saul died, and his three sons, and his armourbearer, and all his men, that same day together.

7 ¶ And when the men of Israel that were on the other side of the valley, and they that were on the other side Jordan, saw that the men of Israel fled, and that Saul and his sons were dead, they forsook the cities, and fled; and the Philistines came and dwelt in them.

8  And it came to pass on the morrow, when the Philistines came to strip the slain, that they found Saul and his three sons fallen in mount Gilboa. 9  And they cut off his head, and stripped off his armour, and sent into the land of the Philistines round about, to publish it in the house of their idols, and among the people. 10  And they put his armour in the house of Ashtaroth: and they fastened his body to the wall of Beth-shan.

11 ¶ And when the inhabitants of Jabesh-gilead heard [∥]of that which the Philistines had done to Saul; 12  All the valiant men arose, and went all night, and took the body of Saul and the bodies of his sons from the wall of Beth-shan, and came to Jabesh, and [*]burnt them there. 13  And they took their bones, and [*]buried them under a tree at Jabesh, and fasted seven days.

* 1.3 Deut. 16. 16.

† 1.3 Heb. from year to year.

∥ 1.5 Or, a double portion.

† 1.6 Heb. angered her.

∥ 1.7 Or, from the time that she, &c.

† 1.7 Heb. from her going up.

† 1.10 Heb. bitter of soul.

† 1.11 Heb. seed of men.

* 1.11 Num. 6. 5 Judg. 13. 5

† 1.12 Heb. multiplied to pray.

† 1.15 Heb. hard of spirit.

∥ 1.16 Or, meditation.

† 1.20 Heb. revolution of days.

∥ 1.20 That is, Asked of God.

∥ 1.28 Or, returned him, whom I have obtained by petition, to the Lord.

∥ 1.28 Or, he whom I have obtained by petition shall be returned.

† 2.3 Heb. hard.

* 2.6 Deut. 32. 39. Tob. 13. 2. Wisd. 16. 13.

* 2.8 Ps. 113. 7.

* 2.10 ch. 7. 10.

† 2.16 Heb. as on the day.

* 2.18 Ex. 28. 4.

∥ 2.20 Or, petition which she asked, &c.

† 2.22 Heb. assembled by troops

∥ 2.23 Or, I hear evil words of you.

∥ 2.24 Or, to cry out.

* 2.28 Lev. 10. 14.

∥ 2.32 Or, the affliction of the tabernacle, for all the wealth which God would have given Israel.

† 2.33 Heb. men.

† 2.36 Heb. Join.

∥ 2.36 Or, somewhat about the priesthood.

∥ 3.7 Or, Thus did Samuel, before he knew the Lord, and before the word of the Lord was revealed unto him.

* 3.11 2 Kings 21. 12.

† 3.12 Heb. beginning and ending.

∥ 3.13 Or, And I will tell him, &c.

* 3.13 ch. 2. 29, 30, 31, &c.

∥ 3.13 Or, accursed.

† 3.13 Heb. frowned not upon them.

† 3.17 Heb. so add.

∥ 3.17 Or, word.

† 3.18 Heb. all the things, or, words.

∥ 3.20 Or, faithful.

∥ 4.1 Or, came to pass.

† 4.1 Heb. was.

† 4.2 Heb. the battle was spread.

† 4.2 Heb. the array.

† 4.3 Heb. take unto us.

† 4.7 Heb. yesterday, or, the third day.

* 4.9 Judg. 18. 1.

† 4.9 Heb. be men.

† 4.11 Heb. died.

* 4.15 ch. 3. 2.

† 4.15 Heb. stood.

† 4.16 Heb. it the thing.

∥ 4.19 Or, to cry out.

† 4.19 Heb. were turned.

† 4.20 Heb. set not her heart.

∥ 4.21 That is, Where is the glory? or, There is no glory.

∥ 5.4 Or, the fishy part.

* 5.6 Ps. 78. 66.

† 6.4 Heb. them.

∥ 6.6 Or, reproachfully.

* 6.6 Ex. 12. 31.

† 6.6 Heb. them.

‡ 6.7 [1611 the]

∥ 6.9 Or, it.

∥ 6.18 Or, great stone.

* 7.3 Josh 24. 15, 23.

* 7.3 Judg. 2. 13.

* 7.3 Deut. 6 4. Matt. 4. 10. Luke 4. 8.

* 7.4 Judg. 2 11.

† 7.8 Heb. Be not silent from us from crying.

∥ 7.9 Or, answered

∥ 7.12 That is, The stone of help.

† 7.16 Heb. and he circuited.

* 8.3 Deut. 16. 19.

* 8.5 Hos. 13. 10. Acts 13. 21.

† 8.6 Heb. was evil in the eyes of Samuel.

∥ 8.9 Or, obey.

∥ 8.9 Or, notwithstanding, when thou hast solemnly protested against them, then thou shalt shew, &c.

† 8.15 Heb. eunuchs.

* 9.1 ch. 14. 51. 1 Chr. 8. 83.

∥ 9.1 Or, the son of a man of Jemini.

∥ 9.1 Or. substance.

† 9.7 Heb. is gone out of, &c.

† 9.7 Heb. is with us?

† 9.8 Heb. there is found in my hand.

† 9.10 Heb. Thy word is good.

† 9.11 Heb. in the ascent of the city.

∥ 9.12 Or, feast.

† 9.13 Heb. to day.

* 9.15 ch. 15. 1. Acts 13. 21.

† 9.15 Heb. revealed the ear of Samuel.

† 9.17 Heb. restrain in.

† 9.20 Heb. to day three days.

† 9.21 Heb. according to this word?

∥ 9.24 Or, reserved.

† 9.27 Heb. to day.

* 10.2 Gen. 35. 20.

† 10.2 Heb. the business.

† 10.4 Heb. ash thee of peace.

† 10.7 Heb. it shall come to pass, that when these signs, &c.

† 10.7 Heb. do for thee as thine hand shall find.

* 10.8 ch. 13. 8.

† 10.9 Heb. shoulder.

† 10.9 Heb. turned.

‡ 10.10 [1611 of the prophets]

† 10.11 Heb. a man to his neighbour.

* 10.11 ch. 19. 24.

† 10.12 Heb. from thence.

‡ 10.23 [1611 the]

† 10.24 Heb. Let the king live.

∥ 10.27 Or, he was as though he had been deaf.

† 11.3 Heb Forbear us.

† 11.7 Heb. as one man.

∥ 11.9 Or, deliverance.

* 12.3 Ecclus. 46. 19.

† 12.3 Heb. ransom.

∥ 12.3 Or, that I should hide mine eyes at him.

∥ 12.6 Or, made.

† 12.7 Heb. righteousnesses, or, benefits.

† 12.7 Heb. with.

* 12.8 Gen. 46. 5, 6.

* 12.8 Ex. 4. 16.

* 12.9 Judg. 4. 2.

* 12.11 Judg. 11. 1.

† 12.14 Heb. mouth.

† 12.14 Heb. be after.

† 12.23 Heb. from ceasing.

∥ 12.24 Or, what a great thing, &c.

† 13.1 Heb. the son of one year in his reigning.

∥ 13.3 Or, The hill.

† 13.4 Heb. did stink.

† 13.7 Heb. trembled after him.

* 13.8 ch. 10. 8.

† 13.10 Heb. bless him.

† 13.12 Heb. intreated the face.

† 13.15 Heb. found.

† 13.21 Heb. a file with mouths.

† 13.21 Heb. to set.

∥ 13.23 Or, standing camp.

∥ 14.1 Or, there was a day.

* 14.3 ch. 4. 21.

† 14.5 Heb. tooth.

* 14.6 2 Chr. 14. 11.

† 14.9 Heb. Be still.

* 14.10 1 Mac. 4. 30.

∥ 14.14 Or, half a furrow of an acre of land.

† 14.15 Heb a trembling of God.

∥ 14.19 Or, tumult.

† 14.20 Heb. were cried together.

* 14.20 Judg. 7. 22. 2 Chr. 20. 23.

∥ 14.28 Or, weary.

* 14.32 Lev. 7. 26. &c 19. 26. Deut. 12. 16.

∥ 14.33 Or, dealt treacherously.

† 14.34 Heb. in his hand.

† 14.35 Heb. that altar he began to build unto the Lord.

* 14.38 Judg. 20. 2.

† 14.38 Heb. corners.

∥ 14.41 Or, Shew the innocent.

† 14.41 Heb. went forth.

∥ 14.48 Or, wrought mightily.

* 15.1 ch 9. 16.

* 15.2 Ex. 17. 8. Num. 24. 20.

∥ 15.5 Or, fought.

∥ 15.9 Or, of the second sort.

† 15.18 Heb. they consume them.

* 15.22 Eccles. 5. 1. Hos 6. 6. Matt. 9. 13. &c 12. 7.

† 15.23 Heb. divination.

∥ 15.29 Or, Eternity, or, victory.

* 15.33 Ex. 17. 11. Num. 14. 45.

† 16.2 Heb. in thine hand.

† 16.4 Heb. meeting.

† 16.7 Heb. eyes.

* 16.7 1 Chr. 28. 9. Ps. 7. 9. Jer. 11. 20. &c 17. 10. &c 20. 12.

* 16.11 2 Sam. 7. 8. Ps. 78. 70.

† 16.11 Heb. round.

† 16.12 Heb. fair of eyes.

∥ 16.14 Or, terrified.

∥ 16.18 Or, speech.

∥ 17.1 Or, The coast of Dammim.

† 17.2 Heb. ranged the battle.

† 17.5 Heb. clothed.

∥ 17.6 Or, gorget.

* 17.12 ch. 16. 1.

† 17.18 Heb. cheeses of milk.

† 17.18 Heb captain of a thousand.

∥ 17.20 Or, place of the carriage.

∥ 17.20 Or, battle array, or, place of fight.

† 17.22 Heb. the vessels from upon him.

† 17.22 Heb. asked his brethren of peace.

† 17.24 Heb. from his face.

* 17.25 Josh. 15. 16.

† 17.30 Heb. word.

† 17.31 Heb. took him.

∥ 17.34 Or, kid.

† 17.38 Heb. clothed David with his clothes.

∥ 17.40 Or, valley.

† 17.40 Heb. vessel.

† 17.46 Heb. shut thee up.

* 17.50 Ecclus. 47. 4. 1 Mac. 4. 30.

‡ 18.1 [1611 omits had]

∥ 18.5 Or, prospered.

∥ 18.6 Or, Philistines.

† 18.6 Heb. three stringed instruments.

* 18.7 ch. 21. 11. &c 29. 5. Ecclus. 47. 6.

† 18.8 Heb. was evil in his eyes.

∥ 18.14 Or, prospered.

† 18.17 Heb. a son of valour.

† 18.20 Heb. was right in his eyes.

† 18.24 Heb. According to these words.

† 18.26 Heb. fulfilled.

‡ 18.27 [1611 omits and went]

† 18.30 Heb. precious.

* 19.5 Judg. 9. 17. &c 12 3. ch 28 21. Ps. 119. 109.

† 19.7 Heb. yesterday third day.

† 19.8 Heb. his face.

† 19.24 Heb. fell

* 19.24 ch. 10. 11.

† 20.2 Heb. uncover mine ear.

∥ 20.4 Or, Say what is thy mind, and I will do, &c.

† 20.4 Heb speaketh, or, thinketh.

‡ 20.5 [1611 fields]

* 20.8 ch. 18. 3 &c 23. 18.

† 20.12 Heb. searched.

† 20.12 Heb. uncover thine ear

† 20.16 Heb. cut

∥ 20.17 Or, by his love towards him

† 20.18 Heb. missed.

∥ 20.19 Or, diligently.

† 20.19 Heb. greatly.

† 20.19 Heb. in the day of the business.

∥ 20.19 Or, that sheweth the way.

† 20.21 Heb. not any thing.

∥ 20.30 Or, Thou perverse rebel.

† 20.30 Heb. Son of perverse rebellion.

† 20.31 Heb. is the son of death.

† 20.36 Heb. to pass over him.

† 20.40 Heb. instruments.

† 20.40 Heb. that was his.

∥ 20.42 Or, the Lord be witness of that which, &c.

† 21.3 Heb. found.

* 21.4 Ex. 25. 30. Lev. 24. 5. Matt. 12. 4.

∥ 21.5 Or, especially when this day there is other sanctified in the vessel.

* 21.9 ch. 17. 2.

* 21.11 ch. 18 7. &c 29. 5. Ecclus. 47. 6.

∥ 21.13 Or, made marks.

∥ 21.14 Or, playeth the mad man.

† 22.2 Heb. had a creditor.

† 22.2 Heb. bitter of soul.

∥ 22.6 Or, grove in a high place.

† 22.8 Heb. uncovereth mine ear.

† 22.12 Heb. Behold me.

† 22.15 Heb. little or great.

∥ 22.17 Or, guard.

† 22.17 Heb. runners.

* 23.6 ch 22. 20.

† 23.12 Heb. shut up.

† 23.19 Heb. on the right hand.

∥ 23.19 Or, the wilderness?

† 23.22 Heb. foot shall be.

† 23.27 Heb. spread themselves upon, &c.

∥ 23.28 That is, The rock of divisions.

† 24.1 Heb. after.

† 24.4 Heb the robe which was Saul's.

† 24.7 Heb. cut off.

† 24.15 Heb. judge.

† 24.18 Heb. shut up.

* 25.1 ch. 28. 3. Ecclus. 46. 13, 20

∥ 25.2 Or, business.

† 25.5 Heb. ask him in my name of peace.

† 25.7 Heb. shamed.

† 25.9 Heb. rested.

† 25.11 Heb. slaughter.

† 25.14 Heb. flew upon them.

† 25.15 Heb. shamed.

‡ 25.16 [1611 omits the]

∥ 25.18 Or, lumps.

† 25.24 Heb. ears.

† 25.25 Heb. lay it to his heart.

† 25.26 Heb saving thyself.

∥ 25.27 Or, present.

† 25.27 Heb. walk at the feet of, &c.

† 25.29 Heb. in the midst of the bought of a sling.

† 25.31 Heb. no staggering, or, stumbling.

† 25.42 Heb. at her feet.

* 25.43 Josh. 15. 56.

* 25.44 2 Sam. 3 14, 15.

* 26.1 ch 23. 19.

* 26.5 ch. 14 50. &c 17. 55.

∥ 26.5 Or, midst of his carriages.

† 26.8 Heb. shut up.

† 26.16 Heb. the sons of death.

† 26.19 Heb smell.

† 26.19 Heb. cleaving.

† 27.1 Heb. be consumed.

† 27.7 Heb. the number of days.

† 27.7 Heb. a year of days

∥ 27.8 Or, Gerzites.

∥ 27.10 Or, Did you not make a road, &c.

† 27.12 Heb. to stink.

* 28.3 ch. 25. 1.

‡ 28.7 [1611 servant]

† 28.14 Heb. What is his form?

† 28.15 Heb. by the hand of prophets.

∥ 28.17 Or, for himself.

* 28.17 ch. 15. 28.

† 28.17 Heb. mine hand.

† 28.20 Heb. made haste, and fell with the fulness of his stature.

* 29.4 1 Chr. 12. 19.

* 29.5 ch. 18. 7. &c 21. 11.

† 29.6 Heb thou art not good in the eyes of the lords.

† 29.7 Heb. do not evil in the eyes of the lords.

† 29.8 Heb. before thee.

† 30.6 Heb. bitter.

† 30.17 Heb. their morrow.

∥ 30.21 Or, asked them how they did.

† 30.22 Heb. men.

† 30.25 Heb. and forward.

† 30.26 Heb. blessing.

* 31.1 1 Chr. 10. 1.

∥ 31.1 Or, wounded.

† 31.3 Heb. shooters, men with bows.

† 31.3 Heb. found him.

∥ 31.4 Or, mock me.

∥ 31.11 Or, concerning him.

* 31.12 Jer. 34. 5.

* 31.13 2 Sam. 2. 4.

1 Thessalonians

1
2
3
4
5

THE FIRST EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO THE THESSALONIANS

1

1  Paul, and Silvanus, and Timotheus, unto the church of the Thessalonians which is in God the Father and in the Lord Jesus Christ: Grace be unto you, and peace, from God our Father, and the Lord Jesus Christ. 2  We give thanks to God always for you all, making mention of you in our prayers; 3  Remembering without ceasing your work of faith, and labour of love, and patience of hope in our Lord Jesus Christ, in the sight of God and our Father; 4  Knowing, brethren [∥]beloved, your election of God. 5  For our gospel came not unto you in word only, but also in power, and in the Holy Ghost, and in much assurance; as ye know what manner of men we were among you for your sake. 6  And ye became followers of us, and of the Lord, having received the word in much affliction, with joy of the Holy Ghost: 7  So that ye were ensamples to all that believe in Macedonia and Achaia. 8  For from you sounded out the word of the Lord not only in Macedonia and Achaia, but also in every place your faith to God-ward is spread abroad; so that we need not to speak any thing. 9  For they themselves shew of us what manner of entering in we had unto you, and how ye turned to God from idols to serve the living and true God; 10  And to wait for his Son from heaven, whom he raised from the dead, even Jesus, which delivered us from the wrath to come.

2

1  For yourselves, brethren, know our entrance in unto you, that it was not in vain: 2  But even after that we had suffered before, and were shamefully entreated, as ye know, at Philippi, we were bold in our God to speak unto you the gospel of God with much contention. 3  For our exhortation was not of deceit, nor of uncleanness, nor in guile: 4  But as we were allowed of God to be put in trust with the gospel, even so we speak; not as pleasing men, but God, which trieth our hearts. 5  For neither at any time used we flattering words, as ye know, nor a cloke of covetousness; God is witness: 6  Nor of men sought we glory, neither of you, nor yet of others, when we might have [∥]been burdensome, as the apostles of Christ. 7  But we were gentle among you, even as a nurse cherisheth her children: 8  So being affectionately desirous of you, we were willing to have imparted unto you, not the gospel of God only, but also our own souls, because ye were dear unto us. 9  For ye remember, brethren, our labour and travail: for labouring night and day, because we would not be chargeable unto any of you, we preached unto you the gospel of God. 10  Ye are witnesses, and God also, how holily and justly and unblameably we behaved ourselves among you that believe: 11  As ye know how we exhorted and comforted and charged every one of you, as a father doth his children, 12  That ye would walk worthy of God, who hath called you unto his kingdom and glory.

13  For this cause also thank we God without ceasing, because, when ye received the word of God which ye heard of us, ye received it not as the word of men, but as it is in truth, the word of God, which effectually worketh also in you that believe. 14  For ye, brethren, became followers of the churches of God which in Judaea are in Christ Jesus: for ye also have suffered like things of your own countrymen, even as they have of the Jews: 15  Who both killed the Lord Jesus, and their own prophets, and have [∥]persecuted us; and they please not God, and are contrary to all men: 16  Forbidding us to speak to the Gentiles that they might be saved, to fill up their sins alway: for the wrath is come upon them to the uttermost.

17  But we, brethren, being taken from you for a short time in presence, not in heart, endeavoured the more abundantly to see your face with great desire. 18  Wherefore we would have come unto you, even I Paul, once and again; but Satan hindered us. 19  For what is our hope, or joy, or crown of [∥]rejoicing? Are not even ye in the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ at his coming? 20  For ye are our glory and joy.

3

1  Wherefore when we could no longer forbear, we thought it good to be left at Athens alone; 2  And sent Timotheus, our brother, and minister of God, and our fellowlabourer in the gospel of Christ, to establish you, and to comfort you concerning your faith: 3  That no man should be moved by these afflictions: for yourselves know that we are appointed thereunto. 4  For verily, when we were with you, we told you before that we should suffer tribulation; even as it came to pass, and ye know. 5  For this cause, when I could no longer forbear, I sent to know your faith, lest by some means the tempter have tempted you, and our labour be in vain. 6  But now when Timotheus came from you unto us, and brought us good tidings of your faith and charity, and that ye have good remembrance of us always, desiring greatly to see us, as we also to see you: 7  Therefore, brethren, we were comforted over you in all our affliction and distress by your faith: 8  For now we [*]live, if ye stand fast in the Lord. 9  For what thanks can we render to God again for you, for all the joy wherewith we joy for your sakes before our God; 10  Night and day praying exceedingly that we might see your face, and might perfect that which is lacking in your faith? 11  Now God himself and our Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ, [∥]direct our way unto you. 12  And the Lord make you to increase and abound in love one toward another, and toward all men, even as we do toward you: 13  To the end he may stablish your hearts unblameable in holiness before God, even our Father, at the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ with all his saints.

4

1  Furthermore then we [∥]beseech you, brethren, and [∥]exhort you by the Lord Jesus, that as ye have received of us how ye ought to walk and to please God, so ye would abound more and more. 2  For ye know what commandments we gave you by the Lord Jesus. 3  For this is the will of God, even your sanctification, that ye should abstain from fornication: 4  That every one of you should know how to possess his vessel in sanctification and honour; 5  Not in the lust of concupiscence, even as the Gentiles which know not God: 6  That no man go beyond and [∥]defraud his brother [∥]in any matter: because that the Lord is the avenger of all such, as we also have forewarned you and testified. 7  For God hath not called us unto uncleanness, but unto holiness. 8  He therefore that [∥]despiseth, despiseth not man, but God, who hath also given unto us his holy Spirit. 9  But as touching brotherly love ye need not that I write unto you: for ye yourselves are taught of God to love one another. 10  And indeed ye do it toward all the brethren which are in all Macedonia: but we beseech you, brethren, that ye increase more and more; 11  And that ye study to be quiet, and to do your own business, and to work with your own hands, as we commanded you; 12  That ye may walk honestly toward them that are without, and that ye may have lack [∥]of nothing.

13  But I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them which are asleep, that ye sorrow not, even as others which have no hope. 14  For if we believe that Jesus died and rose again, even so them also which sleep in Jesus will God bring with him. 15  For this we say unto you by the word of the Lord, that we which are alive and remain unto the coming of the Lord shall not prevent them which are asleep. 16  For the Lord himself shall descend from heaven with a shout, with the voice of the archangel, and with the trump of God: and the dead in Christ shall rise first: 17  Then we which are alive and remain shall be caught up together with them in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air: and so shall we ever be with the Lord. 18  Wherefore [∥]comfort one another with these words.

5

1  But of the times and the seasons, brethren, ye have no need that I write unto you. 2  For yourselves know perfectly that the day of the Lord so cometh as a thief in the night. 3  For when they shall say, Peace and safety; then sudden destruction cometh upon them, as travail upon a woman with child; and they shall not escape. 4  But ye, brethren, are not in darkness, that that day should overtake you as a thief. 5  Ye are all the children of light, and the children of the day: we are not of the night, nor of darkness. 6  Therefore let us not sleep, as do others; but let us watch and be sober. 7  For they that sleep sleep in the night; and they that be drunken are drunken in the night. 8  But let us, who are of the day, be sober, putting on the breastplate of faith and love; and for an helmet, the hope of salvation. 9  For God hath not appointed us to wrath, but to obtain salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ, 10  Who died for us, that, whether we wake or sleep, we should live together with him. 11  Wherefore [∥]comfort yourselves together, and edify one another, even as also ye do.

12  And we beseech you, brethren, to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admonish you; 13  And to esteem them very highly in love for their work’s sake. And be at peace among yourselves. 14  Now we [∥]exhort you, brethren, warn them that are [∥]unruly, comfort the feebleminded, support the weak, be patient toward all men. 15  See that none render evil for evil unto any man; but ever follow that which is good, both among yourselves, and to all men. 16  Rejoice evermore. 17  Pray without ceasing. 18  In every thing give thanks: for this is the will of God in Christ Jesus concerning you. 19  Quench not the Spirit. 20  Despise not prophesyings. 21  Prove all things; hold fast that which is good. 22  Abstain from all appearance of evil. 23  And the very God of peace sanctify you wholly; and I pray God your whole spirit and soul and body be preserved blameless unto the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ. 24  Faithful is he that calleth you, who also will do it. 25  Brethren, pray for us.

26  Greet all the brethren with an holy kiss. 27  I [∥]charge you by the Lord that this epistle be read unto all the holy brethren. 28  The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you. Amen.

The first epistle unto the Thessalonians was written from Athens.

∥ 1.4 Or, beloved of God, your election.

∥ 2.6 Or, used authority.

∥ 2.15 Or, chased us out.

∥ 2.19 Or, glorying.

* 3.8 Rom. 7. 9.

∥ 3.11 Or, guide.

∥ 4.1 Or, request.

∥ 4.1 Or, beseech.

∥ 4.6 Or, oppress, or, overreach.

∥ 4.6 Or, in the matter.

∥ 4.8 Or, rejecteth.

∥ 4.12 Or, of no man.

∥ 4.18 Or, exhort.

∥ 5.11 Or, exhort.

∥ 5.14 Or, beseech.

∥ 5.14 Or, disorderly.

∥ 5.27 Or, adjure.

2 Esdras

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15
16

The Second Book of Esdras

1

1 The second book of the prophet [a]Esdras, the son of [b]Saraias, the son of Azarias, the son of Helchias, the son of [*]Sadamias, the son of Sadoc, the son of Achitob,

2 The son of Achias, the son of Phinees, the son of Heli, the son of Amarias, the son of Aziei, the son of Marimoth, the son of Arna, the son of Ozias, the son of Borith, the son of Abisei, the son of Phinees, the son of Eleazar,

3 The son of Aaron, of the tribe of Levi; which was captive in the land of [c]the Medes, in the reign of Artexerxes king of the Persians.

4 And the word of the Lord came unto me, saying,

5 Go thy way, and [d]shew my people their sinful deeds, and their children their wickedness which they have done against me; that they may tell their children’s children:

6 Because the sins of their fathers are increased in them: for they have forgotten me, and have offered unto strange gods.

7 Am not I even he that [e]brought them out of the land of Egypt, from the house of bondage? but they have provoked me unto wrath, and despised my counsels.

8 [f]Pull thou off then the hair of thy head, and cast all evil upon them, for they have not been obedient unto my law, but [g]it is a rebellious people.

9 [h]How long shall I forbear them, into whom I have done so much [t]good?

10 Many kings have I destroyed for their sakes; [i]Pharaoh with his servants and all his power have I smitten down.

11 [j]All the nations have I destroyed before them, and in the east I have scattered the people of [k]two provinces, even [l]of Tyrus and Sidon, and have slain all their enemies.

12 Speak thou therefore unto them, saying, Thus saith the Lord,

13 [m]I led you through the sea and in the beginning gave you a large and safe [*]passage; I gave you [n]Moses for a leader, and [o]Aaron for a priest.

14 [p]I gave you light in a pillar of fire, and great wonders have I done among you; [q]yet have ye forgotten me, saith the Lord.

15 Thus saith the [r]Almighty Lord, The [s]quails were as a token to you; I gave you tents for your safeguard: nevertheless ye murmured there,

16 And triumphed not in my name for the destruction of your enemies, but ever to this day do ye yet murmur.

17 Where are the [t]benefits that I have done for you? when ye were hungry and thirsty in the wilderness, did ye not cry unto me,

18 Saying, [u]Why hast thou brought us into this wilderness to kill us? [v]it had been better for us to have served the Egyptians, than to die in this wilderness.

19 Then had I pity upon your mournings, and [w]gave you manna to eat; so [x]ye did eat angels’ bread.

20 [y]When ye were thirsty, did I not cleave the rock, and waters flowed out [*]to your fill? for the heat I covered you with the leaves of the trees.

21 I divided among you [z]a fruitful land, I cast out the Canaanites, the Pherezites, and the Philistines, before you: [a]what shall I yet do more for you? saith the Lord.

22 Thus saith the [b]Almighty Lord, When ye were in the wilderness, [*]in the river of the Amorites, being athirst, and blaspheming my name,

23 I gave you not fire for your blasphemies, but [c]cast a tree in the water, and made the river sweet.

24 What shall I do unto thee, O Jacob? [d]thou, Juda, [e]wouldest not obey me: [e]I will turn me to other nations, and unto those will I give my name, that they may keep my statutes.

25 [f]Seeing ye have forsaken me, I will forsake you also; when ye desire me to be gracious unto you, I shall have no mercy upon you.

26 [g]Whensoever ye shall call upon me, I will not hear you: for ye have defiled your hands with blood, and [h]your feet are swift to commit manslaughter.

27 Ye have not as it were forsaken me, but your own selves, saith the Lord.

28 Thus saith the [b]Almighty Lord, Have I not prayed you as a father his sons, as a mother her daughters, and a nurse her young babes,

29 That ye would be my people, [*]and I should be your God; that ye would be my children, and I should be your father?

30 [i]I gathered you together, as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings: but now, what shall I do unto you? I will cast you out from my face.

31 [k]When ye offer unto me, I will turn my face from you: for your solemn feastdays, your new moons, and your circumcisions, have I forsaken.

32 [l]I sent unto you my servants the prophets, whom ye have taken and slain, and torn their bodies in pieces, whose blood I will require of your hands, saith the Lord.

33 Thus saith the [b]Almighty Lord, [m]Your house is desolate, [n]I will cast you out [n][o]as the wind doth stubble.

34 And [p]your children shall not be fruitful; for they have despised my commandment, and done the thing that is an evil before me.

35 Your houses will I give to [q]a people that shall come; which not having heard of me yet shall believe me; to whom I have shewed no signs, yet they shall do that I have commanded them.

36 They have seen no prophets, yet they shall call their sins to remembrance, and acknowledge them.

37 I take to witness the grace of [q]the people to come, whose little ones rejoice in gladness: and [r]though they have not seen me with bodily eyes, yet in spirit they believe the thing that I say.

38 And now, [s]brother, behold what glory; and see [q]the people [t]that come from the east:

39 Unto whom I will give for leaders, [t]Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, Oseas, Amos, and Micheas, Joel, Abdias, and Jonas,

40 Nahum, and Abacuc, Sophonias, Aggeus, Zachary, and Malachy, which is called also an [u]angel of the Lord.

2

1 Thus saith the Lord, [a]I brought this people out of bondage, and [b]I gave them my commandments by menservants the prophets; whom they would not hear, but despised my counsels.

2 The mother that bare them saith unto them, Go your way, ye children; for [c]I am a widow and forsaken.

3 I brought you up with gladness; but with sorrow and heaviness have I lost you: for ye have sinned before the Lord your God, and done that thing that is evil before him.

4 But what shall I now do unto you? [c]I am a widow and forsaken: go your way, O my children, and ask mercy of the Lord.

5 As for me, O father, I call upon thee for a witness over the mother of these children, which would not keep my covenant,

6 That thou bring them to confusion, and [d]their mother to a spoil, [e]that there may be no offspring of them.

7 Let them be scattered abroad among the heathen, let their names be put out of the earth: for they have despised my [*]covenant.

8 Woe be unto thee, Assur, [f]thou that hidest the unrighteous in thee! O thou wicked people, remember [g]what I did unto Sodom and Gomorrha;

9 [g]Whose land lieth in clods of pitch and heaps of ashes: even so also will I do unto them that hear me not, saith the [h]Almighty Lord.

10 Thus saith the Lord unto Esdras, Tell my people that I will give them the kingdom of Jerusalem, which I would have given unto [i]Israel.

11 [i]Their glory also will I take unto me, and give these the [k]everlasting tabernacles, which I had prepared for [i]them.

12 They shall have the [l]tree of life for an ointment of sweet savour; [m]they shall neither labour, nor be weary.

13 Go, and ye shall receive: pray for few days unto you, [n]that they may be shortened: [o]the kingdom is already prepared for you: [p]watch.

14 [q]Take heaven and earth to witness; for I have broken the evil in pieces, and created the good: for [r]I live, saith the Lord.

15 [s]Mother, embrace thy children, and [*]bring them up with gladness, make their feet as fast as a pillar: [t]for I have chosen thee, saith the Lord.

16 And [u]those that be dead will I raise up again from their places, and [u]bring them out of the graves: for I have known [*]my name in Israel.

17 Fear not, thou [s]mother of the children: [t]for I have chosen thee, saith the Lord.

18 For thy help will I send my servants Esau and Jeremy, after whose counsel I have sanctified and prepared for thee [w]twelve trees laden with divers fruits,

19 And as many fountains [x]flowing with milk and honey, and seven mighty mountains, whereupon there grow [y]roses and [y]lilies, whereby I will fill thy children with joy.

20 [z]Do right to the widow, judge for the fatherless, give to the poor, defend the orphan, [a]clothe the naked,

21 Heal the broken and the weak, [b]laugh not a lame man to scorn, defend the maimed, and let the blind man come into the sight of my clearness.

22 Keep the old and young within thy walls.

23 [c]Wheresoever thou findest the dead, [*]take them and bury them, and [d]I will give thee the first place in my resurrection.

24 Abide still, O my people, and take thy rest, for thy quietness still come.

25 Nourish thy children, O thou [e]good nurse; stablish their feet.

26 [f]As for the servants whom I have given thee, there shall not one of them perish; for I will require them from among thy number.

27 Be not weary: for when the day of trouble and heaviness cometh, others shall weep and be sorrowful, but thou shalt be merry and have abundance.

28 The heathen shall envy thee, [g]but they shall be able to do nothing against thee, saith the Lord.

29 [h]My hands shall cover thee, so that thy children shall not see [i]hell.

30 Be joyful, O thou [e]mother, with thy children; for I will deliver thee, saith the Lord.

31 Remember thy children that sleep, for [k]I shall bring them out of the sides of the earth, and shew mercy unto them: for I am merciful, saith the Lord [l]Almighty.

32 Embrace thy children until I come and [*]shew mercy unto them: for my wells run over, and my grace shall not fail.

33 I Esdras received a charge of the Lord upon the mount [m]Oreb, that I should go unto Israel; but when I came unto them, they set me at nought, and despised the commandment of the Lord.

34 And therefore I say unto you, O ye heathen, that hear and understand, look for [n]your Shepherd, he shall give you everlasting [o]rest; for he is nigh at hand, [p]that shall come in the end of the world.

35 Be ready to the reward of the kingdom, for [q]the everlasting light shall shine upon you for evermore.

36 Flee [x]the shadow of this world, receive the joyfulness of [q]your glory: I testify [r]my Saviour openly.

37 O receive the gift that is given you, and be glad, giving thanks unto him [s]that hath led you to the heavenly kingdom.

38 Arise up and stand, behold [t]the number of those that be [u]sealed [*]in [w]the feast of the Lord;

39 Which are departed from [x]the shadow of the world, and [y]have received glorious garments of the Lord.

40 Take thy number, O Sion, and [*]shut up those of thine [y]that are clothed in white, which have fulfilled the law of the Lord.

41 [z]The number of thy children, whom thou longedst for, is fulfilled: beseech the power of the Lord, that thy people, [a]which have been called from the beginning, may be hallowed.

42 I Esdras saw [b]upon the mount Sion [c]a great people, whom I could not number, and they all praised the Lord with songs.

43 And in the midst of them there was a [h]young man of a high stature, taller than all the rest, and upon every one of their heads [d]he set crowns, and was more exalted; which I marvelled at greatly.

44 So I asked [e]the angel, and said, [*][f]Sir, what are these?

45 He answered and said unto me, These be they [g]that have put off the mortal clothing, and put on the immortal, and have confessed the name of God: now [d]are they crowned, and [c]receive palms.

46 Then said I unto [e]the angel, What [h]young person is it that crowneth them, and giveth them palms in their hands?

47 So he answered and said unto me, [d]It is the Son of God, whom they have confessed in the world. Then began I greatly to commend them that stood so stiffly for the name of the Lord.

48 Then [e]the angel said unto me, Go thy way, and [i]tell my people what manner of things, and how great wonders of the Lord thy God, thou hast seen.

3

1 In the thirtieth year after [a]the ruin of the city I was in Babylon, and lay troubled upon my bed, and [b]my thoughts came up over my heart:

2 For I saw the desolation of Sion, and the wealth of them that dwelt at Babylon.

3 And my spirit was sore moved, so that I began to speak words full of fear to the most High, and said,

4 O Lord, [bb]who bearest rule, thou spakest at the beginning, when thou didst plant the earth, and that [c]thyself alone, and commandedst the people,

5 And [d]gavest a body unto Adam without soul, which was the workmanship of thine hands, and [d]didst breathe into him the breath of life, and he was made living before thee.

6 And [e]thou leadest him into paradise, which thy right hand had planted, before ever the earth came forward.

7 And unto him thou gavest commandment to love thy way: which he transgressed, and immediately [f]thou appointedst death in him and in his generations, of whom came nations, tribes, people, and kindreds, out of number.

8 And [g]every people walked after their own will, and [h]did wonderful things before thee, and despised thy commandments.

9 And again in process of time [i]thou broughtest the flood upon those that dwelt in the world, and destroyedst them.

10 And it came to pass in every of them, that as death was to Adam, so was the flood to these.

11 Nevertheless one of them thou leftest, namely, [k]Noah with his household, of whom came all righteous men.

12 And it happened, that when they that dwelt upon the earth began to multiply, and had gotten them many children, and were a great people, they began again to be more ungodly than the first.

13 Now when they lived so wickedly before thee, [l]thou didst choose thee a man from among them, whose name was [m]Abraham.

14 [n]Him thou lovedst, and unto him only thou shewedst thy will:

15 And [o]madest an everlasting covenant with him, promising him that thou wouldest never forsake his seed.

16 And [p]unto him thou gavest Isaac, and [q]unto Isaac also thou gavest Jacob and Esau. As for Jacob, [r]thou didst choose him to thee, and put by Esau: and so [s]Jacob became a great multitude.

17 And it came to pass, that when thou leadest his seed out of Egypt, [t]thou broughtest them up to the mount Sinai.

18 And [u]bowing the heavens, [w]thou didst set fast the earth, movedst the whole world, and [x]madest the depths to tremble, and [y]troubledst the men of that age.

19 And [z]thy glory went through four gates, of fire, and of earthquake, and of wind, and of cold; that thou mightest give the law unto the seed of Jacob, [*]and diligence unto the generation of Israel.

20 And yet tookest thou not away from them a wicked heart, that thy law might bring forth fruit in them.

21 For [a]the first Adam bearing a wicked heart transgressed, and was overcome; and so be all they that are born of him.

22 Thus infirmity was made permanent; and [b]the law (also) in the heart of the people with [c]the malignity of the root; [b]so that the good departed away, and the evil abode still.

23 So the times passed away, and the years were brought to an end: then [d]didst thou raise thee up a servant, called David:

24 [e]Whom thou commandedst to build a city unto thy name, and to offer incense and oblations unto thee therein.

25 When this was done many years, then they that inhabited the city forsook thee,

26 And in all things did even as Adam and all his generations had done: for they also had a wicked heart:

27 And so thou gavest thy city over into the hands of thine enemies.

28 [f]Are their deeds then any better that inhabit Babylon, that they should therefore have the dominion over Sion?

29 For when I came thither, and had seen impieties without number, then my soul saw many evildoers in [g]this thirtieth year, so that [h]my heart failed me.

30 For [i]I have seen how thou sufferest them sinning, and hast spared wicked doers: and hast destroyed thy people, and hast preserved thine enemies, and hast not signified it.

31 I do not [*]remember how this way may be left: [f]Are they then of Babylon better than they of Sion?

32 Or is there any other people that knoweth thee beside Israel? or what generation hath so believed thy covenants as Jacob?

33 And yet their reward appeareth not, and their labour hath no fruit: for I have gone here and there through the heathen, and I see that they [*]flow in wealth, and think not upon thy commandments.

34 Weigh thou therefore our wickedness now in the balance, and their’s also that dwell the world; and so shall thy name no where be found but in Israel.

35 Or when was it that they which dwell upon the earth have not sinned in thy sight? or what people have so kept thy commandments?

36 Thou shalt find that Israel by name hath kept thy precepts; but not the heathen.

4

1 And the angel that was sent unto me, whose name was [a]Uriel, gave me an answer,

2 And said, Thy heart hath gone to far in this world, and [aa]thinkest thou to comprehend the way of the most High?

3 Then said I, Yea, my lord. And he answered me, and said, I am sent to shew thee [b]three ways, and to set forth three similitudes before thee:

4 Whereof if thou canst declare me one, I will shew thee also the way that thou desirest to see, and I shall shew thee from whence the wicked heart cometh.

5 And I said, Tell on, my lord. Then said he unto me, Go thy way, weigh me the weight of the fire, or measure me the blast of the wind, or call me again the day that is past.

6 Then answered I and said, What man is able to do that, that thou shouldest ask such things of me?

7 And he said unto me, If I should ask thee how great dwellings are [c]in the midst of the sea, or how many springs are in the beginning of the deep, or how many springs are above the firmament, or which are the outgoings of [d]paradise:

8 Peradventure thou wouldest say unto me, I never went down into the deep, nor as yet into hell, neither did I ever climb up into heaven.

9 Nevertheless [e]now have I asked thee but only of the fire and wind, and of the day wherethrough thou hast passed, and of things from which thou canst not be separated, and yet canst thou give me no answer of them.

10 He said moreover unto me, Thine own things, and such as are grown up with thee, canst thou not know;

11 How should [f]thy vessel then be able to comprehend the way of the Highest, and, the world being now outwardly corrupted to understand the [*]corruption that is evident in my sight?

12 Then said I unto him, It were better that we were not at all, than that we should live still in wickedness, and to suffer, and not to know wherefore.

13 He answered me, and said, I went into a forest into a plain, and [g]the trees took counsel,

14 And said, Come, let us go and make war against the sea that it may depart away before us, and that we may make us more woods.

15 The floods of the sea also in like manner took counsel, and said, Come, let us go up and subdue the woods of the plain, that there also we may make us another country.

16 The thought of the wood was in vain, for [h]the fire came and consumed it.

17 The thought of the floods of the sea came likewise to nought, for [i]the sand stood up and stopped them.

18 If thou wert judge now betwixt these two, whom wouldest thou begin to justify? or whom wouldest thou condemn?

19 I answered and said, Verily it is a foolish thought that they both have devised, for [*]the ground is given unto the wood, and the sea also hath his place to bear his [*]floods.

20 Then answered he me, and said, Thou hast given a right judgment, but why judgest thou not thyself also?

21 For like as [*]the ground is given unto the wood, and the sea to his floods: even so [e][j]they that dwell upon the earth may understand nothing but that which is upon the earth: and he that dwelleth above the heavens may only understand the things that are above the height of the heavens.

22 Then answered I and said, I beseech thee, O Lord, let me have understanding:

23 For it was not my mind to be curious of the high things, but of such as pass by us daily, namely, [k]wherefore Israel is given up as a reproach to the heathen, and for what cause the people whom thou hast loved is given over unto ungodly nations, and why the law of our forefathers is brought to nought, and the written covenants come [*]to none effect,

24 And we pass away out of the world [l]as grasshoppers, and our life is astonishment and fear, and we are not worthy to obtain mercy.

25 [k]What will he then do unto his name whereby we are called? of these things have I asked.

26 Then answered he me, and said, The more thou searchest, the more thou shalt marvel; for [m]the world hasteth fast to pass away,

27 And cannot comprehend the things that are promised to the righteous in time to come: for [n]this world is full of unrighteousness and infirmities.

28 But as concerning the things whereof thou askest me, I will tell thee; for the evil is sown, but the destruction thereof is not yet come.

29 If therefore that which is sown be not turned upside down, and if the place where the evil is sown pass not away, then cannot it come that is sown with good.

30 For [o]the grain of evil seed hath been sown in the heart of Adam from the beginning, and how much ungodliness hath it [p]brought up unto this time? and how much shall it yet [p]bring forth until the [*][q]time of threshing come?

31 Ponder now by thyself, how great fruit of wickedness the grain of evil seed hath [p]brought forth.

32 And when the ears shall be cut down, which are without number, how great a floor shall they fill?

33 Then I answered and said, How, and when shall these things come to pass? wherefore are our years [r]few and evil?

34 And he answered me, saying, Do not thou hasten above [s]the most Highest: for thy haste is in vain to be above him, for thou hast much exceeded.

35 Did not [t]the souls also of the righteous ask question of these things in their [u]chambers, saying, [t]How long shall I hope on this fashion? when cometh the fruit of the floor of our reward?

36 And unto these things [*]Uriel the [v]archangel gave them answer, and said, [w]Even when the number of seeds is filled in you: for he hath weighed the world in the balance.

37 By measure hath he measured the times; and by number hath he numbered the times; and he doth not move nor stir them, until the said measure be fulfilled.

38 Then answered I and said, [ww]O Lord that bearest rule, even we all are full of impiety.

39 And for our sakes peradventure it is that the floors of the righteous are not filled, because of the sins of them that dwell upon the earth.

40 So he answered me, and said, Go thy way to a woman with child, and ask of her when she hath fulfilled her nine months, if her womb may keep the birth any longer within her.

41 Then said I, No, Lord, that can she not. And he said unto me, In the grave the [u]chambers of souls are like the womb of a woman:

42 For like as a woman that travaileth maketh haste to escape the necessity of the travail: even so do these places haste to deliver those things that are committed unto them.

43 From the beginning, look, what thou desirest to see, it shall be shewed thee.

44 Then answered I and said, [x]If I have found favour in thy sight, and if it be possible, and if I be meet therefore,

45 Shew me then whether there be more to come than is past, or [y]more past than is to come.

46 What is past I know, but what is for to come I know not.

47 And he said unto me, Stand up upon the right side, and I shall expound the similitude unto thee.

48 So I stood, and saw, and, behold, an hot burning oven passed by before me: and it happened that when the flame was gone by I looked, and, behold, the smoke remained still.

49 After this there passed by before me a watery cloud, and sent down much rain with a storm; and when the stormy rain was past, the drops remained still.

50 Then said he unto me, Consider with thyself; as the rain is more than the drops, and as the fire is greater than the smoke; but the drops and the smoke remain behind: so [y]the [*]quantity which is past did more exceed.

51 Then I prayed, and said, [z]May I live, thinkest thou, until that time? or [*][a]what shall happen in those days?

52 He answered me, and said, [a]As for the tokens whereof thou askest me, I may tell thee of them in part: but [z]as touching thy life, I am not sent to shew thee; for I do not know it.

5

1 Nevertheless [a]as coming the tokens, behold, the days shall come, that they which dwell upon earth [*]shall be taken in a great number, and the way of truth shall be hidden, and [b]the land shall be barren of faith.

2 But [c]iniquity shall be increased above that which now thou seest, or that thou hast heard long ago.

3 And [d]the land, [*]that thou seest now to have root, shalt thou see wasted suddenly.

4 But if the most High grant thee to live, thou shalt see [e]after the third trumpet that [f]the sun shall suddenly shine again in the night, and the moon thrice in the day:

5 And [g]blood shall drop out of wood, and [h]the stone shall give his voice, and the people shall be troubled:

6 And even he shall rule, whom they look not for that dwell upon the earth, and the fowls shall take their flight away together:

7 And the Sodomitish sea shall cast out fish, and make a noise in the night, which many have not known: but they shall all hear the voice thereof.

8 There shall be a confusion also in many places, and the fire shall be oft [*]sent out again, and the wild beasts shall change their places, and menstruous women shall bring forth monsters:

9 And salt waters shall be found in the sweet, and all friends shall destroy one another; then [i]shall wit hide itself, and understanding withdraw itself into his [j]secret chamber,

10 And shall be sought of many, and yet not be found: then [c]shall unrighteousness and incontinency be multiplied upon earth.

11 One land also shall ask another, and say, Is righteousness that maketh a man righteous gone through thee? And it shall say, No.

12 At the same time shall men hope, but nothing obtain: they shall labour, but their ways shall not [*]prosper.

13 [k]To shew thee such tokens I have leave; and if thou wilt pray again, and [l]weep as now, and [l]fast even days, thou shalt hear yet greater things.

14 Then I awaked, and an extreme fearfulness went through all my body, and my mind was troubled, [q]so that it fainted.

15 So the angel that was come to talk with me held me, [ll]comforted me, and set me up upon my feet.

16 And in the second night it came to pass, that [m]Salathiel the captain of the people came unto me, saying, Where hast thou been? and why is thy countenance so heavy?

17 Knowest thou not that [n]Israel is committed unto thee in the land of their captivity?

18 Up then, and eat bread, and forsake us not, [o]as the shepherd that leaveth his flock in the hands of cruel wolves.

19 Then said I unto him, Go thy ways from me, and come not nigh me. And he heard what I said, and went from me.

20 And so [l]I fasted seven days, mourning and weeping, [l]like as [p]Uriel the angel commanded me.

21 And after seven days so it was, that the thoughts of my heart were very grievous unto me again,

22 And [q]my soul recovered the spirit of understanding, and I began to talk with the most High again,

23 [r]And said, O Lord that bearest rule, of every wood of the earth, and of all the trees thereof, thou hast ch[s]osen thee one only vine:

24 And of all lands of the whole world thou hast chosen thee [t]one pit: and of all the flowers thereof [u]one lily:

25 And of all the depths of the sea thou hast filled thee [w]one river: and of all builded cities thou hast hallowed Sion unto thyself:

26 And of all the fowls that are created thou hast named thee [x]one dove: and of all the cattle that are made thou hast provided thee [y]one sheep:

27 And among all the multitudes of people thou hast gotten thee one people: and unto this people, [z]whom thou lovedst, thou gavest a law that is approved of all.

28 And now, O Lord, why hast thou given this one people over unto many? and [*]upon [a]the one root hast thou prepared others, and why hast thou scattered thy [s]only one people among many?

29 And they which did gainsay thy promises, and believed not thy covenants, have trodden them down.

30 If thou didst so much hate thy people, yet shouldest thou punish them with thine own hands.

31 Now when I had spoken these words, the angel that came to me [b]the night afore was sent unto me,

32 And said unto me, Hear me, and I will instruct thee; hearken to the thing that I say, and I shall tell thee more.

33 And I said, Speak on, my Lord. Then said he unto me, Thou art sore troubled in mind for Israel’s sake: [c]lovest thou that people better than he that made them?

34 And I said, No, Lord: but of very grief have I spoken: for [d]my reins pain me every hour, while I labour [e]to comprehend the way of the most High, and to seek out part of his judgment.

35 And he said unto me, Thou canst not. And I said, Wherefore, Lord? whereunto was I born then? or [f]why was not my mother’s womb then my grave, that I might not have seen the travail of Jacob, and the wearisome toil of the stock of Israel?

36 And he said unto me, Number me the things that are not yet come, gather me together the dross that are scattered abroad, make me the flowers green again that are withered,

37 Open me the [j]places that are closed, and bring me forth the winds that in them are shut up, shew me the image of a voice: and then I will declare to thee the thing that thou labourest to know.

38 And I said, [g]O Lord that bearest rule, who may know these things, but he [h]that hath not his dwelling with men?

39 As for me, I am unwise: how may I then speak of these things whereof thou askest me?

40 Then said he unto me, Like as thou canst do none of these things that I have spoken of, even so canst thou not find out my judgment, or in the end [i]the love that I have promised unto my people.

41 And I said, Behold, O Lord, yet art thou nigh unto them that be reserved till the end: and what shall they do that have been before me, or we that be now, or they that shall come after us?

42 And he said unto me, I will liken my judgment unto a ring: [k]like as there is no slackness of the last, even so there is no swiftness of the first.

43 So I answered and said, Couldest thou not make those that have been made, and be now, and that are for to come, at once; [l]that thou mightest shew thy judgment the sooner?

44 Then answered he me, and said, The creature may not haste above the maker; neither may the world hold them at once that shall be created therein.

45 And I said, [m]As thou hast said unto thy servant, that thou, which givest life to all, hast given life at once to the creature that thou hast created, and the creature bare it: even so it might now also bear them that now be present at once.

46 And he said unto me, Ask the womb of a woman, and say unto her, If thou bringest forth children, why dost thou it not together, but one after another? pray her therefore to bring forth ten children at once.

47 And I said, She cannot: but must do it by distance of time.

48 Then said he unto me, Even so have I given the womb of the earth to those that be sown in it in their times.

49 For like as a young child may not bring forth the things that belong to the aged, even so have I disposed the world which I created.

50 And I asked, and said, Seeing thou hast now given me the way, I will proceed to speak before thee: for our mother, of whom [m]thou hast told me that she is young, draweth now nigh unto age.

51 He answered me, and said, Ask a woman that beareth children, and she shall tell thee.

52 Say unto her, Wherefore are unto they whom thou hast now brought forth [n]like those that were before, but less of stature?

53 And she shall answer thee, They that be born in the strength of youth are of one fashion, and they that are born in the time of age, when the womb faileth, are otherwise.

54 Consider thou therefore also, how that ye are less of stature than those that were before you.

55 And so are they that come after you less than ye, as the creatures which now begin to be old, and have passed over the strength of youth.

56 Then said I, Lord, I beseech thee, [o]if I have found favour in thy sight, shew thy servant [p]by whom thou visitest thy creature.

6

1 And he said unto me, In the beginning, when the [*]earth was made, before the borders of the world stood, or ever the winds blew,

2 Before it thundered and lightened, or ever the foundations of [a]paradise were laid,

3 Before [aa]the fair flowers were seen, or ever the moveable powers were established, before [b]the innumerable multitude of angels were gathered together,

4 Or ever the heights of the air were lifted up, before [c]the measures of the firmament were named, or ever the chimneys in Sion were hot,

5 And ere the present years were sought out, and or ever the inventions of them that now sin were turned, before they [d]were sealed that have [e]gathered faith [e]for a treasure:

6 Then did I consider these things, and [f]they all were made through me alone, and through none other: by me also they shall be ended, and by none other.

7 Then answered I and said, What shall be the [g]parting asunder of the times? or when shall be the end of the first, and the beginning of it that followeth?

8 And he said unto me, From Abraham unto Isaac, when Jacob and Esau were born of him, [h]Jacob’s hand held [*]first the heel of Esau.

9 For Esau is the end of the world, and Jacob is the beginning of it that followeth.

10 The hand of man is betwixt the heel and the hand: other question, Esdras, ask thou not.

11 I answered then and said, [i]O Lord that bearest rule, [j]if I have found favour in thy sight,

12 I beseech thee, shew thy servant the end of thy tokens, [k]whereof thou shewedst me part [l]the last night.

13 So he answered and said unto me, Stand up upon thy feet, and hear a mighty sounding voice.

14 And it shall be as it were a great [*]motion; but the place where thou standest shall not be moved.

15 And therefore when it speaketh be not afraid: for the word is of the end, and the foundation of the earth is understood.

16 And why? because the speech of these things trembleth and is moved: for it knoweth that the end of these things must be changed.

17 And it happened, that when I had heard it I stood up upon my feet, and hearkened, and, behold, there was a voice that spake, and [m]the sound of it was like the sound of many waters.

18 And it said, Behold, the days come, that I will begin to draw nigh, and [n]to visit them that dwell upon the earth,

19 And will begin to make inquisition of them, what they be that have hurt unjustly with their unrighteousness, and when the affliction of Sion shall be fulfilled;

20 And when the world, that shall begin to vanish away, shall be [*]finished, then will I shew these tokens: [o]the books shall be opened before the firmament, and they shall see all together:

21 And the children of a year old shall speak with their voices, the women with child shall bring forth untimely children of three or four months old, and they shall live, and be raised up.

22 And suddenly shall the sown places appear unsown, the full storehouses shall suddenly be found empty:

23 And [p]the trumpet shall give a sound, which when every man heareth, they shall be suddenly afraid.

24 At that time [q]shall friends [r]fight one against another like enemies, and the earth shall stand in fear with those that dwell therein, the springs of the fountains shall stand still, and in three hours they shall not run.

25 [r]Whosoever remaineth from all these that I have told thee shall escape, and [s]see my salvation, and the end of your world.

26 And the men [t]that are received shall see it, [t]who have not tasted death from their birth: and the heart of the inhabitants shall be changed, and turned into another meaning.

27 For evil shall be put out, and deceit shall be quenched.

28 As for faith, it shall flourish, corruption shall be overcome, and the truth, which hath been so long without fruit, shall be declared.

29 And when he talked with me, behold, I looked by little and little upon him before whom I stood.

30 And these words said he unto me; I am come to shew thee the time of the night to come.

31 [u]If thou wilt pray yet more, and [u]fast seven days again, I shall tell thee [u]greater things [x]by day than I have heard.

32 For thy voice is heard before the most High: for the Mighty hath seen thy righteous dealing, he hath seen also thy chastity, which thou hast had ever since thy youth.

33 And therefore hath he sent me to shew thee all these things, and to say unto thee, [y]Be of good comfort and fear not

34 And hasten not with the times that are past, [z]to think vain things, that thou mayest not hasten from the latter times.

35 And it came to pass after this, [a]that I wept again, and fasted seven days in like manner, that I might fulfil the three weeks which he told me.

36 [a]And in the eighth night was my heart vexed within me again, and I began to speak before the most High.

37 For my spirit was greatly set on fire, and my soul was in distress.

38 And I said, O Lord, thou spakest from the beginning of the creation, even the first day, and saidst thus; [b]Let heaven and earth be made; and thy word was a perfect work.

39 And [c]then was the spirit, and darkness and [cc]silence were on every side; the sound of man’s voice was not yet formed.

40 [d]Then commandedst thou a fair light to come forth [e]of thy treasures, that thy work might appear.

41 [f]Upon the second day thou madest the spirit of the firmament, and commandedst it to part asunder, and to make a division betwixt the waters, that the one part might go up, and the other remain beneath.

42 [g]Upon the third day thou didst command that the waters should be gathered in the seventh part of the earth: six parts hast thou dried up, and kept them, to the intent that of these some being planted of God and tilled might serve thee.

43 For as soon as thy word went forth the work was made.

44 For immediately there was [h]great and innumerable fruit, and many and divers pleasures for the taste, and [i]flowers of unchangeable colour, and odours of wonderful smell: and this was done the third day.

45 [j]Upon the fourth day thou commandedst that the sun should shine, and the moon give her light, and the stars should be in order:

46 And gavest them a charge to do [k]service unto man, that was to be made.

47 [l]Upon the fifth day thou saidst unto [m]the seventh part, where the waters were gathered that it should bring forth living creatures, fowls and fishes: and so it came to pass.

48 [l]For the dumb water and without life brought forth living things at the commandment of God, that all people might praise thy wondrous works.

49 Then didst thou ordain two living creatures, the one thou calledst [*]Enoch, and the other [n]Leviathan;

50 And didst separate the one from the other: for [m]the seventh part, namely, where the water was gathered together, might not hold them both.

51 Unto [o]Enoch thou gavest [m]one part, which was dried up the third day, that he should dwell in the same part, wherein are [p]a thousand hills:

52 But unto Leviathan thou gavest [m]the seventh part, namely, the moist; and [q]hast kept him to be devoured of whom thou wilt, and when.

53 [r]Upon the sixth day thou gavest commandment unto the earth, that before thee it should bring forth beasts, cattle, and creeping things:

54 [s]And after these, Adam also, whom thou madest lord of all thy creatures: of him come we all, and the people also whom thou hast chosen.

55 All this have I spoken before thee, O Lord, because [t]thou madest the world for our sakes

56 As for the other people, which also come of Adam, thou hast said that they are nothing, but be like unto spittle: and hast likened the abundance of them unto a drop that falleth from a vessel.

57 And now, O Lord, behold, these heathen, which have ever been reputed as nothing, have begun to be lords over us, and to devour us.

58 But we thy people, whom thou hast called [u]thy firstborn, thy only begotten, and thy fervent lover, are given into their hands.

59 If [t]the world now be made for our sakes, why do we not possess an inheritance with the world? [w]how long shall this endure?

7

1 And when I had made an end of speaking these words, there was sent unto me [a]the angel which had been sent unto me the nights afore:

2 And he said unto me, Up, Esdras, and hear the words that I am come to tell thee.

3 And I said, Speak on, [b]my God. Then said he unto me, The sea is set in a wide place, that it might be deep and great.

4 But put the case the entrance were narrow, and like a river;

5 Who then could go into the sea to look upon it, and to rule it? if he went not through the narrow, how could he come into the broad?

6 There is also another thing; A city is builded, and set upon a broad field, and is full of all good things:

7 The entrance thereof is narrow, and is set in a [*]dangerous place to fall, like as if there were a fire on the right hand, and on the left a deep water:

8 And one only path between them both, even between the fire and the water, so small that there could but one man go there at once.

9 If this city now were given unto a man for an inheritance, if he never shall pass the danger set before it, how shall he receive this inheritance?

10 And I said, It is so, Lord. Then said he unto me, Even so also is Israel’s portion.

11 Because [c]for their sakes I made the world: and [d]when Adam transgressed my statutes, then was decreed that now is done.

12 Then were the entrances of this world made narrow, [e]full of sorrow and travail: they are but few and evil, full of perils,: and very painful.

13 For the entrances of the [*][f]elder world were wide and sure, and brought [g]immortal fruit.

14 If then they that live labour not to enter these [h]strait and vain things, they can never [i]receive those that are laid up for them.

15 Now therefore why disquietest thou thyself, seeing thou art but a corruptible man? and why art thou moved, whereas thou art but mortal?

16 Why hast thou not considered in thy mind this thing that is to come, rather than that which is present?

17 Then answered I and said, [k]O Lord that bearest rule, thou hast ordained [l]in thy law, that the righteous should inherit these things, but that the ungodly should perish.

18 Nevertheless the righteous shall suffer strait things, and hope for wide: for they that have done wickedly have suffered the strait things, and yet shall not see the wide.

19 And he said unto me. There is no judge above God, and none that hath understanding above the Highest.

20 For there be many that perish in this life, because they despise the law of God that is set before them.

21 For God hath given strait commandment to such as came, what they should do to live, even as they came, and what they should observe to avoid punishment.

22 Nevertheless they were not obedient unto him; but spake against him, and imagined vain things;

23 And deceived themselves by their wicked deeds; and said of the most High, that he is not; and knew not his ways:

24 But [m]his law have they despised, and denied his covenants; in his statutes have they not been faithful, and have not performed his works.

25 And therefore, Esdras, [n]for the empty are empty things, and for the full are the full things.

26 Behold, the time shall come, that these tokens which I have told thee shall come to pass, and the bride shall appear, and she coming forth shall be seen, that now is withdrawn from the earth.

27 And whosoever is delivered from [o]the foresaid evils shall see my wonders.

28 For my son Jesus shall be revealed with those that be with him, and they that remain shall rejoice within [p]four hundred years.

29 [p]After these years shall my son Christ die, and all men that have life.

30 And the world shall be turned into [q]the old silence seven days, like as in the [*]former judgments: so that no man shall remain.

31 And after seven days the world, that yet awaketh not, shall be raised up, and that shall die that is corrupt

32 And [r]the earth shall restore those that are asleep in her, and so [r]shall the dust those that dwell in silence, and the [s]secret places shall deliver those souls that were committed unto them.

33 And [t]the most High shall appear upon the seat of judgment, and misery shall pass away, and the long suffering shall have an end:

34 But judgment only shall remain, [u]truth shall stand, and [u]faith shall wax strong:

35 And [v]the work shall follow, and [w]the reward shall be shewed, and the good deeds shall be of force, and wicked deeds shall bear no rule.

36 Then said I, [x]Abraham prayed first for the Sodomites, and [y]Moses for the fathers that sinned in the wilderness:

37 And [z]Jesus after him for Israel in the time of [*]Achan:

38 And [a]Samuel and [b]David for the destruction: and [c]Solomon for them that should come to the sanctuary:

39 And Helias [d]for those that received rain; and [e]for the dead, that he might live:

40 And [f]Ezechias for the people in the time of Sennacherib: and many for many.

41 Even so now, seeing corruption is grown up, and wickedness increased, and the righteous have prayed for the ungodly: wherefore shall it not be so now also?

42 He answered me, and said, This present life is not the end where much glory doth abide; therefore have they prayed for the weak.

43 But the day of doom shall be the end of this time, and the beginning of [g]the immortality for to come, [g]wherein corruption is past,

44 Intemperance is at an end, [h]infidelity is cut off, righteousness is grown, [h]and truth is sprung up.

45 Then [i]shall no man be able to save him that is destroyed, nor to oppress him [k]that hath gotten the victory.

46 I answered then and said, This is my first and last saying, that it had been better not to have given the earth unto Adam: or else, when it was given him, to have restrained him from sinning.

47 [l]For what profit is it for men now in this present time to live in heaviness, and after death to look for punishment?

48 O thou Adam, what hast thou done? for [m]though it was thou that sinned, thou art not fallen alone, but we all that come of thee.

49 For what profit is it unto us, if there be promised us an immortal time, whereas we have done [n]the works that bring death?

50 And that there is promised us an everlasting hope, whereas ourselves being most wicked are made vain?

51 And that there are laid up for us dwellings of health and safety, whereas we have lived wickedly?

52 And that the glory of the most High is kept to defend them which have led [*]a wary life, whereas we have walked in the most wicked ways of all?

53 And that there should be shewed [o]a paradise, whose fruit endureth for ever, wherein is [*]security and [p]medicine, since we shall not enter into it?

54 (For we have walked in unpleasant places.)

55 And that [q]the faces of them which have used abstinence shall shine above the stars, whereas [r]our faces shall be blacker than darkness?

56 For while we lived and committed iniquity, we considered not that we should begin to suffer for it after death.

57 Then answered he me, and said, This is the [*]condition of the battle, which man that is born upon the earth shall fight;

58 That, if he be overcome, he shall suffer [s]as thou hast said: but if he [k]get the victory, [t]he shall receive the thing that I say.

59 For this is the life whereof Moses spake unto the people while he lived, saying, [u]Choose thee life, that thou mayest live.

60 Nevertheless they believed not him, nor yet the prophets after him, no nor me which have spoken unto them,

61 That there should not be such heaviness in their destruction, as [w]shall be joy over them that are persuaded to salvation.

62 I answered then, and said, I know, Lord, that the most High is called merciful, in that he hath mercy upon them which are not yet come into the world,

63 And upon those also that turn to his law;

64 And that he is [x]patient, and long suffereth those that have sinned, as his creatures;

65 And that he is bountiful, for he is ready to give where it needeth;

66 And that he is of great mercy, for he multiplieth more and more mercies to them that are present, and that are past, and also to them which are to come.

67 For if he shall not multiply his mercies, the world would not [y]continue with them that inherit therein.

68 And he pardoneth; [z]for if he did not so of his goodness, that they which have committed iniquities might be eased of them, the ten thousandth part of men should not [y]remain living.

69 And being judge, if he should not forgive them that are [*]cured with his word, and put out the multitude of [*]contentions,

70 There should be very few left peradventure in an innumerable multitude.

8

1 And he answered me, saying, The most High hath made this world for many, [a]but the world to come for few.

2 I will tell thee a similitude, Esdras; As when thou askest the earth, it shall say unto thee, that it giveth much mould whereof earthen vessels are made, but little dust that gold cometh of: even so is the course of this present world.

3 There be [b]many created, but few shall be saved.

4 So answered I and said, Swallow then down, O my soul, understanding, and devour wisdom.

5 For thou hast agreed to give ear, and art willing to prophesy: [c]for thou hast no longer space than only to live.

6 O Lord, if thou suffer not thy servant, that we may pray before thee, and [*]thou give us seed unto our heart, and culture to our understanding, that there may come fruit of it; how shall each man live that is corrupt, who beareth the place of a man?

7 For thou art alone, and we all one workmanship of thine hands, [d]like as thou hast said.

8 For [*][e]when the body is fashioned now in the mother’s womb, and thou givest it members, thy creature is preserved in fire and water, and nine months doth thy workmanship endure thy creature which is created in her.

9 But that which keepeth and is kept shall both be preserved: and when the time cometh, the womb preserved delivereth up the things that grew in it.

10 For thou hast commanded out of the parts of the body, that is to say, out of the breasts, milk to be given, which is the fruit of the breasts,

11 That the thing which is fashioned may be nourished for a time, till thou disposest it to thy mercy.

12 Thou broughtest it up with thy righteousness, and nurturedst it in thy law, and reformedst it with thy judgment.

13 And [f]thou shalt mortify it as thy creature, and quicken it as thy work.

14 If therefore [g]thou shalt destroy him which with so great labour was fashioned, it is an easy thing to be ordained by thy commandment, that the thing which was made might be preserved.

15 Now therefore, Lord, I will speak; touching man in general, thou knowest best; but touching thy people, for whose sake I am sorry;

16 And for thine inheritance, for whose cause I mourn; and for Israel, for whom I am heavy; and for Jacob, for whose sake I am troubled;

17 Therefore will I begin to pray before thee for myself and for them: for I see the falls of us that dwell in the land.

18 But I have heard [h]the swiftness of the judge which is to come.

19 Therefore hear my voice, and understand my words, and I shall speak before thee. This is the beginning of the words of Esdras, [i]before he was taken up: and I said,

20 O Lord, thou that dwellest in everlastingness which beholdest from above things in the heaven and in the air;

21 Whose throne is inestimable; whose glory may not be comprehended; [j]before whom the hosts of angels stand with trembling,

22 [k]Whose service is conversant in wind and fire; whose word is true, and sayings constant; whose commandment is strong, and ordinance fearful;

23 [l]Whose look drieth up the depths, and indignation [m]maketh the mountains to melt away; which the truth witnesseth:

24 O hear the prayer of thy servant, and give ear to the petition of thy creature.

25 For while I live I will speak, and so long as I have understanding I will answer.

26 O look not upon the sins of thy people; but on them which serve thee in truth.

27 Regard not the wicked inventions of the heathen, but the desire of those that keep thy testimonies in afflictions.

28 Think not upon those that have walked feignedly before thee: but remember them, which according to thy will have known [n]thy fear.

29 Let it not be thy will to destroy them which have lived like beasts; but to look upon them that have clearly taught thy law.

30 Take thou no indignation at them which are deemed worse than beasts; but love them that always put their trust in thy righteousness and glory.

31 For we and our fathers [*]do languish of such diseases: but because of us sinners [o]thou shalt be called merciful.

32 For if thou [*]hast a desire to have mercy upon us, thou shalt be called [p]merciful, to us namely, that have no works of righteousness.

33 For the just, which have many good works laid up with thee, [q]shall out of their own deeds receive reward.

34 For what is man, that thou shouldest take displeasure at him? or what is a corruptible generation, that thou shouldest be so bitter toward it?

35 For in truth [r]them is no man among them that be born, but he hath dealt wickedly; and among the faithful there is none which hath not done amiss.

36 For [o]in this, O Lord, thy righteousness and thy goodness shall be declared, if thou be merciful unto them which have not the [*]confidence of good works.

37 Then answered he me, and said, Some things hast thou spoken aright, and according unto thy words it shall be.

38 For indeed I will not think on [s]the disposition of them which have sinned [t]before death, [u]before judgment, before destruction:

39 But [x]I will rejoice over [s]the disposition of the righteous, and I will remember also their [y]pilgrimage, and the salvation, and the reward, that they shall have.

40 Like as I have spoken now, so shall it come to pass.

41 For as the husbandman soweth much seed upon the ground, and planteth many trees, and yet the thing that is sown good in his season cometh not up, neither doth all that is planted take root: even so is it of them that are sown in the world; [z]they shall not all be saved.

42 I answered then and said, [a]If I have found grace, let me speak.

43 Like as the husbandman’s seed perisheth, if it come not up, and [b]receive not thy rain in due season; or if there come too much rain, and corrupt it:

44 Even so perisheth man also, which is formed with thy hands, and [c]is called thine own image, because thou art like unto him, [d]for whose sake thou hast made all things, and [e]likened him unto the husbandman’s seed.

45 Be not wroth with us but [f]spare thy people, and have mercy upon thine own inheritance: for thou art merciful unto thy creature.

46 Then answered he me, and said, Things present are for the present, and things to cometh for such as be to come.

47 For thou comest far short [g]that thou shouldest be able to love my creature more than I: but I have ofttimes drawn nigh unto thee, and unto it, but never to the unrighteous.

48 In this also thou art marvellous before the most High:

49 In that thou hast humbled thyself, as it becometh thee, and hast not judged thyself worthy to be much glorified among the righteous.

50 For many great miseries shall be done to them that [h]in the latter time shall dwell in the world, because they have walked in great [i]pride.

51 But understand thou for thyself, and seek out the glory for such as be like thee.

52 For unto you is [j]paradise opened, [k]the tree of life is planted, [l]the time to come is prepared, plenteousness is made ready, [m]a city is builded, and [n]rest is allowed, yea, perfect goodness and wisdom.

53 The root of evil [o]is sealed up from you, weakness and the [p]moth is hid from you, and corruption is fled into [*]hell to be forgotten:

54 [q]Sorrows are passed, and in the end is shewed the treasure of immortality.

55 And therefore ask thou no more questions concerning the multitude of them that perish.

56 For [r]when they had taken liberty, they despised the most High, thought scorn of his law, and forsook his ways.

57 Moreover they have trodden down his righteous,

58 And [s]said in their heart, that there is no God; yea, and that knowing they must die.

59 For as [t]the things aforesaid shalt receive you, so [u]thirst and pain are prepared for them: for [v]it was not his will that men should come to nought:

60 But they which be created have [w]defiled the name of him that made them, and were [x]unthankful unto him which prepared life for them.

61 And therefore [y]is my judgment now at hand.

62 These things have I not shewed unto all men, but unto thee, and a few [yy]like thee. Then answered I and said,

63 Behold, O Lord, now hast thou shewed me the multitude of the [z]wonders, which thou wilt begin to do [h]in the last times: but at what time, thou hast not shewed me.

9

1 He answered me then, and said, Measure thou the time diligently in itself: and when thou seest part of the [a]signs past, which I have told thee before,

2 Then shalt thou understand, that it is the very same time, wherein the Highest will begin to visit the world which he made.

3 Therefore when there shall be seen [b]earthquakes and [c]uproars of the people in the world:

4 Then shalt thou well understand, that the most High spake of those things from the days that were before thee, even from the beginning.

5 For like as all that is made in the world hath a beginning and an end, and the end is manifest:

6 Even so the times also of the Highest have plain beginnings in wonder and powerful works, and endings in effects and [a]signs.

7 And every one that shall be saved, and shall be able to escape [d]by his works, and [e]by faith, whereby ye have believed,

8 Shall be preserved from the said perils, and [f]shall see my salvation in my land, and within my borders: for [g]I have sanctified them for me from the beginning.

9 Then [*]shall they be in pitiful case, which now have abused my ways: and they that have cast them away despitefully shall dwell in torments.

10 For such as [h]in their life have received benefits, and have not known me;

11 And they that have loathed my law, [i]while they had yet liberty, and, when as yet [k]place of repentance was open unto them, understood not, but despised it;

12 The same must know it [l]after death by pain.

13 And therefore be thou not curious how the ungodly shall be punished, and when: but enquire [m]how the righteous shall be saved, whose the world is, and [n]for whom the world is created.

14 Then answered I and said,

15 I have said before, and now do speak, and will speak it also hereafter, that [o]there be many more of them which perish, than of them which shall be saved:

16 Like as a wave is greater than a drop.

17 And he answered me, saying, Like as the field is, so is also the seed; as the flowers be, such are the colours also; such as the workman is, such also is the work; and as the husbandman is himself, so is his husbandry also: [*]for it was the time of the world.

18 And now when I prepared the world, which was not yet made, even for them to dwell in that now live, no man spake against me.

19 For then every one obeyed: [*]but now the manners of them which are created in this world that is made are corrupted by a perpetual seed, and by a law which is unsearchable rid themselves.

20 So I considered the world, and, behold, there was peril because of the devices that were come into it.

21 And I saw, and [s]spared it greatly, and [t]have kept me a [*]grape of the cluster, and [t]a plant of a great people.

22 Let [o]the multitude perish then, which was born in vain; and let my [*]grape be kept, and my plant; for with great labour have I made it perfect.

23 Nevertheless, if thou wilt cease [u]yet seven days more, (but thou shalt not fast in them,

24 But go into a field of flowers, where no house is builded, and [w]eat only the flowers of the field; taste no flesh, drink no wine, but [x]eat flowers only;)

25 And pray unto the Highest continually, then will I come and talk with thee.

26 So I went my way into the field which is called Ardath, like as he commanded me; and there I sat among the flowers, and did eat of the herbs of the field, and the meat of the same satisfied me.

27 After seven days I sat upon the grass, and my heart was vexed within me, [y]like as before:

28 And I [z]opened my mouth, and began to talk before the most High, and said,

29 O Lord, thou that shewest thyself unto us, [a]thou wast shewed unto our fathers in the wilderness, in a place where no man [*]treadeth, in a barren place, when they came out of Egypt.

30 And thou spakest saying, Hear me, O Israel; and mark my words, thou seed of Jacob.

31 For, behold, I sow my law in you, and it shall bring fruit in you, and ye shall be honoured in it for ever.

32 But our fathers, which received the law, kept it not, and observed not thy ordinances: and [b]though the fruit of thy law did not perish, neither could it, for it was thine;

33 Yet they that received it perished, because they kept not the thing that was sown in them.

34 And, lo, it is a custom, when the ground hath received seed, or the sea a ship, or any vessel meat or drink, that, that being perished wherein it was sown or cast into,

35 That thing also which was sown, or cast therein, or received, doth perish, and remaineth not with us: but with us it hath not happened so.

36 For we [c]that have received the law perish by sin, and our heart also which received it

37 Notwithstanding [b]the law perisheth not, but remaineth in his force.

38 And when I spake these things in my heart, I looked back with mine eyes, and upon the right side I saw [d]a woman, and, behold, she mourned and wept with a loud voice, and was much grieved in heart, and [e]her clothes were rent, and she had [f]ashes upon her head.

39 [g]Then let I my thoughts go that I was in, and turned me unto her,

40 And said unto her, Wherefore weepest thou? why art thou so grieved in thy mind?

41 And she said unto me, [h]Sir, let me alone, that I may bewail myself, and add unto my sorrow, for I [i]am sore vexed in my mind, and brought very low.

42 And I said unto her, What aileth thee? tell me.

43 She said unto me, I thy servant have been barren, and had no child, though I had an husband thirty years,

44 And those thirty years I did nothing else day and night, and every hour, but [j]make my, prayer to the Highest.

45 After thirty years God heard me thine handmaid, looked upon my misery, considered my trouble, and gave me a son: and I was very glad of him, so was my husband also, and all my neighbours: and we gave great honour unto the Almighty.

46 And I nourished him with great travail.

47 So when he grew up, and came to the time that he should have a wife, [k]I made a feast.

10

1 And it so came to pass, that when my son was entered into his wedding chamber, he fell down, and died.

2 Then we all overthrew the lights, and [a]all my [*]neighbours rose up to comfort me: so I took my rest unto the second day at night.

3 And it came to pass, when they had all left off to comfort me, to the end I might be quiet; then rose I up by night and fled, and came hither into this field, as thou seest.

4 And I do now purpose not to return into the city, but here to stay, and neither to eat nor drink, but continually to mourn and to fast until I die.

5 [b]Then left I the [*]meditations wherein I was, and spake to her in anger, saying,

6 Thou foolish woman above all other, seest thou not our mourning, and what happeneth unto us?

7 How that Sion our mother is full of all heaviness, and [c]much humbled, mourning very sore?

8 And now, seeing we all mourn and are sad, for we are all in heaviness, art thou grieved for one son?

9 For ask the earth, and she shall tell thee, that it is she which ought to mourn for the fall of so many that grow upon her.

10 For out of her came all at the first, and out of her shall all others come, and, behold, they walk almost all into destruction, and a multitude of them is utterly [*]rooted out.

11 Who then should make more mourning than she, that hath lost so great a multitude; and not thou, which art sorry but for one?

12 But if thou sayest unto me, My lamentation is not like the earth’s, because I have lost the fruit of my womb, which I brought forth with pains, and bare with sorrows;

13 [*]But the earth not so: for the multitude present in it according to the course of the earth is gone, as it came:

14 Then say I unto thee, Like as thou hast brought forth with labour; even so the earth also hath given her fruit, namely, man, ever since the beginning unto him that made her.

15 Now therefore keep thy sorrow to thyself, and bear with a good courage that which hath befallen thee.

16 For [d]if thou shalt acknowledge the determination of God to be just, thou shalt both receive thy son in time, and shalt be commended among women.

17 Go thy way then into the city to thine husband.

18 And she said unto me, That will I not do: [e]I will not go into the city, but here will I die.

19 So I proceeded to speak further unto her, and said,

20 Do not so, but be counselled. by me: for how many are the adversities of Sion? be comforted in regard of the sorrow of Jerusalem.

21 For thou seest that [f]our sanctuary is laid waste, [f]our altar broken down, [g]our temple destroyed;

22 Our psaltery is laid on the ground, our song is put to silence, our rejoicing is at an end, [h]the light of our candlestick is put out, [i]the ark of our covenant is spoiled, [k]our holy things are defiled, and the name that is called upon us is almost profaned: our children are put to shame, our priests are burnt, our Levites are gone into captivity, [l]our virgins are defiled, and [l]our wives ravished; our righteous men carried away, our little ones destroyed, our young men are brought in bondage, and our strong men are become weak;

23 And, which is the greatest of all, [m]the seal of Sion hath now lost her honour; for [n]she is delivered into [o]the hands of them that hate us.

24 And therefore shake off thy great heaviness, and put away the multitude of sorrows, that the Mighty may be merciful unto thee again, and the Highest shall give thee rest and ease from thy labour.

25 And it came to pass while I was talking with her, behold, her face upon a sudden shined exceedingly, and her countenance glistered, so that I was afraid of her, and mused what it might be.

26 And, behold, suddenly she made a great cry very fearful: so that the earth shook at the noise of the woman.

27 And I looked, and, behold, the woman appeared unto me no more, but there was [p]a city builded, and a large place shewed itself from the foundations: then was I afraid, and cried with a loud voice, and said,

28 Where is [q]Uriel the angel, who came unto me at the first? for he hath caused me to fall [*]into many trances, and mine end is turned into corruption, and my prayer to rebuke.

29 And as I was speaking these words behold, he came unto me, and looked upon me.

30 And, lo, I lay as one that had been dead, and mine understanding was taken from me: and he took me by the right hand, and [s]comforted me, and [s]set me upon my feet, and said unto me,

31 What aileth thee? and why art thou so disquieted? and why is thine understanding troubled, and the thoughts of thine heart?

32 And I said, Because thou hast forsaken me, and yet I [t]did according to thy words, and I [u]went into the field, and, lo, I have seen, and yet see, that I am not able to express.

33 And he said unto me, Stand up manfully, and I will advise thee.

34 Then said I, Speak on, my lord, in me; only forsake me not, lest I die frustrate of my hope.

35 For I have seen that I knew not, and hear that I do not know.

36 Or is my sense deceived, or my soul in a dream?

37 Now therefore I beseech thee that thou wilt shew thy servant of this [*]vision.

38 He answered me then, and said, Hear me, and I shall inform thee, and tell thee wherefore thou art afraid: for the Highest will reveal many secret things unto thee.

39 He hath seen that thy [*]way is right: for that thou sorrowest continually for thy people, and makest great lamentation for Sion.

40 This therefore is the meaning of the vision which thou lately sawest:

41 [v]Thou sawest a woman mourning, and thou begannest to comfort her:

42 But now seest thou the likeness of the woman no more, but [w]there appeared unto thee a city builded.

43 And whereas she told thee of the death of her son, this is the [*]solution:

44 This woman, whom thou sawest is Sion: and whereas she said unto thee, even she whom thou seest as a city builded,

45 Whereas, I say, she said unto thee, [x]that she hath been thirty years barren: those are the thirty years wherein there was no offering made in her.

46 But after thirty years Solomon builded the city and [y]offered offerings: and then bare the barren a son.

47 And whereas she told thee that she nourished him with labour: that was the dwelling in Jerusalem.

48 But whereas she said unto thee, That my son coming into his marriage chamber [z]happened to have a fail, and died: this was the destruction that came to Jerusalem.

49 And, behold, [v]thou sawest her likeness, and because she mourned for her son, thou begannest to comfort her: and of these things which have chanced, these are to be opened unto thee.

50 For now the most High seeth that thou art grieved unfeignedly, and sufferest from thy whole heart for her, so hath he shewed thee the brightness of her glory, and the comeliness of her beauty:

51 And therefore [a]I bade thee remain in the field where no house was builded:

52 For I knew that the Highest [b]would shew this unto thee.

53 Therefore [a]I commanded thee to go into the field, where no foundation of any building was.

54 For in the place wherein the Highest [b]beginneth to shew his city, there can no man’s building be able to stand.

55 And therefore fear not, let not thine heart be affrighted, but go thy way in, and [c]see the beauty and greatness of the building, as much as thine eyes be able to see:

56 And then shalt thou hear as much as thine ears may comprehend.

57 For thou art blessed above many other, and [*]art called with the Highest; and so are but few.

58 But to morrow at night thou shalt remain here;

59 And so shall the Highest shew thee visions of the [*]high things, which the most High will do unto them that dwell upon the earth [d]in the last days. So I slept that night and another, like as he commanded me.

11

1 Then saw I a dream, and, behold, there came up [a]from the sea [aa]an eagle, which had twelve feathered wings, and three heads.

2 And I saw, and, behold, she spread her wings over all the earth, and all the winds of the air blew on her, and were gathered together.

3 And I beheld, and out of her feathers there grew other [b]contrary feathers; and they became little feathers and small.

4 But her heads were at rest: the head in the midst was greater than the other, yet rested [*]it with the residue.

5 Moreover I beheld, and, lo, the eagle flew with her feathers, and reigned upon earth, and over them that dwelt therein.

6 And I saw that all things under heaven were subject unto her, and no man spake against her, no, not one creature upon earth.

7 And I beheld, and, lo, the eagle rose upon her talons, and spake to her feathers, saying,

8 Watch not all at once: sleep every one in his own place, and watch by course:

9 But let the heads be preserved for the last.

10 And I beheld, and, lo, the voice went not out of her heads, but from the midst of her body.

11 And I numbered her [b]contrary feathers, and, behold, there were [f]eight of them.

12 And I looked, and, behold, [c]on the right side there arose one feather, and reigned over all the earth;

13 And so it was, that when it reigned, the end of it came, and [d]the place thereof appeared no more: so the next following stood up. and reigned, and had a great time;

14 And it happened, that when it reigned, the end of it came also, like as the first, so that it appeared no more.

15 Then came there a voice unto it, and said,

16 Hear thou that hast borne rule over the earth so long: this I say unto thee, before thou beginnest to appear no more,

17 There shall none after thee attain unto thy time, neither unto the half thereof.

18 Then arose the third, and reigned as the other before, and appeared no more also.

19 So went it with all the residue one after another, as that every one reigned, and then appeared no more.

20 Then I beheld, and, lo, in process of time the feathers that followed stood up [c]upon the right side, that they might rule also; and some of them ruled, but within a while they appeared no more:

21 For some of them were set up, but ruled not.

22 After this I looked, and, behold, [e]the twelve feathers appeared no more, nor the [f]two [b]little feathers:

23 And there was no more upon the eagle’s body, but three [g]heads that rested, and [f]six [b]little wings.

24 Then saw I also that two little feathers divided themselves from the six, and remained under the head that was upon the right side: for [i]the four continued [h]in their place.

25 And I beheld, and, lo, [h]the feathers that were under the wing thought to set up themselves and to have the rule.

26 And I beheld, and, lo, there was [i]one set up, but shortly it appeared no more.

27 And [i]the second was sooner away than the first.

28 And I beheld, and, lo, [i]the two that remained thought also in themselves to reign:

29 And when they so thought, behold, there awaked one of [g]the heads that were at rest, namely, it that was in the midst; for that was greater than the two other heads.

30 And then I saw that the two other heads were joined with it.

31 And, behold, the head was turned [j]with them that were with it, and did eat up [i]the two [h]feathers under the wing that would have reigned.

32 But this head put the whole earth in fear, and bare rule in it over all those that dwelt upon the earth [k]with much oppression; and it had the governance of the world more than all the wings that had been.

33 And after this I beheld, and, lo, the head that was in the midst suddenly appeared no more, [l]like as the wings.

34 But there remained the two heads, which also in like sort ruled upon the earth, and over those that dwelt therein.

35 And I beheld, and, lo, the head upon the right side devoured it that was upon the left side.

36 Then I head a voice, which said unto me, Look before thee, and consider the thing that thou seest.

37 And I beheld, and lo, as it were a roaring [m]lion chased out of the wood: and I saw that he sent out a man’s voice unto the eagle, and said,

38 Hear thou, I will talk with thee, and the Highest shall say unto thee,

39 Art not thou it that remainest of [n]the four beasts, whom I made to reign in my world, that the end of their times might come through them?

40 And [o]the fourth came, and overcame all the beasts that were past, and had power over the world with great fearfulness, and over [p]the whole compass of the earth [k]with much wicked oppression; and so long time dwelt he upon the earth with deceit.

41 For the earth hast thou not judged with truth.

42 For thou hast afflicted the meek, thou hast hurt the peaceable, thou hast loved liars, and destroyed the dwellings of them that brought forth fruit, and hast cast down the walls of such as did thee no harm.

43 Therefore is thy wrongful dealing come up unto the Highest, and thy pride unto the Mighty.

44 The Highest also hath looked upon the proud times, and, behold, they are ended, and his abominations are fulfilled.

45 And therefore appear no more, thou eagle, nor [q]thy horrible wings, nor [r]thy wicked feathers nor [q]thy malicious heads, nor thy hurtful [s]claws, nor all thy vain body:

46 That all the earth [t]may be refreshed, and may return, being delivered from thy violence, and that she may hope for the judgment and mercy of him that made her.

12

1 And it came to pass, whiles the lion spake these words unto the eagle, I saw,

2 And, behold, [a]the head that remained and [b]the four wings appeared no more, and [c]the two went unto it and set themselves up to reign, and [c]their kingdom was small, and fill of uproar.

3 And I saw, and, behold, they appeared no more, and the whole body of the eagle was burnt so that the earth was in great fear: then awaked I out of the trouble and [cc]trance of my mind, and from great fear, and said unto my spirit,

4 Lo, this hast thou done unto me, in that thou searchest out the ways of the Highest.

5 Lo, yet am I weary in my mind, and very weak in my spirit; and little strength is there in me, for the great fear wherewith I was afflicted this night.

6 Therefore will I now beseech the Highest, that he will comfort me unto the end.

7 And I said, [d]Lord that bearest rule, [e]if I have found grace before thy sight, and if I am justified with thee before many others, and if my prayer indeed be come up before thy face;

8 Comfort me then, and shew me thy servant the interpretation and plain difference of this fearful vision, that thou mayest perfectly comfort my soul.

9 [f]For [g]thou hast judged me worthy to shew me [h]the last times.

10 And he said unto me, This is the interpretation of the vision:

11 [i]The eagle, whom thou sawest come up from the sea, is the kingdom which was seen [j]in the vision of thy brother Daniel.

12 But it was not expounded unto him, therefore now I declare it unto thee.

13 Behold, the days will come, that there shall rise up a kingdom upon earth, and it shall be feared above all the kingdoms that were before it.

14 In the same [k]shall twelve kings reign, one after another:

15 Whereof [l]the second shall begin to reign, and shall have more time than any of the twelve.

16 And this do the twelve wings signify, which thou sawest.

17 As for the voice which thou heardest speak, and [m]that thou sawest [n]not to go out from the heads but from the midst of the body thereof, this is the interpretation:

18 That after the time of that kingdom there shall arise great strivings, and it shall stand in peril of failing: nevertheless it shall not then fall, but shall be restored again to his beginning.

19 And whereas thou sawest [o]the eight small under feathers sticking to her wings, this is the interpretation:

20 That in him there shall arise eight kings, whose times shall be but small, and their years swift.

21 And [p]two of them shall perish, the middle time approaching: [q]four shall be kept until their end begin to approach: but [r]two shall be kept unto the end.

22 And whereas thou sawest [s]three heads resting, this is the interpretation:

23 [t]In his last days shall the most High raise up three kingdoms, and renew many things therein, and they shall have the dominion of the earth,

24 And of those that dwell therein, [u]with much oppression, above all those that were before them: therefore are they called the heads of the eagle.

25 For these are they that shall accomplish his wickedness, and that shall finish his last end.

26 And whereas thou sawest that [w]the great head appeared no more, it signifieth that one of them shall die upon his bed, and yet with pain.

27 For the two that remain shall be slain with the sword.

28 For [x]the sword of the one shall devour the other: but at the last [y]shall he fall through the sword himself.

29 And whereas thou sawest [r]two feathers under the wings passing over the head that is on the right side;

30 It signifieth that these are they, whom the Highest [r]hath kept unto their end: this is [z]the small kingdom and full of trouble, as thou sawest.

31 And [a]the lion, whom thou sawest rising up out of the wood, and roaring, and speaking to the eagle, and rebuking her for her unrighteousness with all the words which thou hast heard;

32 This is the [*]anointed, which the Highest hath kept for them and for their wickedness unto the end: he shall reprove them, and shall upbraid them with their cruelty.

33 For he shall set them before him alive in judgment, and shall rebuke them, and correct them.

34 For the rest of my people shall he deliver with mercy, those that have been pressed upon my borders, and he shall make them joyful until the coming of the day of judgment, [b]whereof I have spoken unto thee from the beginning.

35 This is the dream that thou sawest, and these are the interpretations.

36 Thou only hast been meet to know this secret of the Highest.

37 Therefore [c]write all these things that thou hast seen in a book, and [cc]hide them:

38 And teach them to the wise of the people, whose hearts thou knowest may comprehend and keep these secrets.

39 But wait thou here thyself yet [d]seven days more, that it may be shewed thee, whatsoever it pleaseth the Highest to declare unto thee. And with that he went his way.

40 And it came to pass, when all the people saw that the seven days were past, and I not come again into [e]the city, they gathered them all together, from the least unto the greatest, and came unto me, and said,

41 What have we offended thee? and what evil have we done against thee, that thou forsakest us, and sittest here in this place?

42 For of all the [*]prophets thou only art left us, [f]as a cluster of the vintage, and [g]as a candle in a dark place, and as [h]a haven or ship preserved from the tempest.

43 Are not the evils which are come to us sufficient?

44 If thou shalt forsake us, [i]how much better had it been for us, if [j]we also had been burned in the midst of Sion?

45 [k]For we are not better than they that died there. And they wept with a loud voice. Then answered I them, and said,

46 Be of good comfort, O Israel; and be not heavy, thou house of Jacob:

47 For the Highest hath you in remembrance, and the Mighty hath not forgotten you in temptation.

48 As for me, I have not forsaken you, neither am I departed from you: but am come into this place, to pray for the desolation of Sion, and that I might seek mercy for the low estate of your sanctuary.

49 And now go your way home every man, and after these days will I come unto you.

50 So the people went their way into the city, like as I commanded them:

51 But I remained still in the field seven days, [l]as the angel commanded me; and [m]did eat only in those days of the flowers of the field, and had my meat of the herbs.

13

1 And it came to pass [a]after seven days, I dreamed a dream by night:

2 And, lo, there arose [*]a wind from the sea, that it moved all the waves thereof.

3 And I beheld, and, lo, that man waxed strong with the [*][b]thousands of heaven: and when he turned his countenance to look, all the things trembled that were seen under him.

4 And whensoever the voice went out of his mouth, all they burned that heard his voice, like as the earth faileth when it feeleth the fire.

5 And after this I beheld, and, lo, there was gathered together a multitude of men, out of number, from the four winds of the heaven, to subdue the man that came out of the sea

6 But I beheld, and, lo, he had graved himself a great mountain, and flew up upon it.

7 But I would have seen the region or place whereout the hill was graven, and I could not.

8 And after this I beheld, and, lo, all they which were gathered together to subdue him were sore afraid, and yet durst fight.

9 And, lo, as he saw the violence of the multitude that came, he neither lifted up his hand, nor held sword, nor any instrument of war:

10 But only I saw that he sent out of his mouth as it had been a blast of fire, and out of his lips a flaming breath, and out of his tongue he cast out sparks and tempests.

11 And they were all mixed together; the blast of fire, the flaming breath, and the great tempest; and fell with violence upon the multitude which was prepared to fight, and burned them up every one, so that upon a sudden of an innumerable multitude nothing was to be perceived, but only dust and smell of smoke: when I saw this I was afraid.

12 Afterward saw I the same man come down from the mountain, and call unto him another peaceable Multitude.

13 And there came much people unto him, whereof some were glad, some were sorry, [bb]and some of them were bound, and other some brought [*]of them that were offered: then was I sick through great fear, and I awaked, and said,

14 Thou hast shewed thy servant these wonders from the beginning, and [c]hast counted me worthy that thou shouldest receive my prayer:

15 Shew me now yet the interpretation of this dream.

16 For as I conceive in mine understanding, woe unto them that shall be left in those days and much more woe unto them that are not left behind!

17 For they that were not left were in heaviness.

18 Now understand I the things that are laid up [d]in the latter days, which shall happen unto them, and [e]to those that are left behind.

19 Therefore are they come into great perils and many necessities, like as these dreams declare.

20 Yet is it easier [f]for him that is in danger [e]to come into [*]these things, than to pass away as a cloud out of the world, and not to see the things that happen [d]in the last days. And he answered unto me, and said,

21 The interpretation of the vision shall I shew thee, and I will open unto thee the thing that thou hast required.

22 Whereas thou hast spoken of [e]them that are left behind, this is the interpretation:

23 He that shall endure the peril in that time [g]hath kept himself: [f]they that be fallen into danger are such as have [h]works, and [h]faith toward the Almighty.

24 Know this therefore, that [e]they which be left behind are more blessed than [e]they that be dead.

25 This is the meaning of the vision: Whereas thou sawest [i]a man coming up from [j]the midst of the sea:

26 The same is he whom God the Highest hath kept a great season, which [k]by his own self shall deliver his creature: and he shall order them [e]that are left behind.

27 And whereas thou sawest, that [l]out of his mouth there came as a blast of wind, and fire, and storm;

28 And that [m]he held neither sword, nor any instrument of war, but that [n]the rushing in of him destroyed the whole multitude [o]that came to subdue him; this is the interpretation:

29 Behold, the days come, when the most High will begin [p]to deliver them that are upon the earth.

30 And he shall come to [q]the astonishment of them that dwell on the earth.

31 And one shall undertake to fight against another, one city against another, one place against another, [r]one people against another, and [r]one realm against another.

32 And the time shall be when these things shall come to pass, and the signs shall happen [s]which I shewed thee before, and then shall my Son be declared, [i]whom thou sawest as a man ascending.

33 And when all the people hear his voice, every man shall in their own land leave the battle they have one against another.

34 And an innumerable multitude shall be gathered together, as thou sawest them, willing to come, and to overcome him by fighting.

35 But he shall stand upon the top of the [t]mount Sion.

36 And Sion shall come, and shall be shewed to all men, being prepared and builded, [t]like as thou sawest the hill graven without hands.

37 And this my Son shall rebuke the wicked inventions of those nations, which for their wicked life are fallen into the [u]tempest;

38 And shall lay before them their evil thoughts, and the torments wherewith they shall begin to be tormented, [u]which are like unto a flame: and he shall destroy them without labour by the law [u]which is like unto fire.

39 And whereas thou sawest that he gathered [x]another peaceable multitude unto him;

40 Those are the ten tribes, [y]which were carried away prisoners out of their own land in the time of Osea the king, whom [z]Salmanasar the king of Assyria led away captive, and he carried them over the waters, and so came they into another land.

41 But they took this counsel among themselves, that they would leave the multitude of the heathen, and go forth into a further country, where never mankind dwelt,

42 That they might there keep their statutes, which they never kept in their own land.

43 And they entered into [a]Euphrates by the narrow places of the river.

44 For the most High then shewed signs for them, and [b]held still the flood, till they were passed over.

45 For through that country there was a great way to go, namely, of a year and a half: and the same region is called [*]Arsareth.

46 Then dwelt they there [c]until the latter time; and now when they shall begin to come,

47 [d]The Highest shall [b]stay the springs of the stream again, that they may go through: therefore sawest thou the multitude with peace.

48 But those that be left behind of thy people are they that are found within my borders.

49 Now when he destroyeth the multitude of the nations that are gathered together, he shall defend his people that remain.

50 And then shall he shew them great wonders.

51 Then said I, [e]O Lord that bearest rule, shew me this: Wherefore have I [f]seen the man coming up from the midst of the sea?

52 And he said unto me, [g]Like as thou canst neither seek out nor know the things that are in the deep of the sea: even so can no man upon earth see my Son, or those that be with him, but in [h]the day time.

53 This is the interpretation of the dream which thou sawest, and whereby thou only art here lightened.

54 For thou hast forsaken thine own way, and applied thy diligence unto my law, and sought it.

55 Thy life hast thou ordered in wisdom, and [i]hast called understanding thy mother.

56 And therefore have I shewed thee the treasures of the Highest: after other three days I will speak other things unto thee, and declare unto thee mighty and wondrous things.

57 Then went I forth into the field, giving praise and thanks greatly unto the most High because of his wonders which he did in time;

58 And because he governeth the same, and such things as fall in their seasons: and there I sat three days.

14

1 And it came to pass [a]upon the third day, I sat under an oak, and, behold, there came a voice out of a bush over against me, and said, Esdras, Esdras.

2 And I said, Here am I, Lord And I stood up upon my feet.

3 Then said he unto me, [b]In the bush I did manifestly reveal myself unto Moses, and talked with him, when my people served in Egypt:

4 And I sent him and led my people out of Egypt, and brought him up to the mount of [c]where I held him by me a long season,

5 And told him many wondrous things, and shewed him the secrets of the times, and the end; and commanded him, saying,

6 These words shalt thou declare, and these shalt thou hide.

7 And now I say unto thee,

8 That thou lay up in thy heart the signs that I have shewed, and the dreams that thou hast seen, and the interpretations which thou hast heard:

9 For thou shalt be taken away from all, and from henceforth thou shalt remain with my [*]Son, and with such as be [d]like thee, until the times be ended.

10 For [e]the world hath lost his youth, and [e]the times begin to wax old.

11 For the world is divided into twelve parts, and the ten parts of it are gone already, and half of a tenth part:

12 And there remaineth that which is after the half of the tenth part.

13 Now therefore [f]set thine house in order, and reprove thy people, comfort such of them as be in trouble, and now renounce corruption,

14 Let go from thee mortal thoughts, [g]cast away the burdens of man, put off now the weak nature,

15 And set aside the thoughts that are most heavy unto thee, and haste thee to flee from these times.

16 For [h]yet greater evils than those which thou hast seen happen shall be done hereafter.

17 For look how much the world shall be weaker through age, so much the more shall evils increase upon them that dwell therein.

18 For [i]the time is fled far away, and [k]leasing is hard at hand: for now hasteth the vision to come, which thou hast seen.

19 Then answered I before thee, and said,

20 Behold, Lord, I will go, [l]as thou hast commanded me, and reprove the people which are present: but they that shall be born afterward, who shall admonish them? thus the world is set in darkness, and they that dwell therein are without light.

21 For [m]thy law is burnt, therefore no man knoweth the things that are done of thee, or the work that shall begin.

22 But [n]if I have found grace before thee, [o]send the Holy Ghost into me, and I shall write all that hath been done in the world since the beginning, which were written in thy law, that men may find thy path, and that they which will live [p]in the latter days may live.

23 And he answered me, saying, Go thy way, gather the people together, and say unto them, [q]that they seek thee not [r]for forty days.

24 But look thou prepare thee many [*]box trees, and take with thee Sarea, Dabria, Selemia, [*]Ecanus, and Asiel, these five which are [s]ready to write swiftly;

25 And come hither, and I [t]shall light a candle of understanding in thine heart, which shall not be put out, till the things be performed which thou shalt begin to write.

26 And when thou hast done, some things shalt thou publish, and [u]some things shalt thou shew secretly to the wise: to morrow this hour shalt thou begin to write.

27 Then went I forth, as he commanded, and gathered all the people together, and said,

28 [w]Hear these words, O Israel.

29 [x]Our fathers at the beginning were strangers in Egypt, from whence they were delivered:

30 And [y]received the law of life, which they kept not, which ye also have transgressed after them.

31 Then was the land, even the land of Sion, parted among you by lot: but your fathers, and ye yourselves, have done unrighteousness, and have not kept the ways which the Highest commanded you.

32 And forasmuch as he is [z]a righteous judge, he took from you in time the thing that he had given you.

33 And now are ye [a]here, and your brethren among you.

34 Therefore if so be that ye will subdue your own understanding, and reform your hearts, ye shall be kept alive and after death ye shall obtain mercy.

35 For [b]after death shall the judgment come, when we shall live again: and then shall the names of the righteous be manifest, and the works of the ungodly shall be declared.

36 [c]Let no man therefore come unto me now, nor seek after me these forty days.

37 So I took [d]the five men, [e]as he commanded me, and we went into the field, and remained there.

38 And the next day, behold, a voice called me, saying, Esdras, [f]open thy mouth, and drink that I give thee to drink.

39 Then opened I my mouth, and, behold, he reached me a full cup, which was full as it were with water, but the colour of it was like fire.

40 And I took it, and drank: and when I had drunk of it, my heart uttered understanding, and wisdom grew in my breast, for my spirit strengthened my memory:

41 And [g]my mouth was opened, and shut no more.

42 The Highest gave understanding unto [e]the five men, and they wrote the wonderful visions of the night that were told, which they knew not: and they sat forty days, and they wrote in the day, and at night they ate bread.

43 As for me. I spake in the day, and I held not my tongue by night.

44 [c]In forty days they wrote [*]two hundred and four books.

45 And it came to pass, when [c]the forty days were filled, that the Highest spake, saying, [h]The first that thou hast written publish openly, that the worthy and unworthy may read it:

46 But [h]keep the seventy last, that thou mayest deliver them only to such as be wise among the people:

47 For in them is the spring of understanding, [i]the fountain of wisdom, and [*]the stream of knowledge.

48 And I did so.

15

1 Behold, speak thou in the ears of my people the words of prophecy, which [a]I will put in thy mouth, saith the Lord:

2 And cause them to be written in [b]paper: for [c]they are faithful and true.

3 Fear not the imaginations against thee, let not the incredulity of them trouble thee, that speak against thee.

4 For [d]all the unfaithful shall die in their unfaithfulness.

5 Behold, saith the Lord, I will bring plagues upon the world; the sword, famine, death, and destruction.

6 For wickedness hath exceedingly polluted the whole earth, and their hurtful works are fulfilled.

7 Therefore saith the Lord,

8 I will hold my tongue no more as touching their wickedness, which they profanely commit, neither will I suffer them in those things, in which they wickedly exercise themselves: behold, [e]the innocent and righteous blood crieth unto me, and [e]the souls of the just complain continually.

9 And therefore, saith the Lord, I will surely avenge them, and receive unto me all the innocent blood from among them.

10 Behold, my people is led [f]as a flock to the slaughter: I will not suffer them now [g]to dwell in the land of Egypt:

11 But I will bring them [h]with a mighty hand and a stretched out arm, and smite Egypt with plagues, as before, and will destroy all the land thereof.

12 [i]Egypt shall mourn, and the foundation of it shall be smitten with the plague and punishment that God shall bring upon it.

13 They that till the ground shall mourn: for their seeds shall fail through the blasting and hail, and with [j]a fearful constellation.

14 [k]Woe to the world and them that dwell therein!

15 For the sword and their destruction draweth nigh, and [l]one people shall stand up and fight against another, and swords in their hands.

16 For there shall be sedition among men, and invading one another; they shall not regard their kings nor princes, and the course of their actions shall stand in their power.

17 A man shall desire to go into a city, and shall not be able.

18 For because of their pride the cities shall be troubled, the houses shall be destroyed, and men shall be afraid.

19 A man shall have no pity upon his neighbour, but shall destroy their houses with the sword, and spoil their goods, [m]because of the lack of bread, and for great tribulation.

20 Behold, saith God, I will call together all the kings of the earth to reverence me, which are from the rising of the sun, from the south, from the east, and [n]Libanus; to turn themselves one against another, and repay the things that they have done to them.

21 Like as they do yet this day unto [nn]my chosen, so will I do also, and [o]recompense in their bosom. Thus saith the Lord God;

22 My right hand shall not spare the sinners, and my sword shall not cease over [p]them that shed innocent blood upon the earth.

23 The fire is gone forth from his wrath, and hath consumed the foundations of the earth, and the sinners, like the straw that is kindled.

24 Woe to them that sin, and keep not my commandments! saith the Lord.

25 I will not spare them: go your way, ye children, from the power, defile not my sanctuary.

26 For the Lord knoweth all them that sin against him, and therefore delivereth he them unto death and destruction.

27 For now are the plagues come upon the whole earth and ye shall remain in them: for God shall not deliver you, because ye have sinned against him.

28 Behold an horrible vision, and the appearance thereof from the east:

29 Where the nations of [q]the dragons of Arabia shall come out with many chariots, and the multitude of them shall be carried as the wind upon earth, that all they which hear them may fear and tremble.

30 Also the [r]Carmanians raging in wrath shall go forth as the wild boars of the wood, and with great power shall they come, and join battle with them, and shall waste a portion of the land of the Assyrians.

31 And then shall [q]the dragons have the upper hand, remembering their nature; and if they shall turn themselves, conspiring together in great power to persecute [r]them,

32 Then [r]these shall be troubled bled, and keep silence through their power, and shall flee.

33 And from the land of the Assyrians shall the enemy besiege them, and consume some of them, and in their host shall be fear and dread, and strife [*]among their kings.

34 Behold clouds from the east and from the north unto the south, and they are very horrible to look upon, full of wrath and storm.

35 They shall smite one upon another, and [s]they shall smite down a great multitude of stars upon the earth, even their own [t]star; and [u]blood shall be from the sword unto the belly,

36 And dung of men unto the camel’s [*]hough.

37 And there shall be great fearfulness and trembling upon earth: and they that see the wrath shall be afraid, and trembling shall come upon them.

38 And then shall there come great storms from the south, and from the north, and another part from the west.

39 And strong winds shall arise from the east, and shall open it; and [x]the cloud which he raised up in wrath, and [t]the star stirred to cause fear toward the east and west wind, shall be destroyed.

40 The great and mighty clouds shall be puffed up [x]full of wrath, and [t]the star, that they may make all the earth afraid, and them that dwell therein; and they shall pour out over every high and eminent place [y]an horrible star,

41 Fire, and hail, and flying swords, and many waters, that all fields may be full, and all rivers, with the abundance of great waters.

42 And they shall break down the cities and walls, mountains and hills, trees of the wood, and grass of the meadows, and their corn.

43 And they shall go stedfastly unto Babylon, and [*][z]make her afraid.

44 They shall come to her, and besiege her, [a]the star and all wrath shall they pour out upon her: then shall the dust and [b]smoke go up unto the heaven, and [c]all they that be about her shall bewail her.

45 And they that remain under her shall do service unto them that have [z]put her in fear.

46 And thou, [d]Asia, that art [*]partaker of the hope of Babylon, and art the glory of her person:

47 Woe be unto thee, thou wretch, because thou hast made thyself like unto her; and hast decked thy daughters in whoredom, that they might please and glory in thy lovers, which have always desired to commit whoredom with thee.

48 Thou hast followed her that is hated in all her works and inventions: therefore saith God,

49 [e]I will send plagues upon thee; widowhood, poverty, famine, sword, and pestilence, to waste thy houses with destruction and death.

50 And the glory of thy Power [f]shall be dried up as a flower, the heat shall arise that is sent over thee.

51 Thou shalt be weakened as a poor woman with stripes, and as one chastised with wounds, so that the mighty and lovers shall not be able to receive thee.

52 [g]Would I with jealousy have so proceeded against thee, saith the Lord,

53 If thou hadst not always slain [h]my chosen, exalting the stroke of thine hands, and saying over their [*]dead, [i]when thou wast drunken,

54 [k]Set forth the beauty of thy countenance?

55 The reward of thy whoredom shall be [l]in thy bosom, therefore shalt thou receive recompence.

56 Like as thou hast done unto [h]my chosen, saith the Lord, even so shall God do unto thee, and shall deliver thee into mischief

57 Thy children shall die of hunger, and thou shalt fall through the sword: thy cities shall be broken down, and all thine shall perish with the sword in the field.

58 They that be in the mountains shall die of hunger, and [m]eat their own flesh, and drink their own blood, for very hunger of bread, and thirst of water.

59 Thou as unhappy shalt come through the sea, and receive plagues again.

60 And in the passage they shall rush on the [n]idle city, and shall destroy some portion of thy land, and [q]consume part of thy glory, and shall return to Babylon that was destroyed.

61 And thou shalt be cast down by them [o]as stubble, and they shall be unto thee as fire;

62 And shall consume thee, and thy cities, thy land, and thy mountains; all thy woods and thy fruitful trees shall they burn up with fire.

63 Thy children shall they carry away captive, and, look, [p]what thou hast, they shall spoil it, and [*][q]mar the [q]beauty of thy face.

16

1 [a]Woe be unto thee, Babylon, and Asia! woe be unto thee, [b]Egypt and Syria!

2 [c]Gird up yourselves with cloths of sack and [d]hair, bewail your children, and be sorry; for your destruction is at hand.

3 A sword is sent upon you, and who may turn it back?

4 [e]A fire is sent among you, and who may quench it?

5 [f]Plagues are sent unto you, and what is he that may drive them away?

6 May any man drive away an hungry lion in the wood? or may any one quench [g]the fire in stubble, when it hath begun to burn?

7 [h]May one turn again the arrow that is shot of a strong archer?

8 [f]The mighty Lord sendeth the plagues and who is he that can drive them away?

9 [e]A fire shall go forth from his wrath, and who is he that may quench it?

10 [i]He shall cast lightnings, and who shall not fear? [i]he shall thunder, and who shall not be afraid?

11 The Lord shall threaten, and who shall not be utterly beaten to powder at his presence?

12 [j]The earth quaketh, and the foundations thereof; the sea ariseth up with waves from the deep, and [k]the waves of it are troubled, and the fishes thereof also, [l]before the Lord, and before the glory of his power:

13 For [m]strong is his right hand that bendeth the bow, [i]his arrows that he shooteth are [n]sharp, and shall not miss, when they begin to be shot into the ends of the world.

14 Behold, the plagues are sent, and shall not return again, until they come upon the earth.

15 [e][o]The fire is kindled, and shall not be put out, till it consume the foundation of the earth.

16 [h]Like as an arrow which is shot of a mighty archer returneth not backward: even so the plagues that shall be sent upon earth shall not return again.

17 Woe is me! woe is me! who will deliver me in those days?

18 [p]The beginning of sorrows and great mournings; the beginning of famine and great death; the beginning of wars, and the powers shall stand in fear; the beginning of evils! what shall I do when these evils shall come?

19 Behold, famine and plague, [q]tribulation and anguish, are sent as scourges for amendment.

20 But for all these things they shall not turn from their wickedness, nor be always mindful of the scourges.

21 Behold, victuals shall be so good cheap upon earth, that they shall think themselves to be in good case, and even then shall [*]evils grow upon earth, sword, famine, and great confusion.

22 For many of them that dwell upon earth shall perish of famine; and the other, that escape the hunger, shall the sword destroy.

23 And [r]the dead shall be cast out as dung, and there shall be no man to comfort them: for the earth shall be wasted, and the cities shall be cast down.

24 There shall be no man left to till the earth, and to sow it

25 The trees shall give fruit, and who shall gather them?

26 The grapes shall ripen, and who shall [s]tread them? for all places shall be desolate of men:

27 So that one man shall desire to see another, and to hear his voice.

28 For of a city there shall be [t]ten left, and two of the field, which shall hide themselves in the thick groves, and [u]in the clefts of the rocks.

29 [x]As in an orchard of Olives upon every tree there are left three or four olives;

30 [x]Or as when a vineyard is gathered, there are left some clusters of them that diligently seek through the vineyard:

31 Even so in those days there shall be [y]three or four left by them that search their houses with the sword.

32 And the earth shall be laid waste, and the fields thereof shall wax old, and her ways and all her paths shall grow full of thorns, because no man shall travel therethrough.

33 [z]The virgins shall mourn, having no bridegrooms; the women shall mourn, having no husbands; their daughters shall mourn, having no helpers.

34 In the wars shall their bridegrooms be destroyed, and their husbands shall perish of famine.

35 Hear now these things and understand them, [a]ye servants of the Lord.

36 Behold, the word of the Lord, receive it: believe not the gods of whom the Lord spake.

37 Behold, the plagues draw nigh, and are not slack.

38 [b]As when a woman with child in the ninth month bringeth forth her son, with two or three hours of her birth great pains compass her womb, which pains, when the child cometh forth, they slack not a moment:

39 Even so shall not the plagues be slack to come upon the earth, and the world shall mourn, and sorrows shall come upon it on every side.

40 O my people, hear my word: make you ready to thy battle, and in those evils be even as [c]pilgrims upon the earth.

41 [d]He that selleth, let him be as he that fleeth away: and he that buyeth, as one that will lose:

42 He that [e]occupieth merchandise, as he that hath no profit by it: and he that buildeth, as he that shall not dwell therein:

43 He that soweth, as if he should not reap: so also he that planteth the vineyard, as he that shall not gather the grapes:

44 They that marry, as they that shall get no children; and they that marry not, as the widowers.

45 And therefore they that labour labour in vain:

46 For strangers shall reap their fruits, and spoil their goods, overthrow their houses, and take their children captives, for [*]in captivity and famine shall they get children.

47 And they that [e]occupy their merchandise with robbery, the more they deck their cities, their houses, their possessions, and their own persons:

48 The more [f]will I be angry with them for their sin, saith the Lord.

49 Like as a whore [g]envieth a [h]right honest and virtuous woman:

50 So shall righteousness [g]hate iniquity, [i]when she decketh herself, and shall accuse her to her face, when he cometh that shall defend him that diligently searcheth out every sin upon earth.

51 And therefore be ye not like thereunto, nor to the works thereof.

52 For [j]yet a little, and iniquity shall be taken away out of the earth, and righteousness shall reign among you.

53 [k]Let not the sinner say that he hath not sinned: for God [l]shall burn coals of fire upon his head, [k]which saith before the Lord God and his glory, I have not sinned.

54 Behold, the Lord knoweth all the works of men, their [z]imaginations, their thoughts, and their [m]hearts:

55 Which spake but the word, [n]Let the earth be made; and it was made: Let the heaven be made; and it was created.

56 In his word were the stars made, and [o]he knoweth the number of them.

57 He searcheth the deep, and the treasures thereof; [p]he hath measured the sea, and what it containeth.

58 [q]He hath shut the sea in the midst of the waters, and with his word [r]hath he hanged the earth [s]upon the waters.

59 [t]He spreadeth out the heavens like a vault; [u]upon the waters hath he founded it.

60 [x]In the desert hath he made springs of water, and pools upon the tops of the mountains, that the floods might pour down from the high rocks to water the earth.

61 [y]He made man, and put his heart in the midst of the body, and gave him breath, life, and understanding.

62 Yea and the Spirit of Almighty God, which made all things, and searcheth out all hidden things in the secrets of the earth,

63 Surely he knoweth your [z]inventions, and what ye think in your hearts, even them that sin, and would hide their sin.

64 Therefore hath the Lord exactly searched out all your works, and he will put you all to shame.

65 And [a]when your sins are brought forth, ye shall be ashamed before men, and your own sins shall be your accusers in that day.

66 What will ye do? or how will ye hide your sins before God and [b]his angels?

67 Behold, [c]God himself is the judge, fear him: leave off from your sins, and forget your iniquities, to meddle no more with them for ever: so shall God lead you forth, and [d]deliver you from all trouble.

68 For, behold, the burning wrath of a great multitude is kindled over you, and they shall take away certain of you, and feed you, [*]being [e]idle, with [f]things offered unto idols.

69 And they that consent unto them shall be had in derision and in reproach, and trodden under foot.

70 For there shall be in every place, and in the next cities, a great insurrection upon those that fear the Lord.

71 They shall be like mad men, sparing none, but still spoiling and destroying those that fear the Lord.

72 For they shall waste and take away their goods, and cast them out of [g]their houses.

73 Then shall they be known, who are [h]my chosen; and [i]they shall be tried as the gold in the fire.

74 Hear, O ye my beloved, saith the Lord: behold, the days of trouble are at hand, but [d]I will deliver you from the same.

75 Be ye not afraid neither doubt; for [k]God is your guide,

76 And the guide of them who keep my commandments and precepts, saith the Lord God: [l]let not your sins weigh you down, and let not your iniquities lift up themselves.

77 Woe be unto them that are bound with their sins, and covered with their iniquities [m]like as a field is covered over with bushes, and the path thereof covered with thorns, that no man may travel through!

78 It is [*]left undressed, and is cast into the fire to be consumed therewith.

a 1.1 To ver. 3, Ezra 7. 1–5.

b 1.1 To ver. 2, 1 Chr. 6. 4–14.

* 1.1 Or, Shallum. 1 Chr. 6. 12, 13. Ezra 7. 2.

c 1.3 See Acts 2. 9.

d 1.5 Isai. 58. 1.

e 1.7 Ex. 20. 2.

f 1.8 Ezra 9. 3. Esther 14. 2.

g 1.8 See Ex. 32. 9.

h 1.9 Num. 14. 11.

t 1.9 Latin as ver. 9.

i 1.10 Exod. 14. 28.

j 1.11 Josh. ch. 8, & 10, & 12.

k 1.11 Numb. 21. 23, 24, 33–35.

l 1.11 Josh. 11. 8.

m 1.13 Ex. 14. 29.

* 1.13 Or, street. Comp. Isai. 62. 10.

n 1.13 Ex. 3. 10.

o 1.13 Ex. 4. 14.

p 1.14 Ex. 13. 21.

q 1.14 See Jer. 2. 32.

r 1.15 ver. 22, 28, 33. ch. 2. 9, 31. See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

s 1.15 See Exod. 16. 13.

t 1.17 Latin as ver. 9.

u 1.18 Numb. 14. 3.

v 1.18 Ex. 14. 12.

w 1.19 Ex. 16. 14, 15.

x 1.19 See Wisd. 16. 20.

y 1.20 See Wisd. 11. 4.

* 1.20 Or, abundantly.

z 1.21 See Ex. 3. 8.

a 1.21 Isai. 5. 4.

b 1.22 ver. 15.

* 1.22 Or, at the bitter waters, or, waters of Marah. Ex. 15. 23, 24.

c 1.23 Ex. 15. 25. Ecclus. 38. 5.

d 1.24 Ps. 81. 11.

e 1.24 Ex. 32. 8, 10. Num. 14. 11, 12.

e 1.24 Ex. 32. 8, 10. Num. 14. 11, 12.

f 1.25 See 2 Chr. 15. 2.

g 1.26 See Prov. 1. 28.

h 1.26 See Isai. 59. 7.

b 1.28 ver. 15.

* 1.29 Or, as I am your God.

i 1.30 Matt. 23. 37. Luke 13. 34.

k 1.31 Isai. 1. 13, 14.

l 1.32 So ch. 2. 1. See 2 Chr. 36. 15, 16.

b 1.33 ver. 15.

m 1.33 Matt. 23. 38. See Luke 13. 35.

n 1.33 So Isai. 40. 24.

n 1.33 So Isai. 40. 24.

o 1.33 See Ps. 83. 13.

p 1.34 Deut. 28. 18. ch. 2. 6.

q 1.35 ver. 37, 38 (Lat.).

q 1.37 ver. 37, 38 (Lat.).

r 1.37 John 20. 29.

s 1.38 Comp. ch. 2. 44, 46, 48. Also Rev. 19. 10. & 22. 9.

q 1.38 ver. 37, 38 (Lat.).

t 1.38 Matt. 8. 11.

t 1.39 Matt. 8. 11.

u 1.40 Mal. 3. 1 (Heb. & Gk.).

a 2.1 So Deut. 4. 20. Amos 2. 10. Micah 6. 4.

b 2.1 So ch. 1. 32. See 2 Chr. 36. 15, 16.

c 2.2 ver. 4. Comp. Isai. 47. 8, 9.

c 2.4 ver. 4. Comp. Isai. 47. 8, 9.

d 2.6 Judith 9. 4. See 1 Esdr. 8. 77.

e 2.6 See ch. 1. 34.

* 2.7 [Or,] sacrament, or, oath. [Lat. not as ver. 5. ch. 3. 15].

f 2.8 Comp. ch. 1. 3.

g 2.8 See Gen. 19. 24.

g 2.9 See Gen. 19. 24.

h 2.9 See ch. 1. 15.

i 2.10 ver. 10.

i 2.11 ver. 10.

k 2.11 Luke 16. 9 (Gk. & Lat.).

i 2.11 ver. 10.

l 2.12 ch. 8. 52. Rev. 2. 7. & 22. 2, 14. See Prov. 3. 18.

m 2.12 So Isai. 5. 27 (Lat.).

n 2.13 Comp. Matt. 24. 22.

o 2.13 Matt. 25. 34. Comp. ch. 8. 52.

p 2.13 Mark 13. 37.

q 2.14 See Deut. 4. 26.

r 2.14 See Isai. 49. 18.

s 2.15 ver. 2, 17, 30. So ver. 25?

* 2.15 Or, bring them up with gladness, as a dove, make their feet fast: for, &c.

t 2.15 ver. 17.

u 2.16 John 5. 28, 29. See Dan. 12. 2.

u 2.16 John 5. 28, 29. See Dan. 12. 2.

* 2.16 Or, thy name, O Israel.

s 2.17 ver. 2, 17, 30. So ver. 25?

t 2.17 ver. 17.

w 2.18 Comp. Rev. 22. 2.

x 2.19 See Ex. 3. 8.

y 2.19 Cant. 2. 1.

y 2.19 Cant. 2. 1.

z 2.20 Isai. 1. 17. See Ex. 22. 22.

a 2.20 Matt. 25. 36.

b 2.21 Comp. Lev. 19. 14. Deut. 27. 18.

c 2.23 Tobit 1. 17, 18.

* 2.23 [Lat.] signing bury them.

d 2.23 Comp. Matt. 19. 28.

e 2.25 See ver. 15.

f 2.26 John 17. 12.

g 2.28 Comp. Isai. 54. 17.

h 2.29 So Isai. 51. 16.

i 2.29 See Matt. 5. 22 (Gk.).

e 2.30 See ver. 15.

k 2.31 Comp. 1 Thess. 4. 14.

l 2.31 See ch. 1. 15.

* 2.32 Or, preach.

m 2.33 Ex. 3. 1. Deut. 4. 10, 15. Ecclus. 48. 7.

n 2.34 John 10. 11.

o 2.34 Matt. 11. 29.

p 2.34 See Heb. 1. 2.

q 2.35 Isai. 60. 19, 20. See Rev. 21. 23.

x 2.36 ver. 36.

q 2.36 Isai. 60. 19, 20. See Rev. 21. 23.

r 2.36 See Luke 1. 47.

s 2.37 1 Thess. 2. 12.

t 2.38 Rev. 7. 4.

u 2.38 ch. 6. 5. & 8. 53. Comp. ch. 6. 20 marg.

* 2.38 Or, for.

w 2.38 Rev. 19. 9. See Matt. 22. 2.

x 2.39 ver. 36.

y 2.39 See Rev. 3. 4.

* 2.40 Lat. conclude.

y 2.40 See Rev. 3. 4.

z 2.41 So ch. 4. 36. Rev. 6. 11. Comp. ch. 5. 43.

a 2.41 ch. 9. 8. Comp. Eph. 1. 4.

b 2.42 Rev. 14. 1.

c 2.42 Rev. 7. 9.

h 2.43 Lat. as ver. 43.

d 2.43 Rev. 2. 10. So Rev. 4. 4.

e 2.44 See ch. 1. 38.

* 2.44 Or, Lord. ch. 4. 3, 5, 22, 41. & 5. 33, 34, 35. & 9. 41.

f 2.44 Rev. 7. 14.

g 2.45 Comp. 2 Cor. 5. 4.

d 2.45 Rev. 2. 10. So Rev. 4. 4.

c 2.45 Rev. 7. 9.

e 2.46 See ch. 1. 38.

h 2.46 Lat. as ver. 43.

d 2.47 Rev. 2. 10. So Rev. 4. 4.

e 2.48 See ch. 1. 38.

i 2.48 Comp. Rev. 10. 11. & 22. 10.

a 3.1 2 Kin. 25. 8, &c.

b 3.1 So Luke 24. 38.

bb 3.4 See ch. 5. 23.

c 3.4 Isai. 44. 24.

d 3.5 Gen. 2. 7.

d 3.5 Gen. 2. 7.

e 3.6 Gen. 2. 8.

f 3.7 Gen. 3. 19.

g 3.8 Gen. 6. 12.

h 3.8 Gen. 6. 11.

i 3.9 Gen. 7. 10.

k 3.11 Gen. 8. 1. 1 Pet. 3. 20.

l 3.13 Gen. 12. 1.

m 3.13 Gen. 17. 5.

n 3.14 See 2 Chr. 20. 7.

o 3.15 Gen. 17. 7.

p 3.16 Gen. 21. 2, 3.

q 3.16 Gen. 25. 25, 26.

r 3.16 Mal. 1. 2, 3. Rom. 9. 13.

s 3.16 Gen. 32. 10.

t 3.17 Exod. 19. 1. So Deut. 4. 10.

u 3.18 See 2 Sam. 22. 10.

w 3.18 Ps. 93. 1. & 96. 10.

x 3.18 Ps. 77. 16.

y 3.18 Ex. 20. 18–21.

z 3.19 Comp. Ex. 19. 16, 18.

* 3.19 [Or,] and to all the generation of Israel, that they should keep it with diligence.

a 3.21 See ch. 7. 48.

b 3.22 Rom. 7. 8–13.

c 3.22 So ch. 8. 53. Comp. Deut. 29. 18.

b 3.22 Rom. 7. 8–13.

d 3.23 1 Sam. 16. 13.

e 3.24 2 Sam. 5. 2. & 7. 5, 13.

f 3.28 ver. 31.

g 3.29 ver. 1.

h 3.29 So Ps. 73. 26.

i 3.30 Comp. ch. 5. 3.

* 3.31 Or, conceive.

f 3.31 ver. 31.

* 3.33 Or, abound.

a 4.1 ver. 36 (text). ch. 5. 20. & 10. 28.

aa 4.2 So ch. 5. 34.

b 4.3 ver. 5.

c 4.7 Lat. as Prov. 23. 34 marg. ch. 13. 25, 51.

d 4.7 ch. 6. 2. & 8. 52.

e 4.9 So ver. 21. Wisd. 9. 16. John 3. 12.

f 4.11 1 Thess. 4. 4. So 2 Cor. 4. 7.

* 4.11 Or, incorruption.

g 4.13 Judg. 9. 8. 2 Chr. 25. 18.

h 4.16 Judg. 9. 15.

i 4.17 Comp. Job 38. 8, 10, 11.

* 4.19 [Or,] the land. ver. 21.

* 4.19 Or, waves. So ver. 15, 17, 21.

* 4.21 [Or,] the land. ver. 19.

e 4.21 So ver. 21. Wisd. 9. 16. John 3. 12.

j 4.21 So Isai. 55. 8, 9. John 3. 31. 1 Cor. 2. 14.

k 4.23 ch. 3. 31–36.

* 4.23 Or, no where.

l 4.24 Comp. Job 4. 19.

k 4.25 ch. 3. 31–36.

m 4.26 See 1 John 2. 17.

n 4.27 So 1 John 5. 19.

o 4.30 See ch. 7. 48.

p 4.30 Lat. as ver. 31.

p 4.30 Lat. as ver. 31.

* 4.30 Or, floor. So ver. 32, 35, 39.

q 4.30 Jer. 51. 33.

p 4.31 Lat. as ver. 31.

r 4.33 Gen. 47. 9.

s 4.34 Lat. as ver. 11.

t 4.35 Rev. 6. 9, 10.

u 4.35 ver. 41. ch. 5. 9, 37 (Lat.). & 7. 32 (Lat.).

t 4.35 Rev. 6. 9, 10.

* 4.36 [Or,] Jeremiel. See ver. 1.

v 4.36 1 Thess. 4. 16. Jude 9.

w 4.36 See ch. 2. 41.

ww 4.38 See ch. 5. 23.

u 4.41 ver. 41. ch. 5. 9, 37 (Lat.). & 7. 32 (Lat.).

x 4.44 Gen. 33. 10. ch. 5. 56. & 6. 11. & 12. 7 (Lat.). So ch. 8. 42. & 14. 22 in the Lat. See Gen. 33. 15.

y 4.45 Comp. ver. 50.

y 4.50 Comp. ver. 50.

* 4.50 Or, measure. So ver. 37.

z 4.51 ver. 51.

* 4.51 Or, who shall be? Manuscript.

a 4.51 ver. 51. ch. 5. 1, 13. See ch. 8. 63.

a 4.52 ver. 51. ch. 5. 1, 13. See ch. 8. 63.

z 4.52 ver. 51.

a 5.1 ch. 4. 52.

* 5.1 [Or,] shall be found with great wealth. So ch. 15. 63 (Lat.).

b 5.1 Comp. Luke 18. 8.

c 5.2 Matt. 24. 12. So ver. 10

d 5.3 Isai. 13. 1, 6, &c. Comp. ch. 3. 30.

* 5.3 Or, that thou treadest upon and seest.

e 5.4 Rev. 8. 10.

f 5.4 Comp. Zech. 14. 7.

g 5.5 John 19. 34. Comp. Wisd. 14. 7.

h 5.5 See Luke 19. 40.

* 5.8 Or, slaked.

i 5.9 See Prov. 22. 3.

j 5.9 See ch. 4. 35.

c 5.10 Matt. 24. 12. So ver. 10

* 5.12 Or, be directed.

k 5.13 ch. 4. 52.

l 5.13 ver. 20. ch. 6. 31.

l 5.13 ver. 20. ch. 6. 31.

q 5.14 Comp. ver. 14.

ll 5.15 ch. 10. 30.

m 5.16 1 Esdr. 5. 5, 48, 56. & 6. 2. See 1 Chr. 3. 17.

n 5.17 Ezra 7. 6.

o 5.18 John 10. 12.

l 5.20 ver. 20. ch. 6. 31.

l 5.20 ver. 20. ch. 6. 31.

p 5.20 ch. 6. 35. See ch. 4. 1.

q 5.22 Comp. ver. 14.

r 5.23 ch. 3. 4. & 4. 38. ver. 38. ch. 6. 11. & 7. 17. & 12. 7. & 13. 51.

s 5.23 ver. 28 (Lat.). See Ps. 80. 8.

t 5.24 Isai. 51. 1?

u 5.24 See Cant. 2. 1.

w 5.25 Ps. 46. 4? Isai. 8. 6?

x 5.26 Gen. 8. 8–11.

y 5.26 Ex. 12. 5? See John 1. 29.

z 5.27 See Deut. 7. 8.

* 5.28 Or, over.

a 5.28 Ps. 80. 9.

s 5.28 ver. 28 (Lat.). See Ps. 80. 8.

b 5.31 ch. 3. 1. & 4. 1. So ch. 6. 12.

c 5.33 ch. 8. 47.

d 5.34 So Ps. 16. 7. & 73. 21.

e 5.34 So ch. 4. 2.

f 5.35 Job 3. 11.

j 5.37 See ch. 4. 35.

g 5.38 See ver. 23.

h 5.38 So Dan. 2. 11.

i 5.40 Comp. Eph. 3. 19.

k 5.42 Comp. 1 Thess. 4. 15.

l 5.43 See ch. 2. 41.

m 5.45 Comp. ver. 50.

m 5.50 Comp. ver. 50.

n 5.52 Gen. 6. 4. Num. 13. 33. 1 Sam. 17. 4. 2 Sam. 21. 16–22.

o 5.56 See ch. 4. 44.

p 5.56 ch. 6. 18.

* 6.1 Or, circle of the earth. So ch. 11. 40.

a 6.2 See ch. 4. 7.

aa 6.3 ver. 44.

b 6.3 Heb. 12. 22. So ch. 13. 3.

c 6.4 Gen. 1. 6, 7.

d 6.5 See ch. 2. 38.

e 6.5 Comp. Rom. 2. 5.

e 6.5 Comp. Rom. 2. 5.

f 6.6 Comp. Prov. 8. 22–30.

g 6.7 ver. 6.

h 6.8 Gen. 25. 26.

* 6.8 Or, from the beginning. ch. 3. 4 (Lat.). & 4. 30.

i 6.11 See ch. 5. 23.

j 6.11 See ch. 4. 44.

k 6.12 ch. 5. 1–13.

l 6.12 See ch. 5. 31.

* 6.14 Or, earthquake. Comp. ch. 3. 18. & 9. 3 in the Lat.

m 6.17 See Rev. 1. 15.

n 6.18 ch. 5. 56.

* 6.20 Or, sealed. See ch. 2. 38.

o 6.20 See Dan. 7. 10.

p 6.23 See 1 Cor. 15. 52.

q 6.24 ch. 5. 9.

r 6.24 Comp. Matt. 10. 21, 22.

r 6.25 Comp. Matt. 10. 21, 22.

s 6.25 ch. 9. 8. See Luke 2. 30.

t 6.26 Comp. 1 Thess. 4. 15.

t 6.26 Comp. 1 Thess. 4. 15.

u 6.31 ch. 5. 13.

u 6.31 ch. 5. 13.

u 6.31 ch. 5. 13.

x 6.31 Comp. ch. 13. 52.

y 6.33 See Josh. 1. 9.

z 6.34 So 1 Sam. 12. 21.

a 6.35 ch. 5. 20, 21. So ch. 9. 23. & 10. 32. & 12. 39.

a 6.36 ch. 5. 20, 21. So ch. 9. 23. & 10. 32. & 12. 39.

b 6.38 Gen. 1. 1.

c 6.39 Gen. 1. 2.

cc 6.39 ch. 7. 30.

d 6.40 Gen. 1. 3.

e 6.40 See Ps. 135. 7.

f 6.41 Gen. 1. 6, 7.

g 6.42 Gen. 1. 9.

h 6.44 Gen. 1. 11.

i 6.44 ver. 3.

j 6.45 Gen. 1. 14.

k 6.46 Gen. 1. 15. Deut. 4. 19.

l 6.47 Gen. 1. 20, 22.

m 6.47 ver. 42.

l 6.48 Gen. 1. 20, 22.

* 6.49 [Or,] Behemoth. See Job 40. 15?

n 6.49 See Job 41. 1.

m 6.50 ver. 42.

o 6.51 ver. 49 marg.?

m 6.51 ver. 42.

p 6.51 Ps. 50. 10.

m 6.52 ver. 42.

q 6.52 Ps. 74. 14.

r 6.53 Gen. 1. 24.

s 6.54 Gen. 1. 26.

t 6.55 ver. 59. ch. 7. 11. So ch. 8. 44. & 9. 13.

u 6.58 Ecclus. 17. 18. & 36. 12. See Ex. 4. 22.

t 6.59 ver. 59. ch. 7. 11. So ch. 8. 44. & 9. 13.

w 6.59 See Ps. 74. 10.

a 7.1 ch. 4. 1. & 5. 31.

b 7.3 Comp. ch. 5. 33.

* 7.7 Or, steep place.

c 7.11 See ch. 6. 55. Comp. ver. 13.

d 7.11 See ver. 48.

e 7.12 So Job 5. 7. & 14. 1.

* 7.13 Or, greater.

f 7.13 Comp. ver. 11.

g 7.13 See Gen. 2. 9.

h 7.14 Comp. Matt. 7. 14.

i 7.14 So ver. 9.

k 7.17 See ch. 5. 23.

l 7.17 See Deut. 8. 1.

m 7.24 See Num. 15. 31.

n 7.25 Comp. 2 Cor. 9. 6.

o 7.27 ver. 20–25.

p 7.28 Comp. Dan. 9. 26.

p 7.29 Comp. Dan. 9. 26.

q 7.30 ch. 6. 39.

* 7.30 Or, first beginning.

r 7.32 So Isai. 26. 19. See Dan. 12. 2.

r 7.32 So Isai. 26. 19. See Dan. 12. 2.

s 7.32 See ch. 4. 35.

t 7.33 Comp. Matt. 25. 31.

u 7.34 So ver. 44.

u 7.34 So ver. 44.

v 7.35 Rev. 14. 13.

w 7.35 Matt. 16. 27. See Ps. 62. 12.

x 7.36 Gen. 18. 23.

y 7.36 Exod. 32. 11.

z 7.37 Josh. 7. 6, 7.

* 7.37 Or, Achor. See Josh. 7. 1.

a 7.38 1 Sam. 7. 9.

b 7.38 2 Sam. 24. 17.

c 7.38 1 Kings 8. 23. &c. 2 Chr. 6. 14, &c.

d 7.39 1 Kings 18. 42, 45. James 5. 18.

e 7.39 1 Kings 17. 21.

f 7.40 2 Kings 19. 15.

g 7.43 1 Cor. 15. 54.

g 7.43 1 Cor. 15. 54.

h 7.44 So ver. 34.

h 7.44 So ver. 34.

i 7.45 Comp. Ps. 49. 7, 8.

k 7.45 So ver. 58. See Rom. 8. 37.

l 7.47 Eccles. 2. 22, 23.

m 7.48 ch. 3. 21, 26. & 4. 30. ver. 11. Rom. 5. 18.

n 7.49 Rom. 6. 23.

* 7.52 Or, a chaste life.

o 7.53 Rev. 2. 7.

* 7.53 Or, fulness.

p 7.53 Rev. 22. 2.

q 7.55 See Matt. 13. 43.

r 7.55 So Lam. 4. 8.

* 7.57 Or, intent.

s 7.58 ver. 55, 56.

k 7.58 So ver. 58. See Rom. 8. 37.

t 7.58 ver. 43.

u 7.59 Deut. 30. 19.

w 7.61 Luke 15. 7, 10.

x 7.64 See Rom. 2. 4.

y 7.67 Lat. as ver. 68.

z 7.68 Ps. 130. 3. See Ps. 143. 2.

y 7.68 Lat. as ver. 68.

* 7.69 Or, created.

* 7.69 Or, contempts.

a 8.1 ver. 3, 55. ch. 9. 15. So Matt. 7. 14. Luke 13. 23. Comp. ch. 7. 70. & 9. 22. ver. 41.

b 8.3 Comp. Matt. 20. 16.

c 8.5 Comp. 1 Cor. 15. 32.

* 8.6 Or, to give us.

d 8.7 Isai. 45. 9. So Isai. 64. 8. Or ver. 2?

* 8.8 Or, how is the body fashioned.

e 8.8 So Ps. 139. 13–16.

f 8.13 Comp. Heb. 9. 27.

g 8.14 Job 10. 8.

h 8.18 James 5. 9. So ver. 61. Rev. 22. 12.

i 8.19 ch. 14. 36–48?

j 8.21 Comp. Isai. 6. 2.

k 8.22 Ps. 104. 4. Heb. 1. 7.

l 8.23 So 2 Sam. 22. 16. Ps. 18. 15.

m 8.23 See Ps. 104. 32.

n 8.28 See Prov. 1. 7.

* 8.31 [Or,] are sick.

o 8.31 So ver. 36. See Ps. 25. 11.

* 8.32 [Or,] be willing. Lat. not as ver. 29.

p 8.32 Comp. Tit. 3. 5.

q 8.33 ch. 9. 7. See Rom. 2. 6, 10.

r 8.35 2 Chr. 6. 36. See 1 Kings 8. 46.

o 8.36 So ver. 36. See Ps. 25. 11.

* 8.36 Or, substance. Heb. 11. 1 (Lat.).

s 8.38 Gen. 6. 5 marg. So ver. 39.

t 8.38 Comp. ch. 9. 12.

u 8.38 See Dan. 12. 2.

x 8.39 So Gen. 4. 4.

s 8.39 Gen. 6. 5 marg. So ver. 39.

y 8.39 See Gen. 47. 9.

z 8.41 See ver. 1.

a 8.42 See ch. 4. 44.

b 8.43 See Acts 14. 17.

c 8.44 Gen. 1. 26, 27.

d 8.44 See ch. 6. 55.

e 8.44 ver. 41.

f 8.45 See Joel 2. 17.

g 8.47 ch. 5. 33.

h 8.50 ver. 63. ch. 12. 23. & 14. 22 in the Lat. So ch. 10. 59. & 12. 9. & 13. 18, 20, 46. 2 Tim. 3. 1.

i 8.50 2 Tim. 3. 2.

j 8.52 See ch. 4. 7. Comp. ch. 3. 6.

k 8.52 ch. 2. 12. Rev. 22. 2.

l 8.52 Comp. ch. 2. 13.

m 8.52 Rev. 21. 2.

n 8.52 See Rev. 14. 13.

o 8.53 See ch. 2. 38.

p 8.53 See Ps. 39. 11.

* 8.53 Or, [the] grave.

q 8.54 See Rev. 7. 17.

r 8.56 So ch. 9. 11.

s 8.58 Ps. 14. 1. & 53. 1.

t 8.59 ver. 52–54.

u 8.59 Comp. Luke 16. 23, 24.

v 8.59 So Ezek. 18. 32. Wisd. 1. 13.

w 8.60 Ezek. 20. 39. & 39. 7.

x 8.60 See 2 Tim. 3. 2. So Rom. 1. 21.

y 8.61 So ver. 18.

yy 8.62 ch. 14. 9.

z 8.63 ch. 4. 52. & 5. 1, 13. & 9. 1, 6. & 13. 32 in the Lat.

h 8.63 ver. 63. ch. 12. 23. & 14. 22 in the Lat. So ch. 10. 59. & 12. 9. & 13. 18, 20, 46. 2 Tim. 3. 1.

a 9.1 See ch. 8. 63.

b 9.3 Matt. 24. 7. So ch. 6. 14 marg.

c 9.3 Comp. Matt. 24. 6.

a 9.6 See ch. 8. 63.

d 9.7 ch. 8. 33. & 13. 23. See Matt. 16. 27.

e 9.7 ch. 13. 23. Comp. Rom. 3. 28.

f 9.8 See ch. 6. 25.

g 9.8 ch. 2. 41. Comp. Ephes. 1. 4.

* 9.9 Or, they shall marvel.

h 9.10 Luke 16. 25.

i 9.11 So ch. 8. 56.

k 9.11 Heb. 12. 17.

l 9.12 Comp. ch. 8. 38.

m 9.13 Comp. 1 Pet. 4. 18.

n 9.13 See ch. 6. 55.

o 9.15 See ch. 8. 1.

* 9.17 [Or,] And now, because the time of the world was come, when I was preparing the world, &c.

* 9.19 [Or,] but when the world was made, both now and then the manners of every one created were corrupted by p a never failing harvest, and q a law r unsearchable.

s 9.21 Mal. 3. 17.

t 9.21 Comp. 2 Kings 19. 4. Isai. 1. 9.

* 9.21 Or, grain.

t 9.21 Comp. 2 Kings 19. 4. Isai. 1. 9.

o 9.22 See ch. 8. 1.

* 9.22 Or, grain.

u 9.23 See ch. 6. 35.

w 9.24 ch. 12. 51.

x 9.24 ch. 12. 17. See Deut. 4. 12 marg.

y 9.27 ch. 6. 37.

z 9.28 ch. 14. 41. See Matt. 5. 2.

a 9.29 Exod. 19. 9. & 24. 10. Deut. 4. 12.

* 9.29 Or, cometh.

b 9.32 So ver. 37.

c 9.36 So ver. 19, 33. Comp. Rom. 7. 10.

b 9.37 So ver. 37.

d 9.38 ch. 10. 41.

e 9.38 See Gen. 44. 13.

f 9.38 Judith 4. 11. & 9. 1. So Esth. 4. 1. See Josh. 7. 6.

g 9.39 So ch. 10. 5.

h 9.41 ch. 2. 44 and marg.

i 9.41 1 Sam. 1. 10 marg.

j 9.44 So 1 Sam. 1. 11.

k 9.47 Tobit 8. 19. See Matt. 22. 2.

a 10.2 Comp. Job 2. 11.

* 10.2 Or, countrymen. [Lat.] citizens. ch. 9. 45.

b 10.5 So ch. 9. 39.

* 10.5 Or, speeches.

c 10.7 Lat. as Luke 22. 15 marg.

* 10.10 Or, abolished.

* 10.13 [Or,] But the earth after the manner of the earth, whereinto the present multitude is gone again, as it came out.

d 10.16 Comp. Ps. 145. 17.

e 10.18 ver. 4.

f 10.21 Lam. 2. 7.

f 10.21 Lam. 2. 7.

g 10.21 See 2 Chr. 36. 19.

h 10.22 Comp. 1 Macc. 1. 21.

i 10.22 Comp. ch. 14. 21. 2 Macc. 2. 5.

k 10.22 So Ezek. 7. 21.

l 10.22 Lam. 5. 11.

l 10.22 Lam. 5. 11.

m 10.23 Comp. Cant. 4. 12.

n 10.23 Ps. 44. 10. & 106. 41.

o 10.23 Luke 1. 71.

p 10.27 ver. 42. Comp. Rev. 21. 10, 14.

q 10.28 See ch. 4. 1.

* 10.28 Or, into the multitude in r a trance.

s 10.30 ch. 5. 15.

s 10.30 ch. 5. 15.

t 10.32 ch. 5. 20. & 6. 35.

u 10.32 ch. 9. 24.

* 10.37 Or, trance. ver. 28 (Lat. not as ver. 40, 59). ch. 12. 3 (comp. ch. 13. 30 Lat.).

* 10.39 Or, purpose.

v 10.41 ver. 49. ch. 9. 38.

w 10.42 ver. 27.

* 10.43 Or, interpretation (Lat. not as ch. 12. 8, 10, 17, &c.).

x 10.45 ch. 9. 43.

y 10.46 1 Kings 8. 62–64.

z 10.48 ver. 1.

v 10.49 ver. 49. ch. 9. 38.

a 10.51 ch. 9. 24.

b 10.52 Lat. as ver. 54.

a 10.53 ch. 9. 24.

b 10.54 Lat. as ver. 54.

c 10.55 Comp. Ps. 48. 12, 13.

* 10.57 Or, art called to be with, &c.

* 10.59 Or, last things.

d 10.59 See ch. 8. 50.

a 11.1 Dan. 7. 3. Rev. 13. 1.

aa 11.1 Comp. Deut. 28. 49. Ezek. 17. 3, 7. Dan. 7. 4.

b 11.3 ver. 11. Comp. ver. 22, 23.

* 11.4 Lat. she.

b 11.11 ver. 11. Comp. ver. 22, 23.

f 11.11 Comp. ver. 11, 23.

c 11.12 ver. 20.

d 11.13 See Ps. 103. 16.

c 11.20 ver. 20.

e 11.22 ver. 1.

f 11.22 Comp. ver. 11, 23.

b 11.22 ver. 11. Comp. ver. 22, 23.

g 11.23 ver. 4, 29.

f 11.23 Comp. ver. 11, 23.

b 11.23 ver. 11. Comp. ver. 22, 23.

i 11.24 Comp. ver. 24, 26, 27, 31.

h 11.24 ver. 3, 31.

h 11.25 ver. 3, 31.

i 11.26 Comp. ver. 24, 26, 27, 31.

i 11.27 Comp. ver. 24, 26, 27, 31.

i 11.28 Comp. ver. 24, 26, 27, 31.

g 11.29 ver. 4, 29.

j 11.31 ver. 30.

i 11.31 Comp. ver. 24, 26, 27, 31.

h 11.31 ver. 3, 31.

k 11.32 ch. 12. 24. So ver. 40.

l 11.33 ver. 22.

m 11.37 ch. 12. 31. See Rev. 5. 5.

n 11.39 Dan. 7. 3.

o 11.40 Dan. 7. 7, 19, 23. Comp. Dan. 2. 40.

p 11.40 So ch. 6. 1 marg.

k 11.40 ch. 12. 24. So ver. 40.

q 11.45 ver. 1.

r 11.45 ver. 3.

q 11.45 ver. 1.

s 11.45 ver. 7 (Lat.).

t 11.46 So Isai. 28. 12.

a 12.2 ch. 11. 35.

b 12.2 ch. 11. 25–28.

c 12.2 ch. 11. 24. ver. 21, 29, 30.

c 12.2 ch. 11. 24. ver. 21, 29, 30.

cc 12.3 Lat. as ch. 13. 30. See ch. 10. 37.

d 12.7 See ch. 5. 23.

e 12.7 See ch. 4. 44.

f 12.9 ch. 10. 59.

g 12.9 ch. 13. 14 (Lat).

h 12.9 See ch. 8. 50.

i 12.11 ch 11. 1.

j 12.11 Dan. 7. 7.

k 12.14 ch. 11. 12.

l 12.15 ch. 11. 17.

m 12.17 ch. 9. 24. See Deut. 4. 12.

n 12.17 ch. 11. 10.

o 12.19 ch. 11. 3, 11.

p 12.21 ch. 11. 22.

q 12.21 ch. 11. 25–28.

r 12.21 ch. 11. 24. ver. 2, 29, 30.

s 12.22 ch. 11. 1, 4.

t 12.23 See ch. 8. 50.

u 12.24 ch. 11. 32.

w 12.26 ch. 11. 33.

x 12.28 ch. 11. 35.

y 12.28 ver. 2, 3.

r 12.29 ch. 11. 24. ver. 2, 29, 30.

r 12.30 ch. 11. 24. ver. 2, 29, 30.

z 12.30 ver. 2.

a 12.31 ch. 11. 37–46.

* 12.32 [Lat. wind, or, spirit].

b 12.34 ch. 8. 38. See Dan. 12. 2.

c 12.37 Rev. 1. 19.

cc 12.37 ch. 14. 26.

d 12.39 ch. 9. 23. See ch. 6. 35.

e 12.40 ch. 3. 1.

* 12.42 Or, people.

f 12.42 Isai. 24. 13.

g 12.42 2 Pet. 1. 19.

h 12.42 Comp. Ps. 107. 30.

i 12.44 Comp. Ex. 14. 12.

j 12.44 Comp. ch. 3. 2.

k 12.45 Comp. 1 Kin. 19. 4.

l 12.51 ver. 39.

m 12.51 ch. 9. 24.

a 13.1 ch. 12. 51.

* 13.2 a certain man as the wind, Junius. Comp. ver. 3, 5, 25, 32.

* 13.3 clouds.

b 13.3 So ch. 6. 3. Jude 14.

bb 13.13 ver. 40.

* 13.13 Junius, of the things that were offered.

c 13.14 ch. 12. 9 (Lat.).

d 13.18 See ch. 8. 50.

e 13.18 Comp. ver. 16.

f 13.20 ver. 23.

e 13.20 Comp. ver. 16.

* 13.20 Or, this day.

d 13.20 See ch. 8. 50.

e 13.22 Comp. ver. 16.

g 13.23 1 John 5. 18.

f 13.23 ver. 23.

h 13.23 See ch. 9. 7.

h 13.23 See ch. 9. 7.

e 13.24 Comp. ver. 16.

e 13.24 Comp. ver. 16.

i 13.25 ver. 2 marg.

j 13.25 ch. 4. 7. ver. 51. See Prov. 23. 34 marg.

k 13.26 Comp. 1 Pet. 2. 24.

e 13.26 Comp. ver. 16.

l 13.27 ver. 10.

m 13.28 ver. 9.

n 13.28 ver. 11.

o 13.28 ver. 5, 8.

p 13.29 Luke 21. 28.

q 13.30 Lat. as ch. 12. 3.

r 13.31 Matt. 24. 7. Mark 13. 8. Luke 21. 10.

r 13.31 Matt. 24. 7. Mark 13. 8. Luke 21. 10.

s 13.32 ch. 5. 1–12? See ch. 8. 63.

i 13.32 ver. 2 marg.

t 13.35 ver. 6.

t 13.36 ver. 6.

u 13.37 ver. 10, 11.

u 13.38 ver. 10, 11.

u 13.38 ver. 10, 11.

x 13.39 ver. 12.

y 13.40 ver. 13.

z 13.40 2 Kings 17. 3.

a 13.43 Comp. Rev. 9. 14. & 16. 12.

b 13.44 ver. 47 (Lat.). Ex. 14. 21. Josh. 3. 15, 16.

* 13.45 Or, Ararath.

c 13.46 See ch. 8. 50.

d 13.47 Comp. Isai. 11. 15, 16.

b 13.47 ver. 47 (Lat.). Ex. 14. 21. Josh. 3. 15, 16.

e 13.51 See ch. 5. 23.

f 13.51 ver. 25.

g 13.52 Comp. Ps. 36. 6.

h 13.52 Comp. ch. 6. 31.

i 13.55 So Ecclus. 15. 2. Comp. Prov. 7. 4.

a 14.1 ch. 13. 56, 58.

b 14.3 Ex. 3. 2–8.

c 14.4 Ex. 24. 18. Comp. ver. 23.

* 14.9 [Or, counsel]. Comp. Prov. 8. 14, 30. Isai. 9. 6.

d 14.9 ch. 8. 62.

e 14.10 Comp. Ps. 102. 26.

e 14.10 Comp. Ps. 102. 26.

f 14.13 2 Sam. 17. 23 (Lat.). So 2 Kin. 20. 1.

g 14.14 So Heb. 12. 1.

h 14.16 Matt. 24. 8. Mark 13. 8.

i 14.18 So ch. 5. 1.

k 14.18 Ps. 4. 2. & 5. 6 only (English).

l 14.20 ver. 13.

m 14.21 Comp. ch. 10. 22 with Ex. 40. 20.

n 14.22 See ch. 4. 44.

o 14.22 Comp. 2 Pet. 1. 21.

p 14.22 See ch. 8. 50.

q 14.23 ver. 36.

r 14.23 See ver. 4.

* 14.24 Or, box tables to write on : Comp. ver. 44.

* 14.24 Or, Banus. So 1 Esdr. 9. 34.

s 14.24 See Ezra 7. 6.

t 14.25 Comp. Ps. 119. 105. Prov. 6. 23.

u 14.26 ch. 12. 37, 38. ver. 45, 46.

w 14.28 So Deut. 5. 1. & 6. 4. & 9. 1. & 20. 3.

x 14.29 Gen. 47. 4.

y 14.30 Acts 7. 53.

z 14.32 Ps. 7. 11 marg. 2 Macc. 12. 6, 41. 2 Tim. 4. 8.

a 14.33 ch. 3. 1.

b 14.35 Heb. 9. 27. See Dan. 12. 2.

c 14.36 ver. 23. Comp. ver. 44, 45.

d 14.37 Comp. Ex. 24. 1.

e 14.37 ver. 24.

f 14.38 Comp. Ezek. 3. 1, 2.

g 14.41 ch. 9. 28. See Matt. 5. 2.

e 14.42 ver. 24.

c 14.44 ver. 23. Comp. ver. 44, 45.

* 14.44 Or, nine hundred and four.

c 14.45 ver. 23. Comp. ver. 44, 45.

h 14.45 See ver. 26.

h 14.46 See ver. 26.

i 14.47 So Ecclus. 1. 5. Baruch 3. 12.

* 14.47 Or, the light of knowledge. So Wisd. 7. 10, 26. Comp. ver. 25.

a 15.1 See Num. 23. 5.

b 15.2 2 John 12. So Tobit 7. 14 (Lat.).

c 15.2 See Rev. 22. 6.

d 15.4 Comp. John 3. 36.

e 15.8 Rev. 6. 10. & 19. 2. So ver. 22.

e 15.8 Rev. 6. 10. & 19. 2. So ver. 22.

f 15.10 Ps. 44. 22.

g 15.10 2 Kin. 25. 26.

h 15.11 So Wisd. 16. 16. See Deut. 4. 34.

i 15.12 Comp. Isai. 19. 1, &c. Ezek. 32. 2, &c.

j 15.13 ver. 40 (Lat.). Comp. ver. 35.

k 15.14 Rev. 8. 13. & 12. 12.

l 15.15 So Isai. 19. 2.

m 15.19 ver. 13.

n 15.20 Deut. 11. 24. Josh. 1. 4. See Judith 1. 7.

nn 15.21 ver. 53, 56.

o 15.21 ver. 55. See Ps. 79. 12.

p 15.22 So ver. 8.

q 15.29 Comp. Isai. 13. 21.

r 15.30 Comp. ver. 30.

q 15.31 Comp. Isai. 13. 21.

r 15.31 Comp. ver. 30.

r 15.32 Comp. ver. 30.

* 15.33 Or, against.

s 15.35 Matt. 24. 29. See Rev. 6. 13.

t 15.35 ver. 13 (Lat.), 39, 40.

u 15.35 So Rev. 14. 20.

* 15.36 Or, pastern, or, litter.

x 15.39 ver. 34.

t 15.39 ver. 13 (Lat.), 39, 40.

x 15.40 ver. 34.

t 15.40 ver. 13 (Lat.), 39, 40.

y 15.40 ver. 13 (Lat.).

* 15.43 Or, destroy. ver. 18, 60.

z 15.43 ver. 45 (Lat.).

a 15.44 ver. 40, 41.

b 15.44 See Rev. 19. 3.

c 15.44 So Rev. 18. 9.

z 15.45 ver. 45 (Lat.).

d 15.46 ch. 16. 1. See 1 Macc. 8. 6.

* 15.46 Or, like unto Babylon.

e 15.49 Comp. Rev. 18. 7, 8.

f 15.50 Comp. Job 15. 30. Ps. 90. 6.

g 15.52 So ch. 16. 48 (Lat.). Nah. 1. 2.

h 15.53 ver. 21, 56. ch. 16. 73.

* 15.53 Lat. death.

i 15.53 So Rev. 17. 6.

k 15.54 Comp. Jer. 4. 30. ch. 16. 50.

l 15.55 ver. 21.

h 15.56 ver. 21, 56. ch. 16. 73.

m 15.58 Comp. Deut. 28. 53 and references.

n 15.60 ch. 16. 68.

q 15.60 Lat. as ver. 60. Comp. Isai. 3. 24.

o 15.61 Isai. 47. 14. ch. 16. 6.

p 15.63 So ch. 5. 1 (Lat.).

* 15.63 Or, blemish.

q 15.63 Lat. as ver. 60. Comp. Isai. 3. 24.

q 15.63 Lat. as ver. 60. Comp. Isai. 3. 24.

a 16.1 ch. 15. 46.

b 16.1 ch. 15. 11.

c 16.2 See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

d 16.2 Rev. 6. 12. See Zech. 13. 4 marg.

e 16.4 ver. 9, 15.

f 16.5 ver. 8.

g 16.6 See ch. 15. 61.

h 16.7 ver. 16.

f 16.8 ver. 8.

e 16.9 ver. 9, 15.

i 16.10 2 Sam. 22. 14, 15.

i 16.10 2 Sam. 22. 14, 15.

j 16.12 2 Sam. 22. 8.

k 16.12 Ps. 77. 16.

l 16.12 So Isai. 2. 10, 19, 21.

m 16.13 Ps. 89. 13. Comp. Wisd. 5. 21.

i 16.13 2 Sam. 22. 14, 15.

n 16.13 Ps. 45. 5.

e 16.15 ver. 9, 15.

o 16.15 Comp. Isai. 30. 33. Ezek. 20. 47, 48.

h 16.16 ver. 16.

p 16.18 Matt. 24. 8. Mark 13. 8.

q 16.19 See Rom. 8. 35.

* 16.21 Or, plagues. Lat. of ch. 15. 5, 27, 49, 59. ver. 5, 8, 14, 16, 37, 39: not as ch. 15. 12. ver. 19.

r 16.23 See 2 Kin. 9. 37.

s 16.26 See Job 24. 11.

t 16.28 Comp. Amos 5. 3.

u 16.28 Isai. 2. 21.

x 16.29 Isai. 17. 6. & 24. 13. So Obad. 5.

x 16.30 Isai. 17. 6. & 24. 13. So Obad. 5.

y 16.31 Amos 1. 3, 6, 9, 11.

z 16.33 Comp. Ps. 78. 63.

a 16.35 See Ps. 113. 1.

b 16.38 Jer 50. 43. See Jer. 6. 24.

c 16.40 See Gen. 47. 9.

d 16.41 To ver. 44, comp. 1 Cor. 7. 29–31.

e 16.42 See Ezek. 27. 9.

* 16.46 [Or, for]. Comp. Deut. 28. 41.

e 16.47 See Ezek. 27. 9.

f 16.48 So ch. 15. 52 (Lat.).

g 16.49 Lat. as ver. 50. So ver. 48.

h 16.49 Ps. 46. 5. & 139. 14 (English).

g 16.50 Lat. as ver. 50. So ver. 48.

i 16.50 Comp. ch. 15. 54.

j 16.52 See Heb. 10. 37.

k 16.53 See Jer. 2. 35.

l 16.53 Comp. Prov. 25. 22.

k 16.53 See Jer. 2. 35.

z 16.54 Lat. as ver. 54.

m 16.54 Luke 16. 15. See 1 Sam. 16. 7.

n 16.55 Gen. 1. 1. Ps. 148. 5.

o 16.56 Ps. 147. 4.

p 16.57 Isai. 40. 12.

q 16.58 Job 26. 10.

r 16.58 Comp. Job 26. 7.

s 16.58 See Ps. 24. 2.

t 16.59 See Job 9. 8.

u 16.59 Gen. 1. 7.

x 16.60 See Ps. 107. 35.

y 16.61 Gen. 2. 7.

z 16.63 Lat. as ver. 54.

a 16.65 See 1 Cor. 4. 5.

b 16.66 See Matt. 25. 31.

c 16.67 See Ps. 75. 7.

d 16.67 So 2 Tim. 4. 18.

* 16.68 Or, being unable to resist.

e 16.68 ch. 15. 60.

f 16.68 See Acts 15. 29.

g 16.72 See John 16. 32 marg.

h 16.73 See ch. 15. 53.

i 16.73 Comp. 1 Pet. 1. 7.

d 16.74 So 2 Tim. 4. 18.

k 16.75 So Ps. 48. 14.

l 16.76 So Ps. 38. 4.

m 16.77 Comp. Prov. 22. 5. Hos. 2. 6.

* 16.78 Or, shut out.

2 Maccabees

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12
13
14
15

The Second Book of the Maccabees

1

1 [*]The brethren, the Jews that be at Jerusalem and in the land of Judea, wish unto the brethren, the Jews that are throughout Egypt health and peace:

2 God be gracious unto you, and [a]remember his covenant that he made with Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, his faithful servants;

3 And give you all an heart to serve him, and to do his will, with a good courage and a willing mind;

4 And [b]open your hearts in his law and commandments, and send you peace,

5 And hear your prayers, and [c]be at one with you, and never forsake you in time of trouble.

6 And now we be here praying for you.

7 What time as [d]Demetrius reigned, in [*]the hundred threescore and ninth year, we the Jews wrote unto you in the extremity of trouble that came upon us in those years, from the time that [e]Jason and his company revolted from the [f]holy land and kingdom,

8 And burned [g]the porch, and shed innocent blood: then we prayed unto the Lord, and were heard; [h]we offered also sacrifices and fine flour, and lighted the lamps, and [i]set forth the loaves.

9 And now see that ye [u]keep [j]the feast of tabernacles in the month [k]Casleu.

10 In [*]the hundred fourscore and eighth year, the people that were at Jerusalem and in Judea, and [l]the council, and Judas, sent greeting and health unto Aristobulus, king [m]Ptolemeus’ [n]master, who was of the stock of the [o]anointed priests, and to the Jews that were in Egypt:

11 Insomuch as God hath delivered us from great perils, we thank him highly, as having been in battle against [s]a king.

12 For he [p]cast them out that fought within [q]the holy city.

13 For when the leader was come into [r]Persia, and the army with him that seemed invincible, they were slain in the temple of Nanea by the deceit of Nanea’s priests.

14 For [s]Antiochus, as though he would marry her, came into the place, and his friends that were with him, to receive money in name of a dowry.

15 Which when the priests of Nanea had [i]set forth, and he was entered with a small company into the compass of the temple, they shut the temple as soon as Antiochus was come in:

16 And opening a privy door of the roof, they threw [t]stones like thunderbolts, and struck down the captain, hewed them in pieces, smote off their heads and cast them to those that were without.

17 Blessed be our God in all things, who hath delivered up the ungodly.

18 Therefore whereas we are now purposed to [u]keep [v]the purification of the temple upon the five and twentieth day of the month [k]Casleu, we thought it necessary to [w]certify you thereof, that ye also might [u]keep it, as the feast [x]of the tabernacles, and of the fire, which was given us when [y]Neemias offered sacrifice, after that he had builded the temple and the altar.

19 For when our fathers were led into [r]Persia, [yy]the priests that were then devout took the fire of the altar privily, and hid it in an hollow place of a pit without water, where they kept it sure, so that the place was unknown to all men.

20 Now after many years, when it pleased God, Neemias, [z]being sent from the king of [r]Persia, did send of the posterity of those priests that had hid it to the fire: but when they [w]told us they found no fire, but thick water;

21 Then commanded he them to draw it up, and to bring it; and when the sacrifices were laid on, Neemias commanded the priests [a]to sprinkle the wood and the things laid thereupon with the water.

22 When this was done, and the time came that the sun shone, which afore was hid in the cloud, there was a great fire kindled, so that every man marvelled.

23 And the priests made a prayer whilst the sacrifice was consuming, I say, both the priests, and all the rest, [b]Jonathan beginning, and the rest answering thereunto, as Neemias did.

24 And the prayer was after this manner; O Lord, Lord God, [bb]Creator of all things, who art fearful and strong, and righteous, and merciful, and the only and gracious King,

25 The only giver of all things, the only just, [c]almighty, and everlasting, thou that deliverest Israel from all trouble, and didst choose the fathers, and sanctify them:

26 Receive the sacrifice for thy whole people Israel, and preserve [d]thine own portion, and sanctify it.

27 Gather [e]those together that are scattered from us, [f]deliver them that serve among the heathen, look upon them that are despised and abhorred, and [g]let the heathen know that thou art our God.

28 Punish them that oppress us, and with pride do us wrong.

29 Plant thy people again in thy [h]holy place,[i] as Moses hath spoken.

30 And the priests sung psalms of thanksgiving.

31 Now when the sacrifice was consumed, Neemias commanded the water that was left to be poured on the great stones.

32 When this was done, there was kindled a flame: but it was consumed by the light that shined from the altar.

33 So when this matter was known, it was told the king of [k]Persia, that in the place, where the priests that were led away had hid the fire, there appeared water, and that [*]Neemias had purified the sacrifices therewith.

34 Then the king, inclosing the place, made it holy, after he had tried the matter.

35 And the king took many [l]gifts, and bestowed thereof on those whom he would gratify.

36 And Neemias called this thing Naphthar, which is as much as to say, a cleansing: but many men call it Nephi.

2

1 It is also found in the [a]records, that Jeremy the prophet commanded them that were carried away to take of the fire, [b]as it hath been signified:

2 And how that the prophet, having given them the law, charged them not to forget the commandments of the Lord, and that they should not err in their minds, [c]when they see images of silver and gold, with their ornaments.

3 And with other such speeches exhorted he them, that the law should not depart from their hearts.

4 It was also contained in [d]the same writing, that the prophet, being warned of God, commanded the tabernacle and the ark to go with him, as he went forth into [e]the mountain, where Moses climbed up, and saw the heritage of God.

5 And when [f]Jeremy came thither, he found an hollow cave, wherein he laid the tabernacle, and [g]the ark, and the altar of incense, and so stopped the door.

6 And some of those that followed him came to mark the way, but they could not find it.

7 Which when Jeremy perceived, he blamed them, saying, As for that place, it shall be unknown until the time that God gather his people again together, and receive them unto mercy.

8 Then shall the Lord shew them these things, and the glory of the Lord shall appear, and the cloud also, [h]as it was shewed under Moses, and [i]as when Solomon desired that the place might be honourably sanctified.

9 It was also [k]declared, that he being wise [l]offered the sacrifice of dedication, and of the finishing of the temple.

10 And [m]as when Moses prayed unto the Lord, the fire came down from heaven, and consumed the sacrifices: even so [n]prayed Solomon also, and the fire came down from heaven, and consumed the burnt offerings.

11 And [o]Moses said, Because the sin offering was not to be eaten, it was consumed.

12 So Solomon kept those [p]eight days.

13 The same things also were reported in [d]the writings and commentaries of Neemias; and how he founding a library gathered together the acts of the kings, and the prophets, and of David, and the epistles [q]of the kings concerning the [r]holy gifts.

14 In like manner also [s]Judas gathered together all those things that [*]were lost by reason of the war we had, and they remain with us,

15 Wherefore if ye have need thereof, send some to fetch them unto you.

16 Whereas we then [t]are about to celebrate the purification, we have written unto you, and ye shall do well, if ye keep the same days.

17 [*]We hope also, that the God, that delivered all his people, and gave them all an heritage, and the [u]kingdom, and the priesthood, and the [w]sanctuary,

18 [x]As he promised in the law, will shortly have mercy upon us, and gather us together out of [y]every land under heaven into [z]the holy place: for he hath delivered us out of great troubles, and hath purified the place.

19 [a]Now as concerning Judas Maccabeus, and his brethren, and [b]the purification of the great temple, and the dedication of the altar,

20 And the wars against [c]Antiochus Epiphanes, and [d]Eupator his son,

21 And [e]the manifest signs that came from heaven unto those that behaved themselves manfully to their honour for Judaism: so that, being but a few, they overcame the whole country, and chased barbarous multitudes,

22 And [f]recovered again the temple renowned [g]all the world over, and freed the city, and upheld the laws which were going down, the Lord being gracious unto them with all [h]favour:

23 All these things, I say, being declared by Jason of [i]Cyrene in five books, we will assay [ii]to abridge in one volume.

24 For considering the infinite number, and the difficulty which they find that desire to look into the [n]narrations of the story, for the variety of the matter,

25 We have been careful, that they that will read may have delight, and that they that are desirous to commit to memory might have ease, and that all into whose hands it comes might have profit.

26 Therefore to us, that have taken upon us this [j]painful labour of abridging, it was not easy, but a matter of sweat and watching;

27 Even as it is no ease unto him that prepareth a banquet, and seeketh the benefit of others: yet [*]for the pleasuring of many we will undertake gladly this [j]great pains;

28 Leaving to [k]the author the exact handling of every particular, and labouring to follow the [l]rules of an abridgement.

29 For as the master builder of a new house must care for the whole building; [ll]but he that undertaketh to set it out, and paint it, must seek out fit things for the adorning thereof: even so I think it is with us.

30 To stand upon every point, and go over things at large, and to be curious in particulars, belongeth to [k]the first author of the story:

31 But to use [m]brevity, and avoid much labouring of the work, is to be granted to him that will make an abridgment.

32 Here then will we begin the [n]story: only adding thus much to that which hath been said, that it is a foolish thing to make a long prologue, and to be short in the story itself.

3

1 Now when [a]the holy city was inhabited with all peace, and the laws were kept very well, because of the godliness of [b]Onias the high priest, and his hatred of wickedness,

2 It came to pass that even the kings themselves did honour the place, and magnify the temple with their best [c]gifts;

3 Insomuch that [*][d]Seleucus of [e]Asia of his own revenues bare all the costs belonging to the service of the sacrifices.

4 But one [ee]Simon of the tribe of Benjamin, who was made governor of the temple, [f]fell out with the high priest about disorder in the city.

5 And when he could not overcome Onias, he gat him to [g]Apollonius the son of Thraseas, who then was governor of [h]Celosyria and Phenice,

6 And told him that [i]the treasury in Jerusalem was full of infinite sums of money, so that the multitude of their [j]riches, [k]which did not pertain to the account of the sacrifices, was innumerable, and that it was possible to bring all into the king’s hand.

7 Now when Apollonius came to the king, and had shewed him of the money whereof he was told, the king chose out Heliodorus his treasurer, and [l]sent him with a commandment to bring him the foresaid money.

8 So forthwith Heliodorus took his journey; [m]under a colour of visiting the cities of [h]Celosyria and Phenice, but indeed to fulfil the king’s [n]purpose.

9 And when he was come to Jerusalem, and had been [o]courteously received of the high priest of the city, he [p]told him what intelligence was given of the money, and [q]declared wherefore he came, and asked if these things were so indeed.

10 Then the high priest told him that there was such [r]money laid up for the relief of [s]widows and fatherless children:

11 And that some of it belonged to Hircanus son of Tobias, a man of great dignity, and not as that wicked Simon had misinformed: the sum whereof in all was four hundred [t]talents of silver, and two hundred of gold:

12 And that it was altogether impossible that such wrongs should be done unto them, [u]that had committed it to the holiness of the place, and to the majesty and inviolable sanctity of the temple, honoured over all the world.

13 But Heliodorus, [v]because of the king’s commandment given him, said, That in any wise it must be brought into the king’s treasury.

14 So at the day which he appointed he entered in to order this matter: wherefore there was no small [w]agony throughout the whole city.

15 But the priests, prostrating themselves before the altar [x]in their priests’ vestments, called unto heaven upon him that [y]made a law concerning [r]things given to be kept, that they should safely be preserved for [u]such as had committed them to be kept.

16 Then whoso had looked the high priest in the face, it would have wounded his heart: for his countenance and the changing of his colour declared the inward [w]agony of his mind.

17 For the man was so compassed with fear and horror of the body, that it was manifest to them that looked upon him, what sorrow he had now in his heart.

18 Others ran flocking out of their houses [*][z]to the general supplication, because the place was like to come into contempt.

19 And the women, [a]girt with sackcloth under their breasts, abounded in the streets, and the virgins that were kept in ran, some to the [b]gates, and some to the walls, and others looked out of the [c]windows.

20 And all, holding their hands toward heaven, made supplication.

21 Then it would have pitied a man to see the falling down of the multitude of all sorts, and the [*]fear of the high priest being in such an a[w]gony.

22 They then called upon the Almighty Lord to keep the things committed of trust safe and sure for [u]those that had committed them.

23 Nevertheless Heliodorus executed that which was decreed.

24 Now as he was there present himself with his guard about [d]the treasury, the [*]Lord of spirits, and the [e]Prince of all power, caused a great [ee]apparition, so that all that presumed to come in with him were astonished at the power of God, and fainted, and were sore afraid.

25 For there appeared unto them an horse with a terrible rider upon him, and adorned with a very fair covering, and he ran fiercely, and smote at Heliodorus with his forefeet, and it seemed that he that sat upon the horse had complete [f]harness of gold.

26 Moreover two other young men appeared before him, notable in strength, excellent in beauty, and comely in apparel, who stood by him on either side; and [ff]scourged him [g]continually, and gave him many sore stripes.

27 And Heliodorus fell suddenly unto the ground, and was compassed with great darkness: but they that were with him took him up, and put him into [gg]a litter.

28 Thus him, that lately came with a great train and with all his guard into the said [d]treasury, they carried out, being unable to help himself with his weapons: and manifestly they acknowledged the power of God.

29 For he by the hand of God was cast down, and lay speechless without all hope of life.

30 But they praised the Lord, that had miraculously honoured his own place: for the temple; which a little afore was full of fear and trouble, when the [h]Almighty Lord appeared, was filled with joy and gladness.

31 Then straightways certain of Heliodorus’ friends prayed Onias, [i]that he would call upon the most High to grant him his life, who lay ready to give up the ghost.

32 So the high priest, [j]suspecting lest the king should misconceive that some treachery had been done to Heliodorus by the Jews, offered a sacrifice for the health of the man.

33 Now as the high priest was making an atonement, [k]the same young men in the same clothing appeared and stood beside Heliodorus, saying, Give Onias the high priest great thanks, insomuch as [i]for his sake the Lord hath granted thee life:

34 And seeing that thou hast been scourged from heaven, declare unto all men the mighty power of God. And when they had spoken these words, they appeared no more.

35 So Heliodorus, after he had offered sacrifice unto the Lord, and made great vows unto him that had saved his life, and [l]saluted Onias, returned with his host to the king.

36 Then testified he to all men the works of the great God, which he had seen with his eyes.

37 And when the king asked Heliodorus, who might be a fit man to be sent yet once again to Jerusalem, he said,

38 If thou hast any enemy or [m]traitor, send him thither, and thou shalt receive him well scourged, if he escape with his life: for in that place, no doubt, there is an especial power of God.

39 For [n]he that dwelleth in heaven hath his eye on that place, and defendeth it; and he beateth and destroyeth them that come to hurt it.

40 And the things concerning Heliodorus, and the keeping of [d]the treasury, fell out on this sort.

4

1 This Simon now, [a]of whom we spake afore, having been a [b]betrayer of the money, and of his country, slandered Onias, [c]as if he had terrified Heliodorus, and been the worker of these evils.

2 Thus was he bold to call him a [d]traitor, [e]that had deserved well of the city, and tendered his own nation, and was so [f]zealous of the laws.

3 But when their hatred went so far, that by one of Simon’s faction murders were committed,

4 Onias seeing the danger of this contention, and that [g]Apollonius, as being the governor of [h]Celosyria and Phenice, did rage, and increase Simon’s malice,

5 He went to the king, [i]not to be an accuser of his countrymen, but seeking the good of all, both publick and private:

6 For he saw that it was impossible that the state should continue quiet, and Simon leave his folly, unless the king [j]did look thereunto.

7 But after the death of [k]Seleucus, when [l]Antiochus, called Epiphanes, took the kingdom, [*][m]Jason the brother of Onias [mm]laboured underhand to be high priest,

8 Promising unto the king by [n]intercession three hundred and threescore talents of silver, and of another revenue eighty talents:

9 Beside this, he promised to assign an hundred and fifty more, if he might have licence to set him up [o]a place for exercise, and for the training up of youth in the fashions of the heathen, and to write them of Jerusalem by the name of [p]Antiochians.

10 Which when the king had granted, and he had gotten into his hand the rule he forthwith [q]brought his own nation to [t]Greekish fashion.

11 And the royal privileges granted of special favour to the Jews by the means of John the father of [qq]Eupolemus, who went ambassador to [r]Rome for amity and aid, he took away; and putting down the governments which were according to the law, he brought up new customs against the law:

12 For he built gladly [o]a place of exercise under [s]the tower itself, and brought the chief young men under his subjection, and made them wear a hat.

13 Now such was the height of [t]Greek fashions, and increase of [u]heathenish manners, through the exceeding profaneness of Jason, that ungodly wretch, and [v]no high priest;

14 That the priests had no courage to serve any more at the altar, but despising the temple, and neglecting the sacrifices, hastened to be partakers of the unlawful allowance in the place of exercise, after [*]the game of Discus called them forth;

15 Not setting by the honours of their fathers, but liking the glory of the Grecians best of all.

16 By reason whereof sore calamity came upon them: for they had them to be their enemies and avengers, whose [w]custom they followed so earnestly, and unto whom they desired to be like in all things.

17 For it is not a light thing to do wickedly against the laws of God: but the time following shall declare these things.

18 [*]Now when the game that was used every fifth year was kept at [x]Tyrus, the king being present,

19 This [y]ungracious Jason sent [*]special messengers from Jerusalem, [p]who were Antiochians, to carry three hundred [z]drachms of silver to the sacrifice of Hercules, which even the bearers thereof thought fit not to bestow upon the sacrifice, because it was not [a]convenient, but to be reserved for other charges.

20 This money then, in regard of the sender, was appointed to Hercules’ sacrifice; but because of the bearers thereof, it was employed to the making of gallies.

21 [*]Now when [b]Apollonius the son of Menestheus was sent into Egypt for the [*]coronation of king [c]Ptolemeus Philometor, Antiochus, understanding him not to be well affected to his affairs, provided for his own safety: whereupon he came to [d]Joppa, and from thence to Jerusalem:

22 Where he was honourably received of Jason, and of the city, and was brought in with torch alight, and with great shoutings: and so afterward went with his host unto [e]Phenice.

23 [*]Three years afterward Jason sent [f]Menelaus, [g]the aforesaid Simon’s brother, to bear [h]the money unto the king, and to put him in mind of certain necessary matters.

24 But he being brought to the presence of the king, when he had magnified him for the glorious appearance of his power, got the priesthood to himself, offering [h]more than Jason by three hundred talents of silver.

25 So he came with the king’s mandate, bringing nothing worthy the high priesthood, but having the fury of a cruel tyrant, and the rage of a savage beast.

26 Then Jason, who had [i]undermined his own brother, being [i]undermined by another, was compelled to flee into the country of the [k]Ammonites.

27 [*]So Menelaus got the principality: but as for the money that he had promised unto the king, he took no good order for it, albeit Sostratis the ruler of [l]the castle required it:

28 For unto him appertained the gathering of the [m]customs. Wherefore they were both called before the king.

29 Now Menelaus left his brother Lysimachus in his stead in the priesthood; and Sostratus left Crates, who was governor of the [n]Cyprians.

30 While those things were in doing, they of [o]Tarsus and Mallos made insurrection, because they were given to the king’s concubine, called Antiochus.

31 Then came the king in all haste to [p]appease matters, leaving [q]Andronicus, a man in authority, for his deputy.

32 Now Menelaus, supposing that he had gotten a convenient time, [r]stole certain vessels of gold out of the temple, and gave some of them to Andronicus, and some he sold into [s]Tyrus and the cities round about.

33 Which when Onias knew of a surety, he reproved him, and withdrew himself into a sanctuary at Daphne, that lieth by [t]Antiochia.

34 Wherefore Menelaus, taking Andronicus apart, prayed, him to get Onias into his hands; who being persuaded thereunto, and coming to Onias in deceit, gave him his right hand with oaths; and though he were suspected by him, yet persuaded he him to come forth of the sanctuary: whom forthwith he shut up without regard of justice.

35 For the which cause not only the Jews, but many also of other nations, took great indignation, and were much grieved for the unjust murder of the man.

36 And when the king was come again from [u]the places about [v]Cilicia, the Jews that were in the city, and certain of the Greeks [w]that abhorred the fact also, [x]complained because Onias was slain without cause.

37 Therefore Antiochus was [y]heartily sorry, and moved to pity, and wept, because of the sober and modest behaviour of him that was dead.

38 [*]And being kindled with anger, forthwith he took away Andronicus his purple, and rent off his clothes, and leading him through the whole city unto that very place, where he had committed impiety against Onias, there slew he the cursed murderer. Thus the Lord rewarded him his punishment, as he had deserved.

39 [*]Now when many sacrileges had been committed in the city by [z]Lysimachus with the [a]consent of Menelaus, and the [b]fruit thereof was spread abroad, the multitude gathered themselves together against Lysimachus, many vessels of gold being already carried away.

40 Whereupon the common people rising, and being filled with rage, Lysimachus armed about three thousand men, and began first to offer violence; one [*][c]Auranus being the leader, a man far gone in years, and no less in folly.

41 They then seeing the [cc]attempt of Lysimachus, some of them caught stones, some clubs, others taking handfuls of dust, that was next at hand, cast them all together upon [d]Lysimachus, and those that set upon them.

42 Thus many of them they wounded, and some they struck to the ground, and all of them they forced to flee: but as for the [e]churchrobber himself, him they killed beside the [f]treasury.

43 Of these matters therefore there was an accusation laid against Menelaus.

44 Now when the king came to [g]Tyrus, three men that were sent from the [h]senate pleaded the cause before him:

45 But Menelaus, being now convicted, promised [i]Ptolemee the son of Dorymenes to give him much money, if he would [j]pacify the king toward him.

46 Whereupon Ptolemee taking the king aside into a certain gallery, as it were to take the air, brought him to be of another mind:

47 Insomuch that he discharged Menelaus from the accusations, who notwithstanding was cause of all the mischief: and [k]those poor men, who, if they had told their cause, yea, before the [l]Scythians, should have been judged innocent, them he [m]condemned to death.

48 Thus they that followed the matter for the city, and for the people, and for the holy vessels, did soon suffer unjust punishment.

49 Wherefore even they of [g]Tyrus, [n]moved with hatred of that wicked deed, caused them to be honourably [o]buried.

50 And so [p]through the covetousness of them that were of power [q]Menelaus remained still in authority, increasing in malice, and being a great [r]traitor to the citizens.

5

1 [*]About the same time [a]Antiochus prepared his second [b]voyage into Egypt:

2 And then it happened, that through all the city, for the space almost of forty days, [e]there were seen horsemen running [c]in the air, in cloth of gold, and armed with lances, like a band of soldiers,

3 And troops of horsemen in array, encountering and running one against another, with shaking of shields, and multitude of [*]pikes, and drawing of swords, and casting of darts, and glittering of golden ornaments, and [d]harness of all sorts.

4 Wherefore every man prayed that that [e]apparition might turn to good.

5 Now when there was gone forth a false rumour, as though Antiochus had been dead, [f]Jason took at the least a thousand men, and suddenly made an [g]assault upon the city; and they that were upon the walls being put back, and the city at length taken, [h]Menelaus fled into [i]the castle:

6 But Jason slew his own citizens without mercy, not considering that to get the day of them of his own nation would be a most unhappy day for him; but thinking they had been his enemies, and not his countrymen, whom he conquered.

7 Howbeit for all this he obtained not the principality, but at the last received shame for the reward of his treason, and f[j]led again into the country of the Ammonites.

8 In the end therefore he had an unhappy return, being accused before [k]Aretas the king of the [l]Arabians, fleeing from city to city, pursued of all men, hated as [m]a forsaker of the laws, and being had in abomination as an [*]open enemy of his country and countrymen, he was [n]cast out into Egypt.

9 Thus he that had driven many out of their country perished in a strange land, retiring to the [o]Lacedemonians, and thinking there to find succour [p]by reason of his kindred:

10 And he that had cast out many unburied had none to mourn for him, nor any [q]solemn funerals at all, nor sepulchre with his fathers.

11 Now when [r]this that was done came to the king’s ear, he thought that Judea had revolted: whereupon [s]removing out of Egypt in a furious mind, he took the city by force of arms,

12 And [t]commanded his men of war not to spare such as they met, and to slay such as went up upon the houses.

13 [u]Thus there was killing of young and old, [w]making away of men, women, and children, slaying of virgins and infants.

14 And there were destroyed within the space of three whole days fourscore thousand, whereof forty thousand were slain in the conflict; and no fewer sold than slain.

15 Yet was he not content with this, but [x]presumed to go into the most holy temple of all the world; [h]Menelaus, that traitor to the laws, and to his own country, being his guide:

16 And [x]taking the holy vessels with polluted hands, and with profane hands pulling down [y]the things that were dedicated by other kings to the augmentation and glory and honour of the place, he gave them away.

17 And [z]so haughty was Antiochus in mind, that he considered not that [a]the Lord was angry for a while for the sins of them that dwelt in the city, and therefore [b]his eye was not upon the place.

18 For had they not been formerly wrapped in many sins, this man, as soon as he had come, had forthwith been scourged, and put back from his presumption, [c]as Heliodorus was, whom [d]Seleucus the king sent to view [e]the treasury.

19 Nevertheless God did not choose the people for [f]the place’s sake, [g]but the place for the people’s sake.

20 And therefore [f]the place itself, that was partaker with them of the adversity that happened to the nation, did afterward communicate in the benefits sent from the Lord: and as it was forsaken in the wrath of the [h]Almighty, so again, the great [a]Lord being reconciled, it was set up with all glory.

21 So when Antiochus [i]had carried out of the temple a thousand and eight hundred talents, he departed in all haste unto [j]Antiochia, weening [k]in his pride to make the land navigable, and the sea passable by foot: such was [z]the haughtiness of his mind.

22 And [l]he left governors to vex the nation: at Jerusalem, [ll]Philip, for his country a [m]Phrygian, and for manners more barbarous than he that set him there;

23 And at [n]Garizim, Andronicus; and besides, Menelaus, who worse than all the rest bare an heavy hand over the citizens, having a malicious mind against his countrymen the Jews.

24 [*][o]He sent also that detestable [p]ringleader [q]Apollonius with an army of two and twenty thousand, commanding him to slay all those that were in their best age, and to sell the women and the younger sort:

25 Who coming to Jerusalem, and [r]pretending peace, did forbear till the holy day of the sabbath, when taking the Jews keeping holy day, he commanded his men to arm themselves.

26 And so he slew all them that were gone to the [s]celebrating of the sabbath, and running through the city with weapons [t]slew great multitudes.

27 But [u]Judas Maccabeus [*]with nine others, or thereabout, [w]withdrew himself into the wilderness, and [w]lived in the mountains after the manner of beasts, with his company, who fed on herbs continually, lest they should be partakers of the pollution.

6

1 Not long after this the king sent an old man of [*]Athens to compel the Jews [a]to depart from the laws of their fathers, and not to [b]live after the laws of God:

2 And [c]to pollute also the temple in Jerusalem, and to call it the temple of Jupiter Olympius; and that in [d]Garizim, of Jupiter the Defender of strangers, [*]as they did desire that dwelt in the place.

3 The coming in of this mischief was sore and grievous to the people:

4 For the temple was filled with [e]riot and [f]revelling by the Gentiles, who dallied with harlots, and had to do with women within the circuit of the holy places, and besides that brought in things that were not l[g]awful.

5 [h]The altar also was filled with profane things, which the law [i]forbiddeth.

6 Neither was it lawful for a man [j]to keep sabbath days or ancient fasts, or to profess himself at all to be a Jew.

7 And in the day of the king’s birth every month they were brought by bitter constraint to [k]eat of the sacrifices; and when the fast of Bacchus was kept, the Jews were compelled to go in procession to [kk]Bacchus, carrying ivy.

8 Moreover [l]there went out a decree to the neighbour cities of the [*]heathen, by the suggestion of [m]Ptolemee, against the Jews, that they should observe the same [n]fashions, and [k]be partakers of their sacrifices:

9 And [o]whoso would not conform themselves to the manners of the Gentiles should be put to death. Then might a man have seen the present misery.

10 For [p]there were two women brought, [p]who had circumcised their children; whom when they had openly led round about the city, the babes hanging at their breasts, they cast them [q]down headlong [q]from the wall.

11 And others, that had run together into [r]caves near by, to keep the sabbath day secretly, being discovered by [s]Philip, were all burnt together, because [t]they made a conscience to help themselves for the honour of the most sacred day.

12 Now I beseech those that read this book, that they be not [u]discouraged for these calamities, [v]but that they judge those punishments not to be for destruction, but for a chastening of our nation.

13 For it is a token of his great goodness, when wicked doers are not suffered any long time, but forthwith punished.

14 For not as with other nations, whom [w]the Lord patiently forbeareth to punish, [x]till they be come to the fulness of their sins, so dealeth he with us,

15 Lest that, being come to the height of sin, afterwards he should take vengeance of us.

16 And therefore he never withdraweth his mercy from us: and [y]though he punish with adversity, yet doth he never forsake his people.

17 But let this that we have spoken be for a [z]warning unto us. And now will we come to the [a]declaring of the matter in a few words.

18 [*]Eleazar, one of the principal [b]scribes, [bb]an aged man, and of a well favoured countenance, was constrained to open his mouth, and [c]to eat swine’s flesh.

19 But he, [d]choosing rather to die gloriously, than to live stained with such an abomination, spit it forth, and came of his own accord to [e]the torment,

20 As it behoved them to come, that are resolute to stand out against such things, as are not lawful for love of life to be tasted.

21 But they that had the charge of that wicked [f]feast, for the old acquaintance they had with the man, taking him aside, besought him to bring flesh of his own provision, such as was [g]lawful for him to use, and [h]make as if he did eat of the flesh taken from the sacrifice commanded by the king;

22 That in so doing he might be delivered from death, and for the old friendship with them find favour.

23 But he began to consider [i]discreetly, and as became his age, and the excellency of his ancient years, and the honour of his gray head, whereon was come, and his most honest [k]education from a child, or rather the holy law made and given by God: therefore he answered accordingly, and willed them straightways to send him to the grave.

24 For it becometh not our age, [l]said he, in any wise to [h]dissemble, whereby many young persons might think that Eleazar, being [m]fourscore years old and ten, were now gone to [n]a strange religion;

25 And so they through mine [h]hypocrisy, and desire to live a little time and a moment longer, should be deceived by me, and I get a stain to mine old age, and make it abominable.

26 For though for the present time I should be delivered from the punishment of men: yet should I not escape the hand of the [nn]Almighty, neither alive, nor dead.

27 Wherefore now, manfully changing this life, I will shew myself such an one as mine age requireth,

28 And leave a [o]notable example to such as be young to die willingly and courageously for the honourable and holy laws. And when he had said these words, immediately he went to [e]the torment:

29 They that led him changing [p]the good will they bare him a little before into hatred, because the foresaid speeches proceeded, as they thought, from [*]a desperate mind.

30 But when he was ready to die with stripes, he [r]groaned, and said, It is manifest unto the Lord, that hath the holy knowledge, that whereas I might have been delivered from death, I now endure sore pains in body by being beaten: but in soul am well content to suffer these things, because I fear him.

31 And thus this man died, leaving his death for an [o]example of a noble courage, and a memorial of virtue, not only unto young men, but unto all his nation.

7

1 It came to pass also, that seven brethren with their mother were taken, and compelled by the king [a]against the law [b]to taste swine’s flesh, and were tormented with scourges and whips.

2 But one of them that spake first said thus, What wouldest thou ask or learn of us? we are ready to die, rather than to transgress the laws of our fathers.

3 [bb]Then the king, being in a rage, commanded [c]pans and caldrons to be made hot:

4 Which forthwith being heated, he commanded [k]to cut out the tongue of him that spake first, and [k]to cut off the utmost parts of his body, the rest of his brethren and his mother looking on.

5 Now when he was thus maimed in all his members, he commanded him being yet alive to be brought to the fire, and to be fried in the pan: and as the vapour of the pan was for a good space dispersed, they exhorted one another with the mother to die manfully, saying thus,

6 The Lord God looketh upon us, and in truth hath comfort in us, as [d]Moses in his song, which witnessed to their faces, [e]declared, saying, [d]And he shall be comforted in his servants.

7 So when the first was dead after this manner, they brought the second to make him [f]a mocking stock: and when they had pulled off the skin of his head with the hair, they asked him, Wilt thou eat, before thou be punished throughout every member of thy body?

8 But he answered [p]in his own language, and said, No. Wherefore he also received [g]the next torment in order, as the former did.

9 And when he was at the last gasp, he said, Thou like a fury [h]takest us out of this present life, but [i]the King of the world shall raise us up, who have died for his laws, [j]unto everlasting life.

10 After him was the third [f]made a mocking stock: and when he was required, [k]he put out his tongue, and that right soon, [k]holding forth his hands manfully.

11 And said courageously, These I had from [l]heaven; and for [l]his laws I [s]despise them; and [j][ll]from him I hope to receive them again.

12 Insomuch that the king, and they that were with him, marvelled at the young man’s courage, for that he nothing regarded the pains.

13 Now when this man was dead also, they tormented and mangled the fourth in like manner.

14 So when he was ready to die he said thus, It is good, being put to death by men, to look for hope from God [j]to be raised up again by him: as for thee, [j]thou shalt have no resurrection to life.

15 Afterward they brought the fifth also, and mangled him.

16 Then looked he unto the king, and said, Thou hast power over men, thou art corruptible, thou doest what thou wilt; yet think not that our nation is forsaken of God;

17 But abide a while, and behold [m]his great power, how he will torment thee and thy seed.

18 After him also they brought the sixth, who being ready to die said, Be not deceived without cause: [n]for we suffer these things for ourselves, having sinned against our God: therefore marvellous things are done unto us.

19 But think not thou, that takest in hand [o]to strive against God, that thou shalt escape unpunished.

20 But the mother was marvellous above all, and worthy of honourable memory: for when she saw her seven sons slain within the space of one day, she bare it with a good courage, because of the hope that she had in the Lord.

21 Yea, she exhorted every one of them [p]in her own language, filled with courageous spirits; and stirring up her womanish thoughts with a manly stomach, she said unto them,

22 [q]I cannot tell how ye came into my womb: for I neither gave you breath nor life, neither was it I that formed the members of every one of you;

23 But doubtless [r]the Creator of the world, who formed the generation of man, and found out the beginning of all things, will also of his own mercy [j]give you breath and life again, as ye now [s]regard not your own selves for his laws’ sake.

24 Now Antiochus, thinking himself despised, and [p]suspecting it to be a reproachful speech, whilst the youngest was yet alive, did not only exhort him by words, but also assured him with oaths, that he would make him both a rich and a happy man, if he would turn from the laws of his fathers; and that also he would take him for his friend, and trust him with [t]affairs.

25 But when the young man would in no case hearken unto him, the king called his mother, and exhorted her that she would counsel the young man to save his life.

26 And when he had exhorted her with many words, she promised him that she would counsel her son.

27 But she bowing herself toward him, laughing the cruel tyrant to scorn, spake [p]in her country language on this manner; O my son, have pity upon me that bare thee nine months in my womb, and gave thee suck three years, and nourished thee, and brought thee up unto this age, and [u]endured the troubles of education.

28 I beseech thee, my son, look upon the heaven and the earth, and all that is therein, and consider that [x]God made them of things that were not; and [y]so was mankind made likewise.

29 Fear not this [z]tormentor, but, being worthy of thy brethren, take thy death that I[j] may receive thee again in mercy with thy brethren.

30 Whiles she was yet speaking these words, the young man said, Whom wait ye for? I will not obey the king’s [a]commandment: but I will obey the commandment of the law that was given unto our fathers by Moses.

31 And thou, that hast been the author of all mischief against the Hebrews, [b]shalt not escape the hands of God.

32 [c]For we suffer because of our sins.

33 And though [d]the living Lord be angry with us a little while for our chastening and correction, yet shall he [e]be at one again with his servants.

34 But thou, O godless man, and of all other most wicked, [f]be not lifted up without a cause, nor puffed up with uncertain hopes, lifting up thy hand against the servants [g]of God:

35 For [h]thou hast not yet escaped the judgment of [i]Almighty God, who seeth all things.

36 For our brethren, who now have suffered a short pain, are dead under [j]God’s covenant of everlasting life: but thou, through the judgment of God, shalt receive just punishment for thy pride.

37 But I, as my brethren, offer up my body and life for the laws of our fathers, beseeching God that he would speedily be merciful unto our nation; and [k]that thou by [l]torments and plagues mayest confess, that [m]he alone is God;

38 And that in me and my brethren the wrath of the [i]Almighty, [c]which is justly brought upon our nation, may cease.

39 [n]Then the king being in a rage, handed him worse than all the rest, and took it grievously that he was mocked.

40 So this man died undefiled, and put his whole trust in the Lord.

41 [o]Last of all after the sons the mother died.

42 Let this be enough now to have spoken concerning [p]the idolatrous feasts, and the extreme [q]tortures.

8

1 [*][a]Then [b]Judas Maccabeus, and they that were with him, went privily into the towns, and called their kinsfolks together, and took unto them all such as continued in the Jews’ religion, and assembled about six thousand men.

2 And they called upon the Lord, that he would look upon the people that was trodden down of all; and also pity [c]the temple profaned of ungodly men;

3 And that he would have compassion upon [c]the city, sore defaced, and ready to be made even with the ground; [d]and hear [e]the blood that cried unto him,

4 And remember the wicked slaughter [f]of harmless infants, and the blasphemies committed against his name; and that he would shew his hatred against the wicked.

5 Now when Maccabeus had his company about him, he could not be withstood by the heathen: for [g]the wrath of the Lord was turned into mercy.

6 Therefore he came at unawares, and burnt up towns and cities, and got into his hands [gg]the most commodious places, and overcame and put to flight no small number of his enemies.

7 But specially took he advantage of the night for such privy attempts, insomuch that the [h]fruit of his holiness was spread every where.

8 So when [hh]Philip saw that this man increased by little and little, and that things prospered with him still [i]more and more, he wrote unto [j]Ptolemeus, [k]the governor of [l]Celosyria and Phenice, to yield more aid to the king’s affairs.

9 Then forthwith choosing [m]Nicanor the son of Patroclus, one of his special friends, he sent him with no fewer than twenty thousand of all nations under him, to root out the whole generation of the Jews; and with him he joined also [m]Gorgias a captain, who in matters of war had great experience.

10 So Nicanor undertook [n]to make so much money of the captive Jews, as should [o]defray the tribute of two thousand talents, which the king was to pay to [p]the Romans.

11 Wherefore immediately he sent to the cities upon the sea coast, [n]proclaiming a sale of the [q]captive Jews, and promising that they should have fourscore and ten [q]bodies for one talent, not expecting the vengeance that was to [r]follow upon him from the [s]Almighty God.

12 [t]Now when word was brought unto Judas of Nicanor’s coming, and he had imparted unto those that were with him that the army was at hand,

13 [u]They that were fearful, and distrusted the justice of God, fled, and conveyed themselves away.

14 Others sold all that they had left, and withal besought the Lord to deliver them, sold [w]by the wicked Nicanor before they met together:

15 And if not for their own sakes, yet for the covenants he had made with their fathers, and [x]for his holy and glorious name’s sake, [y]by which they were called.

16 So Maccabeus called his men together unto the number of six thousand, and [z]exhorted them not to be stricken with terror of the enemy, nor to fear the great multitude of the heathen, who came wrongly against them; but to fight manfully,

17 And to set before their eyes [a]the injury that they had unjustly done to [b]the holy place, and [a]the [c]cruel handling of the city, whereof they made a mockery, and also the taking away of the government of their forefathers:

18 For they, said he, trust in their weapons and boldness; but [d]our confidence is in the [e]Almighty who at a beck can cast down both them that come against us, and also all the world.

19 Moreover, he recounted unto them what[f] helps their forefathers had found, and[g] how they were delivered, when under Sennacherib an hundred fourscore and five thousand perished.

20 And he told them of the [h]battle that they had in Babylon with the [i]Galatians, how they came but eight thousand in all to [ii]the business, with four thousand Macedonians, and that the Macedonians being perplexed, the eight thousand destroyed an hundred and twenty thousand because of the help that they had from heaven, and so received a great booty.

21 Thus when he had made them bold with these words, and ready to die for the law and the country, he divided his army into four parts;

22 And joined with himself his own brethren, [j]leaders of each band, to wit S[k]imon, and J[k]oseph, and Jonathan, giving each o[l]ne fifteen hundred men.

23 Also he appointed [m]Eleazar to read the holy book: and [mm]when he had given them this watchword, The help of God; himself leading the first [n]band, [o]

24 And by the help of the [e]Almighty they slew above nine thousand of their enemies, and wounded and [p]maimed the most part of Nicanor’s host, and so put all to flight;

25 And took [q]their money that came to buy them, and pursued them far: but lacking time they [r]returned:

26 For it was the day before the sabbath, and therefore they would no longer pursue them.

27 So when they had gathered [*]their armour together, and [s]spoiled their enemies, they occupied themselves about the sabbath, [s]yielding exceeding praise and thanks to the Lord, who had preserved them unto that day, which was the beginning of mercy [t]distilling upon them.

28 And after the sabbath, when they had given part of the spoils to the [*]maimed, and [u]the widows, and orphans, the residue they divided among themselves and their servants.

29 When this was done, and they had made a common supplication, they besought [v]the merciful Lord [w]to be reconciled with his servants for ever.

30 Moreover of those that were with [x]Timotheus and [y]Bacchides, who fought against them, they slew above twenty thousand, and very easily got high and strong holds, and divided among themselves many spoils more, and made the [*]maimed, [u]orphans, widows, yea, and the aged also, equal in spoils with themselves.

31 And [z]when they had gathered their armour together, they laid them up all carefully in [gg]convenient places, and the remnant of the spoils they brought to Jerusalem.

32 They slew also Philarches, that wicked person, who was with [x]Timotheus, and had annoyed the Jews many ways.

33 Furthermore at such time as they kept the feast for the victory in their country they burnt Callisthenes, that had set fire upon the holy g[a]ates, who had fled into a little house; and so he received a reward meet for his wickedness.

34 As for that [b]most ungracious Nicanor, who had brought a thousand merchants [c]to buy the Jews,

35 He was [d]through the help of the Lord brought down by them, of whom he made least account; and putting off his glorious apparel, and discharging his company, he came like a fugitive servant through the midland unto [e]Antioch having very great dishonour, for that his host was destroyed.

36 Thus he, [f]that took upon him to make good to the Romans their tribute by means of captives in Jerusalem, told abroad, that the Jews had God to fight for them, and therefore they could not be hurt, because they followed the laws that he gave them.

9

1 [*]About that time [a]came Antiochus [*]with dishonour [b]out of the country of Persia

2 [c]For he had entered the city called Persepolis, and went about to rob the temple, and to hold the city; whereupon the multitude running to defend themselves with their weapons put them to flight; and so it happened, that Antiochus being put to flight of the inhabitants [cc]returned with shame.

3 Now [d]when he came to [e]Ecbatane, news was brought him what had happened unto [f]Nicanor and [g]Timotheus.

4 Then swelling with anger. he thought to avenge upon the Jews the disgrace done unto him by those that made him flee. Therefore commanded he his [h]chariotman to drive [i]without ceasing, and to dispatch the journey, the judgment of [j]God now following him. For he had spoken proudly in this sort, That he would come to Jerusalem and make it [k]a common burying place of the Jews.

5 But the Lord [l]Almighty, the God of Isreal, smote him with an incurable and invisible plague: or as soon as he had spoken these words, [m]a pain of the bowels that was remediless came upon him, and sore torments of the inner parts;

6 [mm]And that most justly: for he had tormented other men’s bowels with many and strange torments.

7 Howbeit he nothing at all ceased from his bragging, but still was filled with pride, [n]breathing out fire in his rage against the Jews, and commanding to haste the journey: but it came to pass that he fell down from his chariot, carried violently; so that having a sore fall, all the members of his body were much pained.

8 And thus he that a little afore thought [o]he might command the waves of the sea, (so proud was he beyond the condition of man) and [p]weigh the high mountains in a balance, was now cast on the ground, and carried in [q]an horselitter, shewing forth unto all the manifest power of God.

9 So that [r]the worms rose up out of the body of this wicked man, and whiles he lived in sorrow and pain, his flesh fell away, and the filthiness of his smell was noisome to all his army.

10 And the man, that thought a little afore [s]he could reach to the stars of heaven, no man could endure to carry for his intolerable stink.

11 [t]Here therefore, being plagued, he began to leave off his great pride, and to come to the knowledge of himself by the [u]scourge of God, his pain increasing every [w]moment.

12 And when he himself could not abide his own smell, he said these words, [x]It is meet to be subject unto God, and that a man that is mortal should not proudly think of himself if he were God.

13 This wicked person vowed also unto the [y]Lord, [z]who now no more would have mercy upon him, saying thus,

14 That [a]the holy city ([b]to the which he was going in haste to lay it even with the ground, and to make it a common buryingplace,) he would set at liberty:

15 And as touching the Jews, whom he had judged not worthy so much as to be buried, but to be cast out with their children to be devoured of the fowls and wild beasts, he would make them all equals to the citizens of [*]Athens:

16 And the holy temple, [c]which before he had spoiled, he would garnish with goodly [d]gifts, and restore all the holy vessels with many more, and [e]out of his own revenue defray the charges belonging to the sacrifices:

17 Yea, and that also he would become a Jew himself, and go through all the world that was inhabited, and declare the power of God.

18 But for all this his pains would not cease: [z]for the just judgment of God was come upon him: therefore [f]despairing of his health, he wrote unto the Jews the letter underwritten, containing the form of a supplication, [g]after this manner:

19 Antiochus, king and governor, to the good Jews his citizens wisheth [h]much joy, health, and prosperity:

20 If ye and your children fare well, and your affairs be to your contentment, I give very great thanks to God, having my hope in heaven.

21 As for me, I was weak, or else I would have remembered kindly your honour and good will r[i]eturning out of Persia, and being taken with a grievous disease, I thought it necessary to care for the common safety of all:

22 [f]Not distrusting mine health, but having great hope to escape this sickness.

23 But considering that even my father, at what time he led an army into [j]the high countries. [k]appointed a successor,

24 To the end that, if any thing fell out contrary to expectation, or if any tidings were brought that were grievous, they of the land, knowing to whom [*]the state was left, might not be troubled:

25 Again, considering how that the princes that are borderers and neighbours unto my kingdom wait for opportunities, and expect what shall be the event. I have [k]appointed my son Antiochus king, [l]whom I often committed and commended unto many of you, when I went up into [j]the high provinces; to whom I have written as followeth:

26 Therefore I pray and request you to remember [m]the benefits that I have done unto you generally, and in special, and that every man will be still faithful to me and my son.

27 For I am persuaded that he [*]understanding my mind will favourably and [n]graciously yield to your desires.

28 Thus the murderer and blasphemer having suffered most grievously, as he entreated other men, [o]so died he a miserable death in a strange country in the mountains.

29 And [p]Philip, [q]that was brought up with him, carried away his body, who also fearing the son of Antiochus went into Egypt to [r]Ptolemeus Philometor.

10

1 [*]Now Maccabeus and his company, the Lord guiding them, [a]recovered the temple and the city:

2 But the altars which the heathen had built in the open street, and also [b]the chapels, they pulled down.

3 And having cleansed the temple [c]they made another altar, and [d]striking stones they took fire out of them, and offered a sacrifice after [e]two years, and [f]set forth incense, and lights, and shewbread.

4 When that was done, [ff]they fell flat down, and besought the Lord that they might come no more into such troubles; but if they sinned any more against him, that [g]he himself would chasten them with mercy, and that they might not be delivered unto the blasphemous and barbarous nations.

5 Now [h]upon the same day that the strangers profaned the temple, on the very same day it was cleansed again, even the five and twentieth day of the same month, which is [i]Casleu.

6 And they kept [j]the eight days with gladness, as in [k]the feast of the tabernacles, remembering that not long afore they had held the feast of the tabernacles, when as they wandered in the mountains and dens like beasts.

7 Therefore they bare [l]branches, and [m]fair boughs, and [m]palms also, and sang [n]psalms unto him that had given them good success in cleansing his place.

8 [*][o]They ordained also by a common statute and decree, That every year those days should be kept of the whole nation of the Jews.

9 And this was the end of Antiochus, called [p]Epiphanes.

10 Now will we declare the acts of [q]Antiochus Eupator, who was the son of this wicked man, [r]gathering briefly the calamities of the wars.

11 So when he was come to the crown, he [s]set one [t]Lysias over the affairs of his realm, and appointed him [u]his chief governor of [v]Celosyria and Phenice.

12 For [w]Ptolemeus, that was called Macron, choosing rather to do justice unto the Jews for the wrong that had been done unto them, endeavoured to continue peace with them.

13 Whereupon being accused of the king’s friends before [q]Eupator, and called traitor [x]at every word because he had left C[y]yprus, that P[z]hilometor had committed unto him, and departed to A[p]ntiochus Epiphanes, a[*]nd seeing that he was in no honourable place, he was so discouraged, that he poisoned himself and died.

14 But when [b]Gorgias was governor of the [*]holds, he hired soldiers, and [c]nourished war [x]continually with the Jews:

15 And therewithall [cc]the Idumeans, having gotten into their hands [d]the most commodious holds, kept the Jews occupied, and receiving [dd]those that were banished from Jerusalem, they went about to [c]nourish war.

16 Then [e]they that were with Maccabeus made supplication, and besought God that he would be their helper; and so they ran with violence upon the strong holds of [cc]the Idumeans,

17 And assaulting them strongly, they won the holds, and kept off all that fought upon the wall, and slew all that fell into their hands, and killed no fewer than twenty thousand.

18 And because certain, who were no less than nine thousand, were fled together into two very strong castles, having all manner of things convenient to sustain the siege,

19 Maccabeus left [f]Simon and [f]Joseph, and Zaccheus also, and them that were with him, who were enough to besiege them, and departed himself unto those places which more needed his help.

20 Now [*]they that were with Simon, being led with covetousness, were [g]persuaded for money through certain of those that were in the castle, and took seventy thousand [h]drachms, and let some of them escape.

21 But when it was told Maccabeus what was done, he called the governors of the people together, and accused those men, that they had sold their brethren for money, and set their enemies free to fight against them.

22 So he slew those that were found traitors, and immediately took [i]the two castles.

23 And having good success with his weapons in all things he took in hand, [k]he slew in the two holds more than twenty thousand.

24 Now [l]Timotheus, [l]whom the Jews had overcome before, [m]when he had gathered a great multitude of foreign forces, and horses out of [n]Asia not a few, came as though he would take Jewry by force of arms.

25 But when he drew near, [*]they that were with Maccabeus turned themselves to pray unto God, and [o]sprinkled earth upon their heads, and [p]girded their loins with sackcloth,

26 And fell down at the foot of the altar, and besought him to be merciful to them, and [q]to be an enemy to their enemies, and an adversary to their adversaries, [q]as the law [r]declareth.

27 So after the prayer they took their weapons, and went on [m]further from the city: and when they drew near to their enemies, they kept by themselves.

28 Now the sun being newly risen, they joined both together; the one part having together with their virtue their refuge also unto the Lord for a [*]pledge of their success and victory: the other side making their rage leader of their battle

29 But when the battle waxed strong, [s]there appeared unto the enemies from heaven five comely men upon horses, with bridles of gold, and two of them[ss] led the Jews,

30 And took Maccabeus betwixt them, and covered him on every side weapons, and kept him safe, but shot arrows and lightnings against the enemies: so that [t]being confounded with blindness, and full of trouble, they were killed.

31 And there were slain of footmen twenty thousand and five hundred, and six hundred horsemen.

32 As for [l]Timotheus himself, he fled into a very strong hold, called [u]Gawra, where [v]Chereas was governor.

33 But [w]they that were with Maccabeus laid siege against the fortress courageously four days.

34 And they that were within, trusting to the strength of the place, blasphemed exceedingly, and uttered [x]wicked words.

35 Nevertheless upon the fifth day early twenty young men [w]of Maccabeus’ company, inflamed with anger because of the blasphemies, assaulted the wall manly, and with a fierce courage killed all that they met withal.

36 Others likewise ascending after them, whiles they were busied with them that were within, [y]burnt the towers, and kindling fires burnt the blasphemers alive; and others broke open the gates, and, having received in the rest of the army, took the city,

37 And killed [l][z]Timotheus, that was [a]hid in a certain pit, and [v]Chereas his brother, with Apollophanes.

38 When this was done, they praised the Lord with [b]psalms and thanksgiving, who had done so great things for Israel, and [c]given them the victory.

11

1 Not long after this, [a]Lysias the king’s [*]protector and [b]cousin, [c]who also managed the affairs, took sore displeasure for the things that were done.

2 And when he had gathered about [d]fourscore thousand with all the horsemen, he came against the Jews, thinking [e]to make the city an habitation of the [*]Gentiles,

3 And to make a gain of the temple, as of the other [f]chapels of the heathen, and [g]to set the high priesthood to sale every year:

4 Not at all considering the power of God but puffed up with his ten thousands of footmen, and his thousands of horsemen, and his fourscore e[h]lephants.

5 So he came to Judea, and drew near to [i]Bethsura, which was a strong town, but distant from Jerusalem about five furlongs, and he laid sore siege unto it.

6 Now when [*]they that were with Maccabeus heard that he besieged the holds, they and all the people with lamentation and tears besought the Lord that he would send [j]a good angel to deliver Israel.

7 Then Maccabeus himself first of all took weapons, [k]exhorting the other that they would jeopard themselves together with him to help their brethren: so they went forth together with a willing mind.

8 And as they were at Jerusalem, [l]there [m]appeared before them on horseback one [n]in white clothing, shaking his armour of gold.

9 Then they praised [nn]the merciful God all together, and took heart, insomuch that they were ready not only to fight with men, but with most cruel beasts, and to pierce through walls of iron.

10 Thus they marched forward in their armour, having an helper from heaven: for the Lord was merciful unto them

11 And giving a charge upon their enemies like lions, they slew eleven thousand footmen, and sixteen hundred horsemen, and put all the other to flight.

12 Many of them also being [o]wounded escaped naked; and Lysias himself fled away shamefully, and so escaped.

13 Who, as he was a man of understanding, [p]casting with himself what loss he had had, and considering that the Hebrews could not be overcome, because the Almighty God helped them, he sent unto them,

14 And persuaded them to agree to all reasonable conditions, and [q]promised [r]that he would persuade the king that he must needs be a friend unto them.

15 Then Maccabeus consented to all that Lysias desired, being careful of the common good; and whatsoever Maccabeus wrote unto Lysias concerning the Jews, the king granted it.

16 For there were letters written unto the Jews from Lysias [s]to this effect: Lysias unto the people of the Jews sendeth greeting:

17 John and [t]Absolom, who were sent from you, delivered me the petition subscribed, and made request for the performance of the contents thereof.

18 Therefore what things soever were meet [u]to be reported to the king, I have [v]declared them, and he hath granted [w]as much as might be.

19 And if then ye will keep yourselves loyal to the state, hereafter also will I endeavour to be a means of your good.

20 But of the particulars I have given order both to these and the other that came from me, to commune with you.

21 [x]Fare ye well. [*]The hundred and eight and fortieth year, the four and twentieth day of the month [*]Dioscorinthius.

22 Now the king’s letter [s]contained these words: King Antiochus unto his [y]brother Lysias sendeth greeting:

23 Since our father is translated unto the gods, our will is, that they that are in our realm live quietly, that every one may attend upon his own affairs.

24 We understand also that the Jews would not consent to our father, for to be brought unto the custom of the Gentiles, but had rather keep their own [z]manner of living: for the which cause they require of us, that we should suffer them to live after their own laws.

25 Wherefore our mind is, that this nation shall be in rest, and we have determined [a]to restore them their temple, that they may [b]live according to the customs of their forefathers.

26 Thou shalt do well therefore to send unto them, and [*]grant them peace, that when they are certified of our mind, they may be of good comfort, and ever go cheerfully [c]about their own affairs.

27 And the letter of the king unto the nation of the Jews was after this manner: King Antiochus sendeth greeting unto [d]the council, and the rest of the Jews:

28 If [x]ye fare well, we have our desire; we are also in good health.

29 [e]Menelaus declared unto us, that your desire was to return home, and [f]to follow your own business:

30 Wherefore [f]they that will depart shall have safe conduct till the thirtieth day of Xanthicus with security.

31 And the Jews shall use their own kind of meats and laws, as before; and none of them any manner of ways shall be molested for things ignorantly done.

32 I have sent also [e]Menelaus, that he may comfort you.

33 [x]Fare ye well. [g]In the hundred forty and eighth year, and the fifteenth day of the month [*]Xanthicus.

34 The [h]Romans also sent unto them a letter containing these words: Quintus Memmius and Titus Manlius, [*]ambassadors of the Romans, send greeting unto the people of the Jews.

35 Whatsoever Lysias [i]the king’s cousin hath granted, therewith we also are well pleased.

36 But touching such things as he judged [j]to be referred to the king, after ye have advised thereof, send one forthwith, that we may declare as [k]it is convenient for you: for we are now going to [l]Antioch.

37 Therefore send some with speed, that we may know what is your mind.

38 Farewell. [g]This hundred and eight and fortieth year, the fifteenth day of the month Xanthicus.

12

1 When these covenants were made, [a]Lysias went unto the king, and [b]the Jews were about their husbandry.

2 [*]But of the governours of several places, [c]Timotheus, and Apollonius the son of Genneus, also Hieronymus, and Demophon, and beside them [d]Nicanor the governor of [e]Cyprus, [f]would not suffer them [ff]to be quiet and live in peace.

3 The men of [g]Joppa also did such an ungodly deed: they prayed the Jews that dwelt among them to go with their wives and children into the boats which they had prepared, as though they had meant them no hurt.

4 Who accepted of it according to the common decree of the city, as being desirous to live in peace, and suspecting nothing: but when they were gone forth into the deep, they drowned no less than two hundred of them.

5 When Judas heard of this cruelty done unto his countrymen, he commanded those that were with him to make them ready.

6 And calling upon God [h]the righteous Judge, he came against those murderers of his brethren, and burnt the haven by night, and set the boats on fire, and those that fled thither he slew.

7 And when the town was shut up, he went backward, [*]as if he would return to root out all them of the city of [g]Joppa.

8 But when he heard that the [i]Jamnites were minded to do in like manner unto the Jews that dwelt among them,

9 He came upon the [i]Jamnites also by night, and set fire on the haven and the [j]navy, so that the light of the fire was seen at Jerusalem two hundred and forty furlongs off.

10 Now when they were gone from thence nine furlongs in their journey toward [c]Timotheus, no fewer than five thousand men on foot and five hundred horsemen of the [k]Arabians set upon him.

11 Whereupon there was a very sore battle; but [l]Judas’ side [ll]by the help of God got the victory; so that the Nomades of Arabia, being overcome, besought Judas [m]for peace, promising both to give him cattle, and to pleasure him otherwise.

12 Then Judas, thinking indeed that they would be profitable in many things, granted them peace: whereupon they shook hands, and so they [*]departed to their tents.

13 He went also about to make a bridge to a certain strong city, which was fenced about with walls, and inhabited by people of divers countries; and the name of it was [n]Caspis.

14 But they that were within it put such trust in the strength of the walls and provision of victuals, that they behaved themselves rudely toward [l]them that were with Judas, railing and blaspheming, and uttering such words as were not to be spoken.

15 Wherefore [l]Judas with his company, calling upon the great [o]Lord of the world, who without rams or engines of war [p]did cast down [q]Jericho in the time of Joshua, gave a fierce assault against the walls,

16 And took the city by the will of God, and made unspeakable slaughters, insomuch that a lake two furlongs broad near adjoining thereunto, being filled full, was seen running with blood.

17 Then departed they from thence seven hundred and fifty furlongs, and came to [r]Characa unto [s]the Jews that are called [t]Tubieni.

18 But as for [c]Timotheus, they found him not in [u]the places: for before he had dispatched any thing, he departed from thence, [v]having left a very strong garrison in a certain [u]hold.

19 Howbeit [w]Dositheus and Sosipater, who were of Maccabeus’ captains, went forth, and slew those that Timotheus had left in the fortress, above ten thousand men.

20 And Maccabeus ranged his army by bands, and set [*]them over the [x]bands, and [y]went against Timotheus, who had about him an hundred and twenty thousand men of foot, and two thousand and five hundred horsemen.

21 Now when Timotheus had knowledge of Judas’ coming, he sent the women and children and the other baggage unto a fortress called [*]Carnion: for the town was hard to besiege, and uneasy to come unto, by reason of the straitness of all the places.

22 But when Judas his first [x]band came in sight, the enemies, being smitten with fear and terror through [z]the appearing of him who seeth all things, fled amain, one running into this way, another that way, so as that they were often hurt of [a]their own men, and wounded with the points of their own swords.

23 Judas also was very earnest in pursuing them, killing those [b]wicked wretches, of whom he slew about thirty thousand men.

24 Moreover Timotheus himself fell into the hands of [c]Dositheus and Sosipater, whom he besought with much craft to let him go with his life, because he had many of the Jews’ parents, and the brethren of some of them, who, if they put him to death, should not be regarded.

25 So when he had assured them with many words that he would restore them without hurt, according to the agreement, they let him go for the saving of their brethren.

26 [d]Then Maccabeus marched forth to Carnion, and [e]to the temple of [*]Atargatis, and there he slew five and twenty thousand [f]persons.

27 And after he had put to flight and destroyed them, Judas removed the host toward [g]Ephron, a strong city, wherein [h]Lysias abode, and a great multitude of divers nations, and the strong young men kept the walls, and defended them mightily: wherein also was great provision of engines and darts.

28 But when Judas and his company had called upon [i]Almighty God, who with his power breaketh the strength of his enemies, [k]they won the city, and slew twenty and five thousand of them that were within,

29 From thence they departed to [l]Scythopolis, which lieth six hundred furlongs from Jerusalem,

30 But when the Jews that dwelt there had testified that the [l]Scythopolitans dealt lovingly with them, and entreated them kindly in the time of their adversity;

31 They gave them thanks, desiring them to be friendly still unto them: and so [m]they came to Jerusalem, [n]the feast of the weeks approaching.

32 And after the feast, called Pentecost, they went forth against [o]Gorgias the governor of [*][p]Idumea,

33 [q]Who came out with three thousand men of foot and four hundred horsemen.

34 And it happened that in their fighting together [r]a few of the Jews were slain.

35 At which time Dositheus, one of Bacenor’s company, who was on horseback, and a strong man, was still upon [o]Gorgias, and taking hold of his coat drew him by force; and when he would have taken that cursed man alive, a horseman of Thracia coming upon him [*]smote off his shoulder, so that Gorgias fled unto [s]Marisa.

36 Now when [c]they that were with [*]Gorgias had fought long, and were weary, Judas called upon the Lord, that he would shew himself to be their helper and leader of the battle.

37 And with that he began [t]in his own language, and sung [tt]psalms with a loud voice, and rushing unawares upon [c]Gorgias’ men, he put them to flight.

38 So Judas gathered his host, and came into the city of [u]Odollam, And when the seventh day came, they purified themselves, as the custom was, and kept the sabbath in the same place.

39 And upon [v]the day following, [*]as the [vv]use had been, [c]Judas and his company came to take up [r]the bodies of them that were slain, and to bury them with their kinsmen in their fathers’ graves.

40 Now under the coats of [r]every one that was slain they found things consecrated to the idols of [w]the Jamnites, which is forbidden the Jews [x]by the law. Then every man saw that this was the cause wherefore they were slain.

41 All men therefore praising the Lord, [y]the righteous Judge, who had opened the things that were hid,

42 Betook themselves unto prayer, and besought him that the sin committed might wholly be put out of remembrance. Besides, that noble Judas exhorted the people to keep themselves from sin, forsomuch as they saw before their eyes the things that came to pass for the sins of those that were slain.

43 And when he had made a gathering throughout the company to the sum of two thousand [z]drachms of silver, he sent it to Jerusalem [a]to offer a sin offering, doing therein very well and honestly, [b]in that he was mindful of the resurrection:

44 For [b]if he had not hoped that they that were slain should have risen again, it had been superfluous and [c]vain to pray for the dead.

45 [b]And also in that he perceived that there was great favour laid up for those that [d]died godly, it was an holy and good thought. Whereupon he made a reconciliation for the dead, that they might be delivered from sin.

13

1 In [*]the hundred forty and ninth year it was told [a]Judas, that [b]Antiochus Eupator was coming with a great power into Judea,

2 And with him [c]Lysias his protector, and ruler of his affairs, having [d]either of them a Grecian power of footmen, an hundred and ten thousand, and horsemen five thousand and three hundred, and [e]elephants two and twenty, and three hundred chariots armed with hooks.

3 [f]Menelaus also joined himself with them, and with great dissimulation encouraged Antiochus, not for the safeguard of the country, but because he thought to have been made governor.

4 But the [g]King of kings moved Antiochus’ mind against this [h]wicked wretch, and Lysias informed the king that this man was the cause of all mischief, so that the king commanded to bring him unto Berea, and to put him to death, as the manner is in that place.

5 Now there was in that place a tower of fifty cubits high, full of ashes, and it had a round instrument which on every side hanged down into the ashes.

6 And whosoever was condemned of [i]sacrilege, or had committed any other grievous crime, there did all men thrust him unto death.

7 Such a death it happened that wicked man to die, not having so much as burial in the earth; [j]and that most justly:

8 For inasmuch as he had committed many sins about the altar, whose fire and ashes were holy, he received his death in ashes.

9 Now the king came with a barbarous and haughty mind to do far worse to the Jews, than had been done in his father’s time.

10 Which things when Judas perceived, he commanded the multitude to call upon the Lord night and day, that if ever at any other time, he would now also help them, being at the point to be put from their law, from their country, and from the holy temple:

11 And that he would not suffer the people, that [*]had even now been but a little [k]refreshed, to be in subjection to the blasphemous nations.

12 So when they had all done this together, and besought [l]the merciful Lord with weeping and fasting, and [m]lying flat upon the ground three days [n]long, Judas, having exhorted them, commanded they should be in a readiness.

13 And Judas, being apart with the elders, determined, before the king’s host should enter into Judea, and get the city, to go forth and try the matter in fight [o]by the help of the Lord.

14 So when he had committed all to the [*][p]Creator of the world, and exhorted his soldiers to fight manfully, even unto death, for the laws, the temple, the city, the country, and the commonwealth, he camped by [q]Modin:

15 And [r]having given the watchword to them that were about him, Victory is of God; with the most valiant and choice young men he went in into the king’s tent by night, and slew in the camp about four thousand men, and the chiefest of the [e]elephants, with all that were upon him.

16 And at last they filled the camp with fear and tumult, and departed with good success.

17 This was done in the break of the day, because [o]the protection of the Lord did help him.

18 Now when the king had taken a taste of the manliness of the Jews, he went about to take the [s]holds by policy,

19 And marched toward [t]Bethsura, which was a strong hold of the Jews: but [u]he was put to flight, failed, and lost of his men:

20 For Judas had conveyed unto them that were in it such things as were necessary.

21 But Rhodocus, who was in the Jews’ host, disclosed the secrets to the enemies; therefore he was sought out, and when they had gotten him, they put him in prison.

22 [v]The king treated with them in [t]Bethsum the second time, [v]gave his hand, took their’s, departed, fought with [a]Judas, was overcome;

23 [w]Heard that Philip, who was left over the affairs in [x]Antioch, [*]was desperately bent, [y]confounded, [z]intreated the Jews, submitted himself, and [z]sware to all equal conditions, agreed with them, and offered sacrifice, honoured the temple, and dealt kindly with the place,

24 And [a]accepted well of Maccabeus, made him principal governor from [b]Ptolemais unto the [c]Gerrhenians;

25 Came to [b]Ptolemais: the people there were grieved for the covenants; for they stormed, because they would [d]make their covenants void:

26 [e]Lysias went up to [f]the judgment seat, said [g]as much as could be in defence of the cause, persuaded, pacified, made them well affected, [h]returned to [x]Antioch. Thus it went touching the king’s coming and [i]departing.

14

1 [a]After three years was [b]Judas informed, that [c]Demetrius the son of [d]Seleucus, having entered by the haven of [c]Tripolis with a great power and [e]navy,

2 [f]Had taken the country, and killed [g]Antiochus, and [h]Lysias his [i]protector.

3 Now one [j]Alcimus, [k]who had been high priest, and had defiled himself wilfully [kk]in the times of their mingling with the Gentiles, seeing that by no means he could save himself, nor have any more access to the holy altar,

4 [k][l]Came to king Demetrius in [*]the hundred and one and fiftieth year, presenting unto him [m]a crown of gold, and [m]a palm, and also of the boughs which were [*][n]used solemnly in the temple: and so that day he held his peace.

5 Howbeit having gotten opportunity to further his foolish enterprize, and being called into counsel by Demetrius, and asked how the Jews stood affected, and what they intended, he answered thereunto:

6 Those of the Jews that he called [o]Assideans, whose captain is Judas Maccabeus, [p]nourish war and are seditious, and will not let the rest be in peace.

7 Therefore I, being deprived of [q]mine ancestors’ honour, I mean the high priesthood, am now come hither:

8 First, verily for the unfeigned care I have of things pertaining to the king; and secondly, even for that I intend the good of mine own countrymen: for all our nation is in no small misery through the unadvised dealing of them aforersaid.

9 Wherefore, O king, seeing knowest all these things, be careful for the country, and our nation, which is pressed on every side, according to the clemency that thou readily shewest unto all.

10 For as long as Judas liveth, it is not possible that the state should be quiet.

11 This was no sooner spoken of him, but others [r]of the king’s friends, being maliciously set against Judas, did more incense Demetrius.

12 And forthwith calling Nicanor, who had been master of [s]the elephants, and [t]making him governor over Judea, [u]he sent him forth,

13 Commanding him to slay Judas, and to scatter them that were with him, and to make [j]Alcimus high priest [uu]of the great temple.

14 Then the heathen, that had fled out of Judea from Judas, came to Nicanor by flocks, thinking the harm and calamities of the Jews to be their welfare.

15 Now when the Jews heard of Nicanor’s coming, and that the heathen [*]were up against them, [v]they cast earth upon their heads, and made supplication to him that had established his people for ever, and who always helpeth [w]his portion with [x]manifestation of his presence.

16 So at the commandment of the captain they removed straightways from thence, and came near unto them at the town of Dessau.

17 Now [y]Simon, Judas’ brother, had joined battle with Nicanor, but was somewhat discomfited through the sudden silence of his enemies.

18 Nevertheless Nicanor, hearing of the manliness of [b]them that were with Judas, and the courageousness that they had to fight for their country, durst not try the matter by the sword.

19 Wherefore he sent Posidonius, and Theodotus, and Mattathias, to [z]make peace.

20 So when they had taken long advisement thereupon, and the captain had made the multitude acquainted therewith, and it appeared that they were all of one mind, they consented to the covenants,

21 [a]And appointed a day to meet in together by themselves: and when the day came, and stools were set for either of them,

22 Ludas placed armed men ready in [aa]convenient places, lest some treachery should be suddenly practised by the enemies: so they made a peaceable conference.

23 Now Nicanor abode in Jerusalem, and [b]did no hurt, but sent away the people that came flocking unto him.

24 And he would not willingly have Judas out of his sight: for he love the man [c]from his heart

25 He prayed him also to take a wife, and to beget children: so he married, [cc]was quiet, and [*]took part of this life.

26 But [e]Alcimus, perceiving the love that was betwixt them, and considering [f]the covenants that were made, came to [g]Demetrius, and told him that Nicanor was not well affected toward the state; for that he had [h]ordained Judas, [i]a traitor to his realm, to be the king’s successor.

27 Then the king [k]being in a rage, and provoked with the accusations of the most wicked man, wrote to Nicanor, signifying that he was much displeased with [f]the covenants, and commanding him that he should send Maccabeus prisoner in all haste unto [l]Antioch.

28 When this came to Nicanor’s hearing, he was much [m]confounded in himself, and took it grievously that he should [n]make void the articles which were agreed upon, the man being in no fault.

29 But because there was no dealing against the king, he watched his time to accomplish this thing by policy.

30 [*]Notwithstanding, when Maccabeus saw that Nicanor began to be [o]churlish unto him, and that he entreated him more roughly than he was wont, perceiving that such [o]sour behaviour came not of good, he gathered together not a few of his men, and withdrew himself from Nicanor.

31 But the other, knowing that he was notably prevented by Judas’ policy, [p]came into [q]the great and holy temple, and commanded the priests, that were offering their usual sacrifices, to deliver him the man.

32 And when they sware that they could not tell where the man was whom he sought,

33 [r]He stretched out his right hand toward the temple, and made an oath in this manner: If ye will not deliver me Judas as [*]a prisoner, I will lay this temple of God even with the ground, and I will break down the altar, and erect a notable temple unto [s]Bacchus.

34 After these words he departed. Then the priests lifted up their hands toward heaven, and besought him that was ever a defender of their nation, saying in this manner;

35 Thou, O Lord of all things, [t]who hast need of nothing, wast pleased that the temple of thine habitation should be among us:

36 Therefore now, O holy Lord of all holiness, keep this house ever undefiled, [u]which lately was cleansed, and [v]stop every unrighteous mouth.

37 Now was there accused unto Nicanor one Razis, one of the elders of Jerusalem, a lover of his countrymen, and a man of very good report, who for his kindness was called a father of the Jews.

38 For in the former times, [w]when they mingled not themselves with the Gentiles, he had been accused of Judaism, and [x]did boldly [y]jeopard his body and life with all [z]vehemency for the religion of the Jews.

39 So Nicanor, willing to declare the hate that he bare unto the Jews, sent above five hundred men of war to take him:

40 For he thought by taking him to do the Jews much hurt.

41 Now when the multitude would have taken the tower, and violently broken into the outer door, and bade that fire should be brought to burn it, he being ready to be taken on every side fell upon his sword;

42 Choosing rather to die manfully, than to come into the hands of [a]the wicked, to be abused otherwise than beseemed his noble birth:

43 But missing his stroke through haste, the multitude also rushing within the doors, he ran boldly up to the wall, and cast himself down manfully among the thickest of them.

44 But they quickly giving back, and a space being made, he fell down into the midst of the void place.

45 Nevertheless, while there was yet breath within him, being inflamed with anger, he rose up; and though his blood gushed out like spouts of water, and his wounds were grievous, yet he ran through the midst of the throng; and standing upon a steep rock,

46 When as his blood was now quite gone, he plucked out his bowels, and taking them in both his hands, he cast them upon the throng, and calling upon [b]the Lord of life and spirit [c]to restore him those again, he thus died.

15

1 [a]But Nicanor, hearing that [b]Judas and his company were in the [c]strong places about [d]Samaria, resolved [e]without any danger to set upon them on the sabbath day.

2 Nevertheless the Jews that were compelled to go with him said, O destroy not so cruelly and barbarously, but give honour to that day, which he, that seeth all things, hath honoured with holiness above all other days.

3 Then [f]the most ungracious wretch demanded, if there were a [g]Mighty one in heaven, that had commanded the sabbath day to be kept.

4 And when they said, There is in heaven [h]a living Lord, and [g]mighty, who commanded the seventh day to be kept:

5 Then said the other, And I also am mighty upon earth, and I command to take arms, and to do the king’s [i]business. Yet he obtained not to have his wicked will done.

6 So Nicanor in exceeding pride and haughtiness determined to set up a publick monument of his victory over [a]Judas and them that were with him.

7 But Maccabeus had [k]ever sure confidence that the Lord would [l]help him:

8 Wherefore [m]he exhorted his people not to fear the coming of the heathen against them, but to remember the help which in former times they had received from heaven, and now to expect the victory and aid, which should come unto them from the [n]Almighty.

9 And so comforting them out of [o]the law and the prophets, and withal putting them in mind of the battles that they won afore, he made them more cheerful.

10 And when he had stirred up their minds, he gave them their charge, shewing them therewithall the falsehood of the heathen, and the breach of oaths.

11 Thus he armed every one of them, not so much with defence of shields and spears, as with comfortable and good words: and beside that, he told them a dream worthy to be believed, as if it had been so indeed, which did not a little rejoice them.

12 And [p]this was his vision: That [q]Onias, who had been high priest, a virtuous and a good man, reverend in conversation, gentle in condition, well spoken also, and exercised from a child in all points of virtue, holding up his hands prayed for the whole body of the Jews.

13 This done, in like manner there appeared a man with gray hairs, and [r]exceeding glorious, who was of a wonderful and excellent majesty.

14 Then [q]Onias [s]answered, saying, This is a lover of the brethren, who prayeth much for the people, and for [t]the holy city, to wit, [u]Jeremias the prophet of God.

15 Whereupon Jeremias holding forth his right hand gave to Judas a sword of gold, and in giving it spake thus,

16 Take this holy sword, a gift from God, with the which thou shalt wound the adversaries.

17 Thus being well comforted by the words of Judas, which were very good, and able to stir them up to valour, and to encourage the hearts of the young men, they determined not to pitch camp, but courageously to set upon them, and manfully to try the matter by conflict, because the city and the sanctuary and the temple were in danger.

18 For the care that they took for their wives, and their children, their brethren, and folks, was in least account with them: but the greatest and principal fear was for the holy temple.

19 Also they that were in the city took not the least care, being troubled for the conflict abroad.

20 And now, [w]when as all looked what should be the trial, and the enemies were already come near, and the army was set in array, and [x]the beasts conveniently placed, and the horsemen set in wings,

21 Maccabeus seeing the coming of the multitude, and the divers preparations of armour, and the fierceness of [x]the beasts, stretched out his hands toward heaven, and called upon the Lord [p]that worketh wonders, knowing that victory cometh not by arms, but even as it seemeth good to him, he giveth it to such as are worthy:

22 [y]Therefore in his prayer he said after this manner; O [z]Lord, [a]thou didst send thine angel in the time of Ezekias king of Judea, and didst slay in the host of Sennacherib an hundred fourscore and five thousand:

23 Wherefore now also, O [b]Lord of heaven, send [c]a good angel before us for a fear and dread unto them;

24 And through the might of thine arm let those be stricken with terror, that come against [d]thy holy people to blaspheme. And he ended thus.

25 Then [e]Nicanor and they that were with him came forward with trumpets and songs.

26 But [e]Judas and his company encountered the enemies with invocation and prayer.

27 So that [f]fighting with their hands, and praying unto God with their hearts, they slew no less than thirty and five thousand men: for through [g]the appearance of God they were greatly cheered.

28 Now when the [h]battle was done, returning again with joy, they knew that [i]Nicanor lay dead in his [k]harness.

29 Then they made a great shout and a noise, praising the [l]Almighty [m]in their own language.

30 And Judas, who was ever the chief defender of the citizens both in body and mind, and who continued his love toward his countrymen all his life, commanded to strike off [n]Nicanor’s head, and his hand with his shoulder, and [n]bring them to Jerusalem.

31 So when he was there, and called them of his nation together, and set the priests before the altar, he sent for them that were of [o]the tower,

32 And shewed them vile Nicanor’s head, and the hand of that blasphemer, [p]which with proud brags he had stretched out against the holy temple of the [q]Almighty.

33 And when he had cut out the tongue of that ungodly Nicanor, he commanded that they should give it by pieces [r]unto the fowls, and hang up the reward of his madness before the temple.

34 So every man [s]praised toward the heaven the glorious Lord, saying, Blessed be he that hath kept his own place undefiled.

35 [t]He hanged also Nicanor’s head upon [o]the tower, an evident and manifest sign unto all of [u]the help of the Lord.

36 And [v]they ordained all with a common decree in no case to let that day pass without solemnity, but to celebrate the thirtieth day of the twelfth month, which in the Syrian tongue is called [w]Adar, [x]the day before [y]Mardocheus’ day.

37 Thus went it with Nicanor: and from that time forth the Hebrews had the city in their power. And here will I make an end.

38 And if I have done well, and as is fitting the story, it is that which I desired: but if slenderly and meanly, it is that which I could attain unto.

39 [z]For as it is hurtful to drink wine or water alone; and as wine mingled with water is pleasant, and delighteth the taste: even so speech finely framed delighteth the ears of them that read the story. And here shall be an end.

* 1.1 About B.C. 144.

a 1.2 See Lev. 26. 42.

b 1.4 See Acts 16. 14.

c 1.5 1 Macc. 13. 50. ch. 7. 33. Acts 7. 26 (Engl.). Comp. Rom. 5. 11 (Engl.).

d 1.7 1 Macc. 10. 67. & 11. 19.

* 1.7 About B. C. 144.

e 1.7 ch. 4. 7.

f 1.7 Wisd. 12. 3.

g 1.8 ch. 8. 33 (Gk.). So ch. 3. 19 (Gk.). Comp. 1 Kin. 6. 3.

h 1.8 1 Macc. 4. 50, 51, 53.

i 1.8 So Rom. 3. 25 (Gk.).

u 1.9 ver. 9. ch. 2. 16. Matt. 14. 6. Luke 24. 21 (Gk.). Acts 19. 38 marg.

j 1.9 So ver. 18. But comp. ch. 10. 5–8 with Lev. 23. 34.

k 1.9 ver. 18. See 1 Macc. 1. 54.

* 1.10 [B.C. 125–4].

l 1.10 1 Macc. 12. 6 (Gk.). ch. 4. 44. & 11. 27. See Judith 4. 8.

m 1.10 1 Macc. 15. 16.

n 1.10 Matt. 10. 24, 25. Luke 6. 40. James 3. 1 (Engl.). See Acts 13. 1.

o 1.10 Lev. 4. 3, 5, 16. & 16. 32.

s 1.11 So ver. 11. See 1 Macc. 1. 10. Comp. ch. 9. 2 with 1 Macc. 6. 1–4.

p 1.12 ch. 5. 8. So Wisd. 10. 19 (Gk.).

q 1.12 ch. 3. 1. & 9. 14. & 15. 14. See 1 Macc. 2. 7.

r 1.13 ver. 19, 33. See 1 Macc. 14. 2.

s 1.14 So ver. 11. See 1 Macc. 1. 10. Comp. ch. 9. 2 with 1 Macc. 6. 1–4.

i 1.15 So Rom. 3. 25 (Gk.).

t 1.16 Comp. 1 Macc. 10. 73.

u 1.18 ver. 9. ch. 2. 16. Matt. 14. 6. Luke 24. 21 (Gk.). Acts 19. 38 marg.

v 1.18 ch. 2. 16. See 1 Macc. 4. 59.

k 1.18 ver. 18. See 1 Macc. 1. 54.

w 1.18 1 Macc. 12. 8. ver. 20. ch. 2. 9. & 3. 9. & 7. 6. & 10. 26. & 11. 18. Matt. 18. 31 in the Gk.

u 1.18 ver. 9. ch. 2. 16. Matt. 14. 6. Luke 24. 21 (Gk.). Acts 19. 38 marg.

x 1.18 Lev. 23. 24, 27, 34. Numb. 29. 1. So ver. 9.

y 1.18 Neh. 8. 14–18.

r 1.19 ver. 19, 33. See 1 Macc. 14. 2.

yy 1.19 Comp. ch. 10. 3.

z 1.20 Neh. 2. 6.

r 1.20 ver. 19, 33. See 1 Macc. 14. 2.

w 1.20 1 Macc. 12. 8. ver. 20. ch. 2. 9. & 3. 9. & 7. 6. & 10. 26. & 11. 18. Matt. 18. 31 in the Gk.

a 1.21 Comp. 1 Kin. 18. 33–35.

b 1.23 Neh. 12. 11.

bb 1.24 Ecclus. 24. 8. So ch. 7. 23. & 13. 14.

c 1.25 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

d 1.26 ch. 14. 15.

e 1.27 See John 7. 35.

f 1.27 Ps. 106. 47.

g 1.27 See Song 22.

h 1.29 ch. 2. 18. & 8. 17.

i 1.29 Deut. 30. 3–8. So ch. 2. 18.

k 1.33 See ver. 13.

* 1.33 Or, Neemias his company. ver. 36. See Song 26.

l 1.35 ch. 3. 6. & 4. 28 in the Gk. See Ecclus. 27. 1 marg.

a 2.1 See Luke 2. 2. Comp. ver. 4, 13.

b 2.1 ch. 1. 19.

c 2.2 See Baruch 6. 4.

d 2.4 ver. 1.

e 2.4 Deut. 32. 49. & 34. 1.

f 2.5 Comp. ch. 15. 14–16.

g 2.5 Comp. 2 Esdr. 10. 22.

h 2.8 Ex. 40. 34, 38.

i 2.8 1 Kin. 8. 10, 23, &c.

k 2.9 See ch. 1. 18.

l 2.9 1 Kin. 8. 62, 63.

m 2.10 Lev. 9. 24.

n 2.10 2 Chr. 7. 1.

o 2.11 Lev. 10. 16, 17.

p 2.12 1 Kin. 8. 65, 66. Comp. ch. 1. 18.

d 2.13 ver. 1.

q 2.13 ch. 5. 16.

r 2.13 ch. 9. 16. Judith 16. 19. Luke 21. 5 in the Gk.

s 2.14 ver. 19? or ch. 1. 10?

* 2.14 [Or, fell out during the war].

t 2.16 See ch. 1. 18.

* 2.17 Gr. Now God it is that saved all his people, and rendered the heritage [to all], and the u kingdom, and the priesthood, and the sanctuary, as he promised in the law: for we hope in God that he will shortly, &c.

u 2.17 Wisd. 5. 16 marg.

w 2.17 Ezek. 45. 4 (Gk.).

x 2.18 See ch. 1. 29.

y 2.18 Baruch 5. 3.

z 2.18 See ch. 1. 29.

a 2.19 See 1 Macc. 1. 1.

b 2.19 ver. 16. See ch. 10. 3.

c 2.20 See 1 Macc. 1. 10.

d 2.20 See ch. 10. 10.

e 2.21 ch. 3. 24. & 5. 4. & 12. 22. & 14. 15. & 15. 27 in the Gk. See 2 Thess. 2. 8. Comp. ch. 5. 2. & 10. 29. & 11. 8. & 15. 12, 22.

f 2.22 ch. 10. 1.

g 2.22 See Esther 13. 2.

h 2.22 See Acts 24. 4.

i 2.23 See Acts 2. 10.

ii 2.23 So ch. 10. 10.

n 2.24 2 Chr. 7. 1.

j 2.26 Gk. as ver. 27.

* 2.27 Or, to deserve well of many. Comp. 2 Cor. 9. 12.

j 2.27 Gk. as ver. 27.

k 2.28 ver. 23, 30.

l 2.28 1 Pet. 2. 21.

ll 2.29 Comp. ch. 15. 39.

k 2.30 ver. 23, 30.

m 2.31 So Acts 24. 4 (Gk.).

n 2.32 ch. 6. 17. Luke 1. 1 in the Gk. So ver. 24.

a 3.1 See ch. 1. 12.

b 3.1 1 Macc. 12. 7, 8, 20? ver. 5. ch. 4. 1, 4, 34, 36. & 15. 12, 14. Not as Ecclus. 50. 1.

c 3.2 See 1 Macc. 2. 18.

* 3.3 About B. C. 187.

d 3.3 1 Macc. 7. 1. ch. 4. 7. & 5. 18. & 14. 1.

e 3.3 See 1 Macc. 8. 6.

ee 3.4 ver. 11. ch. 4. 1, 3, 4, 23.

f 3.4 Wisd. 18. 2 (Gk.).

g 3.5 1 Macc. 10. 69? ch. 4. 4.

h 3.5 ver. 8. See 1 Esdr. 2. 17.

i 3.6 ver. 24, 28, 40. ch. 4. 42. & 5. 18. See 1 Macc. 14. 49. & Mark 12. 41.

j 3.6 See ch. 1. 35.

k 3.6 Comp. ver. 3.

l 3.7 Comp. Dan. 11. 20.

m 3.8 Acts 27. 30 (Engl. So Gk.).

h 3.8 ver. 8. See 1 Esdr. 2. 17.

n 3.8 Acts 27. 13.

o 3.9 Acts 28. 7.

p 3.9 Acts 25. 14. Gal. 2. 2 in the Gk.

q 3.9 See ch. 1. 18.

r 3.10 ver. 15 (Gk.). See 1 Tim. 6. 20.

s 3.10 ch. 8. 28, 30. James 1. 27.

t 3.11 Comp. Ex. 38. 25. ch. 5. 21.

u 3.12 ver. 11, 15, 22. See ch. 5. 19.

v 3.13 ver. 7, 23.

w 3.14 Luke 22. 44. So ver. 21.

x 3.15 Ex. 28. 2–5.

y 3.15 Comp. Ex. 22. 7.

r 3.15 ver. 15 (Gk.). See 1 Tim. 6. 20.

u 3.15 ver. 11, 15, 22. See ch. 5. 19.

w 3.16 Luke 22. 44. So ver. 21.

* 3.18 Or, to make general supplication.

z 3.18 ver. 15, 20.

a 3.19 ch. 10. 25. See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

b 3.19 Gk. as ch. 1. 8. See Luke 16. 20.

c 3.19 Acts 20. 9. 2 Cor. 11. 33.

* 3.21 Gr. expectation. Luke 21. 26 (Gk.). So Acts 12. 11.

w 3.21 Luke 22. 44. So ver. 21.

u 3.22 ver. 11, 15, 22. See ch. 5. 19.

d 3.24 See ver. 6.

* 3.24 Or, Lord of our fathers. See Ecclus. 46. 5.

e 3.24 ch. 12. 15, 28. & 15. 23. 1 Tim. 6. 15 in the Gk.

ee 3.24 See ch. 2. 21.

f 3.25 ch. 5. 3. See 1 Kin. 20. 11.

ff 3.26 ch. 5. 18.

g 3.26 See 1 Thess. 1. 3.

gg 3.27 ch. 9. 8 (Gk.).

d 3.28 See ver. 6.

h 3.30 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

i 3.31 See James 5. 16.

j 3.32 So ch. 4. 1.

k 3.33 ver. 26.

i 3.33 See James 5. 16.

l 3.35 See ch. 13. 24. Comp. ver. 9 (Gk.).

m 3.38 ch. 4. 2.

n 3.39 Ps. 123. 1.

d 3.40 ch. 3. 38. So ver. 50. ch. 14. 26.

a 4.1 ch. 3. 4, 11.

b 4.1 See Matt. 26. 73.

c 4.1 So ch. 3. 32.

d 4.2 ch. 3. 38. So ver. 50. ch. 14. 26.

e 4.2 Luke 22. 25 (Gk.).

f 4.2 See Acts 21. 20.

g 4.4 ch. 3. 5. Comp. ch. 8. 8. & 10. 11.

h 4.4 See 1 Esdr. 2. 17.

i 4.5 So Acts 28. 19.

j 4.6 Acts 24. 2 (Gk.).

k 4.7 See ch. 3. 3.

l 4.7 See 1 Macc. 1. 10.

* 4.7 (B.C. 175.)

m 4.7 ver. 13, 22, 23, 24, 26. ch. 5. 5, 6.

mm 4.7 ver. 26 (Gk.).

n 4.8 1 Tim. 2. 1. & 4. 5 (Gk.).

o 4.9 1 Macc. 1. 14. ver. 12.

p 4.9 ver. 19. ch. 9. 15 marg. See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

q 4.10 So 1 Macc. 1. 41, 42. & 2. 18.

t 4.10 So ver. 10. ch. 6. 8. & 11. 2 marg. Comp. Mark 7. 26.

qq 4.11 1 Macc. 8. 17.

r 4.11 See 1 Macc. 8. 1.

o 4.12 1 Macc. 1. 14. ver. 12.

s 4.12 ver. 27. & 5. 5 in the Gk. So ch. 15. 31, 35. See 1 Macc. 1. 33.

t 4.13 So ver. 10. ch. 6. 8. & 11. 2 marg. Comp. Mark 7. 26.

u 4.13 ch. 6. 24 (Gk.).

v 4.13 ver. 7.

* 4.14 Or, the Discus, which was a stone with a hole in the midst.

w 4.16 ch. 6. 8. & 11. 24. 2 Tim. 3. 10 in the Gk.

* 4.18 About B. C. 174.

x 4.18 ver. 32, 44, 49. Comp. 1 Macc. 11. 59.

y 4.19 ch. 8. 34. & 15. 3 (Engl.).

* 4.19 Gr. who were religious ambassadors.

p 4.19 ver. 19. ch. 9. 15 marg. See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

z 4.19 Tobit 5. 14. ch. 10. 20. & 12. 43. Luke 15. 8, 9 marg.

a 4.19 Ecclus. 10. 23. ch. 6. 4 (Gk.), 21 (Gk.). & 11. 36. Acts 22. 22 (Gk.). Rom. 1. 28.

* 4.21 About B. C. 173.

b 4.21 1 Macc. 3. 10, 12? ch. 5. 24.

* 4.21 Or, enthronizing.

c 4.21 1 Macc. 1. 18. ch. 9. 29. & 10. 13. See Esth. 11. 1.

d 4.21 See Josh. 19. 46.

e 4.22 see 1 Esdr. 2. 17. & Acts 11. 19.

* 4.23 About B. C. 172.

f 4.23 ver. 27, &c. ch. 5. 5, 15, 23. & 11. 29, 32. & 13. 3.

g 4.23 See ver. 1.

h 4.23 ver. 8, 9. Comp. ch. 11. 3.

h 4.24 ver. 8, 9. Comp. ch. 11. 3.

i 4.26 ver. 7 (Gk.).

i 4.26 ver. 7 (Gk.).

k 4.26 1 Macc. 5. 6. ch. 5. 7. See Judith 1. 12.

* 4.27 About B. C. 171.

l 4.27 See ver. 12.

m 4.28 See ch. 1. 35.

n 4.29 ch. 10. 13. & 12. 2. See Acts 4. 36.

o 4.30 See Acts 9. 11.

p 4.31 Acts 19. 35, 36 (Gk.).

q 4.31 ver. 32, 34, 38.

r 4.32 See Acts 5. 2.

s 4.32 ver. 17.

t 4.33 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

u 4.36 Comp. ver. 30.

v 4.36 1 Macc. 11. 14. See Judith 2. 21.

w 4.36 ver. 49 (Gk.).

x 4.36 See 1 Macc. 10. 61 (Gk.). So Acts 25. 24 (Gk.).

y 4.37 ch. 14. 24 (Gk.).

* 4.38 About B. C. 171.

* 4.39 About B. C. 170.

z 4.39 ver. 29.

a 4.39 See 1 Esdr. 7. 4.

b 4.39 See Jer. 10. 22 (Engl.).

* 4.40 Or, Tyrannus.

c 4.40 See Ezek. 47. 16?

cc 4.41 ch. 5. 5 (Gk.).

d 4.41 See Song 26.

e 4.42 Acts 19. 37 (Gk. & Engl.).

f 4.42 See ch. 3. 6.

g 4.44 ver. 17.

h 4.44 See ch. 1. 10.

i 4.45 1 Macc. 3. 38. ch. 6. 8 (not as ch. 8. 8?).

j 4.45 See Acts 12. 20. Comp. ch. 10. 20.

k 4.47 ver. 44.

l 4.47 Comp. Col. 3. 11. Also ch. 7. 4 (Gk.).

m 4.47 Luke 23. 24 (Gk.).

g 4.49 ver. 17.

n 4.49 ver. 36 (Gk.).

o 4.49 ch. 5. 10 (Gk.).

p 4.50 ver. 45.

q 4.50 ch. 11. 29.

r 4.50 See ver. 2.

* 5.1 About B. C. 170.

a 5.1 1 Macc. 1. 17?

b 5.1 Judith 2. 19 (Engl.).

e 5.2 See ch. 2. 21.

c 5.2 Comp. Luke 21. 11.

* 5.3 Or, staves.

d 5.3 See 1 Kin. 20. 11. & 1 Macc. 3. 3.

e 5.4 See ch. 2. 21.

f 5.5 ch. 4. 7, 26.

g 5.5 ch. 4. 41 (Gk.).

h 5.5 ver. 15, 23. See ch. 4. 23.

i 5.5 See ch. 4. 12.

j 5.7 See ch. 4. 26.

k 5.8 Comp. 2 Cor. 11. 32.

l 5.8 See 1 Macc. 5. 39.

m 5.8 Song 9.

* 5.8 Or, executioner. ch. 7. 29 (Gk.).

n 5.8 See ch 1. 12.

o 5.9 See 1 Macc. 12. 2.

p 5.9 1 Macc. 12. 21.

q 5.10 ch. 4. 49 (Gk.).

r 5.11 ver. 5.

s 5.11 1 Macc. 1. 20.

t 5.12 1 Macc. 1. 24.

u 5.13 1 Macc. 2. 9.

w 5.13 So Baruch 3. 19 (Gk.).

x 5.15 1 Macc. 1. 21–23.

h 5.15 ver. 15, 23. See ch. 4. 23.

x 5.16 1 Macc. 1. 21–23.

y 5.16 See ch. 2. 13. Comp. ch. 9. 16.

z 5.17 ver. 21. ch. 7. 34 (Gk.).

a 5.17 ch. 9. 13. See Baruch 6. 6.

b 5.17 Comp. 2 Chr. 30. 9. Ps. 119. 132.

c 5.18 ch. 3. 25, 26.

d 5.18 See ch. 3. 3.

e 5.18 See ch. 3. 6.

f 5.19 ch. 3. 12. ver. 20. See John 11. 48.

g 5.19 Comp. Mark 2. 27.

f 5.20 ch. 3. 12. ver. 20. See John 11. 48.

h 5.20 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

a 5.20 ch. 9. 13. See Baruch 6. 6.

i 5.21 So 1 Macc. 1. 23. Comp. ch. 3. 11.

j 5.21 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

k 5.21 1 Macc. 1. 24. So ver. 17. Comp. ch. 9. 8.

z 5.21 ver. 21. ch. 7. 34 (Gk.).

l 5.22 So 1 Macc. 1. 51.

ll 5.22 ch. 6. 11. & 8. 8.

m 5.22 See Acts 2. 10.

n 5.23 ch. 6. 2. See Judg. 9. 7.

* 5.24 About B. C. 168.

o 5.24 1 Macc. 1. 29–32.

p 5.24 Acts 24. 5 (Engl.).

q 5.24 1 Macc. 3. 10, 12? ch. 4. 21.

r 5.25 ch. 6. 21, 24 (Gk.). See Luke 20. 20.

s 5.26 Luke 23. 48 (Gk.).

t 5.26 So ch. 8. 3.

u 5.27 1 Macc. 2. 4, 66.

* 5.27 Gr. who was the tenth.

w 5.27 See 1 Macc. 1. 53. So 1 Macc. 2. 28, 29. Comp. ch. 6. 11. & 8. 1.

w 5.27 See 1 Macc. 1. 53. So 1 Macc. 2. 28, 29. Comp. ch. 6. 11. & 8. 1.

* 6.1 Antioch: the Latin interpreters. Comp. ch. 9. 15.

a 6.1 So 1 Macc. 1. 42.

b 6.1 ch. 11. 25. See Acts 23. 1.

c 6.2 So 1 Macc. 1. 46, 54. ch. 8. 2.

d 6.2 See ch. 5. 23.

* 6.2 Out of Jos[eph.] lib. 12. [cap.] 7. or, as they were. Comp. 2 Kin. 17. 24.

e 6.4 Eph. 5. 18 (Gk.). Tit. 1. 6. 1 Pet. 4. 4. So Luke 15. 13.

f 6.4 See Wisd. 14. 23.

g 6.4 ver. 21. See ch. 4. 19.

h 6.5 So 1 Macc. 1. 47.

i 6.5 See Acts 10. 28.

j 6.6 1 Macc. 1. 39.

k 6.7 ver. 21. ch. 7. 42 in the Gk. So ver. 8.

kk 6.7 ch. 14. 33.

l 6.8 Comp. 1 Macc. 1. 51.

* 6.8 Gr. Grecians. See ch. 4. 13.

m 6.8 See ch. 4. 45.

n 6.8 See ch. 4. 16.

k 6.8 ver. 21. ch. 7. 42 in the Gk. So ver. 8.

o 6.9 1 Macc. 1. 50.

p 6.10 1 Macc. 1. 60 marg., 61. So ch. 8. 4.

p 6.10 1 Macc. 1. 60 marg., 61. So ch. 8. 4.

q 6.10 Acts 27. 14 (Gk.).

q 6.10 Acts 27. 14 (Gk.).

r 6.11 Heb. 11. 38 (Gk.). Comp. 1 Macc. 1. 53. ch. 5. 27.

s 6.11 ch. 5. 22.

t 6.11 1 Macc. 2. 32–38.

u 6.12 1 Macc. 3. 6 (Gk.).

v 6.12 Comp. Wisd. 3. 4.

w 6.14 See Baruch 6. 6.

x 6.14 See Gen. 15. 16.

y 6.16 So ch. 7. 18, 32, 33.

z 6.17 Rather as Wisd. 16. 11. 2 Tim. 1. 5. 2 Pet. 1. 13. & 3. 1.

a 6.17 See ch. 2. 32.

* 6.18 About B. C. 167.

b 6.18 See Ecclus. 10. 5.

bb 6.18 ver. 24.

c 6.18 Lev. 11. 7. Deut. 14. 8. Isai. 65. 4. & 66. 17. ch. 7. 1. Comp. 1 Macc. 1. 47. See Acts 10. 14.

d 6.19 1 Macc. 1. 63. So ch. 7. 1, &c.

e 6.19 ver. 28. So Heb. 11. 35.

f 6.21 ver. 7 (Gk.).

g 6.21 ver. 4. See ch. 4. 19.

h 6.21 ver. 24 (Gk.). See ch. 5. 25. So ver. 25 (Gk.).

i 6.23 So Acts 7. 20. Heb. 11. 23 in the Gk.

k 6.23 Heb. 13. 7 (Gk.). See Gal. 1. 13.

l 6.24 1 Macc. 1. 50. & 16. 21. ch. 11. 14. See Ex. 18. 4. Comp. ver. 28.

h 6.24 ver. 24 (Gk.). See ch. 5. 25. So ver. 25 (Gk.).

m 6.24 ver. 18.

n 6.24 ch. 4. 13 (Gk.).

h 6.25 ver. 24 (Gk.). See ch. 5. 25. So ver. 25 (Gk.).

nn 6.26 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

o 6.28 So ver. 31.

e 6.28 ver. 28. So Heb. 11. 35.

p 6.29 ver. 21, 22.

* 6.29 Or, q madness, or, pride.

r 6.30 See Susanna 22.

o 6.31 So ver. 31.

a 7.1 See Acts 10. 28.

b 7.1 See ch. 6. 18.

bb 7.3 ver. 39. ch. 14. 27.

c 7.3 Lev. 2. 5. & 6. 21, &c. (Gk.).

k 7.4 Comp. ver. 4.

k 7.4 Comp. ver. 4.

d 7.6 Cited from Deut. 32. 36 (Gk. not Heb.).

e 7.6 See ch. 1. 18.

d 7.6 Cited from Deut. 32. 36 (Gk. not Heb.).

f 7.7 Wisd. 12. 25. Ecclus. 27. 28. Heb. 11. 36 in the Gk. So ver. 10.

p 7.8 ver. 8, 27. See ch. 12. 37. Comp. ver. 24.

g 7.8 ver. 5.

h 7.9 Luke 2. 29 (Gk.).

i 7.9 So Esther 14. 12. See Zech. 14. 9.

j 7.9 Heb. 11. 35. So ch. 12. 43, 44. See Dan. 12. 2.

f 7.10 Wisd. 12. 25. Ecclus. 27. 28. Heb. 11. 36 in the Gk. So ver. 10.

k 7.10 Comp. ver. 4.

k 7.10 Comp. ver. 4.

l 7.11 See 1 Macc. 3. 60. Comp. ver. 34 (Gk.).

l 7.11 See 1 Macc. 3. 60. Comp. ver. 34 (Gk.).

s 7.11 ver. 11 (Gk.). So ch. 14. 46.

j 7.11 Heb. 11. 35. So ch. 12. 43, 44. See Dan. 12. 2.

ll 7.11 So ch. 14. 46.

j 7.14 Heb. 11. 35. So ch. 12. 43, 44. See Dan. 12. 2.

j 7.14 Heb. 11. 35. So ch. 12. 43, 44. See Dan. 12. 2.

m 7.17 See Ecclus. 17. 8.

n 7.18 ver. 32, 33, 38. So ch. 5. 17. & 6. 13–16. & 8. 5, 29.

o 7.19 See Acts 5. 39.

p 7.21 ver. 8, 27. See ch. 12. 37. Comp. ver. 24.

q 7.22 See Eccles. 11. 5.

r 7.23 ch. 13. 14. So Ecclus. 24. 8. ch. 1. 24.

j 7.23 Heb. 11. 35. So ch. 12. 43, 44. See Dan. 12. 2.

s 7.23 ver. 11 (Gk.). So ch. 14. 46.

p 7.24 ver. 8, 27. See ch. 12. 37. Comp. ver. 24.

t 7.24 See 1 Macc. 13. 37.

p 7.27 ver. 8, 27. See ch. 12. 37. Comp. ver. 24.

u 7.27 Acts 13. 18 marg.

x 7.28 So Heb. 11. 3.

y 7.28 Comp. Rom. 4. 17.

z 7.29 ch. 5. 8 marg.

j 7.29 Heb. 11. 35. So ch. 12. 43, 44. See Dan. 12. 2.

a 7.30 1 Esdr. 8. 8 (Gk.).

b 7.31 So ver. 35.

c 7.32 See ver. 18.

d 7.33 ch. 15. 4. So Esther 16. 16.

e 7.33 See ch. 1. 5 (Engl.).

f 7.34 ch. 5. 17 (Gk.).

g 7.34 Comp. Gk. with ver. 11.

h 7.35 Rom. 2. 3. So ver. 31.

i 7.35 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

j 7.36 Comp. 1 Pet. 1. 3, 4.

k 7.37 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 13. ch. 9. 12–18.

l 7.37 So Acts 22. 24, 29 (Gk.).

m 7.37 See Ps. 86. 10.

i 7.38 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

c 7.38 See ver. 18.

n 7.39 ver. 3.

o 7.41 Comp. Gk. of Col. 1. 15.

p 7.42 See ch. 6. 7.

q 7.42 Comp. ch. 8. 28 marg.

* 8.1 About B.C. 166.

a 8.1 To ver. 7, comp. 1 Macc. 3. 1–9.

b 8.1 ch. 5. 27.

c 8.2 So ver. 17. 1 Macc. 3. 45. See ch. 6. 2, 5.

c 8.3 So ver. 17. 1 Macc. 3. 45. See ch. 6. 2, 5.

d 8.3 ch. 5. 24–26.

e 8.3 Gen. 4. 10.

f 8.4 So ch. 6. 10.

g 8.5 See ch. 7. 18. Comp. ver. 29.

gg 8.6 ver. 31. ch. 14. 22 in the Gk. So ch. 10. 15.

h 8.7 See Jer. 10. 22 (Engl.).

hh 8.8 See ch. 5. 22.

i 8.8 Acts 24. 26 (Gk.).

j 8.8 ch. 10. 12 (not as ch. 4. 45?).

k 8.8 Comp. ch. 4. 4. & 10. 11.

l 8.8 See 1 Esdr. 2. 27.

m 8.9 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

m 8.9 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

n 8.10 1 Macc. 3. 41. ver. 25, 34.

o 8.10 So ver. 36.

p 8.10 ver. 36. See 1 Macc. 8. 1.

n 8.11 1 Macc. 3. 41. ver. 25, 34.

q 8.11 See Rev. 18. 13.

q 8.11 See Rev. 18. 13.

r 8.11 ch. 9. 27 marg. See Mark 16. 17.

s 8.11 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

t 8.12 Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 42.

u 8.13 1 Macc. 3. 56.

w 8.14 ver. 10, 11.

x 8.15 See Ezek. 20. 9.

y 8.15 2 Chr. 7. 14.

z 8.16 So 1 Macc. 4. 8. ch. 15. 8, 9.

a 8.17 So ver. 3, 4.

b 8.17 See ch. 1. 29.

a 8.17 So ver. 3, 4.

c 8.17 So ver. 28 marg.

d 8.18 Comp. 1 Sam. 17. 45. Ps. 20. 7.

e 8.18 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

f 8.19 ch. 11. 26. & 15. 7 in the Gk. Ecclus. 11. 12. 1 Cor. 12. 28.

g 8.19 See Tobit 1. 18.

h 8.20 1 Macc. 3. 26. & 12. 41. See Judith 5. 23.

i 8.20 See Acts 16. 6. Comp. 1 Macc. 8. 2.

ii 8.20 See ch. 15. 5.

j 8.22 Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 55.

k 8.22 ch. 10. 19, 20. & 14. 17. Comp. 1 Macc. 2. 2.

k 8.22 ch. 10. 19, 20. & 14. 17. Comp. 1 Macc. 2. 2.

l 8.22 Comp. ver. 16.

m 8.23 1 Macc. 2. 5.

mm 8.23 So ch. 13. 15.

n 8.23 ch. 12. 20, 22. See John 18. 3.

o 8.23 Comp. 1 Macc. 4. 13–16.

e 8.24 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

p 8.24 So Luke 14. 13, 21.

q 8.25 ver. 10, 11, 34.

r 8.25 ch. 9. 1 (Gk.). See Wisd. 2. 1.

* 8.27 That is, the enemies’ armour. So ver. 31.

s 8.27 Comp. 1 Macc. 4. 23, 24.

s 8.27 Comp. 1 Macc. 4. 23, 24.

t 8.27 Comp. Deut. 32. 2.

* 8.28 Or, lamed with tortures. Gk. as ver. 30. Comp. ch. 7. 42. So ver. 18.

u 8.28 See ch. 3. 10.

v 8.29 See ch. 13. 12.

w 8.29 See ver. 5.

x 8.30 ver. 32. ch. 9. 3. & 10. 24, 32, 37. Not ch. 12. 2, 10, 18–21, 24.

y 8.30 See 1 Macc. 7. 8.

* 8.30 Or, lamed. Gk. as ver. 28.

u 8.30 See ch. 3. 10.

z 8.31 ver. 27.

gg 8.31 ver. 31. ch. 14. 22 in the Gk. So ch. 10. 15.

x 8.32 ver. 32. ch. 9. 3. & 10. 24, 32, 37. Not ch. 12. 2, 10, 18–21, 24.

a 8.33 ch. 1. 8 (Gk.).

b 8.34 ch. 15. 3 (Gk. & Engl.). So ch. 12. 23 (Gk.). Also ch. 4. 19 (Engl.).

c 8.34 ver. 25.

d 8.35 See ch. 13. 13.

e 8.35 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

f 8.36 So ver. 10.

* 9.1 About B.C. 164.

a 9.1 ch. 8. 25 (Gk.).

* 9.1 Or, disorderly.

b 9.1 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 1, 3–5.

c 9.2 Comp. ch. 1. 13–16.

cc 9.2 ch. 13. 26 (Gk.).

d 9.3 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 5.

e 9.3 See Tobit 3. 7.

f 9.3 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

g 9.3 See Song 26. & ch. 8. 30.

h 9.4 2 Chr. 18. 33 (Engl.).

i 9.4 See 1 Thess. 1. 3.

j 9.4 See 1 Macc. 3. 60.

k 9.4 ver. 14. Comp. Jer. 26. 23.

l 9.5 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

m 9.5 So 1 Macc. 6. 8.

mm 9.6 ch. 13. 7.

n 9.7 Comp. Acts 9. 1.

o 9.8 Comp. ch. 5. 21.

p 9.8 Comp. Isai. 40. 12.

q 9.8 ch. 3. 27 (Gk.).

r 9.9 So Acts 12. 23.

s 9.10 So Isai. 14. 13. Obad. 4. Comp. Dan. 8. 10.

t 9.11 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 9–13.

u 9.11 See Mark 5. 29.

w 9.11 Luke 4. 5.

x 9.12 See Ecclus. 10. 10. Comp. ch. 7. 37.

y 9.13 See ch. 5. 17.

z 9.13 See Prov. 1. 28.

a 9.14 See ch. 1. 12.

b 9.14 ver. 4.

* 9.15 Or, Antioch. ch. 4. 9. Comp. ch. 6. 1.

c 9.16 ch. 5. 16.

d 9.16 See ch. 2. 13.

e 9.16 So Ezra 6. 9. 1 Macc. 10. 39, 40.

z 9.18 See Prov. 1. 28.

f 9.18 Comp. ver. 22.

g 9.18 ch. 11. 16, 22. See Acts 23. 25.

h 9.19 So 1 Macc. 14. 20. See Acts 15. 23.

i 9.21 ver. 1.

f 9.22 Comp. ver. 22.

j 9.23 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

k 9.23 ver. 25. ch. 10. 11. 1 Esdr. 1. 34, 37, 43, 46. & 2. 3 in the Gk. See Luke 10. 1.

* 9.24 Or, common affairs. So ch. 11. 1, 19. & 13. 2. & 14. 10, 26.

k 9.25 ver. 25. ch. 10. 11. 1 Esdr. 1. 34, 37, 43, 46. & 2. 3 in the Gk. See Luke 10. 1.

l 9.25 Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 33.

j 9.25 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

m 9.26 ver. 14–16.

* 9.27 Or, following. See ch. 8. 11.

n 9.27 Acts 27. 3 (Gk.).

o 9.28 1 Macc. 6. 16.

p 9.29 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 14, 55–63.

q 9.29 Acts 13. 1. So 1 Macc. 1. 6.

r 9.29 See ch. 4. 21.

* 10.1 B.C. 165.

a 10.1 1 Macc. 4. 37, 38. ch. 2. 22. Comp. ch. 11. 25.

b 10.2 1 Macc. 1. 47 (Gk.). ch. 11. 3. See Amos 7. 13 (Engl.).

c 10.3 1 Macc. 4. 47–9.

d 10.3 Comp. ch. 1. 19.

e 10.3 But comp. 1 Macc. 1. 54 with 1 Macc. 4. 52.

f 10.3 1 Macc. 4. 50, 51.

ff 10.4 So ch. 13. 12.

g 10.4 Comp. 2 Sam. 24. 14.

h 10.5 1 Macc. 4. 52, 54.

i 10.5 See 1 Macc. 1. 54. Comp. John 10. 22.

j 10.6 1 Macc. 4. 56. Comp. ch. 1. 9.

k 10.6 See Lev. 23. 27.

l 10.7 Judith 15. 12. Comp. ch. 14. 4.

m 10.7 Lev. 23. 40.

m 10.7 Lev. 23. 40.

n 10.7 Gk. as 1 Macc. 13. 51. So ver. 38. ch. 12. 37.

* 10.8 About B.C. 164, beginning.

o 10.8 1 Macc. 4. 59.

p 10.9 See 1 Macc. 1. 10.

q 10.10 1 Macc. 6. 17. ch. 2. 20. ver. 13. ch. 13. 1. & 14. 2. Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 33.

r 10.10 So ch. 2. 23.

s 10.11 See ch. 9. 23.

t 10.11 See 1 Macc. 6. 17. Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 32. ch. 11. 1.

u 10.11 Comp. ch. 4. 4. & 8. 8.

v 10.11 See 1 Esdr. 2. 17.

w 10.12 ch. 8. 8.

q 10.13 1 Macc. 6. 17. ch. 2. 20. ver. 13. ch. 13. 1. & 14. 2. Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 33.

x 10.13 Gk. as ver. 14.

y 10.13 See ch. 4. 29.

z 10.13 See ch. 4. 21. Comp. 1 Macc. 1. 16–19.

p 10.13 See 1 Macc. 1. 10.

* 10.13 Or, and not bearing his authority a as it becometh a nobleman.

b 10.14 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

* 10.14 Or, strong places. Gk. as ver. 17. ch. 12. 18. & 13. 18. & 15. 1. Not as ver. 15, 16, 23.

c 10.14 ch. 14. 6.

x 10.14 Gk. as ver. 14.

cc 10.15 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 3–5. ver. 16. See Mark 3. 8.

d 10.15 ch. 8. 6, 31 (Gk.).

dd 10.15 Comp. ver. 1.

c 10.15 ch. 14. 6.

e 10.16 ver. 25 marg.

cc 10.16 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 3–5. ver. 16. See Mark 3. 8.

f 10.19 See ch. 8. 22.

f 10.19 See ch. 8. 22.

* 10.20 Or, Simon. So ver. 25. See Song 26.

g 10.20 See ch. 4. 45.

h 10.20 See ch. 4. 19.

i 10.22 ver. 18.

k 10.23 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 5?

l 10.24 See ch. 8. 30.

l 10.24 See ch. 8. 30.

m 10.24 1 Macc. 5. 6, 7?

n 10.24 See 1 Macc. 8. 6.

* 10.25 Or, Maccabeus, and they that were with him. ver. 16, 33, 35. ch. 11. 6. So ver. 20. See Song 26.

o 10.25 1 Macc. 11. 71. So ch. 14. 15. See 1 Macc. 3. 47.

p 10.25 ch. 3. 19. See 1 Kin. 20. 31.

q 10.26 Cited from Exod. 23. 22. So Deut. 28. 7.

q 10.26 Cited from Exod. 23. 22. So Deut. 28. 7.

r 10.26 See ch. 1. 18.

m 10.27 1 Macc. 5. 6, 7?

* 10.28 Or, warrant, or, surety. So Heb. 7. 22.

s 10.29 See ch. 2. 21.

ss 10.29 So ch. 11. 8.

t 10.30 See Acts 2. 6.

l 10.32 See ch. 8. 30.

u 10.32 See 1 Macc. 4. 15. Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 8?

v 10.32 ver. 37.

w 10.33 See ver. 25 marg.

x 10.34 See Acts 10. 28.

w 10.35 See ver. 25 marg.

y 10.36 Comp. 1 Macc. 3. 5. & 5. 5.

l 10.37 See ch. 8. 30.

z 10.37 Comp. ch. 12. 2, &c.

a 10.37 So 2 Sam. 17. 9.

v 10.37 ver. 37.

b 10.38 Gk. as 1 Macc. 13. 51. So ver. 7. ch. 12. 37.

c 10.38 So 1 Cor. 15. 57.

a 11.1 See ch. 10. 11.

* 11.1 Gk. tutor. ch. 13. 2. & 14. 2. Gal. 4. 2.

b 11.1 ver. 35.

c 11.1 ch. 13. 2 (Gk.). So 1 Macc. 3. 32.

d 11.2 Comp. 1 Macc. 4. 28.

e 11.2 So 1 Macc. 1. 38.

* 11.2 Or, Grecians. See ch. 4. 13.

f 11.3 See ch. 10. 2.

g 11.3 Comp. ch. 4. 8, 23, 24.

h 11.4 See 1 Macc. 1. 17.

i 11.5 See 1 Macc. 4. 29.

* 11.6 [Or,] Maccabeus and his company. See ch. 10. 25.

j 11.6 Tobit 5. 21. ch. 15. 23. Comp. Ex. 23. 20.

k 11.7 Acts 18. 27.

l 11.8 See ch. 2. 21.

m 11.8 So ch. 10. 29.

n 11.8 Acts 1. 10. So Matt. 28. 3. Mark 16. 5. John 20. 12.

nn 11.9 So ch. 8. 29. & 13. 12.

o 11.12 So Acts 19. 16.

p 11.13 Luke 24. 17 (Gk.).

q 11.14 See ch. 6. 24.

r 11.14 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 55–60.

s 11.16 ver. 22 (Gk.). See ch. 9. 18.

t 11.17 So 1 Macc. 11. 70. & 13. 11?

u 11.18 So ver. 36 (Gk.).

v 11.18 See ch. 1. 18.

w 11.18 Luke 13. 33 (Gk.). So ch. 13. 26 (Gk.).

x 11.21 ver. 28, 33. See Acts 15. 29.

* 11.21 About B.C. 163. So ver. 33, 38. But comp. 1 Macc. 6. 16.

* 11.21 Or, Dioscoros.

s 11.22 ver. 22 (Gk.). See ch. 9. 18.

y 11.22 See 1 Macc. 10. 18.

z 11.24 See ch. 4. 16.

a 11.25 Comp. ch. 10. 1.

b 11.25 See ch. 6. 1. Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 59.

* 11.26 Or, give them assurance. Gk. as 1 Macc. 11. 62. ch. 12. 11. See 1 Macc. 6. 58 marg.

c 11.26 See ch. 8. 19.

d 11.27 See ch. 1. 10.

x 11.28 ver. 28, 33. See Acts 15. 29.

e 11.29 ver. 32. ch. 4. 50. See ch. 4. 23.

f 11.29 Comp. ch. 12. 1.

f 11.30 Comp. ch. 12. 1.

e 11.32 ver. 32. ch. 4. 50. See ch. 4. 23.

x 11.33 ver. 28, 33. See Acts 15. 29.

g 11.33 See ver. 21.

* 11.33 Or, April. ver. 38.

h 11.34 See 1 Macc. 8. 1.

* 11.34 Or, consuls.

i 11.35 See ver. 1.

j 11.36 So ver. 18 (Gk.).

k 11.36 See ch. 4. 19.

l 11.36 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

g 11.38 See ver. 21.

a 12.1 See 1 Macc. 6. 17.

b 12.1 Comp. ch. 11. 29, 30.

* 12.2 About B.C. 164.

c 12.2 ver. 10, 18–21, 24. 1 Macc. 5. 6, 11, 37. Comp. ch. 10. 37.

d 12.2 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

e 12.2 See ch. 4. 29

f 12.2 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 9, 15.

ff 12.2 ch. 14. 25.

g 12.3 See Josh. 19. 46. & 1 Macc. 11. 6.

h 12.6 So ver. 41. See 2 Esdr. 14. 32.

* 12.7 Or, with a purpose to return.

g 12.7 See Josh. 19. 46. & 1 Macc. 11. 6.

i 12.8 ver. 9, 40. See 1 Macc. 4. 15.

i 12.9 ver. 9, 40. See 1 Macc. 4. 15.

j 12.9 1 Macc. 1. 17. ch. 14. 1.

c 12.10 ver. 10, 18–21, 24. 1 Macc. 5. 6, 11, 37. Comp. ch. 10. 37.

k 12.10 See 1 Macc. 5. 39.

l 12.11 ver. 14, 15 (Gk.). See Song 26.

ll 12.11 See ch. 13. 13.

m 12.11 See ch. 11. 26.

* 12.12 Or, went from place to place, with their families and cattle.

n 12.13 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 26, 36?

l 12.14 ver. 14, 15 (Gk.). See Song 26.

l 12.15 ver. 14, 15 (Gk.). See Song 26.

o 12.15 ver. 28 (Gk.). See ch. 3. 24.

p 12.15 Josh. 6. 20. Heb. 11. 30.

q 12.15 See 1 Macc. 9. 50.

r 12.17 2 Kin. 3. 25?

s 12.17 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 13.

t 12.17 See Judges 11. 3?

c 12.18 ver. 10, 18–21, 24. 1 Macc. 5. 6, 11, 37. Comp. ch. 10. 37.

u 12.18 ch. 10. 14 marg.

v 12.18 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 29.

u 12.18 ch. 10. 14 marg.

w 12.19 ver. 24 (not ver. 35?).

* 12.20 [That is,] Dositheus and Sosipater.

x 12.20 ver. 22. ch. 8. 23. See John 18. 3.

y 12.20 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 37.

* 12.21 [1 Macc. 5. 43, 44. Carnaim]. ver. 26.

x 12.22 ver. 22. ch. 8. 23. See John 18. 3.

z 12.22 See ch. 2. 21. Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 43.

a 12.22 See John 1. 11.

b 12.23 ch. 13. 4. & 14. 42 (Gk.). So ch. 8. 34. & 15. 3 in the Gk.

c 12.24 ver. 19. See Song 26.

d 12.26 See 1 Macc. 5. 36.

e 12.26 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 43, 44.

* 12.26 That is, Venus.

f 12.26 See Rev. 18. 13.

g 12.27 1 Macc. 5. 46.

h 12.27 ver. 1.

i 12.28 ver. 15 (Gk.).

k 12.28 1 Macc. 5. 50, 51.

l 12.29 Judith 3. 10. So 1 Macc. 5. 52. See Josh. 17. 11.

l 12.30 Judith 3. 10. So 1 Macc. 5. 52. See Josh. 17. 11.

m 12.31 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 54.

n 12.31 Deut. 16. 10.

o 12.32 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

* 12.32 [Or, Jamnia, 1 Macc. 5. 58].

p 12.32 See Mark 3. 8.

q 12.33 Comp. 1 Macc. 5. 63.

r 12.34 ver. 39, 40.

o 12.35 See 1 Macc. 3. 38.

* 12.35 [Or], put by his arm: [or,]wounded him in the shoulder: or, stroke him in the shoulder.

s 12.35 See 2 Chr. 11. 8.

c 12.36 ver. 19. See Song 26.

* 12.36 [Or, Esdrin].

t 12.37 ch. 7. 8, 21, 27. & 15. 29.

tt 12.37 ch. 10. 7, 38.

c 12.37 ver. 19. See Song 26.

u 12.38 Gen. 38. 1 (Gk.). See 1 Sam. 22. 1?

v 12.39 Luke 13. 33. Acts 20. 15 (Gk.). So Acts 21. 26 (Gk.).

* 12.39 Or, at such time, &c. Comp. ver. 38.

vv 12.39 See 1 Macc. 13. 37.

c 12.39 ver. 19. See Song 26.

r 12.39 ver. 39, 40.

r 12.40 ver. 39, 40.

w 12.40 Comp. ver. 9, 32 [marg.], 37.

x 12.40 Deut. 7. 25, 26. Comp. Josh. 7. 4–26.

y 12.41 See ver. 6.

z 12.43 See ch. 4. 19.

a 12.43 Lev. 4. 2, &c.

b 12.43 So ch. 7. 9, 11. See Dan. 12. 2.

b 12.44 So ch. 7. 9, 11. See Dan. 12. 2.

c 12.44 So Luke 24 11 (Gk.).

b 12.45 So ch. 7. 9, 11. See Dan. 12. 2.

d 12.45 Dan. 12. 2. So Ecclus. 46. 19. & 48. 13. See John 11. 11.

* 13.1 About B.C. 163. Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 20.

a 13.1 ver. 22. See Song 26.

b 13.1 1 Macc. 6. 28. See ch. 10. 10.

c 13.2 See ch. 11. 1.

d 13.2 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 30.

e 13.2 ver. 15. See 1 Macc. 1. 17.

f 13.3 See ch. 4. 23. Comp. ch. 11. 29, 32.

g 13.4 Rev. 17. 14. & 19. 16. So 1 Tim. 6. 15.

h 13.4 See ch. 12. 23.

i 13.6 Comp. ch. 4. 39.

j 13.7 ch. 9. 6.

* 13.11 Or, had had a little respite.

k 13.11 Ex. 23. 12. 2 Tim. 1. 16.

l 13.12 ch. 8. 29. So ch. 11. 9.

m 13.12 So ch. 10. 4.

n 13.12 See 1 Thess. 1. 3.

o 13.13 ch. 8. 35. & 15. 35. So ch. 12. 11. Comp. ver. 17.

* 13.14 Or, Lord.

p 13.14 See ch. 7. 23.

q 13.14 See 1 Macc. 2. 1.

r 13.15 So ch. 8. 23.

e 13.15 ver. 15. See 1 Macc. 1. 17.

o 13.17 ch. 8. 35. & 15. 35. So ch. 12. 11. Comp. ver. 17.

s 13.18 See ch. 10. 14.

t 13.19 ver. 22. See 1 Macc. 4. 29.

u 13.19 1 Macc. 6. 31.

v 13.22 1 Macc. 6. 49. See 1 Macc. 6. 58 marg. So ch. 14. 19.

t 13.22 ver. 22. See 1 Macc. 4. 29.

v 13.22 1 Macc. 6. 49. See 1 Macc. 6. 58 marg. So ch. 14. 19.

a 13.22 ver. 22. See Song 26.

w 13.23 1 Macc. 6. 55.

x 13.23 ver. 26. See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

* 13.23 Or, rebelled. Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 56.

y 13.23 See Acts 2. 6.

z 13.23 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 60, 61.

z 13.23 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 60, 61.

a 13.24 ch. 3. 9, 35 (Gk.). See Luke 8. 40.

b 13.24 See 1 Macc. 5. 15.

c 13.24 1 Sam. 27. 8?

b 13.25 See 1 Macc. 5. 15.

d 13.25 ch. 14. 28 (Gk.). See 1 Macc. 6. 62.

e 13.26 ver. 2.

f 13.26 See Matt. 27. 19.

g 13.26 See ch. 11. 18.

h 13.26 Comp. 1 Macc. 6. 63.

x 13.26 ver. 26. See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

i 13.26 ch. 9. 2 (Gk.).

a 14.1 Comp. ch. 13. 1.

b 14.1 See Song 26.

c 14.1 ver. 26. 1 Macc 7. 1.

d 14.1 See ch. 3. 3.

c 14.1 ver. 26. 1 Macc 7. 1.

e 14.1 1 Macc. 1. 17. ch. 12. 9.

f 14.2 1 Macc. 7. 2–4.

g 14.2 See ch. 10. 10.

h 14.2 See 1 Macc. 6. 17.

i 14.2 See ch. 11. 1 marg.

j 14.3 ver. 13, 26. 1 Macc. 7. 5.

k 14.3 Comp. ch. 13. 3–8 with ch. 4. 24.

kk 14.3 Comp. ver. 38.

k 14.4 Comp. ch. 13. 3–8 with ch. 4. 24.

l 14.4 So 1 Macc. 7. 25.

* 14.4 B.C. 162. 1 Macc. 7. 1.

m 14.4 1 Macc. 13. 37. Comp. 1 Macc. 10. 20. ch. 10. 7.

m 14.4 1 Macc. 13. 37. Comp. 1 Macc. 10. 20. ch. 10. 7.

* 14.4 Or, thought to be of the temple.

n 14.4 Acts 16. 13.

o 14.6 See 1 Macc. 2. 42.

p 14.6 ch. 10. 14, 15.

q 14.7 So 1 Macc. 7. 14.

r 14.11 Comp. rather 1 Macc. 7. 5.

s 14.12 See 1 Macc. 1. 17.

t 14.12 ver. 26. See Luke 10. 1.

u 14.12 1 Macc. 7. 26.

j 14.13 ver. 13, 26. 1 Macc. 7. 5.

uu 14.13 ver. 31 (Gk.).

* 14.15 Or, were joined to them.

v 14.15 See ch 10. 25.

w 14.15 ch. 1. 26.

x 14.15 See ch. 2. 21.

y 14.17 See ch. 8. 22.

b 14.18 See Song 26.

z 14.19 So ch. 13. 22. See 1 Macc. 6. 58 marg.

a 14.21 To ver. 36, comp. 1 Macc. 7. 27–38.

aa 14.22 See ch. 8. 6.

b 14.23 See Luke 23. 41.

c 14.24 ch. 4. 37 (Gk.).

cc 14.25 ch. 12. 2.

* 14.25 Or, d lived together with him.

e 14.26 See ver. 3.

f 14.26 ver. 20.

g 14.26 See ver. 1.

h 14.26 See ver. 12.

i 14.26 See ch. 4. 2.

k 14.27 ch. 7. 3, 39.

f 14.27 ver. 20.

l 14.27 See 1 Macc. 3. 37.

m 14.28 See Acts 2. 6.

n 14.28 So ch. 13. 25 (Gk.). See 1 Macc. 6. 62.

* 14.30 About B.C. 161.

o 14.30 Luke 19. 21, 22 (Gk.).

o 14.30 Luke 19. 21, 22 (Gk.).

p 14.31 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 33, 36.

q 14.31 ver. 13 (Gk.).

r 14.33 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 47. ch. 15. 32.

* 14.33 Gr. bound. ver. 27. Matt. 27. 15, 16, &c.

s 14.33 ch. 6. 7.

t 14.35 So Acts 17. 25.

u 14.36 ch. 10. 3.

v 14.36 See Ps. 63. 11.

w 14.38 Comp. ver. 3.

x 14.38 So Acts 15. 26.

y 14.38 Judg. 5. 18 (Engl.).

z 14.38 See Acts 12. 5 marg.

a 14.42 See ch. 12. 23.

b 14.46 So ch. 7. 23.

c 14.46 So ch. 7. 11. See Dan. 12. 2.

a 15.1 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 39.

b 15.1 Song 26.

c 15.1 See ch. 10. 14.

d 15.1 See 1 Macc. 3. 10.

e 15.1 Comp. 1 Macc. 2. 41.

f 15.3 See ch. 8. 34.

g 15.3 Ecclus. 46. 6. ver. 29 (Gk.). See 1 Tim. 6. 15.

h 15.4 ch. 7. 33. So Esther 16. 16.

g 15.4 Ecclus. 46. 6. ver. 29 (Gk.). See 1 Tim. 6. 15.

i 15.5 ver. 28 (Gk.). ch. 8. 20. See 1 Macc. 13. 37.

a 15.6 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 39.

k 15.7 See 1 Thess. 1. 3.

l 15.7 See ch. 8. 19.

m 15.8 See ch. 8. 16.

n 15.8 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

o 15.9 Ecclus. Prol. 2, l. 3. Luke 24. 44. Acts 13. 15. Rom. 3. 21. See Acts 26. 22.

p 15.12 See ch. 2. 21.

q 15.12 See ch. 3. 1.

r 15.13 See Ecclus. Prol. 2. l. 32.

q 15.14 See ch. 3. 1.

s 15.14 See Judg. 18. 14.

t 15.14 See ch. 1. 12.

u 15.14 Comp. ch. 2. 5, 7.

w 15.20 Luke 3. 15 marg.

x 15.20 1 Macc. 11. 56 marg. See 1 Macc. 1. 17.

x 15.21 1 Macc. 11. 56 marg. See 1 Macc. 1. 17.

p 15.21 See ch. 2. 21.

y 15.22 To ver. 37, 1 Macc. 7. 40–50.

z 15.22 See Baruch 6. 6.

a 15.22 See Tobit 1. 18.

b 15.23 See ch. 3. 24.

c 15.23 See ch. 11. 6.

d 15.24 See Deut. 7. 6.

e 15.25 See Song 26.

e 15.26 See Song 26.

f 15.27 Comp. Ps. 149. 6.

g 15.27 See ch. 2. 21.

h 15.28 ver. 5 (Gk.).

i 15.28 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 43.

k 15.28 See 1 Kin. 20. 11.

l 15.29 ver. 3, 4 (Gk.).

m 15.29 See ch. 12. 37.

n 15.30 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 47.

n 15.30 Comp. 1 Macc. 7. 47.

o 15.31 ver. 35. See 1 Macc. 1. 33. So ch. 4. 12, 27. & 5. 5.

p 15.32 ch. 14. 33. So 1 Macc. 7. 47.

q 15.32 2 Cor. 6. 18.

r 15.33 So 1 Sam. 17. 44, 46.

s 15.34 See 1 Macc. 3. 60.

t 15.35 Judith 14. 1.

o 15.35 ver. 35. See 1 Macc. 1. 33. So ch. 4. 12, 27. & 5. 5.

u 15.35 See ch. 13. 13.

v 15.36 1 Macc. 7. 49.

w 15.36 See Ezra 6. 15.

x 15.36 So John 12. 1 (Gk.).

y 15.36 Esth. 9. 17, 21.

z 15.39 Comp. ch. 2. 29.

2 Peter

1
2
3

THE SECOND EPISTLE GENERAL OF PETER

1

1  Simon Peter, a servant and an apostle of Jesus Christ, to them that have obtained like precious faith with us through the righteousness of God and our Saviour Jesus Christ: 2  Grace and peace be multiplied unto you through the knowledge of God, and of Jesus our Lord, 3  According as his divine power hath given unto us all things that pertain unto life and godliness, through the knowledge of him that hath called us [∥]to glory and virtue: 4  Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious promises: that by these ye might be partakers of the divine nature, having escaped the corruption that is in the world through lust. 5  And beside this, giving all diligence, add to your faith virtue; and to virtue knowledge; 6  And to knowledge temperance; and to temperance patience; and to patience godliness; 7  And to godliness brotherly kindness; and to brotherly kindness charity. 8  For if these things be in you, and abound, they make you that ye shall neither be barren nor unfruitful in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ. 9  But he that lacketh these things is blind, and cannot see afar off, and hath forgotten that he was purged from his old sins. 10  Wherefore the rather, brethren, give diligence to make your calling and election sure: for if ye do these things, ye shall never fall: 11  For so an entrance shall be ministered unto you abundantly into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.

12  Wherefore I will not be negligent to put you always in remembrance of these things, though ye know them, and be established in the present truth. 13  Yea, I think it meet, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to stir you up by putting you in remembrance; 14  Knowing that shortly I must put off this my tabernacle, even as [*]our Lord Jesus Christ hath shewed me. 15  Moreover I will endeavour that ye may be able after my decease to have these things always in remembrance. 16  For we have not followed cunningly devised fables, when we made known unto you the power and coming of our Lord Jesus Christ, but were eyewitnesses of his majesty. 17  For he received from God the Father honour and glory, when there came such a voice to him from the excellent glory, This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased. 18  And this voice which came from heaven we heard, when we were with him in the holy mount. 19  We have also a more sure word of prophecy; whereunto ye do well that ye take heed, as unto a light that shineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the day star arise in your hearts: 20  Knowing this first, that no prophecy of the scripture is of any private interpretation. 21  For the prophecy came not [∥]in old time by the will of man: but holy men of God spake as they were moved by the Holy Ghost.

2

1  But there were false prophets also among the people, even as there shall be false teachers among you, who privily shall bring in damnable heresies, even denying the Lord that bought them, and bring upon themselves swift destruction. 2  And many shall follow their [∥]pernicious ways; by reason of whom the way of truth shall be evil spoken of. 3  And through covetousness shall they with feigned words make merchandise of you: whose judgment now of a long time lingereth not, and their damnation slumbereth not. 4  For if God spared not the angels that sinned, but cast them down to hell, and delivered them into chains of darkness, to be reserved unto judgment; 5  And spared not the old world, but saved Noah the eighth person, a preacher of righteousness, bringing in the flood upon the world of the ungodly; 6  And turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrha into ashes condemned them with an overthrow, making them an ensample unto those that after should live ungodly; 7  And delivered just Lot, vexed with the filthy conversation of the wicked: 8 (For that righteous man dwelling among them, in seeing and hearing, vexed his righteous soul from day to day with their unlawful deeds;) 9  The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of temptations, and to reserve the unjust unto the day of judgment to be punished: 10  But chiefly them that walk after the flesh in the lust of uncleanness, and despise [∥]government. [*]Presumptuous are they, selfwilled, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities. 11  Whereas angels, which are greater in power and might, bring not railing accusation [∥]against them before the Lord. 12  But these, as natural brute beasts, made to be taken and destroyed, speak evil of the things that they understand not; and shall utterly perish in their own corruption; 13  And shall receive the reward of unrighteousness, as they that count it pleasure to riot in the day time. Spots they are and blemishes, sporting themselves with their own deceivings while they feast with you; 14  Having eyes full of [†]adultery, and that cannot cease from sin; beguiling unstable souls: an heart they have exercised with covetous practices; cursed children: 15  Which have forsaken the right way, and are gone astray, following the way of Balaam the son of Bosor, who loved the wages of unrighteousness; 16  But was rebuked for his iniquity: the dumb ass speaking with man’s voice forbad the madness of the prophet. 17  These are wells without water, clouds that are carried with a tempest; to whom the mist of darkness is reserved for ever. 18  For when they speak great swelling words of vanity, they allure through the lusts of the flesh, through much wantonness, those that were [∥]clean escaped from them who live in error. 19  While they promise them liberty, they themselves are the servants of corruption: for of whom a man is overcome, of the same is he brought in bondage. 20  For if after they have escaped the pollutions of the world through the knowledge of the Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, they are again entangled therein, and overcome, the latter end is worse with them than the beginning. 21  For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteousness, than, after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them. 22  But it is happened unto them according to the true proverb, The dog is turned to his own vomit again; and the sow that was washed to her wallowing in the mire.

3

1  This second epistle, beloved, I now write unto you; in both which I stir up your pure minds by way of remembrance: 2  That ye may be mindful of the words which were spoken before by the holy prophets, and of the commandment of us the apostles of the Lord and Saviour: 3  Knowing this first, that there shall come in the last days scoffers, walking after their own lusts, 4  And saying, Where is the promise of his coming? for since the fathers fell asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the creation. 5  For this they willingly are ignorant of, that by the word of God the heavens were of old, and the earth [†]standing out of the water and in the water: 6  Whereby the world that then was, being overflowed with water, perished: 7  But the heavens and the earth, which are now, by the same word are kept in store, reserved unto fire against the day of judgment and perdition of ungodly men. 8  But, beloved, be not ignorant of this one thing, that one day is with the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day. 9  The Lord is not slack concerning his promise, as some men count slackness; but is longsuffering to us-ward, not willing that any should perish, but that all should come to repentance. 10  But the day of the Lord will come as a thief in the night; in the which the heavens shall pass away with a great noise, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat, the earth also and the works that are therein shall be burned up. 11  Seeing then that all these things shall be dissolved, what manner of persons ought ye to be in all holy conversation and godliness, 12  Looking for and [∥]hasting unto the coming of the day of God, wherein the heavens being on fire shall be dissolved, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat? 13  Nevertheless we, according to his promise, look for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth righteousness. 14  Wherefore, beloved, seeing that ye look for such things, be diligent that ye may be found of him in peace, without spot, and blameless. 15  And account that the longsuffering of [‡]our Lord is salvation; even as our beloved brother Paul also according to the wisdom given unto him hath written unto you; 16  As also in all his epistles, speaking in them of these things; in which are some things hard to be understood, which they that are unlearned and unstable wrest, as they do also the other scriptures, unto their own destruction. 17  Ye therefore, beloved, seeing ye know these things before, beware lest ye also, being led away with the error of the wicked, fall from your own stedfastness. 18  But grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ. To him be glory both now and for ever. Amen.

∥ 1.3 Or, by.

* 1.14 John 21. 18.

∥ 1.21 Or, at any time.

∥ 2.2 Or, lascivious ways, as some copies read.

∥ 2.10 Or, dominion.

* 2.10 Jude 8.

∥ 2.11 Some read, against themselves.

† 2.14 Gr. an adulteress.

∥ 2.18 Or, for a little, or, a while, as some read.

† 3.5 Gr. consisting.

∥ 3.12 Or, hasting the coming.

‡ 3.15 [1611 the Lord]

2 Timothy

1
2
3
4

THE SECOND EPISTLE OF PAUL THE APOSTLE TO TIMOTHY

1

1  Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ by the will of God, according to the promise of life which is in Christ Jesus, 2 To Timothy, my dearly beloved son: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Lord. 3  I thank God, whom I serve from my forefathers with pure conscience, that without ceasing I have remembrance of thee in my prayers night and day; 4  Greatly desiring to see thee, being mindful of thy tears, that I may be filled with joy; 5  When I call to remembrance the unfeigned faith that is in thee, which dwelt first in thy grandmother Lois, and thy mother Eunice; and I am persuaded that in thee also. 6  Wherefore I put thee in remembrance that thou stir up the gift of God, which is in thee by the putting on of my hands. 7  For God hath not given us the spirit of fear; but of power, [‡]and of love, and of a sound mind. 8 Be not thou therefore ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of me his prisoner: but be thou partaker of the afflictions of the gospel according to the power of God; 9  Who hath saved us, and called us with an holy calling, not according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace, which was given us in Christ Jesus before the world began, 10  But is now made manifest by the appearing of our Saviour Jesus Christ, who hath abolished death, and hath brought life and immortality to light through the gospel: 11  Whereunto I am appointed a preacher, and an apostle, and a teacher of the Gentiles. 12  For the which cause I also suffer these things: nevertheless I am not ashamed: for I know whom I have [∥]believed, and [‡]am persuaded that he is able to keep that which I have committed unto him against that day. 13  Hold fast the form of sound words, which thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus. 14  That good thing which was committed unto thee keep by the Holy Ghost which dwelleth in us. 15  This thou knowest, that all they which are in Asia be turned away from me; of whom are Phygellus and Hermogenes. 16  The Lord give mercy unto the house of Onesiphorus; for he oft refreshed me, and was not ashamed of my chain: 17  But, when he was in Rome, he sought me out very diligently, and found me. 18  The Lord grant unto him that he may find mercy of the Lord in that day: and in how many things he ministered unto me at Ephesus, thou knowest very well.

2

1  Thou therefore, my son, be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus. 2  And the things that thou hast heard of me [∥]among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithful men, who shall be able to teach others also. 3  Thou therefore endure hardness, as a good soldier of Jesus Christ. 4  No man that warreth entangleth himself with the affairs of this life; that he may please him who hath chosen him to be a soldier. 5  And if a man also strive for masteries, yet is he not crowned, except he strive lawfully. 6 [∥] The husbandman that laboureth must be first partaker of the fruits. 7  Consider what I say; and the Lord give thee understanding in all things. 8  Remember that Jesus Christ of the seed of David was raised from the dead according to my gospel: 9  Wherein I suffer trouble, as an evil doer, even unto bonds; but the word of God is not bound. 10  Therefore I endure all things for the elect’s sakes, that they may also obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory. 11  It is a faithful saying: For if we be dead with him, we shall also live with him: 12  If we suffer, we shall also reign with him: if we deny him, he also will deny us: 13  If we believe not, yet he abideth faithful: he cannot deny himself. 14  Of these things put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord that they strive not about words to no profit, but to the subverting of the hearers. 15  Study to shew thyself approved unto God, a workman that needeth not to be ashamed, rightly dividing the word of truth. 16  But shun profane and vain babblings: for they will increase unto more ungodliness. 17  And their word will eat as doth a [∥]canker: of whom is Hymenaeus and Philetus; 18  Who concerning the truth have erred, saying that the resurrection is past already; and overthrow the faith of some. 19  Nevertheless the foundation of God standeth [∥]sure, having [‡]this seal, The Lord knoweth them that are his. And, Let every one that nameth the name of Christ depart from iniquity. 20  But in a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but also of wood and of earth; and some to honour, and some to dishonour. 21  If a man therefore purge himself from these, he shall be a vessel unto honour, sanctified, and meet for the master’s use, and prepared unto every good work. 22  Flee also youthful lusts: but follow righteousness, faith, charity, peace, with them that call on the Lord out of a pure heart. 23  But foolish and unlearned questions avoid, knowing that they do gender strifes. 24  And the servant of the Lord must not strive; but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, [∥]patient, 25  In meekness instructing those that oppose themselves; if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth; 26  And that they may [†]recover themselves out of the snare of the devil, who are [†]taken captive by him at his will.

3

1  This know also, that in the last days perilous times shall come. 2  For men shall be lovers of their own selves, covetous, boasters, proud, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy, 3  Without natural affection, trucebreakers, [∥]false accusers, incontinent, fierce, despisers of those that are good, 4  Traitors, heady, highminded, lovers of pleasures more than lovers of God; 5  Having a form of godliness, but denying the power thereof: from such turn away. 6  For of this sort are they which creep into houses, and lead captive silly women laden with sins, led away with divers lusts, 7  Ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth. 8  Now as Jannes and Jambres withstood Moses, so do these also resist the truth: men of corrupt minds, [∥]reprobate concerning the faith. 9  But they shall proceed no further: for their folly shall be manifest unto all men, as theirs also was. 10  But [∥]thou hast fully known my doctrine, manner of life, purpose, faith, longsuffering, charity, patience, 11  Persecutions, afflictions, which came unto me at Antioch, at Iconium, at Lystra; what persecutions I endured: but out of them all the Lord delivered me. 12  Yea, and all that will live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution. 13  But evil men and seducers shall wax worse and worse, deceiving, and being deceived. 14  But continue thou in the things which thou hast learned and hast been assured of, knowing of whom thou hast learned them; 15  And that from a child thou hast known the holy scriptures, which are able to make thee wise unto salvation through faith which is in Christ Jesus. 16  All scripture is given by inspiration of God, and is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for instruction in righteousness: 17  That the man of God may be perfect, [∥]throughly furnished unto all good works.

4

1  I charge thee therefore before God, and the Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead at his appearing and his kingdom; 2  Preach the word; be instant in season, out of season; reprove, rebuke, exhort with all longsuffering and doctrine. 3  For the time will come when they will not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts shall they heap to themselves teachers, having itching ears; 4  And they shall turn away their ears from the truth, and shall be turned unto fables. 5  But watch thou in all things, endure afflictions, do the work of an evangelist, [∥]make full proof of thy ministry. 6  For I am now ready to be offered, and the time of my departure is at hand. 7  I have fought a good fight, I have finished my course, I have kept the faith: 8  Henceforth there is laid up for me a crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, shall give me at that day: and not to me only, but unto [‡]all them also that love his appearing.

9  Do thy diligence to come shortly unto me: 10  For Demas hath forsaken me, having loved this present world, and is departed unto Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, Titus unto Dalmatia. 11  Only Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with thee: for he is profitable to me for the ministry. 12  And Tychicus have I sent to Ephesus. 13  The cloke that I left at Troas with Carpus, when thou comest, bring with thee, [‡]and the books, but especially the parchments. 14  Alexander the coppersmith did me much evil: the Lord reward him according to his works: 15  Of whom be thou ware also; for he hath greatly withstood [∥]our words. 16  At my first answer no man stood with me, but all men forsook me: I pray God that it may not be laid to their charge. 17  Notwithstanding the Lord stood with me, and strengthened me; that by me the preaching might be fully known, and that all the Gentiles might hear: and I was delivered out of the mouth of the lion. 18  And the Lord shall deliver me from every evil work, and will preserve me unto his heavenly kingdom: to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.

19  Salute Prisca and Aquila, and the household of Onesiphorus. 20  Erastus abode at Corinth: but Trophimus have I left at Miletum sick. 21  Do thy diligence to come before winter. Eubulus greeteth thee, and Pudens, and Linus, and Claudia, and all the brethren. 22  The Lord Jesus Christ be with thy spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.

The second epistle unto Timotheus, ordained the first bishop of the church of the Ephesians, was written from Rome, when Paul was brought before Nero the second time.

‡ 1.7 [1611 omits and]

∥ 1.12 Or, trusted.

‡ 1.12 [1611 I am]

∥ 2.2 Or, by.

∥ 2.6 Or The husbandman, labouring first, must be partaker of the fruits.

∥ 2.17 Or, gangrene.

∥ 2.19 Or, steady.

‡ 2.19 [1611 the seal]

∥ 2.24 Or, forbearing.

† 2.26 Gr. awake.

† 2.26 Gr. taken alive.

∥ 3.3 Or, makebates.

∥ 3.8 Or, of no judgment.

∥ 3.10 Or, thou hast been a diligent follower of.

∥ 3.17 Or, perfected.

∥ 4.5 Or, fulfil.

‡ 4.8 [1611 omits all]

‡ 4.13 [1611 omits and the books]

∥ 4.15 Or, our preachings.

3 John

THE THIRD EPISTLE OF JOHN

1

1  The elder unto the wellbeloved Gaius, whom I love [∥]in the truth.

2  Beloved, I [∥]wish above all things that thou mayest prosper and be in health, even as thy soul prospereth. 3  For I rejoiced greatly, when the brethren came and testified of the truth that is in thee, even as thou walkest in the truth. 4  I have no greater joy than to hear that my children walk in truth. 5  Beloved, thou doest faithfully whatsoever thou doest to the brethren, and to strangers; 6  Which have borne witness of thy charity before the church: whom if thou bring forward on their journey after a godly sort, thou shalt do well: 7  Because that for his name’s sake they went forth, taking nothing of the Gentiles. 8  We therefore ought to receive such, that we might be fellowhelpers to the truth.

9  I wrote unto the church: but Diotrephes, who loveth to have the preeminence among them, receiveth us not. 10  Wherefore, if I come, I will remember his deeds which he doeth, prating against us with malicious words: and not content therewith, neither doth he himself receive the brethren, and forbiddeth them that would, and casteth them out of the church.

11  Beloved, follow not that which is evil, but that which is good. He that doeth good is of God: but he that doeth evil hath not seen God. 12  Demetrius hath good report of all men, and of the truth itself: yea, and we also bear record; and ye know that our record is true.

13  I had many things to write, but I will not with ink and pen write unto thee: 14  But I trust I shall shortly see thee, and we shall speak [†]face to face. Peace be to thee. Our friends salute thee. Greet the friends by name.

∥ 1.1 Or, truly.

∥ 1.2 Or, pray.

† 1.14 Gr. mouth to mouth.

Amos

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9

Amos

1

1  The words of Amos, who was among the herdmen of Tekoa, which he saw concerning Israel in the days of Uzziah king of Judah, and in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash king of Israel, two years before the [*]earthquake. 2  And he said, The LORD will [*]roar from Zion, and utter his voice from Jerusalem; and the habitations of the shepherds shall mourn, and the top of Carmel shall wither.

3  Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Damascus, [∥]and for four, I will not [∥]turn away the punishment thereof; because they have threshed Gilead with threshing instruments of iron: 4  But I will send a fire into the house of Hazael, which shall devour the palaces of Ben-hadad. 5  I will break also the bar of Damascus, and cut off the inhabitant from [∥]the plain of Aven, and him that holdeth the sceptre from [∥]the house of Eden: and the people of Syria shall go into captivity unto Kir, saith the LORD.

6 ¶ Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of [*]Gaza, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they [∥]carried away captive the whole captivity, to deliver them up to Edom: 7  But I will send a fire on the wall of Gaza, which shall devour the palaces thereof: 8  And I will cut off the inhabitant from Ashdod, and him that holdeth the sceptre from Ashkelon, and I will turn mine hand against Ekron: and the remnant of the Philistines shall perish, saith the Lord GOD.

9 ¶ Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Tyrus, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they delivered up the whole captivity to Edom, and remembered not [†]the brotherly covenant: 10  But I will send a fire on the wall of Tyrus, which shall devour the palaces thereof.

11 ¶ Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Edom, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he did pursue his brother with the sword, and [†]did cast off all pity, and his anger did tear perpetually, and [‡]he kept his wrath for ever: 12  But I will send a fire upon Teman, which shall devour the palaces of Bozrah.

13 ¶ Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of the children of Ammon, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have [∥]ripped up the women with child of Gilead, that they might enlarge their border: 14  But I will kindle a fire in the wall of Rabbah, and it shall devour the palaces thereof, with shouting in the day of battle, with a tempest in the day of the whirlwind: 15  And their king shall go into captivity, he and his princes together, saith the LORD.

2

1  Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Moab, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because he [*]burned the bones of the king of Edom into lime: 2  But I will send a fire upon Moab, and it shall devour the palaces of Kerioth: and Moab shall die with tumult, with shouting, and with the sound of the trumpet: 3  And I will cut off the judge from the midst thereof, and will slay all the princes thereof with him, saith the LORD.

4 ¶ Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Judah, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because they have despised the law of the LORD, and have not kept his commandments, and their lies caused them to err, after the which their fathers have walked: 5  But I will send a fire upon Judah, and it shall devour the palaces of Jerusalem.

6 ¶ Thus saith the LORD; For three transgressions of Israel, and for four, I will not turn away the punishment thereof; because [*]they sold the righteous for silver, and the poor for a pair of shoes; 7  That pant after the dust of the earth on the head of the poor, and turn aside the way of the meek: and a man and his father will go in unto the same [∥]maid, to profane my holy name: 8 And they lay themselves down upon clothes laid to pledge by every altar, and they drink the wine of [∥]the condemned in the house of their god.

9 ¶ Yet destroyed I the [*]Amorite before them, whose height was like the height of the cedars, and he was strong as the oaks; yet I destroyed his fruit from above, and his roots from beneath. 10  Also [*]I brought you up from the land of Egypt, and led you forty years through the wilderness, to possess the land of the Amorite. 11  And I raised up of your sons for prophets, and of your young men for Nazarites. Is it not even thus, O ye children of Israel? saith the LORD. 12  But ye gave the Nazarites wine to drink; and commanded the prophets, [*]saying, Prophesy not. 13  Behold, [∥]I am pressed under you, as a cart is pressed that is full of sheaves. 14  Therefore the flight shall perish from the swift, and the strong shall not strengthen his force, neither shall the mighty deliver [†]himself: 15  Neither shall he stand that handleth the bow; and he that is swift of foot shall not deliver himself: neither shall he that rideth the horse deliver himself. 16 And he that is [†]courageous among the mighty shall flee away naked in that day, saith the LORD.

3

1  Hear this word that the LORD hath spoken against you, O children of Israel, against the whole family which I brought up from the land of Egypt, saying, 2  You only have I known of all the families of the earth: therefore I will [†]punish you for all your iniquities. 3  Can two walk together, except they be agreed? 4  Will a lion roar in the forest, when he hath no prey? will a young lion [†]cry out of his den, if he have taken nothing? 5  Can a bird fall in a snare upon the earth, where no gin is for him? shall one take up a snare from the earth, and have taken nothing at all? 6  Shall a trumpet be blown in the city, and the people [∥]not be afraid? shall there be evil in a city, [∥]and the LORD hath not done it? 7  Surely the Lord GOD will do nothing, but he revealeth his secret unto his servants the prophets. 8  The lion hath roared, who will not fear? the Lord GOD hath spoken, who can but prophesy?

9 ¶ Publish in the palaces at Ashdod, and in the palaces in the land of Egypt, and say, Assemble yourselves upon the mountains of Samaria, and behold the great tumults in the midst thereof, and the [∥]oppressed in the midst thereof. 10  For they know not to do right, saith the LORD, who store up violence and [∥]robbery in their palaces. 11  Therefore thus saith the Lord GOD; An adversary there shall be even round about the land; and he shall bring down thy strength from thee, and thy palaces shall be spoiled. 12  Thus saith the LORD; As the shepherd [†]taketh out of the mouth of the lion two legs, or a piece of an ear; so shall the children of Israel be taken out that dwell in Samaria in the corner of a bed, and [∥]in Damascus in a couch. 13  Hear ye, and testify in the house of Jacob, saith the Lord GOD, the God of hosts, 14  That in the day that I shall [∥]visit the transgressions of Israel upon him I will also visit the altars of Beth-el: and the horns of the altar shall be cut off, and fall to the ground. 15  And I will smite the winter house with the summer house; and the houses of ivory shall perish, and the great houses shall have an end, saith the LORD.

4

1  Hear this word, ye kine of Bashan, that are in the mountain of Samaria, which oppress the poor, which crush the needy, which say to their masters, Bring, and let us drink. 2  The Lord GOD hath sworn by his holiness, that, lo, the days shall come upon you, that he will take you away with hooks, and your posterity with fishhooks. 3  And ye shall go out at the breaches, every cow at that which is before her; and [∥]ye shall cast them into the palace, saith the LORD.

4 ¶ Come to Beth-el, and transgress; at Gilgal multiply transgression; and bring your sacrifices every morning, and your tithes after [†]three years: 5  And [†]offer a sacrifice of thanksgiving with leaven, and proclaim and publish the free offerings: for [†]this liketh you, O ye children of Israel, saith the Lord GOD.

6 ¶ And I also have given you cleanness of teeth in all your cities, and want of bread in all your places: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD. 7  And also I have withholden the rain from you, when there were yet three months to the harvest: and I caused it to rain upon one city, and caused it not to rain upon another city: one piece was rained upon, and the piece whereupon it rained not withered. 8  So two or three cities wandered unto one city, to drink water; but they were not satisfied: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD. 9  I have smitten you with blasting and mildew: [∥]when your gardens and your vineyards and your fig trees and your olive trees increased, the palmerworm devoured them: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD. 10  I have sent among you the pestilence [∥]after the manner of Egypt: your young men have I slain with the sword, [†]and have taken away your horses; and I have made the stink of your camps to come up unto your nostrils: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD. 11  I have overthrown some of you, as God overthrew [*]Sodom and Gomorrah, and ye were as a firebrand plucked out of the burning: yet have ye not returned unto me, saith the LORD. 12  Therefore thus will I do unto thee, O Israel: and because I will do this unto thee, prepare to meet thy God, O Israel. 13  For, lo, he that formeth the mountains, and createth the [∥]wind, and declareth unto man what is his thought, that maketh the morning darkness, and treadeth upon the high places of the earth, The LORD, The God of hosts, is his name.

5

1  Hear ye this word which I take up against you, even a lamentation, O house of Israel. 2  The virgin of Israel is fallen; she shall no more rise: she is forsaken upon her land; there is none to raise her up. 3  For thus saith the Lord GOD; The city that went out by a thousand shall leave an hundred, and that which went forth by an hundred shall leave ten, to the house of Israel.

4 ¶ For thus saith the LORD unto the house of Israel, Seek ye me, and ye shall live: 5  But seek not [*]Beth-el, nor enter into Gilgal, and pass not to Beer-sheba: for Gilgal shall surely go into captivity, and Beth-el shall come to nought. 6  Seek the LORD, and ye shall live; lest he break out like fire in the house of Joseph, and devour it, and there be none to quench it in Beth-el. 7  Ye who turn judgment to wormwood, and leave off righteousness in the earth, 8  Seek him that maketh the [*]seven stars and Orion, and turneth the shadow of death into the morning, and maketh the day dark with night: that [*]calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth: The LORD is his name: 9  That strengtheneth the [†]spoiled against the strong, so that the spoiled shall come against the fortress. 10  They hate him that rebuketh in the gate, and they abhor him that speaketh uprightly. 11  Forasmuch therefore as your treading is upon the poor, and ye take from him burdens of wheat: [*]ye have built houses of hewn stone, but ye shall not dwell in them; ye have planted [†]pleasant vineyards, but ye shall not drink wine of them. 12  For I know your manifold transgressions and your mighty sins: they afflict the just, they take [∥]a bribe, and they turn aside the poor in the gate from their right. 13  Therefore the prudent shall keep silence in that time; for it is an evil time. 14  Seek good, and not evil, that ye may live: and so the LORD, the God of hosts, shall be with you, as ye have spoken. 15 [*] Hate the evil, and love the good, and establish judgment in the gate: it may be that the LORD God of hosts will be gracious unto the remnant of Joseph.

16  Therefore the LORD, the God of hosts, the Lord, saith thus; Wailing shall be in all streets; and they shall say in all the highways, Alas! alas! and they shall call the husbandman to mourning, and such as are skilful of lamentation to wailing. 17  And in all vineyards shall be wailing: for I will pass through thee, saith the LORD. 18 [*] Woe unto you that desire the day of the LORD! to what end is it for you? the day of the LORD is darkness, and not light. 19  As if a man did flee from a lion, and a bear met him; or went into the house, and leaned his hand on the wall, and a serpent bit him. 20  Shall not the day of the LORD be darkness, and not light? even very dark, and no brightness in it?

21 ¶ [*]I hate, I despise your feast days, and I will not [∥]smell in your solemn assemblies. 22  Though ye offer me burnt offerings and your meat offerings, I will not accept them: neither will I regard the [∥]peace offerings of your fat beasts. 23  Take thou away from me the noise of thy songs; for I will not hear the melody of thy viols. 24  But let judgment [†]run down as waters, and righteousness as a mighty stream. 25 [*] Have ye offered unto me sacrifices and offerings in the wilderness forty years, O house of Israel? 26  But ye have borne [∥]the tabernacle of your Moloch and Chiun your images, the star of your god, which ye made to yourselves. 27  Therefore will I cause you to go into captivity beyond Damascus, saith the LORD, whose name is The God of hosts.

6

1 [*] Woe to them that [∥]are at ease in Zion, and trust in the mountain of Samaria, which are named [*][∥]chief of the nations, to whom the house of Israel came! 2  Pass ye unto Calneh, and see; and from thence go ye to Hamath the great: then go down to Gath of the Philistines: be they better than these kingdoms? or their border greater than your border? 3  Ye that [*]put far away the [*]evil day, and cause the [∥]seat of violence to come near; 4  That lie upon beds of ivory, and [∥]stretch themselves upon their couches, and eat the lambs out of the flock, and the calves out of the midst of the stall; 5  That [∥]chant to the sound of the viol, and invent to themselves instruments of musick, like David; 6  That drink [∥]wine in bowls, and anoint themselves with the chief ointments: but they are not grieved for the [†]affliction of Joseph.

7 ¶ Therefore now shall they go captive with the first that go captive, and the banquet of them that stretched themselves shall be removed.

8 [*] The Lord GOD hath sworn by himself, saith the LORD the God of hosts, I abhor the excellency of Jacob, and hate his palaces: therefore will I deliver up the city with [†]all that is therein. 9  And it shall come to pass, if there remain ten men in one house, that they shall die. 10  And a man’s uncle shall take him up, and he that burneth him, to bring out the bones out of the house, and shall say unto him that is by the sides of the house, Is there yet any with thee? and he shall say, No. Then shall he say, [*]Hold thy tongue: for [∥]we may not make mention of the name of the LORD. 11  For, behold, the LORD commandeth, and he will smite the great house with [∥]breaches, and the little house with clefts.

12 ¶ Shall horses run upon the rock? will one plow there with oxen? for ye have turned judgment into gall, and the fruit of righteousness into hemlock: 13  Ye which rejoice in a thing of nought, which say, Have we not taken to us horns by our own strength? 14  But, behold, I will raise up against you a nation, O house of Israel, saith the LORD the God of hosts; and they shall afflict you from the entering in of Hemath unto the [∥]river of the wilderness.

7

1  Thus hath the Lord GOD shewed unto me; and, behold, he formed [∥]grasshoppers in the beginning of the shooting up of the latter growth; and, lo, it was the latter growth after the king’s mowings. 2 And it came to pass, that when they had made an end of eating the grass of the land, then I said, O Lord GOD, forgive, I beseech thee: [∥]by whom shall Jacob arise? for he is small. 3  The LORD repented for this: It shall not be, saith the LORD.

4 ¶ Thus hath the Lord GOD shewed unto me: and, behold, the Lord GOD called to contend by fire, and it devoured the great deep, and did eat up a part. 5  Then said I, O Lord GOD, cease, I beseech thee: by whom shall Jacob arise? for he is small. 6  The LORD repented for this: This also shall not be, saith the Lord GOD.

7 ¶ Thus he shewed me: and, behold, the Lord stood upon a wall made by a plumbline, with a plumbline in his hand. 8  And the LORD said unto me, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A plumbline. Then said the Lord, Behold, I will set a plumbline in the midst of my people Israel: I will not again pass by them any more: 9  And the high places of Isaac shall be desolate, and the sanctuaries of Israel shall be laid waste; and I will rise against the house of Jeroboam with the sword.

10 ¶ Then Amaziah the priest of Beth-el sent to Jeroboam king of Israel, saying, Amos hath conspired against thee in the midst of the house of Israel: the land is not able to bear all his words. 11  For thus Amos saith, Jeroboam shall die by the sword, and Israel shall surely be led away captive out of their own land. 12  Also Amaziah said unto Amos, O thou seer, go, flee thee away into the land of Judah, and there eat bread, and prophesy there: 13  But prophesy not again any more at Beth-el: for it is the king’s [∥]chapel, and it is the [†]king’s court.

14 ¶ Then answered Amos, and said to Amaziah, I was no prophet, neither was I a prophet’s son; but I was an herdman, and a gatherer of [∥]sycomore fruit: 15  And the LORD took me [†]as I followed the flock, and the LORD said unto me, Go, prophesy unto my people Israel.

16 ¶ Now therefore hear thou the word of the LORD: Thou sayest, Prophesy not against Israel, [*]and drop not thy word against the house of Isaac. 17  Therefore thus saith the LORD; Thy wife shall be an harlot in the city, and thy sons and thy daughters shall fall by the sword, and thy land shall be divided by line; and thou shalt die in a polluted land: and Israel shall surely go into captivity forth of his land.

8

1  Thus hath the Lord GOD shewed unto me: and behold a basket of summer fruit. 2  And he said, Amos, what seest thou? And I said, A basket of summer fruit. Then said the LORD unto me, The end is come upon my people of Israel; I will not again pass by them any more. 3  And the songs of the [‡]temple [†]shall be howlings in that day, saith the Lord GOD: there shall be many dead bodies in every place; they shall cast them forth [†]with silence.

4 ¶ Hear this, O ye that swallow up the needy, even to make the poor of the land to fail, 5  Saying, When will the [∥]new moon be gone, that we may sell corn? and the sabbath, that we may [†]set forth wheat, making the ephah small, and the shekel great, and [†]falsifying the balances by deceit? 6  That we may buy the poor for [*]silver, and the needy for a pair of shoes; yea, and sell the refuse of the wheat? 7  The LORD hath sworn by the excellency of Jacob, Surely I will never forget any of their works. 8  Shall not the land tremble for this, and every one mourn that dwelleth therein? and it shall rise up wholly as a flood; and it shall be cast out and drowned, as by the flood of Egypt. 9  And it shall come to pass in that day, saith the Lord GOD, that I will cause the sun to go down at noon, and I will darken the earth in the clear day: 10  And I will turn your feasts into mourning, and all your songs into lamentation; and I will bring up sackcloth upon all loins, and baldness upon every head; and I will make it as the mourning of an only son, and the end thereof as a bitter day.

11 ¶ Behold, the days come, saith the Lord GOD, that I will send a famine in the land, not a famine of bread, nor a thirst for water, but of hearing the words of the LORD: 12  And they shall wander from sea to sea, and from the north even to the east, they shall run to and fro to seek the word of the LORD, and shall not find it. 13  In that day shall the fair virgins and young men faint for thirst. 14  They that swear by the sin of Samaria, and say, Thy god, O Dan, liveth; and, The manner of Beer-sheba liveth; even they shall fall, and never rise up again.

9

1  I saw the Lord standing upon the altar: and he said, Smite the [∥]lintel of the door, that the posts may shake: and [∥]cut them in the head, all of them; and I will slay the last of them with the sword: he that fleeth of them shall not flee away, and he that escapeth of them shall not be delivered. 2 [*] Though they dig into hell, thence shall mine hand take them; though they climb up to heaven, thence will I bring them down: 3  And though they hide themselves in the top of Carmel, I will search and take them out thence; and though they be hid from my sight in the bottom of the sea, thence will I command the serpent, and he shall bite them: 4  And though they go into captivity before their enemies, thence will I command the sword, and it shall slay them: and [*]I will set mine eyes upon them for evil, and not for good. 5  And the Lord GOD of hosts is he that toucheth the land, and it shall melt, and all that [‡]dwell therein shall mourn: and it shall rise up wholly like a flood; and shall be drowned, as by the flood of Egypt. 6  It is he that buildeth his [∥][†][*]stories in the heaven, and hath founded his [∥]troop in the earth; he that [*]calleth for the waters of the sea, and poureth them out upon the face of the earth: The LORD is his name. 7  Are ye not as children of the Ethiopians unto me, O children of Israel? saith the LORD. Have not I brought up Israel out of the land of Egypt? and the [*]Philistines from Caphtor, and the Syrians from Kir? 8  Behold, the eyes of the Lord GOD are upon the sinful kingdom, and I will destroy it from off the face of the earth; saving that I will not utterly destroy the house of Jacob, saith the LORD. 9  For, lo, I will command, and I will [†]sift the house of Israel among all nations, like as corn is sifted in a sieve, yet shall not the least [†]grain fall upon the earth. 10  All the sinners of my people shall die by the sword, which say, The evil shall not overtake nor prevent us.

11 ¶ In that day will I raise up the [*]tabernacle of David that is fallen, and [†]close up the breaches thereof; and I will raise up his ruins, and I will build it as in the days of old: 12  That they may possess the remnant of Edom, and of all the heathen, [†]which are called by my name, saith the LORD that doeth this. 13  Behold, the days come, saith the LORD, that the plowman shall overtake the reaper, and the treader of grapes him that [†]soweth seed; and the mountains shall drop [∥][*]sweet wine, and all the hills shall melt. 14  And I will bring again the captivity of my people of Israel, and they shall build the waste cities, and inhabit them; and they shall plant vineyards, and drink the wine thereof; they shall also make gardens, and eat the fruit of them. 15  And I will plant them upon their land, and they shall no more be pulled up out of their land which I have given them, saith the LORD thy God.

* 1.1 Zech 14 5

* 1.2 Jer. 25. 30. Joel 3. 16.

∥ 1.3 Or, yea, for four.

∥ 1.3 ver. 6, &c.

∥ 1.5 Or, Bilathaven.

∥ 1.5 Or, Betheden.

* 1.6 2 Chr. 28. 18.

∥ 1.6 Or, carried them away with an entire captivity.

† 1.9 Heb. the covenant of brethren.

† 1.11 Heb. corrupted his compassions.

‡ 1.11 [1611 omits he]

∥ 1.13 Or, divided the mountains.

* 2.1 2 Kin. 3. 27.

* 2.6 ch 8 6.

∥ 2.7 Or, young woman.

∥ 2.8 Or, such as have fined, or, muleted.

* 2.9 Num. 21 24. Deut. 2. 31 Josh 24. 8

* 2.10 Ex. 12. 51.

* 2.12 ch. 7. 12.

∥ 2.13 Or, I will press your place, as a cart full of sheaves presseth.

† 2.14 Heb. his soul, or, life.

† 2.16 Heb. strong of his heart.

† 3.2 Heb. visit upon.

† 3.4 Heb. give forth his voice.

∥ 3.6 Or, not run together.

∥ 3.6 Or, and shall not the Lord do somewhat?

∥ 3.9 Or, oppressions.

∥ 3.10 Or, spoil.

† 3.12 Heb delivereth.

∥ 3.12 Or, on the bed's feet.

∥ 3.14 Or, punish Israel for.

∥ 4.3 Or, ye shall cast away the things of the palace.

† 4.4 Heb. three years of days.

† 4.5 Heb. offer by burning.

† 4.5 Heb. so ye love.

∥ 4.9 Or, the multitude of your gardens, &c. did the palmerworm, &c.

∥ 4.10 Or, in the way.

† 4.10 Heb with the captivity of your horses.

* 4.11 Gen. 19. 24.

∥ 4.13 Or, spirit.

* 5.5 ch. 4. 4.

* 5.8 Job 9 9. &c 38. 31.

* 5.8 ch. 9. 6.

† 5.9 Heb. spoil.

* 5.11 Zeph 1. 13

† 5.11 Heb. vineyards of desire.

∥ 5.12 Or, a ransom.

* 5.15 Ps. 34. 14. &c 97. 10. Rom. 12. 9.

* 5.18 Is. 5. 19. Jer. 30. 7 Joel 2. 2. Zeph. 1. 15.

* 5.21 Is. 1. 11. Jer. 6. 20.

∥ 5.21 Or, smell your holy days.

∥ 5.22 Or, thank offerings.

† 5.24 Heb. roll.

* 5.25 Acts 7. 42.

∥ 5.26 Or, Siccuth your king.

* 6.1 Luke 6. 24.

∥ 6.1 Or, are secure.

* 6.1 Ex. 19. 5.

∥ 6.1 Or, first-fruits.

* 6.3 Ezek. 12. 27.

* 6.3 ch. 5. 18.

∥ 6.3 Or, habitation.

∥ 6.4 Or, abound with superfluities.

∥ 6.5 Or, quaver.

∥ 6.6 Or, in bowls of wine.

† 6.6 Heb. breach.

* 6.8 Jer. 51. 14.

† 6.8 Heb. the fulness thereof.

* 6.10 ch 5. 13.

∥ 6.10 Or, they will not, or, have not.

∥ 6.11 Or, droppings.

∥ 6.14 Or, valley.

∥ 7.1 Or, green worms.

∥ 7.2 Or, who of (or, for) Jacob shall stand?

∥ 7.13 Or, sanctuary.

† 7.13 Heb house of the kingdom

∥ 7.14 Or, wild figs.

† 7.15 Heb. from behind.

* 7.16 Ezek. 21. 2.

‡ 8.3 [1611 Temples]

† 8.3 Heb. shall howl.

† 8.3 Heb. be silent.

∥ 8.5 Or, month.

† 8.5 Heb. open.

† 8.5 Heb. perverting the balances of deceit.

* 8.6 ch. 2. 6.

∥ 9.1 Or, chapiter, or, knop

∥ 9.1 Or, wound them

* 9.2 Ps 139. 8, &c.

* 9.4 Jer. 44. 11.

‡ 9.5 [1611 dwelleth]

∥ 9.6 Or, spheres.

† 9.6 Heb ascensions.

* 9.6 Ps. 104. 3.

∥ 9.6 Or, bundle.

* 9.6 ch. 5. 8.

* 9.7 Jer. 47. 4.

† 9.9 Heb. cause to move.

† 9.9 Heb. stone.

* 9.11 Acts 15. 16.

† 9.11 Heb. hedge, or, wall.

† 9.12 Heb. upon whom my name is called.

† 9.13 Heb. draweth forth.

∥ 9.13 Or, new wine.

* 9.13 Joel 3. 18.

Baruch

1
2
3
4
5
6

The Book of Baruch

1

1 [a]And these are the words of the book, which [b]Baruch the son of [c]Nerias, the son of Maasias, the son of Sedecias, the son of Asadias, the son of Chelcias, wrote in Babylon,

2 In [d]the fifth year, and [d]in the seventh day of the month, what time as the Chaldeans took Jerusalem, and burnt it with fire.

3 And [b]Baruch did read the words of this book in the hearing of [e]Jechonias the son of [*]Joachim king of Juda, and in the ears of all the people that came to hear the book,

4 And in the hearing of the nobles, and of the king’s sons, and in the hearing of the elders, and of all the people, [f]from the lowest unto the highest, even of all them that dwelt at Babylon by the river Sud.

5 Whereupon they wept, fasted, [*]and prayed before the Lord.

6 They made also a collection of money [g]according to every man’s power:

7 And they sent it to Jerusalem unto [*]Joachim the high priest, the son of [h]Chelcias, son of [i]Salom, and to the priests, and to all the people which were found with him at Jerusalem,

8 At the same time when he received [k]the vessels of the house of the Lord, that were carried out of the temple, to return them into the land of Juda, the tenth day of the month [l]Sivan, namely, [m]silver vessels, which [n]Sedecias the son of Josias king of Jada had made,

9 After that Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon [d]had carried away [e]Jechonias, and the princes, and the [*]captives, and the mighty men, and the people of the land, from Jerusalem, and brought them unto Babylon.

10 And they said, Behold, we have sent you [o]money to buy you [p]burnt offerings, and [q]sin offerings, and [r]incense, and prepare ye [*]manna, and offer upon the altar of the Lord our God;

11 And [s]pray for the life of Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon, and for the life of [t]Balthasar his son, that their days may be upon earth as [u]the days of heaven:

12 And the Lord will give us strength, and lighten our eyes, and we shall live [x]under the shadow of Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon, and under the shadow of [t]Balthasar his son, and we shall serve them many days, and [y]find favour in their sight.

13 Pray for us also unto the Lord our God, for we have sinned against the Lord our God; and unto this day the fury of the Lord and his wrath is not turned from us.

14 And ye shall read [z]this book which we have sent unto you, to make confession in the house of the Lord, upon the feasts and solemn days.

15 And ye shall say, [a]To the Lord our God belongeth righteousness, but unto us [b]the confusion of faces, [i]as it is come to pass this day, unto them of Juda, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem,

16 And to our [c]kings, and to our princes, and to our priests, and to our prophets, and to our fathers:

17 For [d]we have sinned before the Lord,

18 [d]And disobeyed him, and [e]have not hearkened unto the voice of the Lord our God, [e]to walk in the commandments that he gave us openly:

19 Since the day that the Lord brought our forefathers out of the land of Egypt, unto this present day, we have been disobedient unto the Lord our God, and we have been negligent in not hearing his voice.

20 Wherefore [f]the evils cleaved unto us, and [g]the curse, which the Lord appointed by Moses his servant at the time that he brought our fathers out of the land of Egypt, to give us [h]a land that floweth with milk and honey, like [i]as it is to see this day.

21 [e]Nevertheless we have not hearkened unto the voice of the Lord our God, [k]according unto all the words of the prophets, whom he sent unto us:

22 But every man followed the imagination of his own wicked heart, to serve [l]strange gods, and to do evil in the sight of the Lord our God.

2

1 Therefore [a]the Lord hath made good his word, which he pronounced against us, and against our judges that judged Israel, and against our kings, and against our princes, and against the men of Israel and Juda,

2 To bring upon us great plagues, such as never happened under the whole heaven, as it came to pass in Jerusalem, [a]according to the things that were written in the law of Moses;

3 [b]That a man should eat the flesh of his own son, and the flesh of his own daughter.

4 Moreover he hath delivered them to be in subjection to [c]all the kingdoms that are round about us, [d]to be as a reproach and [e]desolation among all the people round about, where the Lord hath scattered them.

5 Thus we [*]were cast down, and not exalted, because we have sinned against the Lord our God, and have not been obedient unto his voice.

6 [f]To the Lord our God appertaineth righteousness: but unto us and to our fathers open shame, [o]as appeareth this day.

7 For [a][g]all these plagues are come upon us, which the Lord hath pronounced against us

8 [h]Yet have we not prayed before the Lord, that we might turn every one from the imaginations of his wicked heart.

9 [i]Wherefore the Lord watched over us for evil, and the Lord hath brought it upon us: for [k]the Lord is righteous in all his works which he hath commanded us.

10 [i][l]Yet we have not hearkened unto his voice, [l]to walk in the commandments of the Lord, that he hath set before us.

11 [m]And now, O Lord God of Israel, that hast brought thy people out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and high arm, and with signs, and with wonders, and with great power, and [n]hast gotten thyself a name, [o]as appeareth this day:

12 O Lord our God, [m][p]we have sinned, we have done ungodly, we have dealt unrighteously in all thine ordinances.

13 [q]Let thy wrath turn from us: [r]for we are but a few left among the heathen, where thou hast scattered us.

14 [s]Hear our prayers, O Lord, and our petitions, and deliver us for thine own sake, and [t]give us favour in the sight of them which have led us away:

15 [u]That all the earth may know that thou art the Lord our God, because [*][x]Israel and his posterity is called by thy name.

16 O Lord, [y]look down from thine holy house, and consider us: [z]bow down thine ear, O Lord, to hear us.

17 Open thine eyes, and behold; [a]for the dead that are in the graves, whose [*]souls are taken from their bodies, will give unto the Lord neither praise nor righteousness:

18 But [b]the soul that is greatly vexed, which goeth stooping and feeble, and the eyes that fail, and the hungry soul, will give thee praise and righteousness, O Lord.

19 [b]Therefore we do not make our humble supplication before thee, O Lord our God, for the righteousness of our fathers, and of our kings.

20 For thou hast sent out thy wrath and indignation upon us, [c]as thou hast spoken by thy servants the prophets, saying,

21 Thus saith the Lord, Bow down your shoulders to serve the king of Babylon: so shall ye remain in the land that I gave unto your fathers.

22 But if ye will not hear the voice of the Lord, to serve the king of Babylon,

23 [e]I will cause to cease out of the cites of Judah, and from without Jerusalem, the voice of [ee]mirth, and the voice of [ee]joy, the voice of the bridegroom, and the voice of the bride: and the whole land shall be [f]desolate of inhabitants.

24 But we would not hearken unto thy voice, to serve the king of Babylon: therefore hast thou [g]made good the words that thou spakest by thy servants the prophets, namely, [h]that the bones of our kings, and the bones of our fathers, should be taken out of their place.

25 And, lo,[h][i] they are cast out to the heat of the day, and to the frost of the night, and they died in great miseries[k] by famine, by sword, and by pestilence.

26 And [l]the house which is called by thy name hast thou laid waste, [m]as it is to be seen this day, for the wickedness of the house of Israel and the house of Juda.

27 O Lord our God, thou hast dealt with us after all thy [n]goodness, and according to all that great mercy of thine,

28 As thou spakest by thy servant Moses in the day when thou didst command him to write the law before the children of Israel, saying,

29 [o]If ye will not hear my voice, surely [*]this very great multitude shall be turned into a small number among the nations, where I will scatter them.

30 For I knew that they would not hear me, because it is a [p]stiffnecked people: but [q]in the land of their captivities they shall [*]remember themselves.

31 And [r]shall know that I am the Lord their God: for [s]I will give them an heart, and ears to hear:

32 [q]And they shall praise me in the land of their captivity, and think upon my name,

33 And return from their stiff [*]neck, and from their wicked deeds: for they shall remember the way of their fathers, which sinned before the Lord.

34 And [t]I will bring them again into the land which I promised with an oath unto their fathers, Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob, and they shall be lords of it: and I will increase them, and they shall not be diminished.

35 And [u]I will make an everlasting covenant with them [s]to be their God, and they shall be my people: and I will [x]no more drive my people of Israel out of the land that I have given them.

3

1 O Lord [a]Almighty, God of Israel, the soul in anguish the troubled spirit, crieth unto thee.

2 Hear, O Lord, and have mercy; for thou art merciful: and have pity upon us, because we have sinned before thee.

3 [b]For thou endurest for ever, and we perish utterly.

4 O Lord [a]Almighty, thou God of Israel, hear now the prayers of the [c]dead Israelites, and of their children, which have sinned before thee, and not hearkened unto the voice of thee their God: for the which cause [d]these plagues cleave unto us.

5 Remember not the iniquities of our forefathers: but think upon thy power and thy name now at this time.

6 For thou art the Lord our God, and thee, O Lord, will we praise.

7 And for this cause thou hast put thy fear in our hearts, to the intent that we should call upon thy name, and praise thee in our captivity: for [e]we have [f]called to mind all the iniquity of our forefathers, that sinned before thee.

8 Behold, we are yet this day in our captivity, where thou hast scattered us, [g]for a reproach and [h]a curse, and [i]to be subject to payments, according to all the iniquities of our fathers, which departed from the Lord our God.

9 Hear, Israel, the commandments of life: give ear to understand wisdom.

10 How happeneth it Israel, that thou art in thine enemies’ land, that thou art waxen old in a strange country, that thou art defiled w[c]ith the dead,

11 That [j]thou art counted with them that [k]go down into the grave?

12 Thou hast forsaken [l]the fountain of wisdom.

13 For [m]if thou hadst walked in the way of God, thou shouldest have dwelled in peace for ever.

14 Learn where is wisdom, where is strength, where is understanding; that thou mayest know also where is length of days, and life, where is [n]the light of the eyes, and peace.

15 [o]Who hath found out her place? or who hath come into her treasures?

16 Where are the princes of the heathen become, and such as [p]ruled the beasts upon the earth;

17 They that [q]had their pastime with the fowls of the air, and they that hoarded up silver and gold, [r]wherein men trust, and made no end of their getting?

18 For they that wrought in silver, and were so careful, and whose works are unsearchable,

19 They [s]are vanished and [k]gone down to the grave, and others are come up in their steads.

20 Young men have seen light, and dwelt upon the earth: but [t]the way of knowledge have they not known,

21 Nor understood the paths thereof, nor laid hold of it: their children were far off from that way.

22 It hath not been heard of in Chanaan, [u]neither hath it been seen in [v]Theman.

23 The [w]Agarenes that seek wisdom upon earth, the merchants of [x]Meran and of [v]Theman, the [*]authors of fables, and searchers out of understanding; none of these have known the way of wisdom, or remember her paths.

24 O Israel, how great is the house of God! and how large is the place of his possession!

25 Great, and hath none end; high, and unmeasurable.

26 There were the [y]giants famous from the beginning, that were [z]of so great stature, and so expert in war.

27 Those did not the Lord choose, neither gave he [t]the way of knowledge unto them:

28 But they were destroyed, because they had no wisdom, and perished through their own foolishness.

29 [a]Who hath gone up into heaven, and taken her, and brought her down from the clouds?

30 [a]Who hath gone over the sea, and found her, and will bring her [b]for pure gold?

31 No man knoweth her way, nor thinketh of her path.

32 But he that knoweth all things knoweth her, and hath found her out with his understanding: he that prepared the earth for evermore hath filled it with fourfooted beasts:

33 He that sendeth forth light, and it goeth, calleth it again, and it obeyeth him with fear.

34 The stars shined [c]in their watches, and rejoiced: when [d]he calleth them, they say, Here we be; and so with cheerfulness they shewed light unto him that made them.

35 This is our God, and there shall none other be accounted of in comparison of him

36 He hath found out all [t]the way of knowledge, and hath given it unto Jacob his servant, and to Israel his [e]beloved.

37 Afterward [f]did he shew himself upon earth, and [f]conversed with men.

4

1 This is the book of the commandments of God, and the law that endureth for ever: all they that keep it shall come to life; but such as leave it shall die.

2 Turn thee, O Jacob, and take hold of it: walk [*]in the presence of the light thereof, [a]that thou mayest be illuminated.

3 Give not thine honour to another, nor the things that are profitable unto thee to a strange nation.

4 O Israel, happy are we: for things that are pleasing to God are made known unto us.

5 Be of good cheer, my people, the memorial of Israel.

6 [b]Ye were sold to the nations, not for your destruction: but because ye moved God to wrath, ye were delivered unto the enemies.

7 For ye provoked him that made you by [c]sacrificing unto devils, and not to God.

8 Ye have forgotten [o]the everlasting God, that brought you up; and ye have grieved Jerusalem, that nursed you.

9 For when she saw the wrath of God coming upon you, she said, Hearken, O [d]ye that dwell about Sion: God hath brought upon me great mourning;

10 For I saw [d]the captivity of my sons and daughters, which [o]the Everlasting brought upon them.

11 With joy did I nourish them; but [i]sent them away with weeping and mourning.

12 Let no man rejoice over me, [e]a widow, and forsaken of many, who for the sins of my children am left desolate; because they departed from the law of God.

13 They knew not his statutes, nor walked in the ways of his commandments, nor trod in the paths [*]of discipline in his righteousness.

14 Let them [d]that dwell about Sion come, and [d]remember ye the captivity of my sons and daughters, which [o]the Everlasting hath brought upon them.

15 For [f]he hath brought a nation upon them from far, a shameless nation, and of a strange language, [f]who neither reverenced old man, nor pitied child.

16 These have carried away the dear beloved children of the widow, and left her that was alone desolate without daughters.

17 But what can I help you?

18 For he that brought these plagues upon you will deliver you from the hands of your enemies.

19 Go your way, O my children, go your way: for I am left desolate.

20 [g]I have put off the clothing of [*]peace, and put upon me the sackcloth of my prayer: I will cry unto [o]the Everlasting [*][h]in my days.

21 Be of good cheer, O my children, cry unto the Lord, and he will deliver you from the power and hand of the enemies.

22 For my hope is in the Everlasting, that he will save you; and joy is come unto me from the Holy One, because of the mercy which shall soon come unto you from [o]the Everlasting our Saviour.

23 For [i]I sent you out with mourning and weeping: but God will give you to me again with [j]joy and gladness for ever.

24 Like as now [d]the neighbours of Sion have seen your captivity: so shall they see shortly your salvation from our God which shall come upon you with great glory, and b[a]rightness of t[o]he Everlasting.

25 My children, suffer patiently the wrath that is come upon you from God: for thine enemy hath persecuted thee; but shortly thou shalt see his destruction, and shalt tread upon his neck.

26 [*]My delicate ones have gone rough ways, and were taken away as a flock caught of the enemies.

27 Be of good comfort, O my children, and cry unto God: for ye shall be remembered of him [k]that brought these things upon you.

28 For as it was your mind [kk]to go astray from God: so, being returned, seek him [l]ten times more.

29 For he [k]that hath brought these plagues upon you shall bring you everlasting joy with your salvation.

30 Take a good heart, O Jerusalem: for [m]he that gave thee that name will comfort thee.

31 Miserable are they that afflicted thee, and rejoiced at thy fall.

32 Miserable are the cities which thy children served: miserable is she that received thy sons.

33 For as she rejoiced at thy ruin, and was glad of thy fall: [n]so shall she be grieved for her own desolation.

34 [n]For I will take away the rejoicing of her great multitude, and her pride shall be turned into mourning.

35 For fire shall come upon her from [o]the Everlasting, long to endure; and [n]she shall be inhabited of devils for a great time.

36 [p]O Jerusalem, look about thee toward the east, and behold the joy that cometh unto thee from God.

37 Lo, [p][q]thy sons come, [i]whom thou sentest away, they come gathered together from the east to the west [p]by the word of the Holy One, rejoicing in the glory of God.

5

1 [a]Put off, O Jerusalem, the garment of mourning and affliction, and put on the comeliness of the glory that cometh from God for ever.

2 Cast about thee [b]a double garment of the righteousness which cometh from God; and set a diadem on thine head of the glory of [c]the Everlasting.

3 For God will shew [d]thy brightness unto every country under heaven.

4 For thy name shall be called of God for ever The peace of righteousness, and The glory of G[e]od’s worship.

5 Arise, O Jerusalem, and stand on high, and [f]look about toward the east, and behold thy children gathered from the west unto the east [f]by the word of the Holy One, rejoicing in the remembrance of God.

6 For they departed from thee on foot, and were led away of their enemies: but [g]God bringeth them unto thee exalted with glory, as [h]children of the kingdom.

7 For God hath appointed that [i]every high hill, and banks of long continuance, should be cast down, and valleys filled up, to make even the ground, that Israel may go safely in the glory of God,

8 Moreover even the woods and [k]every sweetsmelling tree shall overshadow Israel by the commandment of God.

9 For God shall lead Israel with joy [d]in the light of his glory with the mercy and righteousness that cometh from him.

The Epistle of Jeremy

6

A copy of an epistle, which Jeremy sent unto them which were to be led captives into Babylon by the king of the Babilonians, to certify them, as it was commanded him of God.

1 A copy of an epistle, which Jeremy sent unto them which were to be led captives into Babylon by the king of the Babylonians, to certify them, as it was commanded him of God.

2 Because of the sins which ye have committed before God, [a]ye shall be led away captives into Babylon by Nabuchodonosor king of the Babylonians.

3 So when ye be come unto Babylon, ye shall remain there many years, and for a long season, namely, [b]seven generations: and after that I will bring you away peaceably from thence.

4 Now shall ye see in Babylon [c]gods of silver, and of gold, and of wood, [d]borne upon shoulders, [o]which cause the nations to fear.

5 Beware therefore that ye in no wise be like to strangers, [o]neither be ye afraid of them, when ye see the multitude before them and behind them, worshipping them.

6 But say ye in your hearts, O [e]Lord, we must worship thee.

7 For [f]mine angel is with you, and I myself caring for your souls.

8 As for their tongue, it is polished by the workman, and they themselves are [g]gilded and laid over with silver; yet are they but false, and [h]cannot speak.

9 And taking gold, as it were for a virgin that loveth to go gay, they make crowns for the heads of their gods.

10 Sometimes also the priests convey from their gods gold and silver, and bestow it upon themselves.

11 Yea, they will give thereof to the [*]common harlots, and [i]deck them as men with garments, being [c]gods of silver, and gods of gold, and wood.

12 Yet cannot these gods save themselves from [j]rust and moth, though they be covered with [i][k]purple raiment.

13 They wipe their faces [l]because of the dust of the temple, when there is much upon them.

14 And he that cannot put to death one that offendeth him holdeth a sceptre, as though he were a judge of the country.

15 He hath also in his right hand a dagger and an ax: but cannot deliver himself from war and [m]thieves.

16 [n]Whereby they are known not to be gods: [n][o]therefore fear them not.

17 For like as a vessel that a man useth is nothing worth when it is broken; even so it is with their gods: when they be set up in the temple, their eyes be [l]full of dust through the feet of them that come in.

18 And as [p]the [*]doors are made sure on every side upon him that offendeth the king, as being [q]committed to suffer death: even so the priests make fast their temples with doors, with locks, and bars, lest their gods be spoiled with [m]robbers.

19 They light them candles, yea, more than for themselves, whereof they cannot see one.

20 They are [qq]as one of the beams of the temple, yet they say their hearts are [*]gnawed upon by things creeping out of the earth; and when they eat them and their clothes, they feel it not.

21 Their faces are blacked through the smoke that cometh out of the temple.

22 Upon their bodies and heads sit bats, swallows, and birds, and the cats also.

23 [n]By this ye may know that they are no gods: [n][o]therefore fear them not.

24 Notwithstanding the gold that is about them to make them beautiful, except they [r]wipe off the [j]rust, they will not shine: for neither when they were molten did they feel it.

25 The things wherein there is no breath are bought for [*]a most high price.

26 [d][s]They are borne upon shoulders, having no feet whereby they declare unto men that they be nothing worth.

27 They also that serve them are ashamed: [s][t]for if they fall to the ground at any time, they cannot rise up again of themselves: neither, if one set them upright, can they move of themselves: neither, [u]if they be bowed down, can they make themselves straight: but they [v]set [*]gifts before them a[w]s unto dead men.

28 As for the things that are sacrificed unto them, [x]their priests sell and [*][y]abuse; [z]in like manner their wives lay up part thereof in salt; but unto the poor and impotent they give nothing of it.

29 Menstruous women and [a]women in childbed eat their sacrifices: [aa]by these things ye may know that they are no gods: [aa]fear them not.

30 For how can they be called gods? because women [b]set meat before [c]the gods of silver, gold, and wood.

31 And the priests sit in their temples, [d]having their clothes rent, and [e]their heads and beards shaven, and nothing upon their heads.

32 [f]They roar and cry before their gods, as men do [g]at the feast when one is dead.

33 The priests also [h]take off their garments, and clothe their wives and children.

34 Whether it be evil that one doeth unto them, or good, they are not able to recompense it: they can neither [hh]set up a king, nor put him down.

35 In like manner, they can neither give riches nor [i]money: [j]though a man make a vow unto them, and keep it not, they will not require it.

36 They can save no man from death, neither deliver the weak from the mighty.

37 They cannot restore a blind man to his sight, nor help any man in his distress.

38 They can shew no mercy to the widow, nor do good to the fatherless.

39 [c]Their gods of wood, and which are [k]overlaid with gold and silver, are like the stones that be hewn out of the mountain: [l]they that worship them shall be confounded.

40 [m]How should a man then think and say that they are gods, when even the Chaldeans themselves dishonour them?

41 [n]Who if they shall see one dumb that cannot speak, they [*]bring him, and intreat [o]Bel that he may speak, as though he were able to understand.

42 Yet they cannot understand this themselves, and leave them: for they have no [*]knowledge.

43 [p]The women also with cords about them, sitting in the ways, burn [q]bran for perfume: but if any of them, drawn by some that passeth by, lie with him, she reproacheth her fellow, that she was not thought as worthy as herself, nor her cord broken.

44 Whatsoever is done among them is false: [m]how may it then be thought or said that they are gods?

45 [r]They are made of carpenters and goldsmiths: they can be nothing else than the workmen will have them to be.

46 And they themselves that made them can never continue long; how should then the things that are made of them be gods?

47 For they left lies and reproaches to them that come after.

48 For when there cometh any war or plague upon them, the priests consult with themselves, where they may be hidden with them.

49 [m]How then cannot men perceive that they be no gods, which can neither save themselves from war, nor from plague?

50 For seeing they be but [s]of wood, and [t]overlaid with silver and gold, it shall be known hereafter that they are false:

51 And it shall manifestly appear to all nations and kings that they are no gods, but [u]the works of men’s hands, and that there is no work of God in them.

52 [m]Who then may not know that they are no gods?

53 For neither can they [v]set up a king in the land, nor [w]give rain unto men.

54 Neither [x]can they judge their own cause, nor [y]redress a wrong, being unable: for they are as crows between heaven and earth.

55 Whereupon when fire falleth upon the house of [s]gods of wood, or [t]laid over with gold or silver, their priests will flee away, and escape; but they themselves shall be burned asunder [z]like beams.

56 Moreover [a]they cannot withstand any king or enemies: [b]how can it then be thought or said that they be gods?

57 Neither are those [c]gods of wood, and [d]laid over with silver or gold, able to escape either from thieves or [e]robbers.

58 Whose gold, and silver, and garments wherewith they are clothed, they that are strong take, and go away withal: [a]neither are they able to help themselves.

59 Therefore it is better to be a king that sheweth his power, or else [f]a profitable vessel in an house, which the owner shall have use of, than such false gods; or to be a door in an house, to keep such things therein, than such false gods. or a pillar of wood in a a palace, than such false gods.

60 For [m]sun, moon, and stars, being bright and sent to do their offices, are obedient.

61 In like manner the lightning when it breaketh forth is easy to be seen; and [*][g]after the same manner the wind bloweth in every country.

62 And when God commandeth the clouds to go over the whole [h]world, they do as they are bidden.

63 And [g]the fire sent from above to consume hills and woods doeth as it is commanded: but these are like unto them neither in shew nor power.

64 Wherefore [i]it is neither to be supposed nor said that they are gods, seeing, they are able neither[j] to judge causes, nor[k] to do good unto men.

65 [l]Knowing therefore that they are no gods, [l]fear them not,

66 For they can neither curse nor bless kings:

67 Neither can they shew signs in the heavens among the heathen, [m]nor shine as the sun, nor give light as the moon.

68 The beasts are better than they: for they can get under a cover and help themselves.

69 [l]It is then by no means manifest unto us that they are gods: [l]therefore fear them not.

70 For as a scarecrow in [n]a garden of cucumbers keepeth nothing: so are their [c]gods of wood, and [d]laid over with silver and gold.

71 And likewise their [c]gods of wood, and [d]laid over with silver and gold, are like to a white thorn in an orchard, that every bird sitteth upon; as also to [o]a dead body, that is cast into the dark.

72 And [l]ye shall know them to be no gods by the [*]bright purple that rotteth upon them: and [q]they themselves afterward shall be eaten, and shall be a reproach in the country.

73 Better therefore is the just man that hath none idols: for he shall be far from reproach.

a 1.1 Comp. Josh. 1. 1. 1 Macc. 1. 1.

b 1.1 See Jer. 32. 12.

c 1.1 Jer. 51. 59.

d 1.2 Comp. ver. 3, 4, 9. 2 Kin. 24. 12. & 25. 27. 2 Chr. 36. 10 with 2 Kin. 25. 8.

d 1.2 Comp. ver. 3, 4, 9. 2 Kin. 24. 12. & 25. 27. 2 Chr. 36. 10 with 2 Kin. 25. 8.

b 1.3 See Jer. 32. 12.

e 1.3 ver. 9. 2 Chr. 36. 8, 9 (Gk.). Comp. Jer. 51. 59–64.

* 1.3 Or, Joacim. 2 Kin. 23. 34 (Gk.).

f 1.4 See Jer. 6. 13.

* 1.5 Or, and vowed vows.

g 1.6 Comp. 1 Cor. 16. 2. 2 Cor. 8. 3. See Rom. 15. 26.

* 1.7 Or, Joacim.

h 1.7 1 Chr. 6. 13 (Gk.). Susanna 2?

i 1.7 So 1 Chr. 6. 12, 13.

k 1.8 2 Kin. 24. 13. 2 Chr. 36. 10.

l 1.8 Esther 8. 9.

m 1.8 Comp. Dan. 5. 3.

n 1.8 2 Kin. 24. 17.

d 1.9 Comp. ver. 3, 4, 9. 2 Kin. 24. 12. & 25. 27. 2 Chr. 36. 10 with 2 Kin. 25. 8.

e 1.9 ver. 9. 2 Chr. 36. 8, 9 (Gk.). Comp. Jer. 51. 59–64.

* 1.9 Or, prisoners. Acts 27. 1, 42.

o 1.10 ver. 6.

p 1.10 Ex. 29. 18.

q 1.10 Ex. 29. 14.

r 1.10 See Ecclus. 50. 8.

* 1.10 Gr. corruptly for mincha, [that is,] a meat offering. Jer. 17. 26. & 41. 5. Dan. 2. 46 in the Gk. Comp. Lev. 2. 1.

s 1.11 See Ezra 6. 10. So 1 Macc. 7. 33.

t 1.11 Dan. 5. 1, 2, &c. & 7. 1. & 8. 1. in the Gk.

u 1.11 See Ecclus. 45. 15.

x 1.12 Ezek. 31. 6. Comp. Dan. 4. 12, 21.

t 1.12 Dan. 5. 1, 2, &c. & 7. 1. & 8. 1. in the Gk.

y 1.12 1 Macc. 10. 60. & 11. 24. So ch. 2. 14.

z 1.14 ver. 1, 3.

a 1.15 Dan. 9. 7. ch. 2. 6. Comp. Neh. 9. 32–37.

b 1.15 See 2 Chr. 32. 21. ch. 2. 6 (Gk.)

i 1.15 ver. 15. ch. 2. 6, 11, 26.

c 1.16 ver. 3, 8.

d 1.17 Dan. 9. 5, 6.

d 1.18 Dan. 9. 5, 6.

e 1.18 Dan. 9. 10. ch. 2. 10 (Gk.).

e 1.18 Dan. 9. 10. ch. 2. 10 (Gk.).

f 1.20 ch. 3. 4 (Gk.).

g 1.20 Deut. 28. 15. ch. 3. 8. So ch. 2. 7. See Dan. 9. 11.

h 1.20 Ecclus. 46. 8. See Ex. 3. 8.

i 1.20 ver. 15. ch. 2. 6, 11, 26.

e 1.21 Dan. 9. 10. ch. 2. 10 (Gk.).

k 1.21 So 2 Chr. 36. 15–17.

l 1.22 2 Esdr. 1. 6 (Lat.).

a 2.1 Dan. 9. 12, 13.

a 2.2 Dan. 9. 12, 13.

b 2.3 Lam. 2. 20. & 4. 10. See Deut. 28. 53.

c 2.4 2 Kings 24. 2.

d 2.4 Isai. 43. 28. ch. 3. 8 in the Gk.

e 2.4 ver. 23. Jer. 25. 38. & 44. 6, 22 in the Gk.

* 2.5 Gr. were beneath, and not above. Deut. 28. 43, 44. See 1 Esdr. 8. 92.

f 2.6 See ch. 1. 15.

o 2.6 ver. 6, 26. ch. 1. 20.

a 2.7 Dan. 9. 12, 13.

g 2.7 So ch. 1. 20.

h 2.8 Dan. 9. 13.

i 2.9 Dan. 9. 14.

k 2.9 See Ezra 9. 15.

i 2.10 Dan. 9. 14.

l 2.10 Dan. 9. 10. ch. 1. 18 (Gk.).

l 2.10 Dan. 9. 10. ch. 1. 18 (Gk.).

m 2.11 Dan. 9. 15.

n 2.11 See Neh. 9. 10.

o 2.11 ver. 6, 26. ch. 1. 20.

m 2.12 Dan. 9. 15.

p 2.12 See Ps. 106. 6.

q 2.13 So Dan. 9. 16.

r 2.13 Jer. 42. 2. So Deut. 28. 62. Song 14.

s 2.14 Dan. 9. 17.

t 2.14 So ch. 1. 12. See Ps. 106. 46.

u 2.15 2 Kin. 19. 19. Isai. 37. 20.

* 2.15 Gr, thy name is called upon Israel. So Dan. 9. 18. Comp. ver. 26

x 2.15 So Dan. 9. 19. Ecclus. 36. 12.

y 2.16 Deut. 26. 15. So Isai. 63. 15.

z 2.16 Dan. 9. 18.

a 2.17 See Ps. 6. 5. So Ecclus. 17. 27, 28.

* 2.17 Gr. spirit, or, life.

b 2.18 So Dan. 9. 18. Comp. Song 16.

b 2.19 So Dan. 9. 18. Comp. Song 16.

c 2.20 Comp. Dan. 9. 6.

e 2.23 See Jer. 7. 34.

ee 2.23 ch. 4. 23 (Gk.).

ee 2.23 ch. 4. 23 (Gk.).

f 2.23 See ver. 4.

g 2.24 ver. 1.

h 2.24 Jer. 8. 1, 2.

h 2.25 Jer. 8. 1, 2.

i 2.25 Jer. 36. 30.

k 2.25 Jer. 27. 13?

l 2.26 Jer. 7. 14. See Jer. 7. 10 marg. Comp. ver. 15 marg.

m 2.26 See ver. 11.

n 2.27 See Wisd. 2. 19.

o 2.29 Lev. 26. 14. Deut. 28. 15, 62.

* 2.29 Gr. this great swarm.

p 2.30 Acts 7. 51. See Ex. 32. 9.

q 2.30 Lev. 26. 39–42.

* 2.30 Or, come to themselves. ch. 3. 7 (Gk.).

r 2.31 So Ex. 7. 5. Ps. 9. 16.

s 2.31 See Jer. 24. 7.

q 2.32 Lev. 26. 39–42.

* 2.33 Gr. back. Comp. Ex. 23. 27 marg.

t 2.34 See Jer. 16. 15.

u 2.35 See Jer. 31. 31.

s 2.35 See Jer. 24. 7.

x 2.35 So Lam. 4. 22.

a 3.1 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

b 3.3 So Ps. 102. 26.

a 3.4 See 2 Cor. 6. 18.

c 3.4 Eph. 2. 1, 5. or comp. ver. 10.

d 3.4 ch. 1. 20 (Gk.).

e 3.7 So Deut. 30. 1.

f 3.7 ch. 2. 30 marg.

g 3.8 See ch. 2. 4.

h 3.8 ch. 1. 20.

i 3.8 Comp. Deut. 28. 44.

c 3.10 Eph. 2. 1, 5. or comp. ver. 10.

j 3.11 See Ps. 28. 1.

k 3.11 Supplied from ver. 19.

l 3.12 Ecclus. 1. 5. So 2 Esdr. 14. 47.

m 3.13 So Ps. 81. 13, 14.

n 3.14 Prov. 15. 30. So Toibt 10. 5.

o 3.15 Job 28. 12, 20.

p 3.16 So Judith 11. 7. See Jer. 27. 6.

q 3.17 Comp. Ezek. 31. 6.

r 3.17 See Mark 10. 24.

s 3.19 So 2 Macc. 5. 13 (Gk.).

k 3.19 Supplied from ver. 19.

t 3.20 ver. 27, 36.

u 3.22 Jer. 49. 7. So Obad. 8, 9.

v 3.22 See 1 Chr. 1. 45.

w 3.23 See 1 Chr. 5. 10. Comp. 1 Kin. 4. 30.

x 3.23 Gen. 37. 36?

v 3.23 See 1 Chr. 1. 45.

* 3.23 Or, expounders.

y 3.26 Ecclus. 16. 7.

z 3.26 Gen. 6. 4.

t 3.27 ver. 27, 36.

a 3.29 Cited generally from Deut. 30. 12, 13. Cited also Rom. 10. 6, 7.

a 3.30 Cited generally from Deut. 30. 12, 13. Cited also Rom. 10. 6, 7.

b 3.30 Job 28. 15–19.

c 3.34 Ecclus. 43. 10.

d 3.34 Comp. Ps. 147. 4.

t 3.36 ver. 27, 36.

e 3.36 See Ecclus. 45. 1.

f 3.37 Prov. 8. 31. So Ecclus. 24. 8. See John 1. 14.

f 3.37 Prov. 8. 31. So Ecclus. 24. 8. See John 1. 14.

* 4.2 Gr. to the shining before the light thereof.

a 4.2 Ecclus. 25. 11. So ver. 24. ch. 5. 3, 9.

b 4.6 Judith 7. 25. See Deut. 32. 30.

c 4.7 Cited from Deut. 32. 17. Cited also 1 Cor. 10. 20.

o 4.8 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

d 4.9 ver. 14, 24 (Gk.).

d 4.10 ver. 14, 24 (Gk.).

o 4.10 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

i 4.11 So ver. 11 Comp. ver. 37.

e 4.12 So Isai. 47. 8, 9.

* 4.13 Or, of his discipline in righteousness.

d 4.14 ver. 14, 24 (Gk.).

d 4.14 ver. 14, 24 (Gk.).

o 4.14 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

f 4.15 See Deut. 28. 49, 50.

f 4.15 See Deut. 28. 49, 50.

g 4.20 So Esther 14. 2.

* 4.20 Or, prosperity. Comp. Esth. 2. 11 marg.

o 4.20 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

* 4.20 Or, in the time of mine affliction. Comp. Ps. 137. 7.

h 4.20 Ps. 116. (Gk.).

o 4.22 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

i 4.23 So ver. 11 Comp. ver. 37.

j 4.23 ch. 2. 23 (Gk.).

d 4.24 ver. 14, 24 (Gk.).

a 4.24 Ecclus. 25. 11. So ver. 24. ch. 5. 3, 9.

o 4.24 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

* 4.26 Or, My darlings. Susanna 31.

k 4.27 ver. 29.

kk 4.28 Ecclus. 51. 13 marg.

l 4.28 See Job 19. 3.

k 4.29 ver. 29.

m 4.30 So Isai. 43. 1. & 45. 4 Or comp. ch. 5. 4.

n 4.33 Comp. Isai. 13. 19–22.

n 4.34 Comp. Isai. 13. 19–22.

o 4.35 ver. 10, 14, 20, 22, 24. ch. 5. 2. So ver. 8.

n 4.35 Comp. Isai. 13. 19–22.

p 4.36 ch. 5. 5. Isai. 60. 4.

p 4.37 ch. 5. 5. Isai. 60. 4.

q 4.37 See Tobit 14. 5.

i 4.37 So ver. 11 Comp. ver. 37.

p 4.37 ch. 5. 5. Isai. 60. 4.

a 5.1 So Esther 15. 1.

b 5.2 Isai. 61. 10.

c 5.2 See ch. 4. 35.

d 5.3 See ch. 4. 2.

e 5.4 1 Tim. 2. 10 (Gk.). Comp. ch. 4. 30.

f 5.5 See ch. 4. 36, 37.

f 5.5 See ch. 4. 36, 37.

g 5.6 Comp. Isai. 66. 20. 1 Esdr. 5. 2. Tobit 14. 5.

h 5.6 Matt. 13. 38.

i 5.7 Isai. 40. 4.

k 5.8 Isai. 41. 19.

d 5.9 See ch. 4. 2.

a 6.2 2 Kin. 24. 12–16. & 25. 11. 2 Chr. 36. 10, 20. Jer. 25. 9.

b 6.3 Comp. 2 Chr. 36. 21.

c 6.4 ver. 30, 39, 50, 55, 57, 70, 71. Ps. 115. 4. & 135. 15. Wisd. 13. 10. 2 Macc. 2. 2. So Isai. 44. 8–10. & 46. 5, 6. Wisd. 14. 8.

d 6.4 ver. 26. Isai. 46. 7. Jer. 10. 5.

o 6.4 Comp. ver. 4, 5.

o 6.5 Comp. ver. 4, 5.

e 6.6 2 Macc. 5. 17, 20. & 6. 14. & 15. 22. See Ecclus. 34. 24.

f 6.7 Ex. 23. 20.

g 6.8 ver. 39, 50, 55, 57, 70, 71. Isai. 30. 22 (Gk.).

h 6.8 Ps. 115. 7. & 135. 16.

* 6.11 Or, which prostitute themselves openly.

i 6.11 Jer. 10. 9.

c 6.11 ver. 30, 39, 50, 55, 57, 70, 71. Ps. 115. 4. & 135. 15. Wisd. 13. 10. 2 Macc. 2. 2. So Isai. 44. 8–10. & 46. 5, 6. Wisd. 14. 8.

j 6.12 ver. 24. See James 5. 2. Comp. ver. 20.

i 6.12 Jer. 10. 9.

k 6.12 ver. 72.

l 6.13 ver. 17.

m 6.15 ver. 18, 57 (Gk.). Ecclus. 36. 26. John 18. 40 (Gk.).

n 6.16 So ver. 23, 29, 65, 69, 72. Comp. ver. 40.

n 6.16 So ver. 23, 29, 65, 69, 72. Comp. ver. 40.

o 6.16 Comp. ver. 4, 5.

l 6.17 ver. 17.

p 6.18 Comp. Jer. 37. 16. & 38. 6.

* 6.18 Or, courts. 1 Macc. 11. 46. See Rev. 11. 2.

q 6.18 Susanna 45. Acts 12. 19 in the Gk.

m 6.18 ver. 18, 57 (Gk.). Ecclus. 36. 26. John 18. 40 (Gk.).

qq 6.20 ver. 55.

* 6.20 Gr. licked.

n 6.23 So ver. 23, 29, 65, 69, 72. Comp. ver. 40.

n 6.23 So ver. 23, 29, 65, 69, 72. Comp. ver. 40.

o 6.23 Comp. ver. 4, 5.

r 6.24 Ecclus. 12. 11.

j 6.24 ver. 24. See James 5. 2. Comp. ver. 20.

* 6.25 Or, any price.

d 6.26 ver. 26. Isai. 46. 7. Jer. 10. 5.

s 6.26 Comp. Wisd. 13. 15, 16.

s 6.27 Comp. Wisd. 13. 15, 16.

t 6.27 1 Sam. 5. 3, 4.

u 6.27 Comp. Isai. 46. 1, 2.

v 6.27 ver. 30.

* 6.27 Or, offerings. Luke 21. 4.

w 6.27 Comp. ver. 32, 71. Or see Jer. 18. 15?

x 6.28 Bel and Drag. 13.

* 6.28 Or, spend.

y 6.28 1 Cor. 7. 31. & 9. 18.

z 6.28 Comp. ver. 33.

a 6.29 Comp. Lev. 12. 4.

aa 6.29 See ver. 16.

aa 6.29 See ver. 16.

b 6.30 ver. 27.

c 6.30 See ver. 4.

d 6.31 Comp. Lev. 21. 4.

e 6.31 Comp. Lev. 21. 5.

f 6.32 So 1 Kin. 18. 26, 28.

g 6.32 See Tobit 4. 17. Comp. ver. 27.

h 6.33 Comp. ver. 28.

hh 6.34 ver. 52.

i 6.35 See Mark 6. 8 marg.

j 6.35 Comp. Wisd. 14. 29

c 6.39 See ver. 4.

k 6.39 See ver. 8.

l 6.39 Isai. 1. 29 (Gk.).

m 6.40 So ver. 44, 56, 64 (Gk.). Comp. ver. 16, 49, 52.

n 6.41 Comp. Wisd. 13. 18.

* 6.41 Or, bid him call upon Bel.

o 6.41 Bel and Drag. 3, &c. See Isai. 46. 1.

* 6.42 Or, sense. See Phil. 1. 9.

p 6.43 Comp. Lev. 19. 29.

q 6.43 Comp. Jer. 7. 18.

m 6.44 So ver. 44, 56, 64 (Gk.). Comp. ver. 16, 49, 52.

r 6.45 See Isai. 40. 19.

m 6.49 So ver. 44, 56, 64 (Gk.). Comp. ver. 16, 49, 52.

s 6.50 See ver. 4.

t 6.50 See ver. 8.

u 6.51 Ps. 115. 4. & 135. 15.

m 6.52 So ver. 44, 56, 64 (Gk.). Comp. ver. 16, 49, 52.

v 6.53 ver. 34.

w 6.53 See Jer. 5. 24.

x 6.54 So ver. 64.

y 6.54 So ver. 36, 38.

s 6.55 See ver. 4.

t 6.55 See ver. 8.

z 6.55 ver. 20.

a 6.56 So ver. 15, 58.

b 6.56 See ver. 40.

c 6.57 See ver. 4.

d 6.57 See ver. 8.

e 6.57 See ver. 15.

a 6.58 So ver. 15, 58.

f 6.59 So Wisd. 13. 11. 2 Tim. 2. 21.

m 6.60 So ver. 60.

* 6.61 Or, the same wind.

g 6.61 Comp. Ps. 148. 8.

h 6.62 See Esther 13. 2.

g 6.63 Comp. Ps. 148. 8.

i 6.64 See ver. 40.

j 6.64 ver. 54.

k 6.64 ver. 36–38.

l 6.65 See ver. 16.

l 6.65 See ver. 16.

m 6.67 So ver. 60.

l 6.69 See ver. 16.

l 6.69 See ver. 16.

n 6.70 Isai. 1. 8.

c 6.70 See ver. 4.

d 6.70 See ver. 8.

c 6.71 See ver. 4.

d 6.71 See ver. 8.

o 6.71 Comp. ver. 27.

l 6.72 See ver. 16.

* 6.72 Or, pq purple and p brightness.

q 6.72 ver. 12.

Daniel

1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

11
12

The Book of Daniel

1

1  In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim king of Judah [*]came Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon unto Jerusalem, and besieged it. 2  And the Lord gave Jehoiakim king of Judah into his hand, with part of the vessels of the house of God: which he carried into the land of Shinar to the house of his god; and he brought the vessels into the treasure house of his god.

3 ¶ And the king spake unto Ashpenaz the master of his eunuchs, that he should bring certain of the children of Israel, and of the king’s seed, and of the princes; 4  Children in whom was no blemish, but well favoured, and skilful in all wisdom, and cunning in knowledge, and understanding science, and such as had ability in them to stand in the king’s palace, and whom they might teach the learning and the tongue of the Chaldeans. 5  And the king appointed them a daily provision of the king’s meat, and of [†]the wine which he drank: so nourishing them three years, that at the end thereof they might stand before the king. 6  Now among these were of the children of Judah, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: 7  Unto whom the prince of the eunuchs gave names: for he gave unto Daniel the name of Belteshazzar; and to Hananiah, of Shadrach; and to Mishael, of Meshach; and to Azariah, of Abed-nego.

8 ¶ But Daniel purposed in his heart that he would not defile himself with the portion of the king’s meat, nor with the wine which he drank: therefore he requested of the prince of the eunuchs that he might not defile himself. 9  Now God had brought Daniel into favour and tender love with the prince of the eunuchs. 10  And the prince of the eunuchs said unto Daniel, I fear my lord the king, who hath appointed your meat and your drink: for why should he see your faces [†]worse liking than the children which are of your [∥]sort? then shall ye make me endanger my head to the king. 11  Then said Daniel to [∥]Melzar, whom the prince of the eunuchs had set over Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, 12  Prove thy servants, I beseech thee, ten days; and let them give [‡]us [†]pulse [†]to eat, and water to drink. 13  Then let our countenances be looked upon before thee, and the countenance of the children that eat of the portion of the king’s meat: and as thou seest, deal with thy servants. 14  So he consented to them in this matter, and proved them ten days. 15  And at the end of ten days their countenances appeared fairer and fatter in flesh than all the children which did eat the portion of the king’s meat. 16  Thus Melzar took away the portion of their meat, and the wine that they should drink; and gave them pulse.

17 ¶ As for these four children, God gave them knowledge and skill in all learning and wisdom: and [∥]Daniel had understanding in all visions and dreams. 18  Now at the end of the days that the king had said he should bring them in, then the prince of the eunuchs brought them in before Nebuchadnezzar. 19  And the king communed with them; and among them all was found none like Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah: therefore stood they before the king. 20  And in all matters of [†]wisdom and understanding, that the king enquired of them, he found them ten times better than all the magicians and astrologers that were in all his realm. 21  And Daniel continued even unto the first year of king Cyrus.

2

1  And in the second year of the reign of Nebuchadnezzar Nebuchadnezzar dreamed dreams, wherewith his spirit was troubled, and his sleep brake from him. 2  Then the king commanded to call the magicians, and the astrologers, and the sorcerers, and the Chaldeans, for to shew the king his dreams. So they came and stood before the king. 3  And the king said unto them, I have dreamed a dream, and my spirit was troubled to know the dream. 4  Then spake the Chaldeans to the king in Syriack, [*]O king, live for ever: tell thy servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation. 5  The king answered and said to the Chaldeans, The thing is gone from me: if ye will not make known unto me the dream, with the interpretation thereof, ye shall be [*][†]cut in pieces, and your houses shall be made a dunghill. 6  But if ye shew the dream, and the interpretation thereof, ye shall receive of me gifts and [∥]rewards and great honour: therefore shew me the dream, and the interpretation thereof. 7  They answered again and said, Let the king tell his servants the dream, and we will shew the interpretation of it. 8  The king answered and said, I know of certainty that ye would [†]gain the time, because ye see the thing is gone from me. 9  But if ye will not make known unto me the dream, there is but one decree for you: for ye have prepared lying and corrupt words to speak before me, till the time be changed: therefore tell me the dream, and I shall know that ye can shew me the interpretation thereof.

10 ¶ The Chaldeans answered before the king, and said, There is not a man upon the earth that can shew the king’s matter: therefore there is no king, lord, nor ruler, that asked such things at any magician, or astrologer, or Chaldean. 11 And it is a rare thing that the king requireth, and there is none other that can shew it before the king, except the gods, whose dwelling is not with flesh. 12  For this cause the king was angry and very furious, and commanded to destroy all the wise men of Babylon. 13  And the decree went forth that the wise men should be slain; and they sought Daniel and his fellows to be slain.

14 ¶ Then Daniel [†]answered with counsel and wisdom to Arioch the [∥][†]captain of the king’s guard, which was gone forth to slay the wise men of Babylon: 15  He answered and said to Arioch the king’s captain, Why is the decree so hasty from the king? Then Arioch made the thing known to Daniel. 16  Then Daniel went in, and desired of the king that he would give him time, and that he would shew the king the interpretation. 17  Then Daniel went to his house, and made the thing known to Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah, his companions: 18  That they would desire mercies [†]of the God of heaven concerning this secret; [∥]that Daniel and his fellows should not perish with the rest of the wise men of Babylon.

19 ¶ Then was the secret revealed unto Daniel in a night vision. Then Daniel blessed the God of heaven. 20  Daniel answered and said, [*]Blessed be the name of God for ever and ever: for wisdom and might are his: 21  And he changeth the times and the seasons: he removeth kings, and setteth up kings: he giveth wisdom unto the wise, and knowledge to them that know understanding: 22  He revealeth the deep and secret things: he knoweth what is in the darkness, and the light dwelleth with him. 23  I thank thee, and praise thee, O thou God of my fathers, who hast given me wisdom and might, and hast made known unto me now what we desired of thee: for thou hast now made known unto us the king’s matter.

24 ¶ Therefore Daniel went in unto Arioch, whom the king had ordained to destroy the wise men of Babylon: he went and said thus unto him; Destroy not the wise men of Babylon: bring me in before the king, and I will shew unto the king the interpretation. 25  Then Arioch brought in Daniel before the king in haste, and said thus unto him, [†]I have found a man of the [†]captives of Judah, that will make known unto the king the interpretation. 26  The king answered and said to Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, Art thou able to make known unto me the dream which I have seen, and the interpretation thereof? 27  Daniel answered in the presence of the king, and said, The secret which the king hath demanded cannot the wise men, the astrologers, the magicians, the soothsayers, shew unto the king; 28  But there is a God in heaven that revealeth secrets, and [†]maketh known to the king Nebuchadnezzar what shall be in the latter days. Thy dream, and the visions of thy head upon thy bed, are these; 29  As for thee, O king, thy thoughts [†]came into thy mind upon thy bed, what should come to pass hereafter: and he that revealeth secrets maketh known to thee what shall come to pass. 30  But as for me, this secret is not revealed to me for any wisdom that I have more than any living, but for their sakes that shall make known the interpretation to the king, and that thou mightest know the thoughts of thy heart.

31 ¶ Thou, O king, [†]sawest, and behold a great image. This great image, whose brightness was excellent, stood before thee; and the form thereof was terrible. 32  This image’s head was of fine gold, his breast and his arms of silver, his belly and his [∥]thighs of brass, 33  His legs of iron, his feet part of iron and part of clay. 34  Thou sawest till that a stone was cut out [∥]without hands, which smote the image upon his feet that were of iron and clay, and brake them to pieces. 35  Then was the iron, the clay, the brass, the silver, and the gold, broken to pieces together, and became like the chaff of the summer threshingfloors; and the wind carried them away, that no place was found for them: and the stone that smote the image became a great mountain, and filled the whole earth.

36 ¶ This is the dream; and we will tell the interpretation thereof before the king. 37  Thou, O king, art a king of kings: for the God of heaven hath given thee a kingdom, power, and strength, and glory. 38  And wheresoever the children of men dwell, the beasts of the field and the fowls of the heaven hath he given into thine hand, and hath made thee ruler over them all. Thou art this head of gold. 39  And after thee shall arise another kingdom inferior to thee, and another third kingdom of brass, which shall bear rule over all the earth. 40  And the fourth kingdom shall be strong as iron: forasmuch as iron breaketh in pieces and subdueth all things: and as iron that breaketh all these, shall it break in pieces and bruise. 41  And whereas thou sawest the feet and toes, part of potters’ clay, and part of iron, the kingdom shall be divided; but there shall be in it of the strength of the iron, forasmuch as thou sawest the iron mixed with miry clay. 42 And as the toes of the feet were part of iron, and part of clay, so the kingdom shall be partly strong, and partly [∥]broken. 43  And whereas thou sawest iron mixed with miry clay, they shall mingle themselves with the seed of men: but they shall not cleave [†]one to another, even as iron is not mixed with clay. 44  And in [†]the days of these kings shall the God of heaven set up a kingdom, [*]which shall never be destroyed: and the [†]kingdom shall not be left to other people, but it shall break in pieces and consume all these kingdoms, and it shall stand for ever. 45  Forasmuch as thou sawest that the stone was cut out of the mountain [∥]without hands, and that it brake in pieces the iron, the brass, the clay, the silver, and the gold; the great God hath made known to the king what shall come to pass [†]hereafter: and the dream is certain, and the interpretation thereof sure.

46 ¶ Then the king Nebuchadnezzar fell upon his face, and worshipped Daniel, and commanded that they should offer an oblation and sweet odours unto him. 47  The king answered unto Daniel, and said, Of a truth it is, that your God is a God of gods, and a Lord of kings, and a revealer of secrets, seeing thou couldest reveal this secret. 48  Then the king made Daniel a great man, and gave him many great gifts, and made him ruler over the whole province of Babylon, and [*]chief of the governors over all the wise men of Babylon. 49  Then Daniel requested of the king, and he set Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, over the affairs of the province of Babylon: but Daniel sat in the gate of the king.

3

1  Nebuchadnezzar the king made an image of gold, whose height was threescore cubits, and the breadth thereof six cubits: he set it up in the plain of Dura, in the province of Babylon. 2  Then Nebuchadnezzar the king sent to gather together the princes, the governors, and the captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, to come to the dedication of the image which Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up. 3  Then the princes, the governors, and captains, the judges, the treasurers, the counsellors, the sheriffs, and all the rulers of the provinces, were gathered together unto the dedication of the image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up; and they stood before the image that Nebuchadnezzar had set up. 4  Then an herald cried [†]aloud, To you [†]it is commanded, O people, nations, and languages, 5  That at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, [∥][†]dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, ye fall down and worship the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king hath set up: 6  And whoso falleth not down and worshippeth shall the same hour be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace. 7  Therefore at that time, when all the people heard the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and all kinds of musick, all the people, the nations, and the languages, fell down and worshipped the golden image that Nebuchadnezzar the king had set up.

8 ¶ Wherefore at that time certain Chaldeans came near, and accused the Jews. 9  They spake and said to the king Nebuchadnezzar, O king, live for ever. 10  Thou, O king, hast made a decree, that every man that shall hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, shall fall down and worship the golden image: 11  And whoso falleth not down and worshippeth, that he should be cast into the midst of a burning fiery furnace. 12  There are certain Jews whom thou hast set over the affairs of the province of Babylon, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego; these men, O king, [†]have not regarded thee: they serve not thy gods, nor worship the golden image which thou hast set up.

13 ¶ Then Nebuchadnezzar in his rage and fury commanded to bring Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. Then they brought these men before the king. 14  Nebuchadnezzar spake and said unto them, Is it [∥]true, O Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, do not ye serve my gods, nor worship the golden image which I have set up? 15  Now if ye be ready that at what time ye hear the sound of the cornet, flute, harp, sackbut, psaltery, and dulcimer, and all kinds of musick, ye fall down and worship the image which I have made; well: but if ye worship not, ye shall be cast the same hour into the midst of a [‡]burning fiery furnace; and who is that God that shall deliver you out of my hands? 16  Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, answered and said to the king, O Nebuchadnezzar, we are not careful to answer thee in this matter. 17  If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace, and he will deliver us out of thine hand, O king. 18  But if not, be it known unto thee, O king, that we will not serve thy gods, nor worship [‡]the golden image which thou hast set up.

19 ¶ Then was Nebuchadnezzar [†]full of fury, and the form of his visage was changed against Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego: therefore he spake, and commanded that they should heat the furnace one seven times more than it was wont to be heated. 20  And he commanded the [†]most mighty men that were in his army to bind Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, and to cast them into the burning fiery furnace. 21  Then these men were bound in their [∥]coats, their hosen, and their [∥]hats, and their other garments, and were cast into the midst of the burning fiery furnace. 22  Therefore because the king’s [†]commandment was urgent, and the furnace exceeding hot, the [∥]flame of the fire slew those men that took up Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego. 23  And these three men, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, fell down bound into the midst of the burning fiery furnace. 24  Then Nebuchadnezzar the king was astonied, and rose up in haste, and spake, and said unto his [∥]counsellors, Did not we cast three men bound into the midst of the fire? They answered and said unto the king, True, O king. 25  He answered and said, Lo, I see four men loose, walking in the midst of the fire, and [†]they have no hurt; and the form of the fourth is like the Son of God.

26 ¶ Then Nebuchadnezzar came near to the [†]mouth of the burning fiery furnace, and spake, and said, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, ye servants of the most high God, come forth, and come hither. Then Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, came forth of the midst of the fire. 27  And the princes, governors, and captains, and the king’s counsellors, being gathered together, saw these men, upon whose bodies the fire had no power, nor was an hair of their head singed, neither were their coats changed, nor the smell of fire had passed on them.

28  Then Nebuchadnezzar spake, and said, Blessed be the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, who hath sent his angel, and delivered his servants that trusted in him, and have changed the king’s word, and yielded their bodies, that they might not serve nor worship any god, except their own God. 29  Therefore [†]I make a decree, That every people, nation, and language, which speak [†]any thing amiss against the God of Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, shall be [*][†]cut in pieces, and their houses shall be made a dunghill: because there is no other God that can deliver after this sort. 30  Then the king [†]promoted Shadrach, Meshach, and Abed-nego, in the province of Babylon.

4

1  Nebuchadnezzar the king, unto all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth; Peace be multiplied unto you. 2 [†] I thought it good to shew the signs and wonders that the high God hath wrought toward me. 3  How great are his signs! and how mighty are his wonders! his kingdom is [*]an everlasting kingdom, and his dominion is from generation to generation.

4 ¶ I Nebuchadnezzar was at rest in mine house, and flourishing in my palace: 5  I saw a dream which made me afraid, and the thoughts upon my bed and the visions of my head troubled me. 6  Therefore made I a decree to bring in all the wise men of Babylon before me, that they might make known unto me the interpretation of the dream. 7  Then came in the magicians, the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers: and I told the dream before them; but they did not make known unto me the interpretation thereof.

8 ¶ But at the last Daniel came in before me, whose name was Belteshazzar, according to the name of my god, and in whom is the spirit of the holy gods: and before him I told the dream, saying, 9  O Belteshazzar, [*]master of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the holy gods is in thee, and no secret troubleth thee, tell me the visions of my dream that I have seen, and the interpretation thereof. 10 Thus were the visions of mine head in my bed; [†]I saw, and behold a tree in the midst of the earth, and the height thereof was great. 11  The tree grew, and was strong, and the height thereof reached unto heaven, and the sight thereof to the end of all the earth: 12  The leaves thereof were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all: the beasts of the field had shadow under it, and the fowls of the heaven dwelt in the boughs thereof, and all flesh was fed of it. 13  I saw in the visions of my head upon my bed, and, behold, a watcher and an holy one came down from heaven; 14  He cried [†]aloud, and said thus, Hew down the tree, and cut off his branches, shake off his leaves, and scatter his fruit: let the beasts get away from under it, and the fowls from his branches: 15  Nevertheless leave the stump of his roots in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth: 16  Let his heart be changed from man’s, and let a beast’s heart be given unto him; and let seven times pass over him. 17  This matter is by the decree of the watchers, and the demand by the word of the holy ones: to the intent that the living may know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will, and setteth up over it the basest of men. 18  This dream I king Nebuchadnezzar have seen. Now thou, O Belteshazzar, declare the interpretation thereof, forasmuch as all the wise men of my kingdom are not able to make known unto me the interpretation: but thou art able; for the spirit of the holy gods is in thee.

19 ¶ Then Daniel, whose name was Belteshazzar, was astonied for one hour, and his thoughts troubled him. The king spake, and said, Belteshazzar, let not the dream, or the interpretation thereof, trouble thee. Belteshazzar answered and said, My lord, the dream be to them that hate thee, and the interpretation thereof to thine enemies. 20  The tree that thou sawest, which grew, and was strong, whose height reached unto the heaven, and the sight thereof to all the earth; 21  Whose leaves were fair, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all; under which the beasts of the field dwelt, and upon whose branches the fowls of the heaven had their habitation: 22 It is thou, O king, that art grown and become strong: for thy greatness is grown, and reacheth unto heaven, and thy dominion to the end of the earth. 23  And whereas the king saw a watcher and an holy one coming down from heaven, and saying, Hew the tree down, and destroy it; yet leave the stump of the roots thereof in the earth, even with a band of iron and brass, in the tender grass of the field; and let it be wet with the dew of heaven, and let his portion be with the beasts of the field, till seven times pass over him; 24  This is the interpretation, O king, and this is the decree of the most High, which is come upon my lord the king: 25  That they shall [*]drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field, and they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and they shall wet thee with the dew of heaven, and seven times shall pass over thee, till thou know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will. 26  And whereas they commanded to leave the stump of the tree roots; thy kingdom shall be sure unto thee, after that thou shalt have known that the heavens do rule. 27  Wherefore, O king, let my counsel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy sins by righteousness, and thine iniquities by shewing mercy to the poor; if it may be [∥]a lengthening of thy tranquillity.

28 ¶ All this came upon the king Nebuchadnezzar. 29  At the end of twelve months he walked [∥]in the palace of the kingdom of Babylon. 30  The king spake, and said, Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for the house of the kingdom by the might of my power, and for the honour of my majesty? 31  While the word was in the king’s mouth, there fell a voice from heaven, saying, O king Nebuchadnezzar, to thee it is spoken; The kingdom is departed from thee. 32  And they shall drive thee from men, and thy dwelling shall be with the beasts of the field: they shall make thee to eat grass as oxen, and seven times shall pass over thee, until thou know that the most High ruleth in the kingdom of men, and giveth it to whomsoever he will. 33  The same hour was the thing fulfilled upon Nebuchadnezzar: and he was driven from men, and did eat grass as oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven, till his hairs were grown like eagles’ feathers, and his nails like birds’ claws.

34  And at the end of the days I Nebuchadnezzar lifted up mine eyes unto heaven, and mine understanding returned unto me, and I blessed the most High, and I praised and honoured him that liveth for ever, whose dominion is [*]an everlasting dominion, and his kingdom is from generation to generation: 35  And all the inhabitants of the earth are reputed as nothing: and he doeth according to his will in the army of heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth: and none can stay his hand, or say unto him, [*]What doest thou? 36  At the same time my reason returned unto me; and for the glory of my kingdom, mine honour and brightness returned unto me; and my counsellors and my lords sought unto me; and I was established in my kingdom, and excellent majesty was added unto me. 37  Now I Nebuchadnezzar praise and extol and honour the King of heaven, all whose works are truth, and his ways judgment: and those that walk in pride he is able to abase.

5

1  Belshazzar the king made a great feast to a thousand of his lords, and drank wine before the thousand. 2  Belshazzar, whiles he tasted the wine, commanded to bring the golden and silver vessels which his father Nebuchadnezzar had [†]taken out of the temple which was in Jerusalem; that the king, and his princes, his wives, and his concubines, might drink therein. 3  Then they brought the golden vessels that were taken out of the temple of the house of God which was at Jerusalem; and the king, and his princes, his wives, and his concubines, drank in them. 4  They drank wine, and praised the gods of gold, and of silver, of brass, of iron, of wood, and of stone.

5 ¶ In the same hour came forth fingers of a man’s hand, and wrote over against the candlestick upon the plaister of the wall of the king’s palace: and the king saw the part of the hand that wrote. 6  Then the king’s [†]countenance [†]was changed, and his thoughts troubled him, so that the [∥][†]joints of his loins were loosed, and his knees smote one against another. 7  The king cried [†]aloud to bring in the astrologers, the Chaldeans, and the soothsayers. And the king spake, and said to the wise men of Babylon, Whosoever shall read this writing, and shew me the interpretation thereof, shall be clothed with [∥]scarlet, and have a chain of gold about his neck, and shall be the third ruler in the kingdom. 8  Then came in all the king’s wise men: but they could not read the writing, nor make known to the king the interpretation thereof. 9  Then was king Belshazzar greatly troubled, and his [†]countenance was changed in him, and his lords were astonied.

10 ¶ Now the queen, by reason of the words of the king and his lords, came into the banquet house: and the queen spake and said, O king, live for ever: let not thy thoughts trouble thee, nor let thy countenance be changed: 11 [*] There is a man in thy kingdom, in whom is the spirit of the holy gods; and in the days of thy [∥]father light and understanding and wisdom, like the wisdom of the gods, was found in him; whom the king Nebuchadnezzar thy [∥]father, the king, I say, thy father, made [*]master of the magicians, astrologers, Chaldeans, and soothsayers; 12  Forasmuch as an excellent spirit, and knowledge, and understanding, [∥]interpreting of dreams, and shewing of hard sentences, and [∥]dissolving of [†]doubts, were found in the same Daniel, whom the king named Belteshazzar: now let Daniel be called, and he will shew the interpretation. 13  Then was Daniel brought in before the king. And the king spake and said unto Daniel, Art thou that Daniel, which art of the children of the captivity of Judah, whom the king my [∥]father brought out of Jewry? 14  I have even heard of thee, that the spirit of the gods is in thee, and that light and understanding and excellent wisdom is found in thee. 15  And now the wise men, the astrologers, have been brought in before me, that they should read this writing, and make known unto me the interpretation thereof: but they could not shew the interpretation of the thing: 16  And I have heard of thee, that thou canst [†]make interpretations, and dissolve doubts: now if thou canst read the writing, and make known to me the interpretation thereof, thou shalt be clothed with scarlet, and have a chain of gold about thy neck, and shalt be the third ruler in the kingdom.

17 ¶ Then Daniel answered and said before the king, Let thy gifts be to thyself, and give thy [∥]rewards to another; yet I will read the writing unto the king, and make known to him the interpretation. 18  O thou king, the most high God gave Nebuchadnezzar thy father a kingdom, and majesty, and glory, and honour: 19  And for the majesty that he gave him, all people, nations, and languages, trembled and feared before him: whom he would he slew; and whom he would he kept alive; and whom he would he set up; and whom he would he put down. 20  But when his heart was lifted up, and his mind hardened [∥]in pride, he was [†]deposed from his kingly throne, and they took his glory from him: 21  And he was [*]driven from the sons of men; and [∥]his heart was made like the beasts, and his dwelling was with the wild asses: they fed him with grass like oxen, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven; till he knew that the most high God ruled in the kingdom of men, and that he appointeth over it whomsoever he will. 22  And thou his son, O Belshazzar, hast not humbled thine heart, though thou knewest all this; 23  But hast lifted up thyself against the Lord of heaven; and they have brought the vessels of his house before thee, and thou, and thy lords, thy wives, and thy concubines, have drunk wine in them; and thou hast praised the gods of silver, and gold, of brass, iron, wood, and stone, which see not, nor hear, nor know: and the God in whose hand thy breath is, and whose are all thy ways, hast thou not glorified: 24  Then was the part of the hand sent from him; and this writing was written.

25 ¶ And this is the writing that was written, MENE, MENE, TEKEL, UPHARSIN. 26  This is the interpretation of the thing: MENE; God hath numbered thy kingdom, and finished it. 27  TEKEL; Thou art weighed in the balances, and art found wanting. 28  PERES; Thy kingdom is divided, and given to the Medes and Persians. 29  Then commanded Belshazzar, and they clothed Daniel with scarlet, and put a chain of gold about his neck, and made a proclamation concerning him, that he should be the third ruler in the kingdom.

30 ¶ In that night was Belshazzar the king of the Chaldeans slain. 31  And Darius the Median took the kingdom, [†]being [∥]about threescore and two years old.

6

1  It pleased Darius to set over the kingdom an hundred and twenty princes, which should be over the whole kingdom; 2  And over these three presidents; of whom Daniel was first: that the princes might give accounts unto them, and the king should have no damage. 3  Then this Daniel was preferred above the presidents and princes, because an excellent spirit was in him; and the king thought to set him over the whole realm.

4 ¶ Then the presidents and princes sought to find occasion against Daniel concerning the kingdom; but they could find none occasion nor fault; forasmuch as he was faithful, neither was there any error or fault found in him. 5  Then said these men, We shall not find any occasion against this Daniel, except we find it against him concerning the law of his God.

6  Then these presidents and princes [∥]assembled together to the king, and said thus unto him, King Darius, live for ever. 7  All the presidents of the kingdom, the governors, and the princes, the counsellors, and the captains, have consulted together to establish a royal statute, and to make a firm [∥]decree, that whosoever shall ask a petition of any God or man for thirty days, save of thee, O king, he shall be cast into the den of lions. 8  Now, O king, establish the decree, and sign the writing, that it be not changed, according to the [*]law of the Medes and Persians, which [†]altereth not. 9  Wherefore king Darius signed the writing and the decree.

10 ¶ Now when Daniel knew that the writing was signed, he went into his house; and his windows being open in his chamber [*]toward Jerusalem, he kneeled upon his knees [*]three times a day, and prayed, and gave thanks before his God, as he did aforetime.

11  Then these men assembled, and found Daniel praying and making supplication before his God. 12  Then they came near, and spake before the king concerning the king’s decree; Hast thou not signed a decree, that every man that shall ask a petition of any God or man within thirty days, save of thee, O king, shall be cast into the den of lions? The king answered and said, The thing is true, according to the law of the Medes and Persians, which altereth not. 13  Then answered they and said before the king, That Daniel, which is of the [‡]children of the captivity of Judah, regardeth not thee, O king, nor the decree that thou hast signed, but maketh his petition three times a day. 14  Then the king, when he heard these words, was sore displeased with himself, and set his heart on Daniel to deliver him: and he laboured till the going down of the sun to deliver him. 15  Then these men assembled unto the king, and said unto the king, Know, O king, that the law of the Medes and Persians is, That no decree nor statute which the king establisheth may be changed. 16  Then the king commanded, and they brought Daniel, and cast him into the den of lions. Now the king spake and said unto Daniel, Thy God whom thou servest continually, he will deliver thee. 17  And a stone was brought, and laid upon the mouth of the den; and the king sealed it with his own signet, and with the signet of his lords; that the purpose might not be changed concerning Daniel.

18 ¶ Then the king went to his palace, and passed the night fasting: neither were [∥]instruments of musick brought before him: and his sleep went from him. 19  Then the king arose very early in the morning, and went in haste unto the den of lions. 20  And when he came to the den, he cried with a lamentable voice unto Daniel: and the king spake and said to Daniel, O Daniel, servant of the living God, is thy God, whom thou servest continually, able to deliver thee from the lions? 21  Then said Daniel unto the king, O king, live for ever. 22  My God hath sent his angel, and hath shut the lions’ mouths, that they have not hurt me: forasmuch as before him innocency was found in me; and also before thee, O king, have I done no hurt. 23  Then was the king exceeding glad for him, and commanded that they should take Daniel up out of the den. So Daniel was taken up out of the den, and no manner of hurt was found upon him, because he believed in his God.

24 ¶ And the king commanded, and they brought those men which had accused Daniel, and they cast them into the den of lions, them, their children, and their wives; and the lions had the mastery of them, and brake all their bones in pieces or ever they came at the bottom of the den.

25 ¶ Then king Darius wrote unto all people, nations, and languages, that dwell in all the earth; Peace be multiplied unto you. 26  I make a decree, That in every dominion of my kingdom men tremble and fear before the God of Daniel: for he is the living God, and stedfast for ever, and his kingdom that which shall not be [*]destroyed, and his dominion shall be even unto the end. 27  He delivereth and rescueth, and he worketh signs and wonders in heaven and in earth, who hath delivered Daniel from the [†]power of the lions. 28  So this Daniel prospered in the reign of Darius, and in the reign of [*]Cyrus the Persian.

7

1  In the first year of Belshazzar king of Babylon Daniel [†]had a dream and visions of his head upon his bed: then he wrote the dream, and told the sum of the [∥]matters. 2  Daniel spake and said, I saw in my vision by night, and, behold, the four winds of the heaven strove upon the great sea. 3  And four great beasts came up from the sea, diverse one from another. 4  The first was like a lion, and had eagle’s wings: I beheld till the wings thereof were plucked, [∥]and it was lifted up from the earth, and made stand upon the feet as a man, and a man’s heart was given to it. 5  And behold another beast, a second, like to a bear, and [∥]it raised up itself on one side, and it had three ribs in the mouth of it between the teeth of it: and they said thus unto it, Arise, devour much flesh. 6  After this I beheld, and lo another, like a leopard, which had upon the back of it four wings of a fowl; the beast had also four heads; and dominion was given to it. 7  After this I saw in the night visions, and behold a fourth beast, dreadful and terrible, and strong exceedingly; and it had great iron teeth: it devoured and brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with the feet of it: and it was diverse from all the beasts that were before it; and it had ten horns. 8  I considered the horns, and, behold, there came up among them another little horn, before whom there were three of the first horns plucked up by the roots: and, behold, in this horn were eyes like the eyes of man, and a mouth speaking great things.

9 ¶ I beheld till the thrones were cast down, and the Ancient of days did sit, whose garment was white as snow, and the hair of his head like the pure wool: his throne was like the fiery flame, and his wheels as burning fire. 10  A fiery stream issued and came forth from before him: [*]thousand thousands ministered unto him, and ten thousand times ten thousand stood before him: the judgment was set, and the [*]books were opened. 11  I beheld then because of the voice of the great words which the horn spake: I beheld even till the beast was slain, and his body destroyed, and given to the burning flame. 12  As concerning the rest of the beasts, they had their dominion taken away: yet [†]their lives were prolonged for a season and time. 13  I saw in the night visions, and, behold, one like the Son of man came with the clouds of heaven, and came to the Ancient of days, and they brought him near before him. 14  And there was given him dominion, and glory, and a kingdom, that all people, nations, and languages, should serve him: his dominion is [*]an everlasting dominion, which shall not pass away, and his kingdom that which shall not be destroyed.

15 ¶ I Daniel was grieved in my spirit in the midst of my [†]body, and the visions of my head troubled me. 16  I came near unto one of them that stood by, and asked him the truth of all this. So he told me, and made me know the interpretation of the things. 17  These great beasts, which are four, are four kings, which shall arise out of the earth. 18  But the saints of the [†]most High shall take the kingdom, and possess the kingdom for ever, even for ever and ever. 19  Then I would know the truth of the fourth beast, which was diverse [†]from all the others, exceeding dreadful, whose teeth were of iron, and his nails of brass; which devoured, brake in pieces, and stamped the residue with his feet; 20  And of the ten horns that were in his head, and of the other which came up, and before whom three fell; even of that horn that had eyes, and a mouth that spake very great things, whose look was more stout than his fellows. 21  I beheld, and the same horn made war with the saints, and prevailed against them; 22  Until the Ancient of days came, and judgment was given to the saints of the most High; and the time came that the saints possessed the kingdom. 23  Thus he said, The fourth beast shall be the fourth kingdom upon earth, which shall be diverse from all kingdoms, and shall devour the whole earth, and shall tread it down, and break it in pieces. 24  And the ten horns out of this kingdom are ten kings that shall arise: and another shall rise after them; and he shall be diverse from the first, and he shall subdue three kings. 25  And he shall speak great words against the most High, and shall wear out the saints of the most High, and think to change times and laws: and they shall be given into his hand until a time and times and the dividing of time. 26  But the judgment shall sit, and they shall take away his dominion, to consume and to destroy it unto the end. 27  And the [*]kingdom and dominion, and the greatness of the kingdom under the whole heaven, shall be given to the people of the saints of the most High, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and all [∥]dominions shall serve and obey him. 28  Hitherto is the end of the matter. As for me Daniel, my cogitations much troubled me, and my countenance changed in me: but I kept the matter in my heart.

8

1  In the third year of the reign of king Belshazzar a vision appeared unto me, even unto me Daniel, after that which appeared unto me at the first. 2  And I saw in a vision; and it came to pass, when I saw, that I was at Shushan in the palace, which is in the province of Elam; and I saw in a vision, and I was by the river of Ulai. 3  Then I lifted up mine eyes, and saw, and, behold, there stood before the river a ram which had two horns: and the two horns were high; but one was higher than [†]the other, and the higher came up last. 4  I saw the ram pushing westward, and northward, and southward; so that no beasts might stand before him, neither was there any that could deliver out of his hand; but he did according to his will, and became great. 5  And as I was considering, behold, an he goat came from the west on the face of the whole earth, and [∥]touched not the ground: and the goat had [†]a notable horn between his eyes. 6  And he came to the ram that had two horns, which I had seen standing before the river, and ran unto him in the fury of his power. 7  And I saw him come close unto the ram, and he was moved with choler against him, and smote the ram, and brake his two horns: and there was no power in the ram to stand before him, but he cast him down to the ground, and stamped upon him: and there was none that could deliver the ram out of his hand. 8  Therefore the he goat waxed very great: and when he was strong, the great horn was broken; and for it came up four notable ones [*]toward the four winds of heaven. 9  And out of one of them came forth a little horn, which waxed exceeding great, toward the south, and toward the east, and toward the [*]pleasant land. 10  And it waxed great, even [∥]to the host of heaven; and it cast down some of the host and of the stars to the ground, and stamped upon them. 11  Yea, he magnified himself even [∥]to the prince of the host, and [∥]by him the daily sacrifice was taken away, and the place of his sanctuary was cast down. 12  And [∥]an host was given him against the daily sacrifice by reason of transgression, and it cast down the truth to the ground; and it practised, and prospered.

13 ¶ Then I heard one saint speaking, and another saint said unto [∥][†]that certain saint which spake, How long shall be the vision concerning the daily sacrifice, and the transgression [∥]of desolation, to give both the sanctuary and the host to be trodden under foot? 14  And he said unto me, Unto two thousand and three hundred [†]days; then shall the sanctuary be [†]cleansed.

15 ¶ And it came to pass, when I, even I Daniel, had seen the vision, and sought for the meaning, then, behold, there stood before me as the appearance of a man. 16  And I heard a man’s voice between the banks of Ulai, which called, and said, [*]Gabriel, make this man to understand the vision. 17  So he came near where I stood: and when he came, I was afraid, and fell upon my face: but he said unto me, Understand, O son of man: for at the time of the end shall be the vision. 18  Now as he was speaking with me, I was in a deep sleep on my face toward the ground: but he touched me, and [†]set me upright. 19  And he said, Behold, I will make thee know what shall be in the last end of the indignation: for at the time appointed the end shall be. 20  The ram which thou sawest having two horns are the kings of Media and Persia. 21  And the rough goat is the king of Grecia: and the great horn that is between his eyes is the first king. 22  Now that being broken, whereas four stood up for it, four kingdoms shall stand up out of the nation, but not in his power. 23  And in the latter time of their kingdom, when the transgressors [†]are come to the full, a king of fierce countenance, and understanding dark sentences, shall stand up. 24  And his power shall be mighty, but not by his own power: and he shall destroy wonderfully, and shall prosper, and practise, and shall destroy the mighty and the [†]holy people. 25  And through his policy also he shall cause craft to prosper in his hand; and he shall magnify himself in his heart, and by [∥]peace shall destroy many: he shall also stand up against the Prince of princes; but he shall be [*]broken without hand. 26  And the vision of the evening and the morning which was told is true: wherefore shut thou up the vision; for it shall be for many days. 27  And I Daniel fainted, and was sick certain days; afterward I rose up, and did the king’s business; and I was astonished at the vision, but none understood it.

9

1  In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus, of the seed of the Medes, [∥]which was made king over the realm of the Chaldeans; 2  In the first year of his reign I Daniel understood by books the number of the years, whereof the word of the LORD came to [*]Jeremiah the prophet, that he would accomplish seventy years in the desolations of Jerusalem.

3 ¶ And I set my face unto the Lord God, to seek by prayer and supplications, with fasting, and sackcloth, and ashes:

4  And I prayed unto the LORD my God, and made my confession, and said, O [*]Lord, the great and dreadful God, keeping the covenant and mercy to them that love him, and to them that keep his commandments; 5 [*] We have sinned, and have committed iniquity, and have done wickedly, and have rebelled, even by departing from thy precepts and from thy judgments: 6  Neither have we hearkened unto thy servants the prophets, which spake in thy name to our kings, our princes, and our fathers, and to all the people of the land. 7  O Lord, righteousness [∥]belongeth unto thee, but unto us confusion of faces, as at this day; to the men of Judah, and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and unto all Israel, that are near, and that are far off, through all the countries whither thou hast driven them, because of their trespass that they have trespassed against thee. 8  O Lord, [*]to us belongeth confusion of face, to our kings, to our princes, and to our fathers, because we have sinned against thee. 9  To the Lord our God belong mercies and forgivenesses, though we have rebelled against him; 10  Neither have we obeyed the voice of the LORD our God, to walk in his laws, which he set before us by his servants the prophets. 11  Yea, all Israel have transgressed thy law, even by departing, that they might not obey thy voice; therefore the curse is poured upon us, and the oath that is written in the [*]law of Moses the servant of God, because we have sinned against him. 12  And he hath confirmed his words, which he spake against us, and against our judges that judged us, by bringing upon us a great evil: for under the whole heaven hath not been done as hath been done upon Jerusalem. 13 As [*]it is written in the law of Moses, all this evil is come upon us: yet [†]made we not our prayer before the LORD our God, that we might turn from our iniquities, and understand thy truth. 14  Therefore hath the LORD watched upon the evil, and brought it upon us: for the LORD our God is righteous in all his works which he doeth: for we obeyed not his voice. 15  And now, O Lord our God, that hast brought thy people forth out of the land of Egypt with a mighty hand, and hast [†]gotten thee [*]renown, as at this day; we have sinned, we have done wickedly.

16 ¶ O Lord, according to all thy righteousness, I beseech thee, let thine anger and thy fury be turned away from thy city Jerusalem, thy holy mountain: because for our sins, and for the iniquities of our fathers, Jerusalem and thy people are become a reproach to all that are about us. 17  Now therefore, O our God, hear the prayer of thy servant, and his supplications, and cause thy face to shine upon thy sanctuary that is desolate, for the Lord’s sake. 18  O my God, incline thine ear, and hear; open thine eyes, and behold our desolations, and the city [†]which is called by thy name: for we do not [†]present our supplications before thee for our righteousnesses, but for thy great mercies. 19  O Lord, hear; O Lord, forgive; O Lord, hearken and do; defer not, for thine own sake, O my God: for thy city and thy people are called by thy name.

20 ¶ And whiles I was speaking, and praying, and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel, and presenting my supplication before the LORD my God for the holy mountain of my God; 21 Yea, whiles I was speaking in prayer, even the man [*]Gabriel, whom I had seen in the vision at the beginning, being caused to fly [†]swiftly, touched me about the time of the evening oblation. 22  And he informed me, and talked with me, and said, O Daniel, I am now come forth [†]to give thee skill and understanding. 23  At the beginning of thy supplications the [†]commandment came forth, and I am come to shew thee; for thou art [†]greatly beloved: therefore understand the matter, and consider the vision. 24  Seventy weeks are determined upon thy people and upon thy holy city, [∥]to finish the transgression, and [∥]to make an end of sins, and to make reconciliation for iniquity, and to bring in everlasting righteousness, and to seal up the vision and [†]prophecy, and to anoint the most Holy. 25  Know therefore and understand, that from the going forth of the commandment to restore and to build Jerusalem unto the Messiah the Prince shall be seven weeks, and threescore and two weeks: the street [†]shall be built again, and the [∥]wall, even [†]in troublous times. 26  And after threescore and two weeks shall Messiah be cut off, [∥]but not for himself: and the people of the prince that shall come shall destroy the city and the sanctuary; and the end thereof shall be with a flood, and unto the end of the war [∥]desolations are determined. 27  And he shall confirm the covenant with many for one week: and in the midst of the week he shall cause the sacrifice and the oblation to cease, and [∥]for the overspreading of [*]abominations he shall make it desolate, even until the consummation, and that determined shall be poured upon the desolate.

10

1  In the third year of Cyrus king of Persia a thing was revealed unto Daniel, whose name was called Belteshazzar; and the thing was true, but the time appointed was [†]long: and he understood the thing, and had understanding of the vision. 2  In those days I Daniel was mourning three [†]full weeks. 3  I ate no [†]pleasant bread, neither came flesh nor wine in my mouth, neither did I anoint myself at all, till three whole weeks were fulfilled. 4  And in the four and twentieth day of the first month, as I was by the side of the great river, which is [*]Hiddekel; 5  Then I lifted up mine eyes, and looked, and behold [†]a certain man clothed in linen, whose loins were [*]girded with fine gold of Uphaz: 6  His body also was like the beryl, and his face as the appearance of lightning, and his eyes as lamps of fire, and his arms and his feet like in colour to polished brass, and the voice of his words like the voice of a multitude. 7  And I Daniel alone saw the vision: for the men that were with me saw not the vision; but a great quaking fell upon them, so that they fled to hide themselves. 8  Therefore I was left alone, and saw this great vision, and there remained no strength in me: for my [∥][*]comeliness was turned in me into corruption, and I retained no strength. 9  Yet heard I the voice of his words: and when I heard the voice of his words, then was I in a deep sleep on my face, and my face toward the ground.

10 ¶ And, behold, an hand touched me, which [†]set me upon my knees and upon the palms of my hands. 11  And he said unto me, O Daniel, [†]a man greatly beloved, understand the words that I speak unto thee, and [†]stand upright: for unto thee am I now sent. And when he had spoken this word unto me, I stood trembling. 12  Then said he unto me, Fear not, Daniel: for from the first day that thou didst set thine heart to understand, and to chasten thyself before thy God, thy words were heard, and I am come for thy words. 13  But the prince of the kingdom of Persia withstood me one and twenty days: but, lo, Michael, [∥]one of the chief princes, came to help me; and I remained there with the kings of Persia. 14  Now I am come to make thee understand what shall befall thy people in the latter days: for yet the vision is for many days. 15  And when he had spoken such words unto me, I set my face toward the ground, and I became dumb. 16 And, behold, one like the similitude of the sons of men touched my lips: then I opened my mouth, and spake, and said unto him that stood before me, O my lord, by the vision my sorrows are turned upon me, and I have retained no strength. 17  For how can [∥]the servant of this my lord talk with this my lord? for as for me, straightway there remained no strength in me, neither is there breath left in me. 18  Then there came again and touched me one like the appearance of a man, and he strengthened me, 19  And said, O man greatly beloved, fear not: peace be unto thee, be strong, yea, be strong. And when he had spoken unto me, I was strengthened, and said, Let my lord speak; for thou hast strengthened me. 20  Then said he, Knowest thou wherefore I come unto thee? and now will I return to fight with the prince of Persia: and when I am gone forth, lo, the prince of Grecia shall come. 21  But I will shew thee that which is noted in the scripture of truth: and there is none that [†]holdeth with me in these things, but Michael your prince.

11

1  Also I in the first year of Darius the Mede, even I, stood to confirm and to strengthen him. 2  And now will I shew thee the truth. Behold, there shall stand up yet three kings in Persia; and the fourth shall be far richer than they all: and by his strength through his riches he shall stir up all against the realm of Grecia. 3  And a mighty king shall stand up, that shall rule with great dominion, and do according to his will. 4  And when he shall stand up, his kingdom shall be broken, and shall be divided toward the four winds of heaven; and not to his posterity, nor according to his dominion which he ruled: for his kingdom shall be plucked up, even for others beside those.

5 ¶ And the king of the south shall be strong, and one of his princes; and he shall be strong above him, and have dominion; his dominion shall be a great dominion. 6  And in the end of years they [†]shall join themselves together; for the king’s daughter of the south shall come to the king of the north to make [†]an agreement: but she shall not retain the power of the arm; neither shall he stand, nor his arm: but she shall be given up, and they that brought her, and [∥]he that begat her, and he that strengthened her in these times. 7  But out of a branch of her roots shall one stand up in his estate, which shall come with an army, and shall enter into the fortress of the king of the north, and shall deal against them, and shall prevail: 8  And shall also carry captives into Egypt their gods, with their princes, and with [†]their precious vessels of silver and of gold; and he shall continue more years than the king of the north. 9  So the king of the south shall come into his kingdom, and shall return into his own land. 10  But his sons [∥]shall be stirred up, and shall assemble a multitude of great forces: and one shall certainly come, and overflow, and pass through: then shall he return, and be stirred up, even to his fortress. 11  And the king of the south shall be moved with choler, and shall come forth and fight with him, even with the king of the north: and he shall set forth a great multitude; but the multitude shall be given into his hand. 12  And when he hath taken away the multitude, his heart shall be lifted up; and he shall cast down many ten thousands: but he shall not be strengthened by it. 13  For the king of the north shall return, and shall set forth a multitude greater than the former, and shall certainly come [†]after certain years with a great army and with much riches. 14  And in those times there shall many stand up against the king of the south: also [†]the robbers of thy people shall exalt themselves to establish the vision; but they shall fall. 15  So the king of the north shall come, and cast up a mount, and take [†]the most fenced cities: and the arms of the south shall not withstand, neither [†]his chosen people, neither shall there be any strength to withstand. 16  But he that cometh against him shall do according to his own will, and none shall stand before him: and he shall stand in the [∥][†]glorious land, which by his hand shall be consumed. 17  He shall also set his face to enter with the strength of his whole kingdom, and [∥]upright ones with him; thus shall he do: and he shall give him the daughter of women, [†]corrupting her: but she shall not stand on his side, neither be for him. 18  After this shall he turn his face unto the isles, and shall take many: but a prince [†]for his own behalf shall cause [†]the reproach offered by him to cease; without his own reproach he shall cause it to turn upon him. 19  Then he shall turn his face toward the fort of his own land: but he shall stumble and fall, and not be found. 20  Then shall stand up in his estate [†]a raiser of taxes in the glory of the kingdom: but within few days he shall be destroyed, neither in [†]anger, nor in battle.

21  And in his estate shall stand up a vile person, to whom they shall not give the honour of the kingdom: but he shall come in peaceably, and obtain the kingdom by flatteries. 22  And with the arms of a flood shall they be overflown from before him, and shall be broken; yea, also the prince of the covenant. 23  And after the league made with him he shall work deceitfully: for he shall come up, and shall become strong with a small people. 24  He shall enter [∥]peaceably even upon the fattest places of the province; and he shall do that which his fathers have not done, nor his fathers’ fathers; he shall scatter among them the prey, and spoil, and riches: yea, and he shall [†]forecast his devices against the strong holds, even for a time. 25  And he shall stir up his power and his courage against the king of the south with a great army; and the king of the south shall be stirred up to battle with a very great and mighty army; but he shall not stand: for they shall forecast devices against him. 26  Yea, they that feed of the portion of his meat shall destroy him, and his army shall overflow: and many shall fall down slain. 27  And both these kings’ [†]hearts shall be to do mischief, and they shall speak lies at one table; but it shall not prosper: for yet the end shall be at the time appointed. 28  Then shall he return into his land with great riches; and his heart shall be against the holy covenant; and he shall do exploits, and return to his own land. 29  At the time appointed he shall return, and come toward the south; but it shall not be as the former, or as the latter.

30 ¶ For the ships of Chittim shall come against him: therefore he shall be grieved, and return, and have indignation against the holy covenant: so shall he do; he shall even return, and have intelligence with them that forsake the holy covenant. 31  And arms shall stand on his part, and they shall pollute the sanctuary of strength, and shall take away the daily sacrifice, and they shall place the abomination that [∥]maketh desolate. 32  And such as do wickedly against the covenant shall he [∥]corrupt by flatteries: but the people that do know their God shall be strong, and do exploits. 33  And they that understand among the people shall instruct many: yet they shall fall by the sword, and by flame, by captivity, and by spoil, many days. 34  Now when they shall fall, they shall be holpen with a little help: but many shall cleave to them with flatteries. 35 And some of them of understanding shall fall, to try [∥]them, and to purge, and to make them white, even to the time of the end: because it is yet for a time appointed. 36  And the king shall do according to his will; and he shall exalt himself, and magnify himself above every god, and shall speak marvellous things against the God of gods, and shall prosper till the indignation be accomplished: for that that is determined shall be done. 37  Neither shall he regard the God of his fathers, nor the desire of women, nor regard any god: for he shall magnify himself above all. 38  But [†]in his estate shall he honour the God of [∥][†]forces: and a god whom his fathers knew not shall he honour with gold, and silver, and with precious stones, and [†]pleasant things. 39  Thus shall he do in the [†]most strong holds with a strange god, whom he shall acknowledge and increase with glory: and he shall cause them to rule over many, and shall divide the land for [†]gain. 40  And at the time of the end shall the king of the south push at him: and the king of the north shall come against him like a whirlwind, with chariots, and with horsemen, and with many ships; and he shall enter into the countries, and shall overflow and pass over. 41  He shall enter also into the [∥][†]glorious land, and many countries shall be overthrown: but these shall escape out of his hand, even Edom, and Moab, and the chief of the children of Ammon. 42  He shall [†]stretch forth his hand also upon the countries: and the land of Egypt shall not escape. 43  But he shall have power over the treasures of gold and of silver, and over all the precious things of Egypt: and the Libyans and the Ethiopians shall be at his steps. 44  But tidings out of the east and out of the north shall trouble him: therefore he shall go forth with great fury to destroy, and utterly to make away many. 45  And he shall plant the tabernacles of his palace between the seas in the [∥][†]glorious holy mountain; yet he shall come to his end, and none shall help him.

12

1  And at that time shall Michael stand up, the great prince which standeth for the children of thy people: and there shall be a time of trouble, such as never was since there was a nation even to that same time: and at that time thy people shall be delivered, every one that shall be found written in the book. 2  And many of them that sleep in the dust of the earth shall awake, [*]some to everlasting life, and some to shame and everlasting contempt. 3  And they that be [∥]wise shall [*]shine as the brightness of the firmament; and they that turn many to righteousness as the stars for ever and ever. 4  But thou, O Daniel, shut up the words, and seal the book, even to the time of the end: many shall run to and fro, and knowledge shall be increased.

5 ¶ Then I Daniel looked, and, behold, there stood other two, the one on this side of the [†]bank of the river, and the other on that side of the bank of the river. 6 And one said to the man clothed in [*]linen, which was [∥]upon the waters of the river, How long shall it be to the end of these wonders? 7  And I heard the man clothed in linen, which was upon the waters of the river, when he [*]held up his right hand and his left hand unto heaven, and sware by him that liveth for ever that it shall be for a time, times, and [∥]an half; and when he shall have accomplished to scatter the power of the holy people, all these things shall be finished. 8  And I heard, but I understood not: then said I, O my Lord, what shall be the end of these things? 9  And he said, Go thy way, Daniel: for the words are closed up and sealed till the time of the end. 10  Many shall be purified, and made white, and tried; but the wicked shall do wickedly: and none of the wicked shall understand; but the wise shall understand. 11  And from the time that the daily sacrifice shall be taken away, and [†]the abomination that [∥]maketh desolate set up, there shall be a thousand two hundred and ninety days. 12  Blessed is he that waiteth, and cometh to the thousand three hundred and five and thirty days. 13  But go thou thy way till the end be: [∥]for thou shalt rest, and stand in [‡]thy lot at the end of the days.

* 1.1 2 Kin 24. 1. 2 Chr. 36. 6.

† 1.5 Heb. the wine of his drink.

† 1.10 Heb. sadder.

∥ 1.10 Or, term, or, continuance.

∥ 1.11 Or, the steward.

‡ 1.12 [1611 omits us]

† 1.12 Heb. of pulse.

† 1.12 Heb. that we may eat, &c.

∥ 1.17 Or, he made Daniel understand.

† 1.20 Heb. wisdom of understanding.

* 2.4 ch. 3. 9.

* 2.5 ch. 3. 29.

† 2.5 Chald. made pieces.

∥ 2.6 ch. 5. 17.

† 2.8 Chald. buy.

† 2.14 Chald. returned.

∥ 2.14 Or, chief marshal.

† 2.14 Chald. chief of the executioners, or, slaughtermen.

† 2.18 Chald. from before God.

∥ 2.18 Or, that they should not destroy Daniel, &c.

* 2.20 Ps 113 2 &c 115. 18.

† 2.25 Chald. That I have found.

† 2.25 Chald. children of the captivity of Judah.

† 2.28 Chald. hath made known

† 2.29 Chald. came up.

† 2.31 Chald. wast seeing.

∥ 2.32 Or, sides.

∥ 2.34 ver. 45.

∥ 2.42 Or, brittle.

† 2.43 Chald. this with this.

† 2.44 Chald. their days.

* 2.44 ch. 4. 3, 34. &c 6. 26. &c 7. 14, 27. Mic. 4. 7. Luke 1. 33.

† 2.44 Chald. kingdom thereof

∥ 2.45 Or, which was not in hand.

† 2.45 Chald. after this.

* 2.48 ch. 4. 9.

† 3.4 Chald. with might.

† 3.4 Chald. they command.

∥ 3.5 Or, singing.

† 3.5 Chald. symphony.

† 3.12 Chald. have set no regard upon thee.

∥ 3.14 Ex 21. 13.

‡ 3.15 [1611 omits burning]

‡ 3.18 [1611 thy]

† 3.19 Chald. filled.

† 3.20 Chald. mighty of strength.

∥ 3.21 Or, mantles.

∥ 3.21 Or, turbans.

† 3.22 Chald. word.

∥ 3.22 Or, spark.

∥ 3.24 Or, governors.

† 3.25 Chald. there is no hurt in them.

† 3.26 Chald. door.

† 3.29 Chald. a decres is made by me.

† 3.29 Chald. error.

* 3.29 ch. 2. 5.

† 3.29 Chald. made pieces.

† 3.30 Chald. made to prosper.

† 4.2 Chald. It was seemly before me.

* 4.3 ch. 2. 44.

* 4.9 ch. 2. 48.

† 4.10 Chald. I was seeing.

† 4.14 Chald with might.

* 4.25 ch. 5. 21, &c.

∥ 4.27 Or, an healing of thine error.

∥ 4.29 Or, upon.

* 4.34 ch 7 14. Mic 4 7. Luke 1. 33.

* 4.35 Job 9. 12. Is. 45. 9.

† 5.2 Chald. brought forth.

† 5.6 Chald. brightnesses.

† 5.6 Chald changed it

∥ 5.6 Or, girdles.

† 5.6 Chald. bindings, or, knots.

† 5.7 Chald. with might.

∥ 5.7 Or, purple.

† 5.9 Chald. brightnesses.

* 5.11 ch. 2. 48.

∥ 5.11 Or, grandfather.

∥ 5.11 Or, grandfather.

* 5.11 ch. 4. 9.

∥ 5.12 Or, of an interpreter, &c.

∥ 5.12 Or, of a dissolver.

† 5.12 Chald knots

∥ 5.13 Or, grandfather.

† 5.16 Chald. interpret.

∥ 5.17 ch 2 6.

∥ 5.20 Or to deal proudly

† 5.20 Chald made to come down.

* 5.21 ch 4. 32.

∥ 5.21 Or, he made his heart equal, &c.

† 5.31 Chald. he as the son of, &c

∥ 5.31 Or, now.

∥ 6.6 Or, came tumultuously

∥ 6.7 Or, interdict.

* 6.8 Esth. 2 1 &c 8. 8.

† 6.8 Chald. passeth not.

* 6.10 1 Kin. 8 48.

* 6.10 Ps. 55. 17.

‡ 6.13 [1611 captivity of the children]

∥ 6.18 Or, table.

* 6.26 ch. 2 44. &c 4 3. &c 7. 14, 27. Luke 1. 33.

† 6.27 Heb. hand

* 6.28 ch. 1. 21.

† 7.1 Chald saw.

∥ 7.1 Or, words.

∥ 7.4 Or, wherewith.

∥ 7.5 Or, it raised up one dominion.

* 7.10 Rev. 5. 11

* 7.10 Rev. 20. 12.

† 7.12 Chald. a prolonging in life was given them.

* 7.14 ch 2 44. Mic. 4. 7. Luke 1. 33.

† 7.15 Chald. sheath

† 7.18 Chald. high ones, that is, things, or, places.

† 7.19 Chald. from all those.

* 7.27 Luke 1. 33.

∥ 7.27 Or, rulers.

† 8.3 Heb. the second.

∥ 8.5 Or, none touched him in the earth.

† 8.5 Heb. a horn of sight.

* 8.8 ch. 11 4

* 8.9 Ps 18 2 Ezek. 20. 6.

∥ 8.10 Or, against the host.

∥ 8.11 Or, against

∥ 8.11 Or, from him

∥ 8.12 Or, the host was given over for the transgression against the daily sacrifice.

∥ 8.13 Or, the numberer of secrets, or, the wonderful numberer.

† 8.13 Heb. Palmoni.

∥ 8.13 Or, making desolate.

† 8.14 Heb. evening morning.

† 8.14 Heb. justified.

* 8.16 ch 9. 21.

† 8.18 Heb. made me stand upon my standing.

† 8.23 Heb. are accomplished.

† 8.24 Heb. people of the holy ones.

∥ 8.25 Or, prosperity.

* 8.25 2 Macc. 9. 9.

∥ 9.1 Or, in which he, &c.

* 9.2 Jer 25. 12 &c 29 10.

* 9.4 Deut. 7 9. Neh 1 5

* 9.5 Bar. 1. 17

∥ 9.7 Or, thou hast, &c.

* 9.8 Bar 1. 15.

* 9.11 Lev. 26. 14, &c. Deut 28. 15, &c. &c 29 20, &c &c 30. 17, 18. &c 31. 17, &c. &c 32. 19, &c.

* 9.13 Lev. 26. 14 Deut. 28. 15 Lam 2. 17.

† 9.13 Heb. intreated we not the face of the &c.

† 9.15 Heb. made thee a name.

* 9.15 Ex. 14. 18.

† 9.18 Heb whereupon thy name is called.

† 9.18 Heb. cause to fall.

* 9.21 ch. 8. 16.

† 9.21 Heb. with weariness, or, flight.

† 9.22 Heb. to make thee skilful of understanding

† 9.23 Heb word.

† 9.23 Heb a man of desires.

∥ 9.24 Or, to restrain.

∥ 9.24 Or, to seal up.

† 9.24 Heb prophet.

† 9.25 Heb shall return and be built.

∥ 9.25 Or, breach, or, ditch.

† 9.25 Heb in strait of times.

∥ 9.26 Or, and shall have nothing

∥ 9.26 Or, it shall be cut off by desolations.

∥ 9.27 Or, with the abominable armies.

* 9.27 Matt. 24 15 Mark 13. 14. Luke 21. 20.

† 10.1 Heb. great.

† 10.2 Heb. weeks of days.

† 10.3 Heb. bread of desires.

* 10.4 Gen. 2. 14

† 10.5 Heb. one man.

* 10.5 Rev. 1 13, 14, 15

∥ 10.8 Or, vigour.

* 10.8 ch. 7. 28.

† 10.10 Heb. moved.

† 10.11 Heb. a man of desires.

† 10.11 Heb stand upon thy standing

∥ 10.13 Or, the first

∥ 10.17 Or, this servant of my lord.

† 10.21 Heb. strengtheneth himself.

† 11.6 Heb. shall associate themselves.

† 11.6 Heb. rights.

∥ 11.6 Or, whom she brought forth.

† 11.8 Heb. vessels of their desire.

∥ 11.10 Or, shall war.

† 11.13 Heb. at the end of times of years.

† 11.14 Heb. the children of robbers.

† 11.15 Heb. the city of munitions.

† 11.15 Heb. the people of his choices.

∥ 11.16 Or, goodly land

† 11.16 Heb. the land of ornament.

∥ 11.17 Or, much uprightness: or, equal conditions.

† 11.17 Heb to corrupt.

† 11.18 Heb. for him.

† 11.18 Heb. his reproach.

† 11.20 Heb. one that causeth an ex acter to pass over.

† 11.20 Heb. angers.

∥ 11.24 Or, into the peaceable and fat, &c.

† 11.24 Heb. think his thoughts.

† 11.27 Heb. their hearts.

∥ 11.31 Or, astonisheth

∥ 11.32 Or, cause to dissemble.

∥ 11.35 Or, by them.

† 11.38 Heb. as for the almighty God, in his seat he shall honour, yea, he shall honour a god whom, &c.

∥ 11.38 Or, munitions.

† 11.38 Heb. Mauzzim.

† 11.38 Heb. things desired.

† 11.39 Heb. fortresses of munitions.

† 11.39 Heb a price.

∥ 11.41 Or, goodly land.

† 11.41 Heb land of delight, or, ornament.

† 11.42 Heb. send forth.

∥ 11.45 Or, goodly.

† 11.45 Heb mountain of delight of holiness.

* 12.2 Matt. 25 46 John 5. 29.

∥ 12.3 Or, teachers.

* 12.3 Matt. 13. 43.

† 12.5 Heb. lip.

* 12.6 ch. 10 5.

∥ 12.6 Or, from above.

* 12.7 Rev. 10 5.

∥ 12.7 Or, part.

† 12.11 Heb. to set up the abomination, &c.

∥ 12.11 Or, astonisheth.

∥ 12.13 Or, and thou, &c.

‡ 12.13 [1611 the]